<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-11T00:00:33+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Anniversary of the Women of the Prelature</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Anniversary of the Women of the Prelature" /><published>2026-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em><br />
<br />
In the Entrance Antiphon of today’s Mass, we read, “Sing psalms and hymns and inspired songs among yourselves, singing and chanting to the Lord in your hearts” (Eph. 5:19).</p>

<p>Today, the 14th of February, is a day of celebration and of thanksgiving in Opus Dei for all of the graces that God has given to us.</p>

<p>As we realize another year has passed, a year of our vocation, a year of the history of the Work on the earth, another year of the fulfillment of God’s plans, of how He’s using His Work to do all sorts of wonderful things in us and through us.</p>

<p>Our Father said, “Always be giving thanks to God constantly for everything: for what seems good and for what seems bad, for what is sweet and for what is bitter, for the white and for the black, for small things and for big things, for what seems meager and for what seems bountiful, for what is temporal and for what reaches unto eternity (J. Escrivá, <em>Notes</em>, December 25, 1972).</p>

<p>We all have great reasons to give thanks to God for the women of the Prelature and also for the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross, whose founding we also celebrate today: very special gifts that God has given to His Work. He crowned them in a special way.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro, on the 60th anniversary of the founding of the women of the Prelature, wrote that on the 14th of February 1930, Our Lord wanted to offer our Father a tangible proof of the divinity of the Work.</p>

<p>Before that date, as we all know, our Founder was very sure that there would not be women in Opus Dei. He told us on more than one occasion, “I had written down, because of the difference between Opus Dei and another institution that existed outside of Spain, that we would never work with women.”</p>

<p>This must have been, he said, around 1929. “Shortly afterwards, on the 14th of February 1930, I was celebrating Mass in the house of an elderly lady, when the women of the Prelature came to the world.”</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “It was a super clear, supernatural light which our Founder received in the Mass, after Communion, on that Friday, 14th of February 1930. As always, when Our Lord manifested His will to him in an extraordinary way, in the first moments, his first reaction was that of feeling a bit disturbed. Then he perceived in the intimacy of his being, those words of Our Lord to Our Lady: ‘Do not be afraid’ (Luke 2:10). And he remained full of peace.”</p>

<p>He began, as he did in 1928 with men, to work apostolically, particularly from the confessional box, with the women and young girls who came to seek his advice.</p>

<p>With great thanksgiving and gratitude to Our Lord, He liked to remember the help that a sister of ours gave him who was taken up with great pain from a great illness. She offered this treasure of her sufferings for this divine enterprise.</p>

<p>When we go back and hear the words of Don Álvaro speaking about the beginnings, we can make a great act of faith, and also of thanksgiving, because we see how God has acted in the world, and very particularly, how He acted in the life of our Father.</p>

<p>When we look around at the reality of Opus Dei, what it is in the world today, it’s a very different phenomenon to what was there in 1930. There was almost nothing. Yet because of our Father’s correspondence, his holiness, his humility, that spirit of Opus Dei has spread all over the world.</p>

<p>Everything that our Father has done and everything that he has written has great relevance for us. God speaks to us through his life and through his correspondence, beckoning us, calling us, encouraging us to walk in the footsteps of our Father, as the pathway that Our Lord has laid out for us in order that we might know Him and love Him.</p>

<p>When the Confessor of our Father heard about this new manifestation of the will of God, without intervening in any way in the organization of the Work, he confirmed to our Father with great sureness that “this is just as much from God as the rest.”</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Look at how Our Lord works. He loves us with all of His goodness. He takes care of us with the refined diligence. He gathers us up with His immense mercy. He never leaves us alone. Even more, He always reaches out with a hand to us.</p>

<p>“Fill yourself with joy, my daughter, my son, because this God of ours, omnipotent and eternal, speaks to us constantly in the silence of our prayer. And we know His voice, also in moments of dryness, because if we are ready and open, as our Father was, to put into practice what Our Lord asks of us, even though we have to go against the grain, He gives us that unequivocal sign of interior peace.”</p>

<p>We can thank God also for that peace that we have in our vocation, in our life, in the means of formation, in our own personal apostolate, in the bringing forward of all the apostolic works, in taking on our shoulders the economic responsibility for all of this great apostolic work that God wants us to do, so that we take our vocation very seriously, we are willing to carry the cross, because we know God will fill us with His interior peace.</p>

<p>“He also speaks to us,” said Don Álvaro, “through other people in spiritual direction. It was Our Lord who spoke to each one of us at the beginning of our vocation, when somebody opened up for us this joyful horizon so that we would give ourselves to the Work. Later on, we count on that blessed personal experience. Our Lord continues to reach out His hand to us all along our pathway until our final pilgrimage on this earth, making use also of spiritual direction to show His will to us.”</p>

<p>There is a conclusion from all of this, and that is that in our interior life, we have to have initiative. Initiative, but at the same time we don’t direct ourselves. Our apostolate is a directed apostolate. We need that obedience, that docility, from those who are there to guide us.</p>

<p>We have this great treasure of the spirit of Opus Dei in our hands. There are aspects of our Father’s life that we are discovering and rediscovering all the time, every time that we read some of his writings, or we discover something new about his life, or the new things that people are writing about him.</p>

<p>One of the ideas that is worth thinking about is that our Father was one of the greatest Christian feminists of the 20th century. Possibly nobody in the history of the Church has done as much for women in the world as our Father has done.</p>

<p>He encouraged women to use their talents to the full in all fields of human endeavor: in business, in politics, in medicine, in engineering, in the home, in science, in all sorts of areas. He wrote very dramatic things about the role of women in society that in many ways were ahead of their time.</p>

<p>In <em>Conversations</em> he says, “The development, maturity, emancipation of women should not mean a pretension to equality, to uniformity with men, a servile imitation of a man’s way of doing things. That would not get us anywhere. Women would turn out losers, not because they’re better than men or worse, but because they’re different.”</p>

<p>He liked to outline these particular characteristics of women and the great talents that they bring to any enterprise. He said, “Women, like men, possess the dignity of being persons and children of God. … They’re called to bring to the family, to society, and to the Church, characteristics which are their own and which they alone can give: their gentle warmth and untiring generosity, their love for detail, their quick-wittedness and intuition, their simple and deep piety, their constancy” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 87).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul liked to say that every man coming into the world is entrusted to the care of a woman (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Mulieris dignitatem</em>, Point 30, August 15, 1988).</p>

<p>He liked to say that while both parents play a role, it’s the woman in particular that teaches the man what it means to be human. Ultimately, she teaches him what it means to love, and then this is his greatest maturity.</p>

<p>One American educationalist says that every baby coming into the world comes into the world like a self-satisfying, hedonistic gorilla. The role of parents is to turn that hedonistic, self-satisfying gorilla into an adult.</p>

<p>The little baby screams for its milk. ‘Give me my milk, and even if it’s three in the morning, get up out of bed and give me my milk because I am the most important person in the world. And I’m going to scream and scream and scream until I get it.’ The role of parents is to turn this little gorilla into an adult.</p>

<p>He says that adults are not just people who can take care of themselves, because a dog or a cat or a hothouse plant can do that. An adult is somebody who fundamentally can take care of others. An adult is somebody who can forget about themselves.</p>

<p>That’s what love is. That’s why some people never become adults, because love is sacrifice. The mother has sacrificed herself for her child. She, more than the father, teaches that lesson to the child: what love is, how to forget about yourself, how to give yourself to others.</p>

<p>He continues in <em>Conversations</em>, “It is not only outside the home that a woman achieves her perfection, as though time spent at home was time stolen from the development of her personality. … The attention given to her family will always be a woman’s greatest dignity. In the care she takes of her husband and children...in her work of creating a warm and formative atmosphere around her, a woman fulfills the most indispensable part of her mission. It follows that she can achieve her personal perfection here” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>While encouraging women to take their place in the world, to go as far as they can, to use all their talents, to play a great role in society, he also emphasizes the fundamental role that a woman plays in the family, in the home—of forming new human beings, of making that home and that family a school of deeper humanity, a school of virtue, a school of piety, the domestic Church.</p>

<p>He continues, “In all spheres, women have their own valuable contribution...which will be rendered to the extent that they are humanly and professionally equipped. Both family and society clearly need this special contribution, which is in no way secondary to that of men.”</p>

<p>We can think of all the great ways that the Catholic Church has promoted the authentic development of women all over the world through our history—the great education orders that have educated girls in every last part of the globe, the healthcare orders who took care of the sick in all sorts of ways, giving great example,</p>

<p>The Church has always promoted the care and education of women as much as possible. But St. Josemaría has sort of brought it to a different level. Their great contribution will be “insofar as they are humanly and professionally equipped.” He encourages women to go as far as they can, to be experts in various fields.</p>

<p>“The essential equality with men and women,” he says, “demands an understanding of the complementary roles which they play in the Church’s growth and in the progress of society” (<em>Conversations</em>, Point 14).</p>

<p>In marriage a man does not complete a woman or the woman does not complete a man. They are already complete in themselves. They complement each other.</p>

<p>“Not in vain,” he says, “did God make them man and woman. This diversity should be considered not in a ‘patriarchal’ sense but in its full, rich depth of tones and consequences” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Diversity is something good. It’s willed by God, something we have to foster. God created the male and female. The male should be more male and the female should be more female.</p>

<p>“In this way,” he continues, “men are freed from the temptation of ‘masculinizing’ the Church and society, and women from seeing their mission in the People of God and in the world as no more than showing that they can do equally well the tasks which were formerly reserved to men. I think that both men and women should rightly consider themselves as the protagonists in the history of salvation, but each complementing the work of the other” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>I was on a plane a few years ago and there was a young couple with their young baby. I couldn’t help noticing how the mother was looking after the baby very well and keeping him happy.</p>

<p>Then, after a little while she passed the baby to the father. You could sort of see this young father—he did his best, he did what he could. But his way of carrying the baby, looking after the baby, and trying to satisfy the needs of the baby, compared to the mother, was just inadequate.</p>

<p>It was almost amusing to see. In spite of his best efforts, he really couldn’t hack it. In that little moment or two, you could see the difference in the quality of the talents of each individual person. We all have a different role to play.</p>

<p>When we look at the seeds that St. Josemaría has sown in the world by the will of God with the women of the Prelature, we could think, on this feast day—as we begin to look towards the hundredth anniversary that is coming up in a few years, which the Father has encouraged us to focus on—we could think of all the wonderful horizons that are opening up in front of us.</p>

<p>As the Prelate likes to tell us, we have to think back of the early people who went to each country to start the work. There’s a book about the first women who went to Japan. They left Rome. Their boat got as far as—I think it was Aden or Suez or someplace—and they found a letter waiting for them there from our Father.</p>

<p>He followed them every step of the journey. He sent these daughters of his to faraway places to plant that seed. He took great care that the seed would find good soil.</p>

<p>When we look back and see how the women of the Prelature have developed in every country, we see this great divine enterprise from a different perspective.</p>

<p>But then also we have to see how that same faith that our Father had in sending out those sisters of ours, and they themselves, who gave themselves so completely—we have to try and have the same dispositions in our apostolate, as we also “launch out into the deep” (Luke 5:4).</p>

<p>In 1988, on the 60th anniversary of the founding of the men of the Prelature, Don Álvaro talked about the spirit of the beginnings.</p>

<p>He said, “This 60th anniversary is an excellent occasion that Our Lord gives us to remind ourselves that we always have to go forward with the stimulating spirit full of the novelty of the beginnings, that spirit with which our Founder started the Work on the 2nd of October 1928, to carry out the task that God was entrusting to him, that made him the happiest person in the world because of the confidence that Our Father in heaven gave him.”</p>

<p>Each one of us is called to “launch out into the deep,” to see the new horizons of apostolate that God is placing before us, new people that we get to meet, new possibilities.</p>

<p>The pandemic, social media, there are all sorts of new means for transmitting the message of the Gospel. There are new people who are hungry to hear these things. We have to look to the future.</p>

<p>Recently, Pope Francis has talked about how there is a great spiritual emptiness in the world (Pope Francis, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Querida Amazonia</em>, Point 108, February 2, 2020; <em>Angelus</em>, June 19, 2016).</p>

<p>Our Father would like to say this is our world. This moment of history—it is the world that God has entrusted to us.</p>

<p>He wants us to fill that spiritual emptiness with all the good things that we have to give, with the apostolate of apostolates, with the care of our homes and of our family, with all sorts of details of taste and elegance—often unconscious details that transmit a great refinement and transmit the message of the dignity of every human person.</p>

<p>Our Father has said that every corner of the homes of every supernumerary, every cooperator, has to become a corner of the home in Nazareth. It is our job to make that happen.</p>

<p>Each one of us has to help our sisters to fulfill that great goal: caring for the work of the Catering, taking care of the dining room, taking care with things of laundry, order, looking after the <em>regulae internae,</em> the criteria of separation that our Father has given us, learning how to serve in a better way so that the work of our sisters reaches further, and so that from each one of our homes and our centers, there radiates that spirit of Christian fraternity that hopefully will help to spread the seeds of many vocations in many families.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Without wanting to be exhaustive, I want to remind you of certain concrete points that we have to keep very much in mind as we try to faithfully fulfill the Work of God on this earth.”</p>

<p>Like our Father Abraham, you could say of our Founder that he believed “against all hope” (Rom. 4:18), confiding in the Word of God. That supernatural sureness that the Work would be carried out was confirmed to him by Our Lord on many different occasions. It presupposed the exercise of a heroic faith on the part of our Founder.</p>

<p>As we look to the future, we’re also called to have heroic faith in our vocation, in the Church, in the Holy Father, in Our Father God who is beside us all the time—in this particular apostolic task that God has placed in front of me, this Circle, that class, this recollection, this retreat, this town or village that I have to try and bring the Work to, with a number of journeys.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to have the same hope, confidence, fortitude, perseverance as our Father had in fulfilling these things.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Without failing before any of the difficulties that humanly speaking were enormous, difficulties that presented themselves to him along his pathway, he didn’t vacillate in any way. He thought of that aspiration: ‘The waters will pass through the mountains’ (Ps. 104:10). Our Lord comforted him with that aspiration on the 12th of December 1931 when the obstacles to the development of the Work were truly immense.</p>

<p>“None of us in our efforts to spend ourselves to bring forth Opus Dei will ever encounter the same sort of obstacles that our Father encountered. God placed these aspirations in his soul, in his heart, so that he would transmit them to us, so that we would always walk with faith and optimism along the pathways of the earth, very confident that God is acting in us and through us.</p>

<p>“With the fortitude of God and the faith of our Founder,” said Don Álvaro, “we have to personify until the end of time ‘waters will pass through the mountains,’ overcoming all sorts of difficulties that will never be lacking.”</p>

<p>We can’t be surprised that there are difficulties or crosses or problems. That’s par for the course. It’s a given. It’s a good sign. God blesses us with the cross.</p>

<p>The Father has said that the expansion of Opus Dei goes forward in and from the cross. We’re not surprised by the cross in our life. We can thank God for those crosses. They help us to be more supernatural, to turn to our prayer a little more.</p>

<p>One time, many years ago, Don Álvaro went to visit England. He was told that they were redoing a number of the centers, doing a lot of rebuilding and extending and all sorts of developments, and that they had huge financial problems.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro said, “Wonderful. I wish you many financial problems, because then you will pray more.”</p>

<p>The problems lead us to pray, lead us to be supernatural. These were great lessons that our Father and Don Álvaro learned in the course of time that they wanted to transmit to us.</p>

<p>He continues, “This must be our attitude in our personal apostolate, and in the tasks that the Work confides to us. Sure of the power of God, with the spirit of initiative and the mentality of pioneers, we have to launch ourselves to open up new channels through which the spirit of Opus Dei can circulate, carrying to the most diverse environments that supernatural savor capable of vivifying all honorable human occupations.”</p>

<p>What an enormous horizon! Through our friends and contacts, we come to know of new environments, professions, areas where perhaps the spirit of God and the doctrine of God needs to circulate.</p>

<p>So many people who are in need of new ideas or of doctrine are in formerly Christian countries that have forgotten all their Christian formation and need to be born again.</p>

<p>We are here to carry out this great work of evangelization. God wants to use inadequate instruments with all of their miseries—that is, each one of us.</p>

<p>“We can’t dilute,” he says, “our personal responsibility, that of each one of us, into that of the directors or a supposed structure. Our Father affirmed that the Work is ‘a disorganized organization.’ That means that as a consequence, there could never be lacking our personal spontaneity, and that of all the members of the Prelature, at the time of proposing and bringing forward apostolic activities.”</p>

<p>Each one of us is to think: What can I do? What does God want me to do? Where can I have initiative and responsibility in bringing things forward?</p>

<p>“The organization of the Work,” he says, “does not hem us in in any way. Rather, through its very nature, it stimulates us. It fosters a great liberty of movement not only in professional and political areas, but that of each one of us, in the enormously wide fields of personal apostolic initiative.”</p>

<p>That word initiative is a very attractive word on the lips of a member of Opus Dei. He says, “We cannot forget that a woman of Opus Dei, a man of Opus Dei, must in all moments be a person who is an apostle.”</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady, Mother of Fair Love, that she might help us to go very deep on this special day, and ask Our Lord to help us to have a greater spirit of wonder and gratitude for our vocation, as we look to the future and all the great horizons that the Father is placing before us.</p>

<p><em>Mater Pulchrae Dilectiones, filios tuos adiuva!</em></p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>DWM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Lady of Lourdes</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Lady of Lourdes" /><published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that You are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We're told in the story of Cana of Galilee that “the Mother of Jesus was there” (John 2:1).</p>

<p>Today is the feast of Our Lady of Lourdes.</p>

<p>John Paul II, talking about the popularity of Lourdes in the last century, would like to say that possibly it’s because also “the Mother of Jesus is there” (John Paul II, <em>Introduction to the Recitation of the Rosary</em>, August 14, 2004). Today, the World Day of the Sick, is a day to ask Our Lady of Lourdes for special things.</p>

<p>It's a day that marks the first apparition of Our Lady there in 1858 to a young girl, 14-year-old Bernadette Soubirous.</p>

<p>There were a total of eighteen apparitions in all, quite a large number. The message of Lourdes was, as always, a message of personal conversion, of prayer, of charity.</p>

<p>It was approved as a feast day by Pope Leo XIII, and Pope Pius X extended this feast day to the Universal Church. Bernadette herself was beatified and canonized by Pope Pius XI in 1925.</p>

<p>A couple of years previously, in 1854, the Church had defined as infallible the dogma of the Immaculate Conception. Then just four years later, in this very obscure little village which Lourdes is, hidden there in the Pyrenees, a place you'd pass by at the moment, you'd blink, you'd miss it, Our Lady chose to appear to this shepherd girl.</p>

<p>She appeared a number oftimes. Bernadette was eventually encouraged to ask the Lady who she was.</p>

<p>The whole phenomenon caused a lot of consternation of the local people, all sorts of interest and curiosity. And when she asked her, Bernadette said later, “She said, ‘I am the Immaculate Conception.’”</p>

<p>When she told this to the local priest and bishop, they realized there was no way that this little farming rural girl could possibly know what those words meant. But of course, they knew about the dogma that had been proclaimed four years earlier.</p>

<p>Little by little, in spite of many contradictions, and a lot of misunderstanding, which always accompanies the supernatural—Bernadette had to suffer a lot in her family: misunderstandings, accusations of fraud, all sorts of things, punishments—eventually, she was believed, and a sculptor tried to make an image of the Lady that had appeared.</p>

<p>It was a very beautiful statue. When it was finished, Bernadette was asked what she thought of the statue: “Did the Lady look anything like this?” Despite the statue being a very beautiful statue, Bernadette said, “Oh, no, no, the Lady was much more beautiful” (Bernadette Soubirous, <em>A Short Life of Bernadette of Lourdes</em>). The sculptor had done his best, but he didn't quite make it.</p>

<p>There was a curious statistic that I heard a number of years ago. Somebody was talking about the main tourist destinations in France. Of course, when you think about the main tourist destinations, I think most people in Europe certainly would think about the popular places that you hear about on the French Riviera, very stylish supper places.</p>

<p>But curiously, at the very top of the list of tourist destinations in France is Lourdes. None of these other very chic places attract anything like the numbers that Lourdes has attracted over the years. There's something special there. The Mother of Jesus was there.</p>

<p>She appeared with her message of charity, of looking out for the sick. Today is the World Day of the Sick.</p>

<p>She was there to encourage the sick, to help them. And over time, she has performed many miracles; some of them spiritual, many physical. The cures and the miracles are almost numberless.</p>

<p>I met an Australian missionary [Paul Glynn] in Japan. (I was in Japan, I met him in Singapore many years ago.) He wrote a book about Lourdes. It's a rather interesting book. It was called <em>Healing Fire from Frozen Earth.</em></p>

<p>It was like a modern history of Lourdes, written in a very secular way, for a very secular readership of the 21st century, but with very cogent descriptions. You have to admit there's something very supernatural that was taking place there.</p>

<p>Our Lord wanted to entrust Our Lady with very special riches that she would transmit to humanity, a reminder of the infinite mercy of God. Our Lady reaches out to every single person.</p>

<p>In the Litany, we refer to her as Health of the Sick, Comfort of the Afflicted. At some stage in our life, we've all been more or less sick, or we know people that have been.</p>

<p>It's wonderful to know that we have a Mother to turn to, somebody who always understands us, somebody also who can bring good out of every suffering, so that in every little bit of suffering that we might endure and that Our Lady might permit in our life, we know that she's going to take this thing and convert it into something of great value.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story of how there was a lady in the late 19th century, late 1800s, in Paris, a French lady, Catholic lady, who married a man who was the chairman of the Communist Party. He was also the editor of the Communist newspaper, a very prominent Communist.</p>

<p>She felt that God had given her this husband to convert him. He was a very intelligent man; she was just a very normal lady. She tried to brush up on her theology as best she could, or her doctrine, to engage him intellectually. But she more or less got nowhere; she didn't achieve anything. But after several years of marriage, she got very sick.</p>

<p>I think it was TB of the spine or something, and she had to be in an iron lung for a number of years. She suffered an awful lot, but she and her husband were very much in love.</p>

<p>One day, after many years, she said to him, “After I die, you will convert and become a Catholic.” He was thinking, “I think my wife is nearing her end.” Because there was nothing further from his mind.</p>

<p>Then she said, “After that, you will enter a seminary and you will be ordained a Catholic priest.”</p>

<p>He said, “Definitely my wife is losing her mind.” There was nothing further from his thoughts; it was outside the bounds of possibility.</p>

<p>Then she said, “Because I have asked God to send me enough suffering in my life, to save your soul.” He dismissed these thoughts as the thoughts of a dying woman.</p>

<p>Then she passed away, and he had an awful lot of grief because he had loved her very much. He wanted somehow to reconnect with her spirit or to relive the moments they had spent together. He took time off, and he decided to go and visit all the places that they had been to in France on their honeymoon.</p>

<p>He began to travel all over France, as they did on their honeymoon. At one stage, he found himself in a small village outside the local church, and he remembered that on their honeymoon, they had gone into the church.</p>

<p>It wasn't politically correct for him to be seen going to churches. He also hated going to churches; he had no time for that sort of thing. But he had made a promise to himself to go everywhere they had been on their honeymoon, so he went into the church.</p>

<p>Inside the church, he got this tremendous desire to go to Lourdes. Well, he had hated Lourdes. He had dismissed Lourdes as one of those Catholic superstitions and frauds in his communist newspaper. He condemned it from a height as silly superstitious stuff.</p>

<p>But here he had this great desire to go to Lourdes, so he went to Lourdes.</p>

<p>Standing in front of the grotto of Lourdes, he underwent a monumental conversion. So great were the graces of his conversion that the thought of going back to Paris and resigning from the chairmanship of the Communist Party and the editorship of the communist newspaper. It didn't cost him a thought.</p>

<p>A couple of months later, he entered a Dominican seminary, and eventually, he was ordained a priest.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says, “I did my retreat given by that Dominican priest in 1925. It's not often in the course of your life where you attend a retreat where the preacher frequently says, ‘as my wife Elizabeth used to say.’”</p>

<p>Our Lady is capable of the most monumental conversions. On feast days like today, we join the whole Church and the whole world in bringing to Our Lady our every need.</p>

<p>We know that she knows us very well. She hears our petitions, no matter what they may be.</p>

<p>That motherly assistance will fill us with peace and joy. In the last 150 years or more, she has heard the voices of so many children who pray to her.</p>

<p>Today, somebody sent me a little video clip of a Mass in Lourdes this morning, packed with thousands of people. So, the devotion to Our Lady of Lourdes is still very much alive and well.</p>

<p>Small children, when they stray from their mother, get uneasy. They can feel a bit lost, and more than a bit lost. Likewise, we have to try and make sure that we don't stray too much from Our Lady. We stay close to her.</p>

<p>In the intimacy of our personal prayer, we can ask her for things. Or see how we turn to Our Mother frequently during the day with our <em>Angelus</em>, with our Rosary, maybe in our <em>Morning Offering</em>, with our <em>Memorares</em>, or other little aspirations that we may say, asking for help in this thing or that thing, or lights to understand things a little better, or the fortitude we need to get this thing done, or that problem solved, or placing before her all of our children and grandchildren, so that we are truly a powerful force in their lives, a force of prayer.</p>

<p>I remember I had a relation whose parents were not—well, one was Catholic, one wasn't—they weren't practicing. This little girl managed to make her First Holy Communion. I remember my mother commenting, “It's the prayers of your grandmother.”</p>

<p>I always remember those words, trying to figure out, How do the prayers of my grandmother have anything to do with this little seven-year-old making her First Holy Communion?—as though saying it was a major miracle.</p>

<p>There are many things, perhaps as parents and grandparents, that we bring about through our prayer, and that God has been planning from all eternity, and our fidelity in prayer, our turning to Our Lady:</p>

<p>“Remember, O most Gracious Virgin Mary, that never was it known, that anyone who fled to your protection, implored your help, or sought your intercession was left unaided” (Prayer, <em>The Memorare</em>).</p>

<p>We know she's looking out for us all the time. She had a very clear message when she appeared in the grotto. She wanted to remind humanity of the need for conversion and penance. In nearly all of her apparitions, she said the same thing.</p>

<p>As in nearly all of her other apparitions, she's also prayed the Rosary with Bernadette, as though emphasizing the power of the Rosary.</p>

<p>She also spoke of how we can be co-redeemers with Christ, redeeming with Him, uniting our sufferings with Him on the Cross—any pain, physical or moral, difficulties in our life, challenges, contradictions, mysteries—and also voluntary mortifications that we might do some day out of generosity, offering those things to Our Lady in atonement for all the sins of men.</p>

<p>With Our Lady beside us, we can come to see how things that might appear to be a great tragedy can in fact bring about great good, and consider it through the eyes of faith.</p>

<p>I was at a special Mass about a week or so ago in Msongari in Loreto in Nairobi. It was the 100th anniversary of the Loreto Sisters in Kenya, and of course it was a very special moment. It’s possibly one of the longest-serving religious orders in Kenya.</p>

<p>Archbishop Kivuva [Martin Kuviva Musonde] said the Mass and he was saying many beautiful things about the contribution the Sisters had made to the Church in Kenya; what the Church in Kenya would not have been if it hadn't been for Loreto Sisters, and how he'd asked a number of kids, “Do you go to Loreto School?” They'd say, “No, but my mother did.”</p>

<p>He said, half the country said the same thing, in a couple of little clips that are very apt.</p>

<p>But being at this Mass and thinking about the six Sisters that arrived here in 1921, and a hundred years later, I reckon about a million girls have been educated. You can trust that beginning with the arrival point that we've reached 100 years later, it’s just unimaginable.</p>

<p>We couldn't even dream about it or think about it. Just incredible. You can't explain it in human terms. But of course, the story is one of faith and also one of heroism.</p>

<p>Along the way, there have been a lot of tragedies. There was a bus that went off the road in Meru a couple of years ago. Some students lost their lives, some lost limbs.</p>

<p>There was a train in the late 1990s that was coming from Mombasa with two Kenyan Loreto Sisters who were destined for important administrative positions, perhaps in the development of their order. There was a flood, the bridge was washed away, and when the train came there, it went into the river and that was the end of those nuns.</p>

<p>All sorts of heartbreaking tragedies have been part of the story. But when 100 years have passed and you look back, it's just amazing what has been achieved.</p>

<p>You see what God wants to do with our correspondence to grace. In our marriage, in our family, despite the contradictions or the difficulties or the things that haven't worked out, it's all a story of faith, of heroism, and of grace.</p>

<p>We can have great faith and trust in all the miracles that Our Lady wants to work in us and through us, through our fidelity, and places these examples before us.</p>

<p>This is a great message that we can transmit to people who may have illnesses, serious illnesses, maybe chronic things, or people who are born disabled, or who don't have the physical or mental talents that we might have. All these things invite us to trust more in God and to put God's power above our meager efforts.</p>

<p>He can do much greater things in a much greater way, but He just wants to use us as His humble instruments.</p>

<p>Maybe we make mistakes, and maybe things go wrong, but we just put one foot in front of the other. St. Paul tells us that we will not be tested beyond our strength (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:13).</p>

<p>Even though there might be contradictions, or difficulties, or heartbreaks, we see these things through the eyes of faith, and we know that God has permitted this thing.</p>

<p>If He gives me this cross, He’ll give me the grace to be able to carry it. There will be no trial that will be too much.</p>

<p>If we remember that we are just children of God, children of Mary, we know that He will never let us down. The millions and millions of people that go to Lourdes every year, in many ways that's what they're stating with their feet. They go there to entrust themselves once again to Our Lady, telling her that we know that she will never give us more than we can handle.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Do everything possible and ask for what is impossible” (<em>cf</em>. St. Augustine, <em>Treatise on Nature and Grace</em>).</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to say, “We're not just here to do the possible, anybody can do the possible; we're here to do the impossible” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 216).</p>

<p>When you look at the history of that particular religious order, you see that in many ways they've achieved the impossible.</p>

<p>Some of them were telling me that when they set up Loreto Limuru, the first school for African girls in the whole of East Africa, sometimes they didn't have food to eat. or in the emergency, the bullets were flying with the Mau Mau, all sorts of amazing challenges. But yet they hung in there.</p>

<p>Some of them were saying that when they got the initial girls that came to the first school, they managed to convince some of the chiefs to try and educate their daughters. Education was unheard of. The first group of ten or twelve came to the school, and within twenty-four hours, they all ran away. They had to be coaxed back to the school.</p>

<p>Then it was a boarding school. It was far away from where they lived, so they had to live in conditions, and they had sacks that were filled with grass. That's what the mattresses were. It was all very rudimentary.</p>

<p>But little by little they got these girls to the stage of doing the Cambridge exam. It was a big thing to be able to send the papers of these girls, after decades, to be corrected in England and get that standard.</p>

<p>This nun told me that when they sent the papers of the girls to be corrected in England, the nuns kept a carbon copy of the answers of the girls, in case the ship went down. Wow. Nothing was to stand in the way of the education of these girls.</p>

<p>You hear an anecdote or two like that, and you realize, my goodness, these were some women, with incredible ideas. That's why Archbishop Kivuva was able to say they have changed the face of education in this country. They set the standards, and they did incredible things, in the face of all sorts of difficulties.</p>

<p>Of course, their great boast is Wangari Maathai, a Nobel Prize winner. Not every school can boast of that. But of course, to achieve those sorts of things, there's commitment, there's ideals, there's the whole missionary thrust of the Church, the whole social teaching of the Church.</p>

<p>I wrote a bit of an article about this event, and I was saying: You know, we hear an awful lot about the empowerment of women in the world today in the 21st century, as though this is something enormously new.</p>

<p>But if you look back 100 years ago, these women were full of the ideals of the empowerment of women. It's very deeply there, the social teaching of the Catholic Church.</p>

<p>And they had to overcome all sorts of obstacles to make it happen: colonial governments and powers and all sorts of things. That's why their school was far away from Nairobi, near the railway.</p>

<p>We see a story of people going forward, step by step, doing things with the help of Our Lady, not being held back by anything, by any human force. We learn from this how we have to try and have that same faith.</p>

<p>John Paul II talked about how the vocation, or anybody's vocation, but particularly the vocation of Our Lady, was “a pilgrimage of faith” (John Paul II, <em>General Audience</em>, March 21, 2001; Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 58). A pilgrimage is a journeying forward, step by step.</p>

<p>The whole of your marriage vocation is a pilgrimage of faith. The whole of your Christian vocation, your apostolic vocation—there's always something for us to do. God is working there behind the scenes all the time.</p>

<p>We find many people going to shrines of Our Lady. Here in this country we have national shrines in Subukia; there's another one coming up in Kitui. Probably they will mushroom over time.</p>

<p>It’s a pretty good thing to let our children and grandchildren be aware of these places, or to go on pilgrimages there from time to time.</p>

<p>We hope to foster Marian piety, so that people also know the history of these sorts of places—particularly Lourdes, the major Marian shrine in the world—and to see how it's a place for them to go to, or a devotion to Our Lady of Lourdes, in time of difficulty.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to ask the question, “Why is it precisely the sick who go on pilgrimage to Lourdes?” He says, “...because the Mother of Jesus is there” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, February 11, 1980).</p>

<p>Some powerful, attractive force. She draws them there with great power because they know that she's there somehow.</p>

<p>I heard a story recently about a very good father somewhere in the rural States. On the parish grounds, there was a grotto of Our Lady of Lourdes, as there are all over the world.</p>

<p>He had a young son, and he wanted to have the son to have a lot of Marian piety. The son happened to ask him, “What's this grotto all about?”</p>

<p>He said, “Well, this is a very, very famous grotto. It goes back a long way in history, and there's one just like it in France. This was the major one here in our parish.” Some people get the story a little bit wrong, but at least the intentions are there.</p>

<p>John Paul II says, “The miraculous cure remains, however, in spite of everything, an exceptional event. Christ's salvific power, propitiated by the intercession of His Mother, is revealed at Lourdes, particularly in the spiritual sphere. It is in the hearts of the sick that Mary makes the voice of her Son heard: a voice that dissolves miraculously the stiffening of bitterness and rebellion, and restores eyes to the soul to see in a new light the world, others, and one's destiny” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>To people who may be suffering a lot, or long term, or God may have afflicted them with special things, this story that their suffering can be worthwhile, can be reunited to the Cross of Christ, and have enormous meritorious value—this changes everything.</p>

<p>It makes them thank God for the crosses that He sends them. It helps them to see each day in a different way. We see that all the little difficult things that we may do—it's all earning great rewards for us in heaven.</p>

<p>Our Lady leads us to her Son, who has a special love for the sick. Christ went around the place “doing good and healing all…” (Acts 10:38).</p>

<p>He loved to heal people. He didn’t heal the whole world, but He did heal an awful lot of people.</p>

<p>We see how Christ reaches out to them. We can also see in the people we know, elderly or sick, that Christ is there in this person. “Whenever you did it to one of these little ones, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>It can be a very consoling thought when we reach out in some way to people that we needn't reach out to, or we go the extra mile, or we go out of our way in some way, or maybe we don't get any thanks, or we're not appreciated: “Whenever you did it to one of these little ones, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Tell Our Lord, We're doing it for you. It's not just for human thanks or human glory.</p>

<p>John Paul liked to say, “Christ was sensitive to every human suffering, whether of the body or of the soul” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici</em> <em>Doloris</em>, Point 16, February 11, 1984). There are many people in the world who are suffering.</p>

<p>We are on the weekend of the hearts, the 14th of February, all around the place, and Valentine's. Everybody's talking about hearts, and we see lovely hearts all drawn beautifully, and they all link up together again.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to say that our hearts are not like that, because God has taken a piece of our heart, and He's kept it for Himself in heaven. We only get that piece of our heart back when we go to heaven.</p>

<p>When we pray for a while, maybe He gives it back to us for a while as well. But he said we all suffer from a hole in the heart, and that hole can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>Nothing in this world satisfies it. If those Valentine's Day hearts drew the truth, there'd be a big jagged edge missing from all of those hearts.</p>

<p>“Our hearts are restless, Lord, until they rest in you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>).</p>

<p>Christ allowed His heart to be fit by a lance on the Cross, allowed His heart to be broken, so that He could be like the patron saint of all broken hearts.</p>

<p>Our Lady allowed her heart to be pierced by a spiritual sword (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35), so that she could be there also.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says, “Only Christ and Our Lady can mend broken hearts, but you've got to give them all the pieces.”</p>

<p>There was an English Lord who was in Nairobi about ten years ago. He came to give a talk at an Ethics Conference at Strathmore University: Lord Alton. He is the main Catholic peer.</p>

<p>In his discourse, he said one thing that was rather interesting. He said, “Only Christianity can change the hearts of men. Governments can't, NGOs can't. Only Christ can, only Christianity.”</p>

<p>This is one of the great powers of the Church, the power to change the hearts of men. We have an inroad into every human heart.</p>

<p>Our Lady has that inroad, the capacity to change hearts with beauty, with truth, and with love. Our Mother is there guiding us to those hearts, that we can give that witness, in our family, in our neighborhood, in the things we do, in the way that we carry the crosses that He gives us, knowing that there will always be sufficient graces, in difficult circumstances, that we can use to draw our friends closer to Him.</p>

<p>We can certainly ask Our Lord to heal our infirmities and resolve our problems. We can ask Him that we might be more docile to His grace, and increase our faith, our hope, our charity.</p>

<p>There were many things initially that Bernadette did not understand. It took quite a while for her to grasp what was taking place. But then, with her correspondence, as she entered a convent, she underwent a lot of sufferings in her life. And she died young, but always happy.</p>

<p>We can put our pains and our sufferings in the hands of God.</p>

<p>“Therefore,” He says, “do not be anxious about tomorrow, for tomorrow will have anxieties of its own. Sufficient for the day is its own trouble” (Matt. 6:34).</p>

<p>Everybody has a cross to carry. We solve all our problems by thinking about the others, helping that other person to correspond generously to the will of God for them.</p>

<p>One spiritual writer says, “Suffering, which in the eyes of men is so disagreeable, can be a fountain of sanctification and apostolate when it is united to Christ” (Adolphe Tanquerey, <em>The Divinization of Suffering</em>).</p>

<p>It is the great secret of Christianity that we have to communicate to other people: there is an opportunity to co-redeem with Jesus, to be beside Mary on the Cross, to atone to their hearts for all the ways in which their hearts suffer.</p>

<p>Many times, when Our Lady appeared, she talked about that heart of Christ’s that was suffering: “Behold, this heart that has loved men so much...and all I get in return are insults. And it is those that are most consecrated to me very often that hurt me most.” These were Christ’s words to St. Margaret Mary Alacoque (Émile Bougaud, <em>Life of the Blessed Margaret Mary Alacoque</em>).</p>

<p>We are called to atone to that heart of Mary, that Immaculate Heart, to offer her things that ease the pain, that say that we’re sorry, that we want to improve our life. We know that Our Mother will give us consolation, she’s Consoler of the Afflicted, Help of the Sick, Help of Christians.</p>

<p>She is always there in all those moments for us to go to her. Mary, Our Lady of Lourdes, may we spread your message with our words and with our actions.</p>

<p>May we foster that devotion to you, which we know you want us to spread around the place, and help many people to find consolation in finding joy in your Immaculate Heart.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Priestly Society of the Holy Cross</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Priestly Society of the Holy Cross" /><published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Like living stones, let yourself be built into a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ” (1 Pet. 2:5), we are told in the letter of Saint Peter. Today is the anniversary of the founding of the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría was a diocesan priest. He had great love for all diocesan priests and all priests, but he particularly wanted to do something, and saw that God wanted him to do something, to help diocesan priests, particularly in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>On the one hand, he saw that he was called to found Opus Dei, but he was all the time searching for a way whereby that spirit of Opus Dei and the formation that was there could be extended to diocesan priests. Little by little, God let him see that that was possible.</p>

<p>On the 14th of February 1943, the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross was born. The Priestly Society is an association of priests inseparably united to Opus Dei.</p>

<p>All the formation that lay people receive in Opus Dei—to sanctify their work, to be holy in the middle of the world—priests also can receive. It provides ongoing formation for priests to help them in their spiritual life and professional life through all the various means that Opus Dei uses: regular Confessions, spiritual direction, circles, retreats, seminars.</p>

<p>It tries to foster a great priestly fraternity among the clergy, all the time in very close union with the bishop. There was a juridical problem because diocesan priests could not become members of Opus Dei because their superior is their bishop. The association of priests was formed whereby the Prelate of Opus Dei is concurrently the president of the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross.</p>

<p>That way the juridical bond of the diocesan priest with their bishop to whom they are answerable, and his care for them, is maintained. They benefit from the spirit of Opus Dei while maintaining themselves juridically incardinated in their diocese.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say that today is a day of prayer for priests. He indicated a number of special days in the year for that.</p>

<p>The anniversary of the first three priests of Opus Dei is on June 25th and the Feast of the Curé of Ars, the patron saint of all parish priests, is on August 4th. It’s a day of prayer for priests, priests of the universal Church, and also very particularly, priests of the Prelature.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría brought something like a thousand priests to the altar. Blessed Álvaro brought about 700. He’s taught us to have a great love for the institution of the priesthood, to have great love and respect for priests.</p>

<p>While priests are ordained to the ministerial priesthood, he liked to remind all lay people that they also have a participation in what is called the common priesthood of the faithful, or the universal priesthood of the faithful, that we receive with our Baptism.</p>

<p>Even though we might not be ordained to the ministerial priesthood, we are all called to live out our priesthood in union with Christ on the Cross. And ultimately that’s what priestly soul means: having the same sentiments as Christ on the Cross.</p>

<p>Lay people are not ordained to administer the sacraments, which is the main function of the ordained ministry, priestly ministry. The lay people are called to order the temporal realities.</p>

<p>While they have a priestly soul, they’re called to have a fully lay mentality. The priestly society gives this ongoing formation to priests to help them to sanctify their priestly work, to be holy in and through their ministry, to be priests 100 percent, good shepherds to the others, and to benefit in this way from all of the things which the spirit of Opus Dei gives us in terms of formation.</p>

<p>The first three priests of Opus Dei—their process of beatification is ongoing. This thing of holiness in and through the ministry is not just a nebulous idea, but something very concrete.</p>

<p>We’re told also in St. Peter, “You are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God’s own people, in order that you may proclaim the mighty acts of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light” (1 Pet. 2:9).</p>

<p>Any way that we can help our parish priests or other diocesan priests to grow in their vocation; it is something we should try and foster.</p>

<p>If you have the means to help your local priest get to an annual retreat or to a seminar or some other means of formation, it’s a very good thing to try and achieve.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say that every priest can bring a thousand souls to heaven. So, one way of fostering evangelization is that prayer and care for priests, helping them to care for their vocation, being close to them in the parish, helping them to understand also the spirit of Opus Dei through your example, through your words, through your apostolates, in all the things that we do.</p>

<p>What is a priest? A priest is somebody who offers sacrifices. In the priesthood of the Old Testament, the priest offered the sacrifices of animals, the blood of goats and cows and heifers.</p>

<p>In the New Testament, the priest also offers sacrifices. He offers the blood of Christ. The main duty of the priest is to celebrate the Mass. And when we’re called to have the priestly soul, a priestly soul is something we receive at Baptism when that character is imprinted on our soul—the seal of Baptism that gives us a participation in the priesthood of Christ.</p>

<p>Christ was most a priest when He offered Himself in sacrifice to His heavenly Father. He practiced all the priestly virtues of humility, of sacrifice, of service, of obedience, of generosity. In our daily life, we have ample opportunities on a regular basis to practice these virtues.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. John, “In truth, I tell you, unless the grain of wheat falls into the ground and dies, it remains only a single grain; but if it dies, it yields a rich harvest” (John 12:24).</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “I urge you then, brethren, remembering the mercies of God, to offer your bodies as a living sacrifice, dedicated and acceptable to God. That is the kind of worship for you as sensible people” (Rom. 12:1).</p>

<p>We’re invited to make of our lives a holocaust, to live out our priesthood in the ordinary events of every day. It’s not just those who are ordained to the ministerial priesthood that live their priesthood. But the Second Vatican Council talked about the ‘universal priesthood of the faithful” (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 10, November 21, 1964; <em>Presbyterorum ordinis</em>, Point 2, December 7, 1965).</p>

<p>In that sense, we’re all priests. We’re called to live out our common or universal priesthood in our work, in our apostolate, in the fulfillment of our family duties, in our marriage, in saying “no” to ourselves, in uniting ourselves to the Cross of Christ and being there with Jesus.</p>

<p>The exercise of our priesthood means above all to serve. We are all called to serve. That’s the purpose of our formation and of all education.</p>

<p>There was a professor once who asked some students in secondary school, Why were they in this school with the Catholic ethos? They said, ‘We’re here to do well in our final exam so that we can get a good result, so we can get into a good university, so we can get a good degree, so we can get a good job, so we can get a good salary.’ He said that wasn’t a very good answer.</p>

<p>He went to some university students in a university with a Catholic ethos and asked them the same question. They said, ‘We’re here in this university to study and to get a good degree so we can get a good job, so we can get a good salary.’</p>

<p>This professor said, This represents the failure of Catholic education, because the purpose of all Catholic education is to serve, “because Christ came not to be served, but to serve” (<em>cf</em>. Mark 10:45).</p>

<p>We’re called to exercise our priestly soul through service. A priest who is ordained to the ministerial priesthood is ordained to serve. That’s the purpose of his ministry. All priesthood leads to that.</p>

<p>Mother Teresa tells a story of how one time a journalist came to her and asked her, What was her opinion of women priests? She said, “I often think that the person who was most cut out to be a priest was Our Lady, because she was the most dignified person that was ever created. She was conceived without original sin. She was full of grace. She had some very special privileges because of her divine maternity. There was nobody who was created so suitable for the priesthood as Our Lady. But yet her vocation was to be ‘the handmaid of the Lord’” (Luke 1:38).</p>

<p>The following day in the newspaper, Mother Teresa said there was a headline that said, ‘Mother Teresa says that women make better priests than men.’ She had to get someone to call the newspaper and say, “That wasn’t exactly what I said.”</p>

<p>Somebody else said once that a woman who wants to be a priest is as misguided as a man who wants to be pregnant. We need to get very clear ideas. If we hear women talking about the fact of how they would like to be priests, it means they have not understood the concept of the common or universal priesthood of the faithful.</p>

<p>It was very clearly expounded in the Second Vatican Council that we are already priests. We have a priestly soul. We’re called to serve.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Letter to the Hebrews, “Every high priest is taken from among human beings and is appointed to act on their behalf in relationships with God, to offer gifts and sacrifices for sins” (Heb. 5:1).</p>

<p>One time in Rome in the early 1950s, there was a consistory about to take place where they appointed cardinals. One young fellow said to St. Josemaría in a get-together: ‘Father, maybe you will be made a cardinal.’</p>

<p>St. Josemaría changed the topic very quickly but afterwards called him to his room. This young person was a medical doctor. St. Josemaría pulled up his cassock and pulled up his shirt and pulled up his undershirt and showed him a big red rash that he had across his chest.</p>

<p>The doctor immediately recognized the rash as the rash of shingles, herpes zoster, a very painful infection of the nerve roots, where people usually have a fever. They’re often in the hospital. Yet St. Josemaría was walking around and talking at that get-together and working as if nothing was the matter.</p>

<p>He pointed to the red of the rash and said, “My son, this is the only red that God has in mind for me, not the red of a cardinal’s hat.”</p>

<p>Many decades later, that medical student, Don Julián Herranz, was made a cardinal. I’m sure he remembered those words of St. Josemaría’s.</p>

<p>With our priestly soul, we take the blows, we offer up the sacrifices. We’re willing to be with Christ on the Cross. We find so many solutions to our problems there.</p>

<p>One time there was a get-together on Easter Sunday night. John Paul II invited the UNIV students to an inner patio there in the Vatican called the San Damaso.</p>

<p>At the end of the sort of get-together they had, a musical get-together, he said, “I am very happy to see all of you here from different countries. So youthful, so happy and so united among yourselves from different places, different cultures, and different backgrounds, but yet there’s a great unity among you.”</p>

<p>The master of ceremonies who had the microphone, a young student, was very quick, and added to that: “United to you, Holy Father.”</p>

<p>And as quick as a wink, the Holy Father, without missing a beat, immediately said, <em>uniti in Cristo</em>, united to Christ. It was a beautiful, spontaneous expression of the priestly soul, everything in our life united to Christ.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story about how he went to see Pope Paul VI in 1968, just after the issuing of the encyclical of <em>Humanae Vitae</em>, which is all about the regulation of birth and conjugal love. Beautiful document. A major document of the 20th century. It was also known as the document that banned contraception.</p>

<p>The Holy Father was getting an awful lot of flack in the international press. Fulton Sheen said to him, “Holy Father, you’re well named Paul, because Paul they stoned, and now they’re stoning you.”</p>

<p>The Holy Father said, “Yes, it’s 10 in the evening before I get to open my personal mail, and with each letter, there comes a thorn. When I lie down on my bed at night, I lie down on a crown of thorns.”</p>

<p>“But,” he said, “I can’t tell you the joy, the happiness, the peace I get out of knowing that I’m making up in my body of what is lacking in the sufferings of Christ.”</p>

<p>With that, he was quoting St. Paul to the Colossians, who says, “It makes me happy to be suffering for you now. And in my own body, to make up all the hardships that still have to be undergone by Christ for the sake of his body, the Church” (Col. 1:24).</p>

<p>There is nothing lacking in the sufferings of Christ. But what is lacking is our participation in those sufferings.</p>

<p>Really, what the Holy Father was expressing was that sentiment of priestly soul that’s there within him, finding joy and peace and happiness.</p>

<p>There may be some time in our life when we come across somebody with a broken heart. This week, around the 14th of February, the whole world is looking at hearts and selling hearts and buying hearts. They’re all beautiful hearts. The hearts that are drawn on Valentine’s Day cards, one line links up with the other. Very complete hearts.</p>

<p>But Pope St. John Paul said that our hearts are not like that. He said, God has taken a piece of our heart, and He’s kept it for Himself in heaven. We only get it back when we go there.</p>

<p>“Our hearts are restless, Lord, until they rest in you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions,</em> Book 1:1-2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul said we all suffer from a hole in the heart, and that hole can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>Even though these days we see so many beautiful, complete hearts, we also know from the human experience that hearts can be broken. Our Lady’s heart was pierced by a sword, a spiritual sword (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35).</p>

<p>Christ’s heart was pierced by a lance and there flowed out blood and water (John 19:34), the fountain of the sacramental life of the Church. We know that all these things can happen.</p>

<p>Our hearts may be broken some time, or we might meet people with broken hearts. Fulton Sheen said that if ever God allows hearts to be broken, it’s because He wants to enter into them a little more (<em>cf</em>. Fulton J. Sheen, <em>Through</em> the <em>Year with Fulton J. Sheen</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lady and Our Lord whose hearts are pierced, they’re a bit like the patron saints of broken hearts. They can mend all broken hearts.</p>

<p>If ever you meet someone with a broken heart, lead them to Jesus, to Mary. They find their peace and their serenity there. They learn how to begin again.</p>

<p>The heart is very important in our faith. God reads the heart. “Rend your heart and not your garments. Come back to me with all your heart” (Joel 2:12-13).</p>

<p>Our priestly soul also leads us to have a great desire to spread truth, to give doctrine, to spread doctrine in every way we can, which are good ideas, the ideas of Christ and the ideas with which He wants us to shape the world.</p>

<p>That priestly soul leads us to spend ourselves for souls, to give ourselves to the apostolate with our whole heart and mind, seeing it’s the greatest occupation and ideal we could have that fills our day and every hour with meaning and with purpose.</p>

<p>Christ came to save souls. The Church is all about souls. That apostolic zeal adds a great dynamism to our life.</p>

<p>Therefore, that leads us to never say ‘enough’ or ‘up to here and no further.’ Those words don’t exist.</p>

<p>We’ve come to give ourselves. Christ emptied Himself. He didn’t just shed one drop of His blood, but He let His blood flow copiously on the Cross.</p>

<p>We’re called to offer everything. We hold nothing back.</p>

<p>If we look at Christ on the Cross, we can get a great encouragement, an example there, a beckoning to fall in love with Him, to follow Him, and to never leave Him.</p>

<p>Our priestly soul finds perfect expression in the Mass and in the prayers of the Mass and the liturgy that can be so meaningful. In the <em>Preface</em> of the First Sunday in Ordinary Time, it says:</p>

<p>“Father, all-powerful and every living God. We do well always and everywhere to give you thanks, through Jesus Christ, Our Lord. Through his cross and resurrection, he freed us from sin and death and has called us to the glory that he has made us a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people set apart. Everywhere we proclaim your mighty works, for you have called us out of darkness into your own wonderful light.”</p>

<p>We’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>: “You say that you’re now beginning to understand what a ‘priestly soul’ means. Don’t be annoyed with me if I tell you that the facts show that you only realize it in theory. —Every day the same thing happens to you: at nighttime, during the examination, it’s all desire and resolutions; during the morning and afternoon at work, it’s all objections and excuses. Are you in this way living a ‘holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ’ (1 Pet. 2:5)?” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 499).</p>

<p>We have a priestly soul, but lay people are also called to live out their priestly soul with a very lay mentality. That’s the way that God wants us to live out our priestly soul in all situations.</p>

<p>To be a layperson is a real vocation. It has certain characteristics. Lay people are not called to imitate priests in the way they talk, the way they walk, and what they talk about. Lay people are called to be fully lay people.</p>

<p>If everybody is talking about football, then we talk about football, or whatever is the thing that people in the middle of the world talk about. We’re not meant to be ‘churchy,’ but rather, fully lay and fully up to date with the ordinary things that lay people do.</p>

<p>That priestly soul has a lot of applications. It can mean our total availability for whatever is necessary for the apostolate. It can be very useful in moments when we come to see our miseries, our limitations, and the ups and downs of each day—to carry on there where God has placed us, in this marriage, in this family, in this job—in persevering in spite of my failures, beginning again.</p>

<p>We can thank God for the priestly occasions when we don’t have what we need or what we’d like to have. It’s a moment to offer our minds and heart and soul to God and say, “Here I am because you’ve called me” (1 Sam. 3:5-10).</p>

<p>With our priestly soul, we overcome the obstacles with the spirit of the beginnings, because we know that God is with us and united to our lay mentality. It doesn’t allow us to remain passive in the face of difficulties.</p>

<p>If on some occasion we have a little bit of extra work—in cleaning or in the kitchen or in cooking at Christmas time, or we find everybody wants a barbecue, or somebody is sick in the house—these are opportunities to offer these things to God with our priestly soul.</p>

<p>Or someday we’re not feeling well, or we have to overcome our whims and our caprices, or we feel a bit rebellious—these are times to offer things to God, persevering in the apostolate entrusted to us, and the jobs that are given to us.</p>

<p>The more we think this and live it, the more truly lay mentality we’ll also have. We can ask Our Lord for the grace to live out this priestly soul a little better.</p>

<p>All the time we find Our Lady standing beside the Cross. Mary lived her priestly soul at that moment more than any other.</p>

<p><em>Stabat Mater dolorosa, iuxta Crucem lacrimósa, dum pendébat Fílius</em>. The Stabat Mater that we read on the Feast of Our Lady of Sorrows, the sequence of that Mass, is very eloquent.</p>

<p>Our Lady is the Lady of Fair Weeping. Her tears are beautiful. She has the sorrows of the one who is all beauty, fully free from the deformity of sin.</p>

<p>One writer says the sinless Spirit-filled heart of Mary is beautifully centered on the will of the Father.</p>

<p>Our Lady lived out her priestly soul by fully accepting the will of God in that moment of the Cross. She gives, she offers, she doesn’t merely let go. She doesn’t just tolerate. She doesn’t assist passively or patiently at the sacrifice of her Son. She’s totally involved.</p>

<p>That’s why the Church called her a co-redeemer. [Update: In <em>Mater Populi Fidelis</em>, a Doctrinal Note issued by the Dicastery for the Doctrine of the Faith with Pope Leo XIV’s approval on November 4, 2025, it was clarified in Points 3, 21, 22 that while her unique cooperation is acknowledged, she is not a co-redeemer nor co-redemptrix.]</p>

<p>St. Albert said, “Our Lady joined herself to the Father of Mercies in his greatest work of mercy when she shared in the Passion of her Son and ‘thus became the helper of our redemption and the Mother of our spiritual generation’” (Albertus Magnus, <em>Summa Theologica</em> <em>IV, 15</em>).</p>

<p>With that poem, the Stabat Mater from the sequence of Pentecost Sunday, we could say: <em>Fac, ut árdeat cor meum in amándo Christum Deum</em>. Make my heart to burn in loving Christ Our Lord.</p>

<p>When Cardinal Ratzinger visited Cavabianca in 1987, he said the Prelature of the Holy Cross in Opus Dei invites its members to stand by Mary there, that Our Lord may see us and each of us become a beloved disciple, hearing the words, “Behold your mother” (John 19:27).</p>

<p>Our Lady beside the Cross was silent. We can learn silence from Our Lady. Our silence can be a measure of our holocaust, of our unity to the Cross of Christ.</p>

<p>We can end our prayer by speaking to Our Lady, the Mother of all priests, thanking her for the priesthood of our Father, a priesthood that she helped so much and so continuously all throughout his life.</p>

<p>Help us, Mother, to value the great institution of the priesthood, to love priests like our Father did, to pray for them, to support them, to see what we can do for the diocesan priesthood as God wants us to do, moving heaven and earth to support that priesthood in every way we can, because we know the great evangelizing influence it can have in every country and in the whole world.</p>

<p>Mary, Mother of the Redeemer, Mediatrix of All Graces, Mother of priests, pray for us now and always.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fidelity in Marriage</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/fidelity-in-marriage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fidelity in Marriage" /><published>2026-02-09T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-09T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/fidelity-in-marriage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/fidelity-in-marriage/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>A lawyer in Sydney, Australia tells a story of how one day an elderly couple came to see him. He was 86 and she was 83. The lawyer asked them, “What can I do for you?”</p>

<p>And they said, “We want to get a divorce.”</p>

<p>“Why do you want to get a divorce?” “Because we don’t love each other anymore.”</p>

<p>“How long have you been married?” “Forty years.”</p>

<p>The lawyer tried to quickly recall all the points from the meditation he heard about charity and perseverance and fidelity on his last retreat, and he gave them an impromptu talk.</p>

<p>“Charity is patient, charity is kind” (1 Cor. 13:4). It’s beginning again. It’s loving other people with their defects. It’s letting the waters pass under the bridge. It’s not making a mountain out of a molehill, et cetera.</p>

<p>He asked them to go away, think about it for a while, come back some other day, and they would talk a little more. The couple went away, and three years later the wife came back.</p>

<p>She said, “I’ve just come back to tell you that my husband just passed away. But I want to thank you because we’ve just had three of the most wonderful years of our whole life.”</p>

<p>The moral of the story is that we’re always beginning again in love. Love is a mystery. “God is love” (1 John 4:8).</p>

<p>In the course of our life, we try to learn a little more about that mystery of love. Perseverance and fidelity in marriage are very much based on love and keeping that love alive—taking care of that love.</p>

<p>We have the grace from the sacrament to help that to happen. St. Paul says, “My grace is sufficient for you” (2 Cor. 12:9).</p>

<p>He also says; “Let us never slacken in doing good, for if we do not give up, we shall have a harvest in due time” (Gal. 6:9).</p>

<p>We have to keep trying to persevere in doing good, working at our marriage, beginning again; keeping our love young and fresh after many years like it was before we got married.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to give great importance to details (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 122; <em>The Forge</em>, Point 870, etc.). Love is in the details. Perfection is in the details. It’s remembering little things. It’s sweeping the other party off their feet from time to time with little gestures of love and affection.</p>

<p>There is a song by Julio Iglesias in Spain many years ago. It’s the lament of a man whose loved one has left him. The title of the song is <em>Me Olvidé de Vivir los Detalles Pequeños–</em>I Forgot to Take Care of the Small Details. Often those small details can cost us a little bit.</p>

<p>The Lord said, “If anyone wants to be a follower of mine, let him renounce himself and take up his cross every day and follow me” (Matt. 16:24).</p>

<p>That’s quite a program for marriage: to renounce ourselves, forget about ourselves, and take up the cross that God has planned for us. That’s the marriage vocation.</p>

<p>We have a vocation that comes with our Baptism: a vocation to holiness. Then there’s a specification of that vocation over the years and in the course of our life.</p>

<p>One of the specifications of that vocation is our vocation to marriage—to this particular person at this particular time in history; in this particular place; with these particular difficulties of finance, of health, of employment.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “We’ve been chosen out before the foundation of the world” (<em>cf</em>. Eph. 1:4). Every aspect of our life has been chosen by God. Nothing is an accident.</p>

<p>God wants us to work then at making our marriage a success, and in making our family life a success, so that the domestic Church can really be everything that it’s supposed to be: a pathway to holiness, a seedbed of vocations.</p>

<p>That means each spouse has to try and live like a great human person—a great human person that gives example to children of what being a great human person means—which ultimately means virtue. Living the virtues in a concrete way.</p>

<p>By doing so, we reveal gold—spiritual gold—to the other members of our family, to our spouse, to our neighbors, to our friends.</p>

<p>But gold nuggets don’t sit on top of the soil. One needs to dig. Often, one has to dig with patience, with constancy, with effort. One has to begin and begin again with a new hope, with a new perseverance.</p>

<p>And so, perseverance in marriage is a gift of God. It’s a grace that we have to ask for. Pray for it. Ask for it. It’s the fruit of faith, of hope, of love.</p>

<p>Our perseverance in our marriage vocation makes many things possible. It’s a commitment of love. We’re committed.</p>

<p>It’s not something that’s superficial. We’re not a fly-by-night when it comes to this particular reality. We’ve given our word, and love seeks to be definitive.</p>

<p>God will always give us the power to go on, even if we feel we don’t have any more energy, or willpower, or desire.</p>

<p>To love is to do things God’s way. He said, “I am the way, the truth, and the life” (John 14:6).</p>

<p>In Christ, we find the meaning and the purpose of our life (<em>cf</em>. Pope John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, August 14, 1993), and very particularly, in Christ on the Cross we find the meaning and the purpose of our life.</p>

<p>We draw close to the Sacred Humanity of Christ and to His wounds: “To draw water, in joy, from the wells of salvation” (Isa. 12:3).</p>

<p>If we trust in Him, we will not be disappointed. We derive our strength from Christ for the battles that we need.</p>

<p>We can “leave the past to God’s mercy, the future to God’s providence” (St. Augustine) and live “the sacrament of this moment” (Jean Pierre de Caussade). It’s a gift.</p>

<p>A sacrament is something that has a visible and an invisible part. We’re living out the sacrament of this moment: what we see, what we feel, what we hear.</p>

<p>But there’s an invisible part. God lives in an eternal now and we know that He has a gold medal prepared for us. It does not corrode. There is merit in struggle, and God wants us to get that merit.</p>

<p>Love is a decision: ‘I will love you into heaven.’</p>

<p>We know that in the battles and the challenges and the journeys of every day, the winds may blow. But if the house is founded on rock—not just the rock of doctrine, but the rock of family life, of apostolate, of Our Lady—the building will not fall.</p>

<p>But for this, we need to struggle. We need to sacrifice ourselves. Sacrifice needs to be always present in our daily life.</p>

<p>Sometimes, perseverance needs sacrifice. If you look at any of the long-distance runners, Kenyan runners that win the marathons all over the world, there’s tremendous sacrifice there. There’s tremendous perseverance.</p>

<p>We’ve got to be careful with that perseverance. To put our perseverance in danger could be a serious sin of infidelity to God in this wonderful commitment of love that God wants us to live out.</p>

<p>At the bottom of all infidelity, there is a pocket of corruption. Something that wasn’t right from the start. Something that needs to be clarified.</p>

<p>That’s one of the reasons why we have to be very careful about our formation: our marriage formation, our spiritual formation, our doctrinal formation.</p>

<p>The Church places an awful lot of importance on formation. Often in parishes, there’s a pre-marriage course or pre-marriage formation. But of course, the whole of our marriage isn’t just prepared for in one short seminar on a quick weekend.</p>

<p>We start preparing for our marriage in primary school, in our own families, in what we see in the lives of our parents, and how we build family life at home.</p>

<p>We work at that marriage preparation through high school, possibly through third-level education. A lot of it involves the formation in virtue.</p>

<p>But humans are fickle-minded. All the apostles said “yes” to Christ, but one changed his mind.</p>

<p>The passing things of this world can never be the source of our happiness. So, we have to be a little bit careful with football, or fashion, or the movies, or professional success.</p>

<p>Our happiness has to come from much deeper things. We find our happiness in the risen Lord.</p>

<p>Just like our marriage, life may not be a romance all the time. There might be periods of dryness, or no ideas, or no affections.</p>

<p>Our spiritual life might be the same. But we’ve got to work at it. Go back and begin again.</p>

<p>The goal of our fidelity is not just for fifty years’ time, but in this moment. It cannot just depend on our mood, on our health, on our hormones, on our family situation.</p>

<p>Fidelity is something dynamic. It’s not static. It finds expression every day.</p>

<p>Mother Teresa was once asked if she really thought that all the things she was doing could make an impact in the poverty of India. Would she be able to solve all the problems of India? The problems of poverty?</p>

<p>Her answer was very quick: “I am not called to be successful. I am [just] called to be faithful” (Art Beals with Larry Libby, <em>Beyond Hunger: Biblical Mandate for Social Responsibility–Foreword</em> by Mark O. Hatfield).</p>

<p>There’s a lot of wisdom for that in every Christian vocation in the world. I may not be very successful in building my family, in building my marriage, in earning money, in my profession, in various areas.</p>

<p>But I am called to be faithful—and to try to do so with a sense of humor and perspective, so that I never give up on the ideal of marriage and married love.</p>

<p>If the solutions to the problems of marriage and family in the world today don’t come from the Catholic Church, they’re not going to come from anywhere, because we have the truth. We have the answers. It’s all there in the documents of the Church. Spiritual treasures.</p>

<p>We have to try and know very well the ideal of marriage and married love to understand what love is. Human love is one of the most beautiful realities on the planet. It’s a reflection of divine love. That’s why the devil has gone to so much trouble to mess it up for young people.</p>

<p>Our marriage vocation is a vocation to witness to the truth of authentic love—the truth, the beauty, and the meaning of conjugal love. That’s why fidelity in marriage is always moving and inspiring.</p>

<p>Fidelity is to fall in love with God—to grow in this day by day, and to foster this around us; to focus on one thing, not many.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to Martha, “Only one thing is necessary” (Luke 10:42). It’s not difficult to persevere in marriage. The vast majority of people persevere.</p>

<p>At the same time, fidelity doesn’t come with age. Often, older people don’t persevere. If ever that’s the case, it’s because there’s been a focal point of corruption earlier. People did not want to keep struggling. They were not in love enough with their marriage vocation.</p>

<p>Virtues are manifestations of love. When love disappears, all the virtues disappear—and a lot of human things: human talents, abilities, intelligence, big degrees, prestige, well-paying jobs, apostolic successes. These don’t necessarily make us faithful and persevering. We’ve got to work at it out of commitment to the ideals at the beginning.</p>

<p>It would be crazy to worry about whether or not I’m going to persevere in my marriage. We just have to try and live today, try and persevere today, to trust, to hope, to identify ourselves with Christ, and to renew our generosity all the time.</p>

<p>Generosity is a very beautiful virtue. Authentic love leads us to be generous.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord: Lord, give me the heart with which you want me to love you in and through my marriage and my family, so that I can “sing a new song unto the Lord” (Ps. 98:1).</p>

<p>The sureness of divine love that is with us is shown in cheerfulness. ‘Lord, may others see God in me—sometimes in my defects, but in the defects in which I struggle.’</p>

<p>Our first loyalty is to God through our vocation—to live out today the duties of my state that God has placed in front of me, and to fight to place myself at the service of my spouse, of my family.</p>

<p>Because that’s what it’s all about: all our formation, all our education has the goal of service, because Christ “did not come to be served, but to serve” (Matt. 20:28).</p>

<p>Often, our beginning again in marriage is a question of beginning again in our service. How can I serve better? What is wanted of me? What can I contribute in this particular moment or situation?</p>

<p>Peter Drucker in <em>The Effective Executive</em> asked the question: What makes people effective? He says it’s because they ask themselves the right question. They don’t just do good things or ask themselves good questions. They do the right things because they ask themselves the right question. And the right question is: What can I contribute? What can I give?</p>

<p>If we can contribute something or give something in this situation, in this family gathering, in this family—even though my family members might be on the other side of the world—if I can contribute something that nobody else can contribute, that makes me effective.</p>

<p>If our children are relatively grown up, maybe our greatest effectiveness is through prayer or being faithful to our spiritual life, and giving that example of virtue, of fidelity, of perseverance.</p>

<p>An attitude to foster can be loyalty even on a human level: to be loyal to people, to be true to our word. “Let your ‘Yes’ be ‘Yes’ and your ‘No’ be ‘No’” (Matt. 5:37).</p>

<p>Fidelity is not staying out of other beds; it’s loving the bed that we’re in, with all of its characteristics. For fidelity, we need an inner toughness to dominate the ego, so that we’re not ruled by likes and dislikes.</p>

<p>Sometimes, we need to burn our bridges to give ourselves, to conquer our addictions, because we’re all addicted to something: our laziness, our selfishness, our football, our fashions, our food, our drink.</p>

<p>There was a story of a man in Mexico many years ago who, with his wife, used to go to the bullfights every Saturday afternoon. For twenty-five years without fail, they went to the bullfights every Saturday afternoon, until one day the wife said, “Let’s not go to the bullfights. I’m fed up going to the bullfights.”</p>

<p>The husband said, “Okay, let’s not go to the bullfights. I never really wanted to go to the bullfights anyway.” There was a man who knew how to keep his first love in first place.</p>

<p>With the passage of time, sometimes our other loves can creep into first and second place, and our first love can get relegated to fifth or sixth place.</p>

<p>Often, we need to rectify, go back, and put more order in things, to recognize that we are vessels of clay.</p>

<p>“We carry this treasure,” says St. Paul, “in vessels of clay” (2 Cor. 4:7). Earthenware vessels. We make mistakes. We put our foot in it. We do the wrong thing.</p>

<p>Difficulties to our fidelity can come from our human limitations—our weaknesses, sometimes our tiredness.</p>

<p>There can be a lack of love. There could be important external changes coming at a bad moment.</p>

<p>Never make long-term decisions, or decisions that affect us in the long term, in a low moment, because that low moment can seriously affect the decision we’re going to make.</p>

<p>There can also be difficulties from temporary blindness, a temporary blindness that can pass. It may blow away by next week.</p>

<p>Our Lord says, “The person who puts their hand to the plough and looks backward is not fit for the kingdom of heaven” (Luke 9:62).</p>

<p>Our goal is to keep our hand on the plough and keep looking forward. The devil often wants us to look back and to turn back. If we keep looking back, it won’t be long before we turn back.</p>

<p>We should try and keep our hand on the plough and keep looking to the future, because if we start looking back, we can start to place conditions on our proposed commitment, when we have committed ourselves to give ourselves completely. Unconditional surrender.</p>

<p>‘Dear Lord, help me not to look back.’</p>

<p>That Palestinian plough that Our Lord was talking about was a difficult plough. It wasn’t easy to direct. The soil in the fields beside the Sea of Galilee was hard soil, so it was difficult to direct and keep your hand on it.</p>

<p>The ploughman has to have a fixed point towards which he directs the plough through difficult ground. If not, he may not be able to open up a straight furrow.</p>

<p>At times, the temptation to look back can come from our own limitations, or from an environment that’s hostile to the obligations we’ve taken on.</p>

<p>Temptation may even be provided by the behavior of others who should be an example and are anything but. Because of the way they live, they seem to tell us that being faithful is not one of the basic values.</p>

<p>At other times, temptation could come from a lack of hope, when we see holiness in marriage as just a far-away thing, as remote an objective as ever, in spite of all of our efforts to keep on struggling.</p>

<p>“After the initial enthusiasm,” especially in the early years of marriage, “there could be doubts, hesitations, anxieties that all begin to take effect” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 133). If we’re forewarned against these things, we can be forearmed.</p>

<p>But we’ve given our word. When we give our word, in a certain sense we give ourselves. We put ‘on the line’ what is most intimate to ourselves.</p>

<p>In spite of our personal failings, a true disciple and follower of Christ will be honest and loyal, a man of his word. Whoever keeps His word is faithful.</p>

<p>There may be a lot of people, irrespective of their age, who seem ignorant of the noble obligation of keeping their word, to fulfill the commitments they once assumed with complete freedom, or to behave in accordance with the decisions they made before God or man, in civil or religious life.</p>

<p>Difficulties may arise, but the faith and the teaching of the Church and the example of the saints that have gone before us can show us that it is possible to live these virtues. God does not deny His grace to those who do what they can.</p>

<p>We must be firmly convinced and help others to have the same conviction: that it is possible to live all the virtues with all the demands that they make.</p>

<p>There is a certain idea that may be in vogue around the place: that virtues and commitments are ideals or goals to aim at, but without much hope of attaining them. But we could ask God that we might never fall into that error.</p>

<p>A Christian who is loyal will not cave in when upright moral behavior imposes or seems to impose serious difficulties.</p>

<p>We can ask God for an upright conscience to be ready to face all situations.</p>

<p>There was a planeload of travel agents who were going to an island off Argentina many years ago for a weekend to explore some new resorts so they could write about it and promote it.</p>

<p>Shortly after takeoff, somebody took the microphone and began talking about how “we’re going to have the weekend of our lives; we’re going to have a great time.” The picture he was painting was not particularly savory.</p>

<p>But then there was another man who tried to take care of his family formation and his spiritual life. He went and he took the microphone after this fellow and said, “Fine, let’s have a great time. Let’s have a wonderful weekend. But let’s just remember also that twenty minutes ago at the airport, we left our wife and our children. Let’s not do anything this weekend that might displease them.”</p>

<p>In just a couple of words, he changed the whole tone of the weekend. We have to be that sort of person, creating an atmosphere of fidelity around us; helping people to live in accordance with the commitments that they have made.</p>

<p>A person who may have a desire in theory to practice a particular virtue—they may not wish to sin, but in practice, when the temptation is great or when difficulties arise that are serious difficulties, they may feel justified in more or less giving in.</p>

<p>It can happen in a work situation, or when we’re faced with the obligation to react energetically when sensuality threatens to intervene, or when we need a serious effort to finance our children’s education, or to be faithful to our spouse or our vocation.</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture, “The rains fell, and the floods came, and the winds blew and beat upon that house; but it did not fall, because it was founded on rock” (Matt. 7:25).</p>

<p>We have to try and make sure that our marriage vocation is founded on rock.</p>

<p>Mary’s vocation was founded on rock. She and St. Joseph faced all sorts of uncertainties, risks, dangers. But yet they listened to what God was saying to them and everything worked out.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady with that great title <em>Virgo fidelis</em>, Virgin most faithful, that we might grow our fidelity to this particular marriage vocation that God has given to us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seed and Grace</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/seed-and-grace/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seed and Grace" /><published>2026-02-09T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-09T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/seed-and-grace</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/seed-and-grace/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“He also said, ‘This is what the kingdom of God is like. A man scatters seed on the land. Night and day, while he sleeps, when he is awake, the seed is sprouting and growing. How, he does not know. Of its own accord the land produces first the shoot, then the ear, then the full grain in the ear. And when the crop is ready, at once he starts to reap, because the harvest has come” (Mark 4:26-29).</p>

<p>St. Mark, writing the Gospel of St. Peter, includes this description of this agricultural process, something which Our Lord liked to return to again and again, possibly something that He learned from St. Joseph.</p>

<p>The main message of the seed growing, night and day, “How, he does not know. Of its own accord the land produces first the shoot, then the ear”—it’s a message for us that God’s grace always bears fruit if we do not place obstacles in the way.</p>

<p>Our Lord tells us how the seed grows when it’s planted in the ground. Once it has been sown, it grows independently of whether the owner of the field is asleep or keeps watch over it, or whether he knows what causes the growth.</p>

<p>These words can be very encouraging, because of all the seeds we sow in the lives of our children, in the home, in the classroom, in the school, on the football field, on the volleyball court, on the hockey pitch. Every little seed of virtue that we sow, every little bit of kindness, every bit of encouragement—and children need a lot of encouragement—none of this goes to waste.</p>

<p>Likewise, every seed that we sow in the spiritual formation of our children, and also in the spiritual lives of those around us—the seeds we sow are growing night and day because God’s grace is there, and we know with faith that all of these seeds will eventually bear fruit.</p>

<p>The seeds of grace sown in our own souls are just like that. There might be something we remember that a parent or a teacher said many years ago in the dim and distant past, or some anecdote will come back to us from some Standard Two class or something some uncle or grandmother said, but eventually, it all bears fruit.</p>

<p>If we don’t place any obstacles in its way, if we allow it to grow, that fruit will come. It doesn’t depend on the person who does the sowing, or the person doing the reaping. St. Paul says to the Corinthians, “God gives the growth” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 3:6-7).</p>

<p>We sow the seeds, and then we leave everything in God’s hands. We pray for the fruits. T. S. Eliot, the famous writer, says, “Ours is only the trying. The rest is none of our business” (T. S. Eliot, <em>Collected Poems</em>).</p>

<p>God is using us as His instruments in the lives of, sometimes, very few people immediately around us, and sometimes in the lives of millions, and the social influence that we try to have by living our lives as upright Christians. God uses this as a great seed in the sowing in the other souls around us.</p>

<p>It gives us great confidence in carrying out our apostolate to consider frequently that, as St. Josemaría says in <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, “the teaching, the message which we have to communicate, has in its own right an infinite effectiveness which comes not from us, but from Christ” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 159).</p>

<p>There’s an 82-year-old Loreto sister, an Irish Loreto sister here in Nairobi, who tells a story of how when she was in a kindergarten school, a missionary came back from Africa and was going around different kindergarten schools, talking about little children in Africa who didn’t know Jesus, and asking the little children to pray for those little children in Africa who didn’t know Jesus.</p>

<p>This six-year-old little girl was very taken with this. Looking back now, she says, “I think that was the beginning of my vocation. Many years later, I tried looking for that priest or finding out who he might have been, because he sowed the seeds of vocation in my soul. He asked us to go home to our parents and ask them if the last decade of the Rosary each night could be for the little children in Africa who didn’t know Jesus.”</p>

<p>She went home to her mum, and her mother said, “No, the last decade is for the Pope, but it can be the second last.” They began to pray the second last decade of the Rosary each night for the little children in Africa who didn’t know Jesus.</p>

<p>Now she has spent sixty years of her life teaching in a school in Africa and running many other schools. The seeds of that priest talking to those little children are yielding abundant fruit. And here we are talking about it almost 100 years later—well, not quite—seventy years later.</p>

<p>We don’t know how God is going to use us, or how He’s going to use the seeds that we sow or the seeds that other people have sown in the lives of people around us, which over time can bear fruit in our own lives.</p>

<p>This can fill us with an awful lot of hope. It can bring about a deep transformation in our souls, because that grace is always at work, whether we are aware or whether we’re not aware.</p>

<p>That can cause us to constantly make resolutions to be faithful, to begin and to begin again, in spite of our miseries or our failures.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría placed great emphasis on that process of beginning and beginning again. He said the whole of our interior life is a process of “beginning and beginning again” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 384).</p>

<p>We fail here, we fail there, we fall down, but we get up again, like Our Lord on the way to Calvary. That doesn’t matter. Grace is at work all the time.</p>

<p>That can lead us to give ourselves more fully and to try to correspond more fervently with the grace that God gives us; also, in the course of our life, to have a deeper hunger for that grace that comes to us in the sacraments.</p>

<p>His grace is acting in us at this moment while we’re praying, while you’re listening to this meditation.</p>

<p>God constantly offers us His grace to help us to be faithful in fulfilling the little duty of each moment. What is God asking of me in this particular moment as I go through the day? He lets us know His Will so that we can become saints by fulfilling that Will faithfully.</p>

<p>On our part, we have to try and accept this help from God and cooperate with generosity and docility.</p>

<p>Sometimes God may permit great crosses in our lives. I heard a story today of a mother who lost a grown-up daughter in some tragedy in another country. She immediately responded with the words, “I forgive, I forgive.”</p>

<p>God can always give us the graces to react in a supernatural way to the apparent tragedies that may take place in our lives.</p>

<p>In our soul as in our body, something similar happens: our lungs need to take in oxygen constantly so as to renew our blood. Anyone who does not breathe dies of suffocation. One writer says anyone who does not accept with docility the grace that God constantly gives us ends by dying of spiritual suffocation (Réginald Garrigou-Lagrange<em>, The Three Ages of the Interior Life</em>, Vol. 1).</p>

<p>Receiving grace with docility means being determined to fulfill all that the Holy Spirit suggests to us in the depths of our heart. He’s always speaking to us.</p>

<p>It means trying to fulfill our duties as perfectly as possible; first of all, in all those things that relate to our commitment towards God, even if we find it difficult., too much, or we fail again and again. We’re like little children learning to walk. They stand up and then they fall down, they stand up and they fall down.</p>

<p>We have those very encouraging words of Our Lord, who tells us: “Unless you become like little children, you cannot enter the kingdom of heaven” (Matt. 18:3).</p>

<p>No matter how difficult we might find the way that God has placed out for us, there’s grace there to help us carry on in that way.</p>

<p>Sometimes we have to make up our minds to acquire a specific virtue that may be, or may seem, out of reach. We try again and again to bear, with supernatural graciousness and simplicity, some setback or other, without losing our peace, without getting angry, without letting everyone around us know that we’re upset.</p>

<p>We try to live out the peace of Christ in all those moments, no matter how long that setback may last or how difficult we may find it. God moves us interiorly, and often He may remind us of the advice that we have received in spiritual direction, because the Holy Spirit is there.</p>

<p>The more faithful that we are to such grace, the better disposed we will be to receive further grace, the easier we will find it to do good deeds, and the happier we will be, because happiness is always related to the way we correspond with grace.</p>

<p>We have to be docile to the inspirations of the Holy Spirit if we are to preserve our life of grace and be supernaturally effective.</p>

<p>As Our Lord tells us in the parable, the seed sown in our hearts has sufficient strength to germinate, to grow, and to bear fruit. Our Lord’s examples can be very powerful.</p>

<p>“The seed is sprouting and growing,” He says. “Of its own accord the land produces first the shoot, then the ear, then the full grain in the ear. And when the crop is ready, at once he starts to reap, because the harvest has come” (<em>cf</em>. Mark 4:27-29).</p>

<p>First of all, we have to enable the seed to reach our heart. We have to make room for it within us, to accept it, not put it to one side, because the opportunities that God gives us don’t wait.</p>

<p>If on some occasion in our prayer or during our spiritual reading, we get an idea, or walking along the street, some idea hits us that’s related to our spiritual life, it’s a very good idea to write those ideas down. Bring them further to your prayer.</p>

<p>Or some advice that you’re given in spiritual direction, write it down. It might not seem particularly relevant at this particular moment. But with the passage of time, the graces of the Holy Spirit and the lights of the Holy Spirit become ever more and more relevant and fruitful.</p>

<p>St. John Henry Newman says, “The opportunities that God gives us…they come and they go. The word of life does not tarry.” We’ve got to catch the wind while it’s blowing. “If we don’t catch hold of it, the devil can bear it away” (John Henry Newman, <em>Sermon for Sexagesima Sunday: Calls of Grace</em>).</p>

<p>Maybe that seed is going to be a very important seed. “The devil is not lazy; rather does he always have his eyes open, and he’s ever ready to spring, and to snatch away the gift that you do not use” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>We need to live a series of little things. The little mortification of tidying up after our work. The little effort to get to Confession on the particular day that we have fixed. Examining our conscience in sufficient depth so that we can be aware of where we’re falling and of what God wants us to fight on the next day.</p>

<p>Living the <em>heroic minute</em> in the morning—getting up on time. Changing the conversation or at least keeping silent when someone is being criticized in their absence.</p>

<p>Resistance to grace, says one writer, produces the same effect in the soul as “hail beating on a tree in blossom which gave hopes of bearing much fruit; but the blossom is spoilt and the fruit does not ripen” (Garrigou-Lagrange<em>, loc. cit.</em>). Our interior life can wane and die.</p>

<p>We cannot keep count of all the times the Holy Spirit grants us the grace to avoid deliberate venial sin, and also all those faults which, without properly being sins, are displeasing to God.</p>

<p>The saints are the people who have responded with the greatest sensitivity to that supernatural help.</p>

<p>Neither can we keep count of all the graces we receive to help us sanctify the actions of our ordinary life, carrying them on with determination, with perfection, and with purity of intention, for supernatural reasons as well as for human ones.</p>

<p>If we are faithful from morning to night to the help that we receive, we will have filled each day with acts of love of God and neighbor, at both the pleasant moments and at those times when perhaps we felt tired and had less strength and enthusiasm.</p>

<p>All these actions help to make us effective. One grace leads to another. We are told in St. Mark, “For to him who has, will more be given” (Mark 4:25). The soul is strengthened in goodness to the extent that it practices goodness; it depends on the distance it tries to cover.</p>

<p>Each day is a great gift that God gives us. He wants us to fill it with love by corresponding cheerfully with His grace and by not being surprised at any difficulties or setbacks. He wants us to count on His help to overcome such obstacles and use them so that they will urge us on to holiness and apostolate. Everything is very different when we do it with love and for love.</p>

<p>We also have to try and avoid any discouragement that might arise when our defects don’t disappear and we come to realize that we have failed to acquire certain virtues. Constantly we have to start again.</p>

<p>“A person scatters the seed on the ground when he forms a good resolution in his heart...and the seed germinates and grows without his realizing it, even though he cannot be expected to be aware of its growth.</p>

<p>“Once virtue is conceived,” says St. Gregory the Great, “it journeys towards perfection, and the ground bears fruit of itself because, with the help of grace, a man’s soul rises up spontaneously to do good. But the earth produces first the blade, then the stalk, and finally the ear of grain” (Gregory the Great, <em>Homilies on Ezekiel</em>).</p>

<p>Interior life needs time. It grows and ripens like wheat in a field.</p>

<p>Faithfulness to the impulses God wants us to have is also shown by our avoiding discouragement at our failures and the impatience that comes when we still find it hard to finish our prayer with depth, or to root out a defect, or to think of God often during our work.</p>

<p>The farmer is patient. He doesn’t dig up the seed or abandon the field because he has not found the fruit he expected within a certain time.</p>

<p>Farmers know well that they must work and wait. They hope to have periods of warmth and sunshine, and maybe they hope for rain also. They know that the seed is coming to maturity, “he knows not how,” and that harvest time will come.</p>

<p>In <em>Furrow,</em> Point 668, St. Josemaría says, “Grace, like nature, normally acts gradually. We cannot, properly speaking, move ahead of grace. [ ]{.underline} But in all that does depend on us we have to prepare the way and cooperate when God grants grace to us.</p>

<p>“Souls have to be encouraged to aim very high; they have to be impelled towards Christ’s ideal. Lead them to the highest goals which should not be scaled down or made less lofty in any way.</p>

<p>“But remember that sanctity is not primarily worked out with one’s own hands. Grace normally takes its time, and is not normally inclined to act with violence or irresistible force. Encourage your holy impatience, but do not lose your patience.”</p>

<p>Just as the farmer, with the wisdom of centuries, does not lose his patience, we must learn to aim very high in sanctity and apostolate, waiting for the right moment, without ever losing heart. We will frequently have to start again with our unmodified ambitious resolution.</p>

<p>We need to be able to wait and to struggle with patient perseverance, with the conviction that overcoming a defect or acquiring a virtue does not normally depend on sporadic and violent effort, but on humble constancy in the struggle, the constancy of trying time and time again, counting on God’s mercy.</p>

<p>We cannot, because of impatience, cease to be faithful to the grace we receive. That impatience, generally, can have its roots in pride. “We have to be patient with everyone,” St. Francis de Sales says, “but first of all with ourselves” (Francis de Sales, <em>Letters</em>).</p>

<p>Nothing is beyond remedy for the person who hopes in the Lord; nothing is totally lost. We always have the possibility of being forgiven, and of beginning again; humility, sincerity, repentance ... Then we begin again.</p>

<p>We have to correspond with God, who is determined that we should overcome all obstacles. We can experience deep joy each time that we begin again, and during our time on earth, we will have to do that many, many times, because we will always have faults, deficiencies, weaknesses, and sins.</p>

<p>We must be humble and patient. God allows for our failures, but He also expects many little victories from us throughout our lives, victories that we carry off each time we are faithful to an inspiration, to a motion of the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “They are those who, hearing the word, hold it fast in an honest and good heart, and bring forth fruit with patience” (St. Augustine, <em>Sermon 101</em>).</p>

<p>All are capable of giving abundant fruits to the Lord, regardless of their past history. God is always sowing the seed of His grace.</p>

<p>“The most important thing is not to become like a much-trodden path, like outcrop rock, like thistles. … We have to become good ground. … The heart cannot be fair game for birds and passers-by. It has to provide enough ground for the seed to take root. The sun of human passions and a dissolute life should not scorch the seedlings of divine promise” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>The three prerequisites for our becoming good ground: to listen with a contrite and humble heart, to be earnest in prayer and mortification, and, finally, to be ready to begin and begin again in the interior struggle. We can’t let ourselves become discouraged if the fruits of our struggle are not readily apparent, even after many years of effort.</p>

<p>“A new heart I will give you,” we’re told, “and a new spirit I will put within you; and I will take out of your flesh the heart of stone and give you a heart of flesh” (Ezek. 36:26).</p>

<p>If we’re willing to change our ways, Our Lord is more than willing to transform us into ‘good ground.’ He will bring this about in the deepest recesses of our being.</p>

<p>The grace of God is all-powerful. The crucial thing is to return again and again to His side. St. Augustine teaches, “God is a farmer and if he abandons man, man becomes a desert. Man is also a farmer and if he leaves God, he turns himself into a desert as well” (St. Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 145</em>).</p>

<p>We can resolve never to be separated from Our Lord and to have recourse to His merciful heart many times each day.</p>

<p>Our Lady, who is the Mediatrix of all graces, will help all those graces to yield abundant fruit in the good soil that she wants each one of us to be.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Salt That Has Lost Its Savor</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/salt-that-has-lost-its-savor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salt That Has Lost Its Savor" /><published>2026-02-08T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-08T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/salt-that-has-lost-its-savor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/salt-that-has-lost-its-savor/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Salt without savor is no longer good for anything, except to be thrown out and trodden underfoot by men” (Matt. 5:13).</p>

<p>Our Lord has told His disciples that they are “the salt of the earth” (Matt. 5:13). They do to the world exactly what salt does to food, keeping it from going bad and making it agreeable to the palate.</p>

<p>But salt can sometimes lose its savor or in itself deteriorate, and then it becomes useless. This kind of change is, after sin, the saddest thing that can befall a Christian, the point of whose existence has been to give light to many, whereas now, in fact, they have become darkness.</p>

<p>Far from being able to point the people he comes in touch with in the right direction, that person now becomes disoriented and aimless himself. Having been placed on earth to give strength to others, he has nothing left to communicate now but weakness.</p>

<p>Lukewarmness is a disease of the soul that affects both the intellect and the will, and leaves the Christian devoid of the strength to carry out apostolate, at the same time filling him with a deep feeling of sadness and impoverishment.</p>

<p>The sickness starts with a weakening of the will, brought about by means of repeated faults and culpable omissions, of frequently doing wrong, and possibly even worse, failing to do what is right.</p>

<p>The Christian no longer sees Christ clearly on the horizon of his life. Because he’s been consistently careless regarding the little details that are a proof of love, he now discovers that Christ seems far removed from him. His interior life undergoes a profound change; it no longer has Our Lord as its focal point.</p>

<p>The person who is lukewarm finds that their practices of piety have become empty of content; he no longer puts his heart and soul into them. He goes through the motions, performing them out of routine or habit, no longer out of love.</p>

<p>One spiritual writer says: “In this state, a man loses all spontaneity and joy—recognizable characteristics of a soul in love—in responding to anything that has a reference to God.</p>

<p>“A lukewarm Christian is somehow ‘inside out’; his is a soul that has ‘grown weary’ in its endeavor to improve. Christ has faded from the horizon of his life.</p>

<p>“The soul decries God, if he sees him at all, describes him as a remote and distant figure, hazy and indistinct, with ill-defined features, and probably indifferent to him. No longer does he perform positive acts of generosity as he formerly did. He is now prepared to settle for much less” (<em>cf</em>. Francis Fernández, <em>Lukewarmness</em>).</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas cites as a feature of this state “a kind of sadness, whereby a man becomes sluggish in spiritual exercises because they weary the body” (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part I, Question 63).</p>

<p>All norms of piety and devotion become a burden for us, a burden we find increasingly hard to bear, instead of being a powerful center of energy, driving us forward and helping us to overcome any difficulties we may encounter.</p>

<p>There are many Christians who have sunk into lukewarmness. There is, in our time, a great deal of savorless salt about.</p>

<p>We can consider in our prayer today whether we are going forward with the firmness and confidence that Our Lord asks of us, whether we regard our conversation with Him as the treasure which enables our interior life to intensify and keep growing, and whether we properly nourish our love.</p>

<p>We can consider whether, when we become aware of our weakness and our lack of correspondence with grace, we promptly make acts of contrition to close the breach the enemy has made, and is attempting to widen in our defenses.</p>

<p>We mustn’t confuse the state of the lukewarm soul with the sense of dryness sometimes experienced when we perform our acts of piety, a sensation produced on occasions or for long periods by tiredness, or illness, or by the temporary loss of physiological keenness and enthusiasm.</p>

<p>In such cases, in spite of the feeling of dryness, our will is firmly set on all that is good. Our soul knows that it is traveling directly towards Christ, even though it is at this moment passing over a stony waste where the going is hard and we can’t find a single well or even a spring of cool water.</p>

<p>But our soul knows where its destination lies and goes straight towards it in spite of our weariness and thirst and the unfriendly terrain we have to tread.</p>

<p>In the state of what’s called aridity, even though the soul has no feeling and it seems difficult to pray, to carry on any real conversation with God, true devotion nevertheless remains.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas has defined this type of devotion as the “will to give oneself readily to things concerning the [service] of God” (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part II-II, Question 82).</p>

<p>This “readiness” grows weak if the will falls into a state of lukewarmness.</p>

<p>“I have this against you,” says Our Lord in the Book of Revelation, “that you have abandoned the love you had at first” (Rev. 2:4)—that you have weakened, that you no longer love me as you did formerly.</p>

<p>A person who is determined to keep up their prayer, even in times of aridity, when all feeling is absent, is perhaps like the person who draws water from a well, bucket by bucket, one aspiration after another, an act of sorrow. It’s hard work and demands effort, but he does draw out water.</p>

<p>On the other hand, in a state of lukewarmness, our imagination strays and runs wild. We’re no longer firmly determined to dispel voluntary distractions and in practice, abandon prayer with the excuse that we’re getting no results from it.</p>

<p>Genuine conversation with God, on the other hand, even if God allows it to be arid, is always fruitful, whatever the circumstances, as long as we have rectitude of intention and are firmly intent on being close to God.</p>

<p>We can remind ourselves, here and now, in the presence of God, that true piety is not a matter of feelings, although sensitive affections are good and they can be a great help in our prayer and in the whole of our interior life, because they’re an important part of human nature as it was created by God.</p>

<p>But our feelings can be mistaken. You can feel very well, and you could have a big cancer inside you. You might feel very sick, and you might be as healthy as a horse. Feelings can be misleading. Christ’s feelings on the Cross cannot have been wonderful, with three big nails going through Him.</p>

<p>And so, our affections should not occupy a disproportionately important place in our life of piety. They’re not the main part of our relationship with God.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to say that the day you’re doing your prayer and you feel awful, you feel you’re getting nothing, you feel it’s a waste of time—he said, “Persevere in that prayer, because that might be the best prayer that you ever did, because that prayer is all done for God; there are no human compensations” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 101).</p>

<p>If our prayer and our life of piety are full of compensations, it could be that we’re looking for the compensations, not necessarily seeking Him.</p>

<p>Feelings help, but achieve no more than this assistance, because the essence of piety does not consist in feelings, but in the will’s being determined to serve God, quite independently of any state of mind—which is always so changeable!—or of any other circumstances.</p>

<p>In matters of piety, we need to take care not to let ourselves be guided by feelings, but rather by our intellect, enlightened and helped, as we pray it will be, by faith.</p>

<p>One writer said, “To allow oneself to be guided by feelings would be like handing over the management of one’s house to a servant, while you as its real owner abdicate responsibility for it. It’s not the feelings that are bad, but rather the degree of importance that we attribute to them” (Joseph Tissot, <em>The Interior Life</em>).</p>

<p>Lukewarmness is sterile. Salt without savor “is no longer good for anything except to be thrown out and trodden underfoot by men” (Matt. 5:13).</p>

<p>On the other hand, aridity can be the positive sign that God wants to purify a particular soul.</p>

<p>In our apostolic life, there might be times when we’re asked to do things that don’t give us pleasant feelings. We might be asked to give a talk. We might be asked to go and find material means to set up some apostolic work. We might be asked to do research on a certain topic for some apostolic purpose. And we might find all of those things particularly distasteful.</p>

<p>Our feelings might not be there, but if we approach those tasks with a supernatural outlook and see that as the will of God for us, then great fruits may result.</p>

<p>We need to have interior life. As human beings, we can be a cause of happiness or sadness, of light or darkness. We can be the source of peace or of anxiety, either the leaven that enhances or a dead weight that hinders the progress of others.</p>

<p>Our passage over this earth can never be a matter of indifference as far as others are concerned. We help others to find Christ or we separate them from Him. We enrich others or we impoverish them.</p>

<p>And we come across so many of these others—friends, workmates, members of our family, neighbors—who seem to go after material goods as though they hungered for them, material goods that only serve to lure them away from the true good who is Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>They can journey through life like people who are lost. If the guide of the blind is not to become blind himself (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 15:14), it’s not enough for him to know the way from hearsay, or from coming across mere references to it.</p>

<p>If we are to help the people around us, it’s not enough for us to have a vague and superficial knowledge of the way. We need to walk along it ourselves and to have first-hand knowledge of the obstacles that lie in our path and which need to be surmounted.</p>

<p>We need to have interior life, to enter daily into personal conversation with Jesus. We need to know His doctrine ever more deeply; to struggle with still more determination to overcome our own defects. The apostolate is the result of a great love for Christ.</p>

<p>The first Christians were the true <em>salt of the earth</em>, and they preserved people and institutions—the whole of society—from corruption.</p>

<p>What can it be that has happened in so many nations? Why is it that Christians should now be giving the sad impression that they’re unable to slow down and halt the wave of corruption that’s bursting in on the family, on schools, and on institutions?</p>

<p>The faith is still the same. And Christ lives among us now just as He did previously. His power is still infinite, divine.</p>

<p>One writer says, “Only the lukewarmness of so many thousands, indeed millions, of Christians, explains how we can offer to the world a spectacle of a Christianity that allows all kinds of heresies and stupidities to be propounded within itself.</p>

<p>“Lukewarmness destroys the strength and endurance of the faith and is the soulmate, in both a personal and a collective way, of compromise and of a spirit of comfort-seeking” (Pedro Rodríguez, <em>Faith and Life of Faith</em>).</p>

<p>It’s difficult to explain many of the things that happen nowadays at a personal and public level, if we don’t bear in mind that so many people who should be awake, watchful, and attentive have allowed their faith to fall asleep.</p>

<p>Love has been snuffed out in so very many hearts. In many spheres, the ‘normal Christian’ now generally appears as someone who is lukewarm and mediocre.</p>

<p>Among the first Christians, the ‘normal Christian’ meant someone who lived the heroism of each day and, when the occasion presented itself, accepted martyrdom itself. It could and did mean very often the surrender of one’s very life in defense of the faith.</p>

<p>When love grows cold and faith falls asleep, the salt loses its savor and is no longer good for anything. It’s just something to throw away. What a pity if a Christian were to become as useless as this.</p>

<p>Lukewarmness is often the cause of apostolic ineffectiveness, because if we are in its grip, the little we do becomes a task devoid of human or supernatural attractiveness, and bereft of a spirit of sacrifice.</p>

<p>Faith that appears moribund and radiates little love and is unable to win anyone over or find the right words with which to attract others to a deep and intimate relationship with Christ.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord for the strength to react. We will be the “salt of the earth” if we keep up our daily conversation with God, if we go with ever greater faith and love to receive the Blessed Eucharist.</p>

<p>Love was, and is, the moving force of the life of the saints. It’s the whole reason for being of every life dedicated to God.</p>

<p>Love gives us wings with which to soar over any personal barriers to our advance, or any obstacles presented to us by our surroundings. Love makes us unyielding when confronted by setbacks.</p>

<p>Lukewarmness, on the other hand, gives up at the slightest difficulty—a letter we need to write, a phone call we should make, a visit or a conversation that we need to have, or the lack of some material means. It makes mountains out of molehills.</p>

<p>On the other hand, love for God makes a molehill out of a mountain. It transforms the soul, gives it new lights, and opens up new horizons for it. It makes the soul capable of achieving its highest desires and gives it capacities it had never as much as dreamed of possessing.</p>

<p>Love doesn’t make a fuss about the effort involved and fills the soul with happiness as it surveys the results of its efforts.</p>

<p>In the parable of the prodigal son, we’re also told about the elder son. “He was in the field, and as he came and drew near to the house, he heard music and dancing. And he called one of the servants and asked what this meant.</p>

<p>“The servant said to him, ‘Your brother has come, and your father has killed the fatted calf, because he has received him safe and sound’” (Luke 15:25-27).</p>

<p>St. Augustine comments: “But he was angry and refused to go in. Are you not moved by the celebration in the father’s house? The banquet with the fatted calf, has this not given you pause? No one will exclude you from the banquet. It all is for nothing, however. The elder son becomes furious and will not go in” (St. Augustine, <em>Sermon 11</em>).</p>

<p>In his fit of pique, he reveals his deepest motivation: “Look, these many years I have served you, and I never disobeyed your command; yet you never gave me a kid, that I might make merry with my friends. But when this son of yours comes, who has devoured your living with harlots, you killed for him the fatted calf” (Luke 15:28-30).</p>

<p>The father in the parable is God. He always has His arms outstretched, being full of mercy. The younger son is the image of the sinner who converts to God.</p>

<p>And the elder son? He is the worker who has labored in the fields, but without joy. He has served because he had to serve. Over the course of time, his heart has grown cold. His sense of charity has evaporated. His brother has become “this son of yours.”</p>

<p>He is like salt which has lost its savor. There is a striking contrast between the magnanimity of the father and the meanness of the elder son.</p>

<p>Serving God and enjoying His friendship should be a continual feast. The Second Vatican Council in <em>Lumen gentium</em> said, “To serve is to reign” (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 36, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>The elder son represents those who forget that serving God is a tremendous honor. In the act of service is to be found a good measure of the compensation.</p>

<p>“His father says to him, ‘Son, you are always with me, and all that is mine is yours’ (Luke 15: 31). Therefore, all honor and glory are ours if we are really of God” (St. Augustine, <em>ibid.</em>).</p>

<p>God Himself will give us of His riches. What more can we ask for?</p>

<p>“Each one of us must do as he has made up his mind, not reluctantly or under compulsion,” says St. Paul, “for God loves a cheerful giver” (2 Cor. 9:7).</p>

<p>There are always many reasons for us to celebrate if we truly live in the presence of God. We have a special opportunity to be magnanimous in our dealings with those closest to us.</p>

<p>St. Thérèse of Lisieux said, “How sweet a joy it is to think that God is just. In other words, he makes allowances for our weaknesses and understands perfectly the frailty of our humanity.</p>

<p>“So what have I to be afraid of? If God, who is perfectly just, shows such mercy in forgiving the prodigal son, must he not also be just to me ‘who am always with him’ (Luke 15:31)?” (Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>Autobiography of a Soul</em>).</p>

<p>As we finish our prayer, we can turn with confidence to Our Lady, the perfect model of loving correspondence to the Christian vocation.</p>

<p>The <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> says that in Mary we find the model of all virtues (<em>cf</em>. <em>Catechism</em>, Point 829; Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 65, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>Mary, may you remove effectively from our soul any shadow of lukewarmness. May you guide the angels to make us diligent in God’s service, so that we might always be in our family, in our workplace, in society, the salt that God has planned us to be.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MML</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Christian Outlook on Death</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Christian Outlook on Death" /><published>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Thessalonians, “For you yourselves know well that the day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night” (1 Thess. 5:2).</p>

<p>Our Lord Himself has said, “I am the resurrection and the life. He who believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives and believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26).</p>

<p>St. Paul to the Ephesians says, “Look carefully then how you walk, not as unwise men, but as wise, making the most of the time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>A lot of these statements in Scripture can remind us not to be blind to our final moment on earth.</p>

<p>The Church in some ways encourages us to prepare for death on a daily basis. Our Lord has said that His coming in glory will take people unawares.</p>

<p>“For as the lightning flashes and lights up the sky from one side to the other, so will the Son of Man be in his day” (Luke 17:24). Our Lord tells us that nothing can block His second coming at the end of time.</p>

<p>The disciples had a natural curiosity about when and where this would happen. “Where, Lord?” they asked Him. “Where the body is,” He replied, “there the eagles will be gathered” (Luke 17:37).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that everyone will be drawn to the Son of God at the end of time just as eagles converge on their prey.</p>

<p>The same can be said about each person’s moment of death.</p>

<p>St. Paul warns those Christians of Thessalonica that He will come ‘like a thief in the night.” It is one more call to vigilance.</p>

<p>We cannot be blind to our final moment on earth, the day of the Lord, when we will meet God face to face. St. Augustine has written that the Lord keeps the circumstances of His coming hidden so that we might always be on the alert (<em>cf</em>. St. Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 120</em>).</p>

<p>In modern culture, in certain environments, it’s not easy to speak about death and dying. In a materialistic culture, death is taboo because it suggests the end of everything.</p>

<p>It’s easy for people to forget the spiritual nature of man, that every person has a soul and that soul is immortal. It has an eternal destiny. It’s one of the most important truths of our faith, with enormous consequences.</p>

<p>But in a materialistic culture, the very mention of the subject of death can be regarded by some as a sign of bad taste. But it’s the certainty of death that illuminates our life.</p>

<p>The Church invites us to meditate frequently on the inevitability of our death so that we won’t be taken by surprise when it comes.</p>

<p>Pagan culture would have us live as though death were a distant mirage, something that only affects other people.</p>

<p>Regrettably, many who consider themselves good Christians can be unduly influenced by such a seductive approach to life. They’re led astray because they fail to come to terms with the real meaning of death.</p>

<p>Rather than see death as a friend, or even as a sister, as St. Josemaría says in <em>The Way,</em> Points 735 and 739, they view it as an enormous catastrophe, as something that will undermine all their worldly hopes and accomplishments.</p>

<p>I remember accompanying an elderly lady in another country once, at the moment of her death.</p>

<p>I was rather impressed by some of her final words. She said, ‘If I had known death was so beautiful, I would have tried to die a long time ago.’ She was a very holy woman and very well prepared for her death.</p>

<p>This earthbound approach explains why death has to be put in the closet, as it were. It’s too uncomfortable a subject to deal with. Instead of looking upon death as the key to the fullness of joy, the tendency is to see it as the end of the road, the checkout counter on what is for them a kind of terrestrial shopping spree.</p>

<p>These misguided people have lost sight of the fact that every person is in possession of an eternal soul. In <em>The Way</em>, Point 744, St. Josemaría says, “Death is nothing more than a change of lodging.”</p>

<p>The liturgy often reminds us of that truth. In the <em>Preface for the Dead</em>, it says, “Life is changed, not taken away.”</p>

<p>Life changes. It’s not something we’re deprived of.</p>

<p>Christians believe that death represents the end of an earthly pilgrimage. Believers prepare for death on a daily basis.</p>

<p>It’s through the sanctification of ordinary realities that we will win heaven as an eternal reward and the Christian who behaves accordingly will not be alarmed by death’s arrival.</p>

<p>That person will have been patiently readying themselves for this definitive encounter with the Lord. In the words of St. Cyprian, “Death is a stepping up into eternity after we have run in this earthly race” (St. Cyprian, <em>Treatise on Mortality</em>).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow,</em> Point 891, St. Josemaría says: “If at any time you feel uneasy at the thought of our sister death, because you see yourself to be such a poor creature, take heart. Heaven awaits us and consider: what will it be like when all the infinite beauty and greatness, and happiness and love of God will be poured into the poor vessel of clay that the human being is, to satisfy it eternally with the freshness of an ever new joy?”</p>

<p>Death acquires a new meaning with the death and resurrection of Christ.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “God did not make death, and He does not delight in the death of the living” (Wis. 1:13). There was no such thing as death with all its pain and suffering, before our first parents committed original sin. Death is a consequence of sin.</p>

<p>Man had been given the gift of immortality in the Garden of Paradise. But when our first parents committed that sin, they lost that gift. They lost that gift! St. Paul says, “By the sin of one man, death entered the world” (Rom. 5:12).</p>

<p>The rebellion of our first parents led to the loss of that preternatural gift. By his disobedience, Adam lost his friendship with God and that gift of immortal life.</p>

<p>Since that time, our passage to the house of the Father, our final resting place, takes us to this fateful gateway—the moment when we “depart out of this world to the Father” as quoted in St. John (John 13:1).</p>

<p>St. Paul says Jesus Christ “abolished death and brought life” (2 Tim. 1:10). He removed the essential evil from death and gave it a new meaning, making death into a stepping stone to Life.</p>

<p>His victory is shared by all who believe in Him and who participate in His Life. Our Lord has told us, “I am the resurrection and the life. He who believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives and believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26). Our Lord’s words can fill us with hope, a hope that does not disappoint.</p>

<p>Death is the enemy of the natural life of man. Christ has converted it into our friend and sister. Though the human person suffers defeat at the hands of this foe, he or she can in the end be triumphant thanks to Christ’s immortal sacrifice.</p>

<p>For a materialistic society in which pleasure and comfort reign supreme, death and even life itself are devoid of lasting value. Those who adopt a pagan lifestyle behave as if suffering, failure, and death were curses to be avoided at any cost.</p>

<p>Such people act as if Christ never achieved redemption.</p>

<p>The Psalmist says in his prayer to God: “Those who hate the righteous will be condemned” (Ps. 34:21). But “precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints” (Ps. 116:15).</p>

<p>From her earliest days, the Church has celebrated the anniversaries of the death by martyrdom of her saints. The Church likes to say that these are the <em>dies natalis</em>, the birthdays to that new Life which entails joy without end.</p>

<p>St. John tells us in the Book of Revelation, “I heard a voice from heaven saying: ‘Write this: Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord henceforth.’ ‘Blessed indeed,’ says the Spirit, ‘that they may rest from their labors, for their deeds follow them.” (Rev. 14:13).</p>

<p>We know that we will be rewarded for even the smallest service that we have done for the Lord. We’re told in St. Matthew that “whoever gives...even a cup of cold water, because he is a disciple of the Lord, shall not go without His reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>We have the joy of looking forward to every little thing being rewarded that we have done for other people in this world.</p>

<p><em>Gaudium et Spes</em> of the Second Vatican Council has said: “For after we have obeyed the Lord, and in His Spirit nurtured on earth the value of human dignity, brotherhood, and freedom, and indeed all the good fruits of our nature and enterprise, we will find them again, but freed of stain,…transfigured, when Christ hands over to the Father: ‘a kingdom eternal and universal...’” (Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et Spes,</em> Point 39).</p>

<p>All the things of the world will perish and be forgotten, but their good “deeds will follow them.”</p>

<p>We can be reminded of that phrase of Scripture which says, “Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, where dust and moth consume, and thieves break in and steal. But store up for yourselves treasures in heaven” (Matt. 6:19-20).</p>

<p>Every day, every hour, is an opportunity for us to store up for ourselves treasures in heaven.</p>

<p>Death can teach us many things about life. It can inspire us to live with only what we need, to be detached from the things we own and use, to respect the lasting merit of our good works, and to get rid of superfluous things—many good things.</p>

<p>Occasionally in your family, go through the cabinets of your children or their rooms and help them to make a decision to pass on to others what they don’t need, so that in a subtle way, they get all these messages: they are not here just to accumulate things.</p>

<p>It’s not that the one who has accumulated the most toys wins. Rather, the more we have gotten rid of things and passed them on to others will we be ready for the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>Death also teaches us to make good use of every day, to have goals, to have a plan for our spiritual life and, also for our professional and material life. Things I need to do today, with priorities, to do number one and then number two.</p>

<p>Ancient writers used to use the phrase <em>Carpe diem</em> <em>(</em>Horace<em>, Odes 1,11,17).</em> Horace, an early Latin writer, used this phrase ‘Seize the day’ to encourage people to make the most of the present moment.</p>

<p>Look around you and see if people on your mode of transport or people that you meet every day are making the most out of every moment. If they have an article or a book they’re reading in spare moments, in the little pieces of time—one writer used to call them the butts of time—the little pieces of time throughout the day when maybe nothing is happening, to have something to be reading, something to be doing, catching up on other little projects or little things to be done here and there. Using our time well.</p>

<p>These words of Horace were a pagan maxim, but we can impart a Christian meaning to it by living each day with joy as if it were our whole life. We can ask ourselves: What is the will of God for me today?</p>

<p>From the things that happened from hour to hour—ups and downs, reversals of fortune, pieces of good news, pieces of bad news—we can decipher what exactly it is that God wants me to do today and try to follow His will with a lot of peace and serenity.</p>

<p>It’s a chance that will never be repeated. Time is like a flowing divine treasure: it comes, it’s here, and then it goes, never to return.</p>

<p>During our examination of conscience, we can please Our Lord with the quantity of acts of love, of our aspirations, of our moments of talking to our guardian angel, of favors we’ve done on behalf of others, of the quiet fulfillment of our duties, of our struggle to be patient.</p>

<p>Perhaps Our Lord will convert these deeds into splendid jewels of eternal worth. “Death ends our time of meriting” (<em>cf</em>. Leo X, Bull, <em>Exsurge Domine</em>, June 15, 1520). Interesting point.</p>

<p>I know a priest who went to see a man on his deathbed. This priest was really renowned for making money, helping people to be detached. He reminded this man on his deathbed: Look, after you die, really nothing belongs to you. It all belongs to God.</p>

<p>There’s not much merit in giving away things after you die. There’s much more merit in giving away things while you are still alive. That way you gain merit—an act of generosity, charity, justice.</p>

<p>We can make a resolution not to waste the days that remain to us in our lives. We do not know when we will die.</p>

<p>Every so often we hear of people dying young, or we hear of accidents, or we hear of people having heart attacks, young people. Those are like little gentle reminders to us from the Holy Spirit that we live in the hands of God.</p>

<p>That very uncertainty helps us to be watchful, like the doorkeeper awaiting the arrival of his master (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:35-36). Hence the importance of regular sacramental Confession to be always in a state of grace. The Church has always recommended regular Confession.</p>

<p>Our examination of conscience at the end of the day can help us to recognize and discover the failings we may have had this day—failings of charity, of patience, of kindness, of justice, or failings in sensuality, failings in pride and vanity.</p>

<p>Therefore, we can build up those little details that we want to bring to Confession at the end of the week, to cleanse our soul from venial sin, and from any omissions that would indicate a lack of love.</p>

<p>Sometimes our greatest faults or sins could be our sins of omission, or our sins of neglect, things that we could have done and didn’t do, or things that we could have done much better than we did.</p>

<p>Our meditation on death can move us to work more earnestly on the great project of our own sanctification. St. Paul says to the Ephesians, <em>“</em>Look carefully then how you walk, not as unwise men but as wise, making the most of time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>We need to make up for lost time<em>.</em> … Let us take to heart that wise observation written almost twenty centuries ago. Seneca, an ancient Latin writer, said, “It’s not that we have so little time,” he said, “but that we have wasted so much of it” (Seneca<em>, De brevitate vitae,</em> 1,3). He was writing in the early centuries. Clocks and stopwatches had not yet been invented.</p>

<p>We could make an act of contrition for all the time that we may have wasted in our lives and make a resolution to make many wise decisions about our use of time.</p>

<p>We should want to have a long life so that we can give God abundant service. St. Josemaría used to say that if God has invested an awful lot in our education, in our formation, it’s very good that we give Him a good return on that investment. It makes good economic sense.</p>

<p>It’s a good thing to ask Our Lord for a long life so that we can serve more, so that hopefully we go before Our Lord with our arms full. It’s so right for us to love life since this is a gift from God.</p>

<p>I heard of a person once who was involved in fundraising for a center for young people where they would get a lot of formation, growth in holiness, and learn many other skills, and develop their personality, and develop many other virtues.</p>

<p>To try and get his friends to contribute to the growth of this youth center, a center for young people, he said, ‘Look, if you buy a brick in this place, that brick will always be there. Long after you die, that brick will still be there. It would be like an investment for the future. That brick helping that center to form young people will give great glory to God over time and all that glory will be to your benefit at the end of time, at the last judgment.’</p>

<p>There are ways that we can remind people that they have to make good use of their time and also of everything that they have, for that abundant service of God.</p>

<p>We have the grace to open horizons for them, to see those things that perhaps they haven’t seen, so that they also can go before Our Lord with their arms full.</p>

<p>If we’re faithful to our Christian vocation, when the time comes for our encounter with Our Lord we will be prepared to make a tremendous act of love for Our Father God.</p>

<p>What a beautiful thing to die with words of love on our lips. That holy woman that I just mentioned did precisely that. She went out of this world giving praise to God.</p>

<p>“As in one’s whole life, so also in one’s death. Each one should struggle to give glory to the Lord Our God” (St. Ignatius of Loyola, <em>Constitutions</em>).</p>

<p>It’s good to be aware that most people die as they have lived. The concept of last-minute deathbed conversions is very rare.</p>

<p>It’s today we have to live better. This hour. Today we have to practice the virtues. Today we have to live with a greater awareness that there is an end to all this.</p>

<p>St. Ignatius of Loyola says, “May He be honored and glorified. May other people be edified by the example of our patience and fortitude, by the testimony of our living faith, our hope, and our love for the eternal goods” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Our last moment on earth should be spent for the glory of God.</p>

<p>I remember a 19-year-old person dying in a hospital once in Asia and the doctor who was looking after him—this young fellow who had no religion, no formation, no nothing—remarked, ‘He died like a soldier.’ It’s rather a beautiful comment.</p>

<p>We’re called to die like soldiers, but “soldiers of Christ” (2 Tim. 2:3).</p>

<p>It will be a great joy when we give Our Lord the present of our professional work well done; of the apostolate that we’ve tried to do with all the opportunities that He’s given to us; of those many, many details of service to our neighbors, in our family life, in our environment, in our office, in our club, in our neighborhood; to present to Him the joy that we contributed to our family life; and the effort that we made to overcome our defects.</p>

<p>We will leave behind us works that will endure. We will take our departure from this world in a way described by a poet: “I left my love the shore and the singing current. I did not return to the bank for his love, for his love was the water” (B. Llorens, <em>A secret spring).</em></p>

<p>We know that if we live close to Our Lady all through our life, every hour and every day in the presence of Our Mother, she will also be with us. We say so frequently and throughout our life, we have said now, “at the hour of our death” (Prayer, <em>Hail Mary</em>).</p>

<p>There was a lady in Singapore whose husband passed away. But when he was alive, they would go to the happy hour every day in the local pub, and she would put on her earrings and her make-up and they’d go and have a good time.</p>

<p>Then her husband passed away, and she ended her days in a home for the elderly.</p>

<p>She had no religion, but the good nuns were converting her and teaching her the basic prayers, and she learned all of them very well.</p>

<p>During this time, when the time came for the happy hour each day, she liked to remember the good old times and to pretend that she was going to the happy hour. She’d also put on her earrings, maybe some make-up, to pretend she was accompanying her husband to the happy hour.</p>

<p>She learned all of the basic prayers, ready for her Baptism. But she couldn’t quite master the second part of the <em>Hail Mary</em> because she kept saying: Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners, now and at the happy hour of our death, Amen. But somehow, she had put her finger on the nerve.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady to accompany us in that happy hour and to help any people around us also to find Our Lady and to be with her in that very special moment.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Cup of Cold Water</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cup of Cold Water" /><published>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“If anyone can give so much as a cup of cold water to one of these little ones, because he is a disciple, then I tell you solemnly, he will most certainly not lose his reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>Giving a cup of cold water—and notice specifically how Scripture says cold water, not warm water—to someone who needs it is not going to make headlines. Most likely only the giver and the receiver will be aware of it.</p>

<p>And yet Our Lord holds up this small act of kindness as having tremendous value.</p>

<p>Even the simplest acts in which we lose ourselves for others have eternal significance. The cloth of holiness is woven in small details.</p>

<p>With this and with other examples that Our Lord gives to us, He speaks to us about the value of little things.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say, “A little act, done for love, is worth so much!” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, 814).</p>

<p>Mother Teresa has said, “A few words of kindness may be very simple and very brief, but their echoes are endless.”</p>

<p>On one occasion Our Lord sat up to the Temple treasury and He watched people putting money into the receptacle for alms. The scene takes place in one of the porticos, the so-called Treasure Chamber or Hall of Offerings. The days of the Passion were almost upon Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord didn't comment at all on the many people who contributed large amounts. But He saw a woman come up who was dressed in the typical garb of widows, and who was obviously poor (Mark 12:41).</p>

<p>She had perhaps waited for the crowd to thin out before depositing two small coins there. These coins had the least value of any in circulation at the time.</p>

<p>St. Mark explains the real value of these particular units of currency for the benefit of his non-Jewish readers, to whom his Gospel was principally addressed. He wants everyone to know how very little they were worth.</p>

<p>In men's eyes that anonymous offering had very little value. The two coins were worth just a small amount. “That coin,” St. Mark says, “was worth a quarter” (Mark 12:42). It's like a tenth of a denarius, which was the basic monetary unit; a denarius was a day's wages for a farm worker. And so, a quarter would scarcely buy anything.</p>

<p>If anyone was keeping a record of the offerings made that day in the temple, he probably would have thought it was not worth recording that widow's contribution. But we see that in fact this was the most valuable contribution of all.</p>

<p>It would be so pleasing to God that Our Lord called together His disciples, who were scattered around the place, so that they might be taught the lesson to be learned from this widow.</p>

<p>Those tiny pieces of copper could scarcely be heard falling into the treasury box. But Our Lord clearly perceived the love of this woman who said nothing but who was giving all her savings to God.</p>

<p>“Jesus said, ‘Truly I say to you, this poor widow has put in more than all those who are contributing to the treasury. For they all contributed out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty has put in everything she had, her whole living’” (Mark 12:43-44).</p>

<p>It often happens that what God considers important is very different from what men consider important. His standard of measurement and ours are not the same.</p>

<p>We are generally impressed by the big gesture, by unusual things of the kind that attract everyone's attention. But God is moved by little details filled with love—"a cup of cold water”—which are within the radius of action of everyone, even small children.</p>

<p>Of course, He's also moved by happenings that we consider to be very important, but only when they're carried out with the same spirit of rectitude of intention, of humility, and of love.</p>

<p>The apostles, who later were to be the very foundation of the Church, did not forget the lesson they were taught that day. That woman has taught all of us to touch God's heart every day in the only way that most of us can: through little things.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, Point 824, St. Josemaría says, “Have you noticed how human love consists of little things? Well, divine Love also consists of little things.”</p>

<p>In these passages of the Gospel, we learn the true value of these things. We can turn everything that happens, no matter how inconsequential it may seem, into something very pleasing to God. And because it's pleasing to Him, it's turned into something of great value. Only those things that we make pleasing to God have any true and eternal value.</p>

<p>We could consider in our prayer the vast number of opportunities that present themselves to us. We’re told by St. Francis de Sales, “Great opportunities to serve God seldom arise, but little ones are frequent; [and our Lord himself has told us that] ‘he who is faithful over a few things will be placed over many’ (Luke 16:10). Do all things in the name of God, and you will do all things well, provided you know how to fulfill your duties properly.</p>

<p>“Then, whether you eat or drink, whether you sleep, or take recreation, or turn the spit of an oven, you will profit greatly in God's sight by doing all these things, because God wishes you to do them” (St. Francis de Sales, <em>Introduction to the Devout Life</em>).</p>

<p>Often, it's the small things that make a job perfect, worthy of being offered to God: the double-checking of an email or a WhatsApp message that we write, the looking back to double-check on a room that we've just cleaned, or a floor we've just polished, or a table we've just laid, or some little professional job that we have done.</p>

<p>Perfection is in the details. It's not enough that what we're doing is good, whether it's work or prayer or football or hockey or volleyball. It also has to be well finished.</p>

<p>“For there to be virtue,” St. Thomas Aquinas teaches, “it is necessary to attend to two things: to what is being done, and also to the way it is being done” (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Quodlibet</em>, IV).</p>

<p>As far as the way it is being done is concerned, the final touches with the chisel or brush can turn that work into a masterpiece, and Our Lord wants us to work masterpieces every day.</p>

<p>On the other hand, shoddy workmanship, work which is done clumsily or carelessly, is a sign of spiritual laziness or of lukewarmness in a Christian who should be sanctifying himself through his daily work.</p>

<p>We're told in the Book of Revelation, “I know your works: you have the name of being alive, and you are dead. ... For I have not found your works perfect in the sight of my God” (Rev. 3:1-2).</p>

<p>The very nature of our Christian vocation demands that we take care of little things. A teacher who picks up a piece of paper off the floor may give a greater lesson to all his students, or to anybody who happens to be in that particular corridor or place, than all the other classes he may have given in his whole professional lifetime, because with that little gesture we teach the value of order, of tidiness, but also the value of the small things.</p>

<p>Our aim should be to imitate Our Lord during His years in Nazareth, those long years of work, of family life, of friendly relationships with His countrymen.</p>

<p>Doing little things with love for God's sake demands attention, sacrifice, and generosity. A single isolated little detail may not in itself be very important. St. Augustine says, “What is small is small, but he who is faithful in small things is great” (St. Augustine, <em>On Christian Doctrine</em>).</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>, “Love is what gives little things their value” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>The Way,</em> Point 814).</p>

<p>If this love were lacking, our endeavor to look after little things would be pointless; it would become a mania or merely Pharisaical. We would pay tithes in mint, dill and cumin—as the Pharisees do—and we would run the risk of leaving out the most essential points of the law, those of justice and of mercy.</p>

<p>Although what we have to offer may seem very little—just as the contribution of that poor widow did—it acquires a great value if you place it on the altar and unite it to the offering that Our Lord makes of Himself to the Father.</p>

<p>St. John Paul said in one of his homilies: “Our humble surrender—insignificant in itself like the oil of the widow of Sarepta, or the poor widow's mite—becomes acceptable in God's eyes through its union with the offering of Jesus” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, November 7, 1982).</p>

<p>At other times, details in our work, in our study, in our relationships with other people are the crowning of something good which would remain incomplete without those details.</p>

<p>One of the most obvious warning signs that we're starting on the path to lukewarmness is that we give little value to the details of our life of piety, to details in our work, and to little specific acts of virtue. If we ignore these symptoms, we end up paying little attention to big things as well.</p>

<p>“The misfortune is all the more grievous and incurable,” said one writer, “when we barely notice that we are sliding downwards and only slowly come to realize this … That if we are in this state, we give a mortal blow to the life of the spirit, and that can be something obvious to everyone” (Benedict Baur, <em>Frequent Confession</em>).</p>

<p>Love for God, on the other hand, is shown by our inventiveness, by our unremitting zeal, and our effort to find in everything an occasion for showing our love of God and for giving service to others.</p>

<p>Holiness is a cloth woven of little details. God is not indifferent to a love that knows how to care for small details. He's not indifferent, for example, as to whether we go to greet Him, first of all, when we go into a church or when we happen to be passing by a church.</p>

<p>He's not indifferent to the effort we make to arrive on time (better, a few minutes early) for Holy Mass, to the way we genuflect in front of Him in the tabernacle, or the way we behave or try to be recollected in His presence.</p>

<p>There was a man once who tried to do a lot of apostolate in his office, befriending as many people as he could, being close to them, trying to help them in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>He gave a lot of support to people in their marriage, in their family, tried to invite them to recollections, to retreats, to grow spiritually.</p>

<p>But there was one man in the office who refused all of his overtures. He had no time for these sorts of things.</p>

<p>But one day that man came to this other fellow and said, ‘Look, I have a big problem in my marriage. My wife is about to divorce me. Can you give me any advice?’</p>

<p>The original man was a bit surprised. He said, ‘You know, I've often tried to give you advice or reach out to you in different ways, and you never seemed very interested. Why do you come to me?’</p>

<p>The guy said, ‘Well, you're the only one that speaks about anything serious around here.’</p>

<p>The original man said, ‘Okay, let me think about it and pray about it’—which is always a good thing to say to people because they realize you're taking them seriously.</p>

<p>That evening in his prayer, he brought this topic to talk to Our Lord about it. He couldn't really see any great solutions. But for some reason, a scene in a movie with St. Josemaría came to mind, where St. Josemaría mentioned how husbands should try and bring their wives some flowers from time to time.</p>

<p>He was thinking to himself, ‘It's a bit late for flowers. That's not a very prudent sort of advice to give this fellow.’</p>

<p>But that was all he saw in his prayer. With a lot of supernatural outlook, he thought, ‘If that's all I see in my prayer, that, maybe, is what I have to transmit to this fellow.’</p>

<p>But he wasn't terribly convinced himself. It didn't seem very helpful.</p>

<p>The following day, he told his friend, ‘Look, I thought about this, and I prayed about it. My suggestion to you is that you perhaps bring some flowers to your wife.’</p>

<p>The second fellow was thinking, ‘I was really wasting my time talking to you. What a stupid piece of advice. She's about to divorce me and you're telling me to bring her flowers.’</p>

<p>He dismissed his suggestion and went off. But that evening, as he was going home, he was thinking about this and he thought, ‘Even if I get her flowers, I suppose it can't do any harm. The worst thing that could happen is that she might hit me with them.’</p>

<p>So he bought some flowers. When he got home, his wife opened the door and he handed her the flowers. She burst into tears and said, ‘This is the first time in twenty years that you have brought me flowers.’ After that, they lived happily ever after.</p>

<p>Sometimes the little things can make a huge difference.</p>

<p>Moreover, when we see somebody make a devout genuflection before the tabernacle, it's easy for us to think: that person has faith and loves God. That sign of adoration helps others to have greater faith and greater love.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI says, “It may perhaps seem to you that the Liturgy is made up of little things: the position of the body, genuflections, inclinations of the head; the way the thurible, the missal, and the cruets are to be moved. It is then that we have to recall Christ's words in the Gospel: ‘He who is faithful in a very little is faithful also in much’” (Luke 16:10).</p>

<p>“Moreover,” said St. Paul VI, “nothing is small in the Sacred Liturgy, when we think of the greatness of him to whom it is directed” (Paul VI, <em>Address</em>, May 30, 1967).</p>

<p>Our spirit of mortification usually consists in specific little sacrifices throughout the day: keeping up a persevering struggle in our particular examination of conscience, sobriety at meals, punctuality, being pleasant to people, getting up on time, not leaving our work for later even though we find it difficult or trying, having order in our work and taking care of the tools or implements and materials that we use, being grateful for whatever food is placed in front of us, not allowing ourselves whims and fancies.</p>

<p>In order to live charity in a way that becomes ever more refined and heroic, it would be necessary for us to apply this approach right down to the smallest and least important details of daily life.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in the <em>Furrow</em> says, “Your duty to be a brother to all souls will lead you to practice the ‘apostolate of little things’ without others noticing it. You will want to serve them so that for them, their way becomes agreeable” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 737).</p>

<p>At times it will mean taking a real interest in what other people are saying; at other times it will mean putting aside our own personal concerns so as to give our attention to the people we live with.</p>

<p>A little girl was talking to her father who was reading the newspaper and she said to him, ‘Daddy, you're not listening to me.’</p>

<p>Continuing to read the newspaper, he said, ‘Yes, I am. I'm hearing every word.’</p>

<p>But then she said, ‘But you're not looking at me.’</p>

<p>The child was aware, and the child wanted his full attention. A small thing, but it meant everything to the child.</p>

<p>Care of those little things will mean not getting annoyed about what are really trivia, not being touchy, making people feel welcome.</p>

<p>If those little disturbances come during the day, little things, changes of plans, or funny things go wrong, that can be a trigger to repeat our <em>Morning Offering</em>.</p>

<p>We shall tell Our Lord: I'm really serious with the <em>Offering</em> that I made to you. It's these things I wanted to offer to you.</p>

<p>We will try to help others in a way that they may not notice, or might never find out, but which lightens their burden. We try to pray to God for them when they're in need, to avoid having critical spirit towards them, and always to be grateful to them.</p>

<p>All of these things are within the reach and the scope of each one of us. And we should try and do the same where each one of the virtues is concerned.</p>

<p>If we give attention to little things, we will live each day to the full, and will know how to fill each moment with the sense of preparation for eternity. To do this, we could frequently ask Our Lady for help.</p>

<p>Our Lady, Mother of God, pray for us, now, and in every ordinary little situation of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>PKN</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Merciful Messiah</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Merciful Messiah" /><published>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’ Large crowds came to him, bringing the lame, the crippled, the blind, the dumb, and many others; and they put these down at his feet and he cured them. The crowds were astonished to hear the dumb speaking, to see the cripples whole again, the lame walking, and the blind with their sight restored” (Matt. 15:32, 30-31).</p>

<p>We’re told, “Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’” This is why the heart of Our Lord is so often moved. In His mercy, He was to follow up this episode with the wonderful miracle of the multiplication of the loaves (Matt. 15:32-39).</p>

<p>We’re reminded in these passages to turn always to the mercy of Our Lord, and to meditate on His life, so as to learn to be merciful to others.</p>

<p>The liturgy places this passage before us during Advent because of an abundance of good things and the limitless mercy which will be the signs of the coming of the Messiah.</p>

<p>“I feel sorry for all these people.” This is an overriding reason for giving ourselves to others: to be compassionate and to have mercy.</p>

<p>In order to learn how to be merciful, we have to fix our eyes on Christ, who comes “to save that which was lost” (Luke 19:10).</p>

<p>He doesn’t come to crush the broken reed or to wholly extinguish the wick that still smolders (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 12:20), but to take upon Himself our wretchedness and save us from it, and to share in their misfortune with those who suffer and are in need. Each page of the Gospel is an example of divine mercy.</p>

<p>We should meditate on the life of Jesus because, as St. Josemaría says, “[The life of] Jesus is a summary and compendium of the [story] of the divine mercy. Many other scenes of the Gospel,” he continues, “also make a deep impact on us, such as his forgiveness of the woman taken in adultery, the parables—the prodigal son, the lost sheep, the pardoned debtor—and the raising to life of the son of the widow at Naim.</p>

<p>“How many reasons based on justice could Christ have found to work as great a wonder as this last one! The only son of that poor widow had died—he who gave meaning to her life, he who would help her in her old age. Jesus did not perform his miracle out of justice, but out of compassion, because his heart was moved by the spectacle of human suffering” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 7).</p>

<p>The mercy of God is the essence of the whole history of salvation, the reason for all His saving actions.</p>

<p>God is mercy. And this divine attribute is like the engine supplying the power that energizes the life story of every human being.</p>

<p>When the apostles wanted to sum up God’s revelation, His mercy always appeared to them to be the essence of an eternal and gratuitous plan springing from God’s generosity. With good reason, the Psalmist could affirm: “The earth is full of the steadfast love of the Lord” (Ps. 33:5).</p>

<p>Mercy is constant in God’s attitude to mankind. And recourse to it is the universal remedy for all our ills, including those for which we thought there was no answer.</p>

<p>Meditating on the mercy of God should fill us with great confidence “now and at the hour of our death,” as we pray in the <em>Hail Mary</em>.</p>

<p>What a joy to be able to say to God, with St. Augustine: “All my hope lies solely in your great mercy!” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>, <em>Book 10</em>).</p>

<p>Solely in that, Lord. On your mercy rests all my hope. Not on my merits, but on your mercy.</p>

<p>In a special way, God shows His mercy towards sinners: He pardons them their sins. The Pharisees often criticize Him for this. He rebuts their criticisms saying: “It is not those who are well who have need of a physician, but those who are sick” (Matt. 9:12).</p>

<p>We who are sinners are sick of soul and need to have recourse many times to the divine mercy. In the Psalms, we say, “Show us, O Lord, your mercy; and grant us your salvation” (Ps. 85:7). The Church repeats these words continually in this liturgical season.</p>

<p>On so many occasions, every day even, we will have need to have recourse to the merciful Heart of Jesus and say: “Lord, if you will, you can make me clean” (Matt. 8:2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul in his encyclical <em>Dives in Misericordia</em> (“Rich in Mercy”), says, especially in these circumstances, “The knowledge of God, the God of mercy and benign love, is a constant and inexhaustible source of conversion, not only as a momentary interior act, but also as a stable disposition, like a state of mind. Those who come to know God in this way, those who so regard Him, cannot live without being incessantly transformed by Him.”</p>

<p>We can also say, as it is said in the Book of Sirach: “How great is the mercy of the Lord, and his forgiveness for those who turn to him!” (Sir. 17:29). Great is the divine mercy toward each one of us.</p>

<p>This can lead us to turn frequently to God, in repentance for our faults and sins, especially in that sacrament of divine mercy which we call Confession.</p>

<p>God has placed a condition for our obtaining His compassion and mercy for our offenses and weaknesses. The condition is that we too should have a heart of compassion for those around us.</p>

<p>In the parable of the good Samaritan (Luke 10:30-37), Our Lord teaches us the attitude that we should adopt towards a neighbor in distress. We’re not permitted to “pass by on the other side” in detached indifference. Rather we must “go” to him.</p>

<p>One morning many years ago, I was going to say Mass in a conference center outside Dublin. It was, maybe, a 45-minute drive. I was a little bit late, so I had my foot on the accelerator. Then I happened to see a car coming out of a side road and hitting a lorry. The front wing of the car was torn off. It was a bit dramatic.</p>

<p>I slowed down. I could see that the only damage really was to the car. Nobody was injured. There was a bit of drama, but nothing else. So, I kept going and I put my foot on the accelerator to try and catch up on the time that I had lost.</p>

<p>But after going about 100 meters, I remembered the story of the Gospel about the priest who went by on the other side of the road.</p>

<p>Listening to my conscience, I had to turn around and go back and double-check that everybody was okay, and give my phone number as a witness, and a few more things. Then I proceeded with my journey a bit more serenely than before.</p>

<p>We can all be that person who goes by on the other side of the road with all sorts of hurried excuses. St. John Paul, in his Apostolic Lette<em>r Salvifici doloris</em> (“The Salvation of Sorrow or Pain”) says: “A good Samaritan is one who stops to relieve the suffering of the other, no matter who he or she may be. This stopping is not just merely from curiosity, but rather from the desire to make ourselves available.</p>

<p>“It’s a specific interior disposition of the heart, which also has its emotional side. Good Samaritans are those who are affected by the suffering they see around them; they are genuinely moved by their neighbor’s misfortune.”</p>

<p>Each of us has to feel bad that people around us do not perhaps have the dignity or the care that they should have as human beings. And it’s not enough for us to feel bad about it. We have to try and do something about it, and infect other people with that sort of thinking, particularly our children, with our words and with our examples.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “If Christ, who knows the interior of man, emphasizes this compassion, this means that it’s important for our whole attitude towards the sufferings of others. Therefore one must cultivate this sensitivity of heart, which bears witness to compassion towards a suffering person. Sometimes this compassion remains the only or the principal expression of our love for and of our solidarity with the sufferer” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici doloris</em>, Point 28, February 11, 1984).</p>

<p>The word compassion comes from two Latin words, <em>com passio</em>, to suffer with.</p>

<p>Throughout Sacred Scripture there’s an urgency on God’s part to see that men also have the stirrings of sympathy and deep-seated feelings of mercy, that they too have this “compassion for another’s misery, which moves us to remedy it, if at all possible” (St. Augustine, <em>The City of God)</em>.</p>

<p>We can look around us and see in our home, in our office, in our workshop, in our neighborhood—is there not some person who’s handicapped, either physically or morally, or elderly, who perhaps needs urgently our time, our affection, and our attention?</p>

<p>Our Lord promises us happiness if we have a merciful heart towards others, and gives assurance that “we will obtain mercy” (Heb. 4:16) from God in the same measure as we show it to our fellow men.</p>

<p>The scope for mercy is as great as the extent of the human suffering that needs to be remedied. And, since mankind is subject to misery and calamity in the physical, intellectual, and moral order, the possible works of mercy are innumerable—as many as men have needs—though traditionally, by way of example, fourteen ‘works of mercy’ have been cited, since in them, this virtue is capable of being exercised in a special way.</p>

<p>Our attitude of compassion and mercy must, in the first place, be shown towards those who are near us—our family, our friends, our close associates—to those whom God has placed at our side, and then to those beyond who are most in need.</p>

<p>Mercy will frequently consist in our attention to the health, the recreation, and the nourishment of those whom God has commended to our care. The sick merit a special attention in terms of our company and our real interest in their illness, as we show them how and help them to offer their sufferings to God.</p>

<p>In a society dehumanized by frequent attacks on the family, more and more old people and those who are ill are left without consolation and affection. Visiting them in their loneliness is a work of mercy that has never been more necessary.</p>

<p>The time spent in keeping them company is rewarded by God in a special way: “As you did it to one of the least of these my brethren, you did it to me,” said Our Lord (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Alongside the so-called material works of mercy, we should also carry out those that are spiritual. In the first place it is our privilege and duty <em>to correct those in</em> <em>error</em> with our advice when the opportunity arises, and charitably, without ever causing offense.</p>

<p>Secondly, it is <em>to teach those who don’t know,</em> especially with regard to ignorance of religion, an ignorance which is the great enemy of God; it increases daily in alarming proportions so that catechesis has become a work of mercy of prime importance and urgency. St. Teresa of Calcutta says ignorance is the greatest poverty.</p>

<p>Next comes giving <em>counsel to the doubting</em>, honestly and with the right intention, so as to help them on their way to God. Then follows the <em>consolation of the afflicted</em>, by sharing their sorrow and encouraging them to recover their happiness in their supernatural understanding of the pain they suffer.</p>

<p><em>Pardon for those who have offended us</em>, promptly and as often as necessary, without giving excessive importance to the offense. We are advised too, <em>to give help to the needy</em>, carrying out this service generously and joyfully.</p>

<p>And finally, we have to <em>pray for the living and the dead</em>, feeling ourselves linked in a special way through the Communion of Saints to those we owe most because of family relationships, or friendship, or whatever else.</p>

<p>Our attitude of merciful benevolence towards others must extend to many different aspects of life because, says St. John Chrysostom, “nothing can make you such an imitator of Christ as your concern for others. Although you fast, although you sleep on the floor, even though, I dare to say, you kill yourself, if you are not attentive to your neighbor, you have done very little; you are very far from being an image of Christ” (St. John Chrysostom, <em>Commentary on the First Epistle to the Corinthians</em>).</p>

<p>We will ourselves obtain God’s mercy and perhaps also merit it for others in that immense depth of “mercy that extends from generation to generation,” as Our Lady prophesied to her cousin Elizabeth (Luke 1:50).</p>

<p>We can also call down the divine mercy on ourselves, who are so much in need of it.</p>

<p>As Christians, we manifest our unity of life by encouraging the works of justice and mercy. Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse the lepers...</p>

<p>From the Church’s earliest days, faithful Christians spread the faith to all parts of the world. From those first years too, vast numbers of Christians have “committed their powers and their lives to liberation from every form of oppression and to the promotion of human dignity.</p>

<p>“The experience of the saints and the example of so many works of service to one’s neighbor are an incentive and a beacon for the liberating undertakings that are needed today,” said the Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith (CDF, <em>Instruction on Christian Freedom and Liberation</em>, Point 57, March 22, 1986).</p>

<p>They are needed perhaps with an even greater urgency than in other periods of history.</p>

<p>Our faith in Christ moves us to be aware of our common involvement with the problems and shortages that other people experience, often with their ignorance and their lack of economic resources.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says this solidarity with our fellow man is not a “superficial sentiment about the evils that beset so many people, whether close to us or far away,” but “a firm and persevering determination to strive for the common good; that is to say, for the good of all and of all individuals, so that we may all be truly responsible for all persons” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Sollicitudo rei socialis</em>–The Concern of the Church for the Social Order, Point 38, December 3, 1987).</p>

<p>Faith leads us to feel a deep respect for others, for each person, and never to remain indifferent to other people’s needs.</p>

<p>Following Christ will manifest itself in deeds of justice and mercy; it will show itself too in our determination to get to know the principles of the social doctrine of the Church and to carry them out, first of all in all our surroundings, right there where we live.</p>

<p>I remember my father coming back from bringing us to swimming lessons as kids. We’d see sometimes a crocodile file of orphans who were going to a local orphanage and were coming from, maybe, the beach as well.</p>

<p>We didn’t know who these people were, what these kids were about, or what was their problem. We didn’t understand. I remember him buying ice cream for those kids, and we were still left with question marks.</p>

<p>Only many years later do you realize what that little gesture was, from a father of a family, in silence, doing that little gesture. It left its mark.</p>

<p>This period coming up to Christmas is a very interesting period, a potential period to engrave these messages in the lives of our children.</p>

<p>It should be possible to say of each one of us at the end of our lives, as it was said about Our Lord: “He went about doing good” (<em>cf</em>. Acts 10:38).</p>

<p>We have to do good within our own families, among our colleagues at work and among our friends, and even with those people whom we just chance to come across.</p>

<p>Our Lord has opportunities outlined for us. There’s a document of the Spanish Episcopal Conference, <em>Catholics in Public Life,</em>which says: “As disciples of Christ, we have to be stewards of fraternity, whatever occasions and circumstances life brings with it. When a man or woman lives the Christian spirit in all its intensity, all his or her activities and relationships reflect and communicate God’s love and the surpassing goods of the Kingdom.</p>

<p>“As Christians we need to know how to make fast and strengthen our relationships each day with our families, our friends, and our neighbors, whether we are at work or at leisure, sealing them with the seal of Christian love, which is simplicity, truthfulness, faithfulness, meekness, generosity, solidarity, and joy.”</p>

<p>We can ask for the mercy of God to be extended to our generation through Mary, Mother of Mercy, our life, our sweetness, and our hope (Prayer, <em>Hail Holy Queen</em>).</p>

<p>Now that the Feast of the Immaculate Conception is so near, our confident reliance on Our Lady will, if we have recourse to her, be more continuous and loving.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MML</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abandonment</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abandonment" /><published>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Gospel, “Can you not buy two sparrows for a penny? Yet not one falls to the ground without your Father knowing” (Matt. 10:29).</p>

<p>Our Lord uses this curious analogy of us with sparrows. It’s curious that He would want to compare us to sparrows, but yet there is a very important message there.</p>

<p>We look at a sparrow, and you blow at a sparrow, it could fall over; very fragile, very timid, not very strong. And yet God tells us that this sparrow can't do a single thing “without your Father knowing” about it and we are “of much more value than any sparrow” (Matt. 10:31).</p>

<p>Our Lord is inviting us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of trust and abandonment. This trust and abandonment, to a large extent, flows from the fact that we are children of God.</p>

<p>We celebrated a few days ago, at the beginning of the month, the Baptism of Our Lord, the institution of the Sacrament of Baptism. Through that sacrament and through all the other sacraments we get divine grace into our soul.</p>

<p>Divine grace is the presence of the Blessed Trinity within us.</p>

<p>Our Lord said we will “come and make our abode in him” (cf. John 14:23), and so when we are in the state of grace, God is in our soul. Therefore, all the fruits of God can be present in our life, in our words, in our actions.</p>

<p>Hopefully, people can somehow detect that this person is trying to lead a holy life, that they're in a state of grace, and therefore God is in control.</p>

<p>If we are not in the state of grace, if God is not in our soul in grace, then the devil may be there. Then all the fruits of the devil can be present in our life, in our works, in our actions, in the atmosphere we carry with us.</p>

<p>Because God is there within us in our soul in grace, we're told in Scripture that we become “children of God” (1 John 3:1). We're told that we're carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves us.</p>

<p>Therefore, everything that happens to us in our life, we can try to see from a supernatural perspective, and see that God is somehow in control, or He has permitted this particular thing—this joy, or sometimes this sorrow, or this contradiction, or this difficulty, or this challenge.</p>

<p>Or sometimes God can sweep the feet from under us and leave us hanging there. And when that happens it’s because He wants us to learn how to trust in Him, to have a great sense of abandonment like the sparrows.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, Our Lord says: “Look at the birds of the air: they neither sow nor reap or gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of abandonment and trust and leave things in His hands. On the one hand, He wants us to use all the human initiative that we have to solve problems.</p>

<p>When He sent the apostles out, He said: “Go ye therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:19). He didn't build chapels. He didn't build schools or hospitals. He didn't give them technology or money or all the other means to fulfill their mission.</p>

<p>He just sent them out with a few ideas. Those ideas were very important ideas, and He wanted them to convert the world with those ideas. He wanted them to be very clear that He would be acting in them and through them.</p>

<p>What He wanted was their faith, their trust, and their abandonment, that He would be at work through them.</p>

<p>Shortly after I was ordained, I was giving a retreat in the south of Spain. (I was ordained there.) There was a number of men on the retreat.</p>

<p>On the first day of the retreat, an 80-year-old man came to chat with me. Usually, people wait a few hours or a few days before they talk to the priest about their resolutions or what they've got from the retreat.</p>

<p>This man came first thing that morning and told me, “You know, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for a number of years, and the person in charge of the recollection asked me if I would come to this retreat. I said no, and I had three very good reasons for saying no.</p>

<p>“One is that I train a certain type of horse. There are some people coming these days to buy some of my horses from another country. I want to be there when they come.</p>

<p>“Secondly, there are some people coming to put drains on my house and I've been waiting for two years for them to come to put drains on my house. I want to be there also when they come.</p>

<p>“Thirdly, it's the weekend of the local fiesta, which is a big thing in Spain. Ever since I was seven, I have never missed this local feast. All my friends will be there. It’s a time to catch up. We meet, we talk, we set ourselves up for the next year. It's just unthinkable that I wouldn't be at the local fiesta.</p>

<p>“So I had three very good reasons for telling this man who was in charge of this recollection that I would not go on the retreat. And he asked me again a few weeks later, and again, I said no; and he asked me a third time, and again, I said no.”</p>

<p>But then he said, “I began to feel very uncomfortable, and the only way that I could find any peace was to finally say yes, and so here I am on this retreat very reluctantly. I came thinking about all the things I'm missing, but you know, I've only been here a couple of hours, and already I'm very glad I came.</p>

<p>“Because you see, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for the last couple of years, and I keep hearing this idea of divine filiation—that we are all children of God because God lives in our soul in grace. They talk about the life of childhood and spiritual childhood, and I've been trying to figure out what this means.</p>

<p>“Here I am, 80 years of age, and they're telling me I have to become like a child. What does that mean? Does it mean I have to put on short pants or what?</p>

<p>“Now I've come to realize what it means. I have to abandon myself into the arms of my Father God. I've got to let Him call the shots.I've got to let Him make the decisions.</p>

<p>“I've got to try and let myself be like a little child in the arms of his Father, with one hand in the hand of his Father, let God lead me and go where He leads me, irrespective of all the other human or material considerations. I've got to try and do His Will and do His thing, in fact, my Christian vocation.”</p>

<p>In those days, it was as though that man discovered “the pearl of great price” (Matt. 13:45-46).</p>

<p>There are treasures in the Gospel, great spiritual treasures. At certain stages of our life, God may reveal those treasures to us, and those treasures can be worth far more than all sorts of material things, because it's there that we can find our peace and our joy. A peace and joy that this world cannot give.</p>

<p>Therefore, there is great importance in living in the state of grace, of being close to the sacraments, of learning how to savor these great treasures that God gives us.</p>

<p>I heard of a kid once who was walking along the beach and his foot hit against a pouch of stones. He picked up the pouch of stones, and he began to take a stone, and he flung it as far as he could into the sea. He said at the same time, ‘When I grow rich, I'm going to get myself a big house.’</p>

<p>He flung another stone and said, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy myself a fine car’; and another stone, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy fine clothes’; and another stone, ‘I'm going to have great food.’</p>

<p>One by one, he threw all the stones as far as he could into the sea. When he got down to the last stone, suddenly a little sunbeam or something hit the stone and it glistened. So, he looked again. It was a diamond!</p>

<p>He'd been throwing diamonds far out into the sea, dreaming about treasures that he might never have, but he'd been throwing away the treasures that he had in his hand.</p>

<p>With this story, we have to come to try and realize that maybe we have great treasures in our lives, in our spiritual life in particular, things that we are perhaps not as aware of as we could be. We don't realize the treasures.</p>

<p>One great way of trying to get to know the treasures that we have in our life is through acts of thanksgiving.</p>

<p>If you thank God from the moment you get up in the morning until the moment you get to bed at night, for the fact that you can see, the fact that you can hear, the fact that you can walk around the place and have two arms and two legs—these are all wonderful treasures that can lead us to appreciate all the other treasures that are present every day of our life: the air that we breathe, the things that we see, the health of the people around us.</p>

<p>There are so many wonderful things to be grateful for. So we need to learn how to abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>I got a haircut last week in Nairobi, and when I came out of the place where I got it, I was driving up the street and saw a young girl crawling on all fours with a little cup, begging. Not something you often see: a young girl crawling on all fours, she had no wheelchair, she had nothing.</p>

<p>The following day, with a friend of mine, we decided to go and look for this girl and try and see if we could do something for her. We found her in a completely different place, purely by accident, crawling across a busy street with several crossings.</p>

<p>So my friend got out of the car and went to talk to her. She had no English and I don't have Swahili. They talked and she explained that she was from Migori. She was 22, she had come to Nairobi two years previously, she lived with two other people with disabilities, and somehow, she had managed to survive.</p>

<p>When she moved around Nairobi, she would hop onto a <em>matatu</em>. She got to different places from which she could beg, and she managed to carry on like this: a very cheerful lady and very happy to talk.</p>

<p>Then she came with us and we got her a wheelchair. Hopefully, she's now using that wheelchair.</p>

<p>But thinking about how that girl has survived in an unknown city far away from her home territory, and not having English, and not knowing the place, and managing to move around like that—there must be a tremendous abandonment in her, in her life, in her spirit. She went away from her own home to a strange place.</p>

<p>So sometimes with people we meet we can learn an awful lot about the spirit of abandonment, trust, of having faith in God, because we know that God has a plan for us.</p>

<p>He wants us to live out that plan. He has a mission for us. There's nothing in our life that He has not foreseen.</p>

<p>And so, as we start a new year we could try to ask Our Lord in the Blessed Sacrament that we might have a greater spirit of faith and trust and abandonment to live out those consequences of being a child of God, so that we may leave the future in His hands.</p>

<p>And if we see, as we can probably do, that when we look back, God has really taken care of so many things in our life: our primary education, our secondary education, perhaps our tertiary education, our work, our family, our children, our health—so many things that God has looked after in all sorts of special ways. We have every reason to grow in faith and trust in Him.</p>

<p>St. Thérèse of Lisieux says, “When…we feel no courage, no energy, for the practice of virtue, this is grace” (Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>Letters of Soeur Thérèse to Céline</em>, October 20, 1888). This is the moment to depend solely on Jesus.</p>

<p>There might be moments in our life when Our Lord precisely sweeps the feet from under us and leaves us hanging there. In those situations, He wants us to look up.</p>

<p>He wants us to trust completely in Him, to leave things in His hands, to learn what real hope is, what real abandonment is.</p>

<p>A farmer told me how one time he was going through his farm, and there’d been a fire on the farm. He came across all sorts of things that had been very burnt.</p>

<p>At one moment he came across a chicken that was very badly burnt, totally dead, and he gave it a good kick—this chicken that was totally dead, burnt black—but out from underneath the chicken ran four or five little chicks.</p>

<p>He said, “I suddenly remembered that phrase from Scripture: ‘I will gather you under my wing as a hen gathers her chicks’” (Matt. 23:27).</p>

<p>He said this hen saw the danger, the fire coming, she gathered her chicks. So he was very aware of the fact that Our Father God looks after us in all sorts of ways, takes care of us, preserves us from danger.</p>

<p>Sometimes we might wonder, Why? Why did this happen to my family, to my parents, to my siblings, to my children, to my work? Why do all these things specifically happen to me?</p>

<p>In certain moments, we may not appreciate that. But when time passes, sometimes we can discover there's some great divine plan behind the cross. God is at work. He has other plans that He's working out.</p>

<p>A man in another country told me once how he had a primary school education. He began to be a salesman selling pots and pans.</p>

<p>He knocked one day on the door of the president of the Ford Corporation who didn't want any pots and pans. He thought he would get his wife, but he got the husband.</p>

<p>But the husband was impressed with his sales pitch. He said, “Young man, how would you like to try selling cars? OK? So come along on Monday morning, we'll start you out selling cars.”</p>

<p>So he sold a lot of cars. He graduated to Mercedes-Benzes. He ended up importing Rolls Royces from London. He could tell you the mileage on the clock of every Rolls Royce in Asia. He made a lot of money.</p>

<p>Then he gave a present of a watch to some man in government, which is something you cannot do in that particular country. The government turned around and bankrupted him.</p>

<p>So he lost everything. He lost all his money. He lost his house. He lost his business. His wife left him. At the age of 49, he developed stage 4 cancer.</p>

<p>That's when I got to know him. He used to go to a support group in his parish for people who were recovering from cancer. This was a fairly well-to-do parish with a lot of wealthy people, and they would get together and talk week by week.</p>

<p>Then they heard of a new drug that had been made in Houston, Texas, a new cancer drug which was very expensive. One by one all these very wealthy people flew off to Houston, Texas to try out this new drug.</p>

<p>He came to me and he said, “You know, it's not fair. There’s no justice in this world. The wealthy can do all these things, and here I am, I’m bankrupt, they’ve taken away my passport, I can't leave the country, I couldn't have any money to fly, and so poor me, I can't try out this new drug.”</p>

<p>And he said, “I was complaining to God for weeks and months about how unfair this life is. Then, you know, the first one died; and then after three months, the next one died; and after six months, another one died; and now they're nearly all dead and I'm still here. So I'm saying thank you, Lord, thank you, Lord.”</p>

<p>So sometimes all the injustices of this world are the things that we find we can do. When time passes and you look back, sometimes you can see, maybe the hand of God was working in funny ways here.</p>

<p>Maybe God has me in the palm of His hand, looking after me in special ways or looking after my family.</p>

<p>There are times when there are things that maybe we'd like to have and we can't have them. God doesn't permit us to have them: luxuries or things that other people have. Maybe it's because God just wants us to trust in Him, to abandon ourselves. He has some other plan. Maybe that's not our mission.</p>

<p>When there are things in life that we find other people have, and we can't afford them and we can't have them, it may be that God is forming our soul at that moment more than at any other time.</p>

<p>Perhaps He's giving us spiritual treasures, teaching us what authentic detachment means, or teaching us authentic hope or authentic trust, which ultimately are the messages that Christ gives to us in Bethlehem.</p>

<p>Christ abandoned Himself in Bethlehem into the arms of Mary, into the arms of Joseph.</p>

<p>Sometimes that's what God wants us to do. If we were to hear tomorrow that we have some fatal disease, we can abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God. It can be totally peaceful.</p>

<p>I knew some men a couple of years ago who used to come to recollections like this. Both of them developed cancer, but they were leading very good spiritual lives.</p>

<p>They happened to find themselves in the same hospital room, and one said to the other: “Are you worried about anything? Do you feel bad about anything?” “No, I'm very peaceful.” “Me too, there’s nothing to worry about. I leave everything in the hands of God. It's a great way to live and a great way to die.”</p>

<p>It’s a wonderful thing to be able to look forward to our death because our souls are in the right state.</p>

<p>In the house where I lived, two people passed away in the last two or three months. One was 87, the other was 94. They were both looking forward to their death.</p>

<p>The 94-year-old priest in particular kept saying, “I want to die. I want to die.”</p>

<p>We brought him into the hospital at one stage, The Mater Hospital in Nairobi, and the nurse said to me, “You know, he keeps saying he wants to die, he wants to die, but everyone in this hospital wants to live. We’re wondering, is there something wrong? Is there something we should be doing?”</p>

<p>At one moment he refused all his medication and all of his food. I said to him, “Father, why don't you eat your food or take your medicine?”</p>

<p>“It's the only weapon I have to get out of this place.” So he had a great sense of humor. He died laughing. A great way to live and a great way to die. Abandonment in the moment of death, in the arms of God, because he lived a holy life.</p>

<p>Likewise, the other one, 87, saying his rosary every day, getting to Confession every week, receiving Holy Communion every day. I asked him in the last couple of days before he died, “Is there anything that you'd like?”</p>

<p>“Well, if you could find this dark chocolate, I'd be very happy.” I went to the supermarket and I found the dark chocolate. He liked a particular type of dark chocolate. So he went to heaven, enjoying himself! Great way to live, great way to die.</p>

<p>I have no worries, I’ve lived a good life, I abandon myself into the arms of my Father God, because we have tremendous things to look forward to.</p>

<p>“Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered the heart of man, the things that God has prepared for those who love him” (1 Cor. 2:9). If we live our lives focused on heaven, it's a great way to live.</p>

<p>We try to make our life on earth as heavenly as possible, but we realize that everything here is passing. It’s worth nothing, it’s fading away.</p>

<p>The things of the spirit, the things of the soul, the things that are worth having—these are the things worth acquiring, the treasures that God gives to us.</p>

<p>We look at little children, we see how they abandon themselves, and how they can get great joy out of little things.</p>

<p>Over the last few weeks, I was involved in a number of Christmas parties for poor kids. I have a friend who organizes these parties, and he gets big numbers. He brings lollipops and chapatis and sodas.</p>

<p>One time we were going to a place, and I said, Where are you going to get the children for the party? He said, You just watch.</p>

<p>So he gives two sodas to two kids. They go away. Fifty kids come within five minutes. So he gives them a lollipop, one by one.</p>

<p>Well, you see the faces of those kids light up with the lollipops and sometimes they have to struggle to get the tight wrapping off the lollipop, because it seems to be there with concrete or something. They fight to get it off. The joy on their faces, the happiness, the little things.</p>

<p>Sometimes God wants us with our childlike spirit to get great joy and happiness out of simple things. It's a great way to learn to be happy.</p>

<p>In the writings of St. Josemaría, you'll find in one place it says, “Be content with what enables you to live a simple and sober life (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 631).</p>

<p>Great advice. Who do you know in this world who is content—content with what they have, happy with what they have, thanking God for what they have.</p>

<p>A great way to live every day: Thank you, God, for the food we have on the table, for the air that I breathe, for the fact that my hands and legs work, that I can see, that I can hear. So many things that we take for granted too much.</p>

<p>We abandon every day, every hour, in our work, this project, the dreams we have for this coming year, in our workplace, in our family, in the problems we'd like to solve.</p>

<p>Maybe God has precisely given us those problems to work at solving them, not because He wants us to worry about it or be perturbed about it. He just wants us to work at them, but we know that things will work out.</p>

<p>“If you, evil as you are,” we’re told in Scripture, “know how to give good things to your children, how much more will your heavenly Father give good things to those who ask him?” (Matt. 7:11).</p>

<p>If you think back over the last few weeks, how many parents in the world did their best at Christmastime to give good things from Father Christmas to their children?</p>

<p>Maybe even if their children didn't deserve them, they still wanted to give them good things, the best they could find. Our Lord tells us, “How much more will your heavenly Father…” It's a great world for all of them.</p>

<p>Our Father God is waiting to give us all the best presents in the world, all the best treasures, but He wants us to trust in Him, to leave everything in His hands.</p>

<p>Every day of our life we can ask Our Lord for an increase in faith, an increase in hope, an increase in charity, an increase in that spirit of divine filiation, that God is my Father.</p>

<p>There may be twists and turns along the pathway of our life, but we know it will work out well in the end.</p>

<p>There was a little girl who asked Santa Claus for a thousand dolls for Christmas. Her father was an atheist.</p>

<p>She got one doll. Her father said to her, “Well, your God didn't listen to your prayer, did he?”</p>

<p>The little girl said, “Yes, He did. He said no. And that's okay. He's my Father, so it's okay for Him to say no from time to time. You're my father, you say ‘no’ pretty frequently also. That’s no big deal; that doesn't mean you don't exist.”</p>

<p>Wow, profound wisdom from a small child.</p>

<p>Sometimes, God might seem not to answer our prayer. Sometimes He says yes, sometimes He says no and sometimes He says, Wait, I’ll give that to you later. Or, Wait, because I have something better to give you, I have something greater off the line.</p>

<p>Or maybe, I don't want to give you that material thing, but I have some great spiritual thing to give you, which is worth far more than you realize, far more than a diamond. Abandonment!</p>

<p>There is a movie that came out about twenty or thirty years ago about a nun talking to a prisoner on death row. This nun is trying to convert this prisoner, helping him to repent and make his peace with God.</p>

<p>The movie is her conversation with this prisoner on death row, and at one stage she says to him: “Did you ever hear that you are a son of God?”</p>

<p>And he replied saying, “You know, in the course of my life I've been called a son of many things, but I have never been called a son of God.”</p>

<p>Well, this great reality can be something that can open our eyes, that we are truly sons of God, children of God.</p>

<p>God is my Father and therefore I can make this new beginning, this new year, with an awful lot of confidence and hope and trust that God is going to be there for me. He's going to work things out.</p>

<p>When we look back over the last year, possibly we can thank God for all the graces that He's given to us in the past year, all the things that are worked out.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was sitting in her garden, and she noticed there was a rose in the garden. Suddenly her attention began to focus on the rose, a beautiful rose.</p>

<p>She began to think how man has been able to put men on the moon, but no man can make a rose like that. That was the beginning of a profound spiritual conversion.</p>

<p>She began to focus on all the great spiritual things in her life. She’d led a very busy career woman life up to then. She became a very spiritual person.</p>

<p>In this coming year, God also wants some sort of spiritual conversion inside us, so that we live out that spiritual childhood, that abandonment, in so many ways.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to the apostles, “Do not be afraid.” On many occasions He said those words.</p>

<p>In the face of the supernatural, very often there was fear. There was the storm on the lake when He came walking to them: “Do not be afraid! It is I. Have courage, do not be afraid” (John 6:20).</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lord and ask Him that we might also respond to those words. Remember that we're worth more than many sparrows and not a single sparrow falls to the ground without Our Father God knowing it.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord that we might have this greater spirit of trust and abandonment, the trust and abandonment that we see that Our Lady had throughout her life.</p>

<p>She didn't understand what was going to happen in Bethlehem. She didn't know that they were going to go to Egypt. She didn't know how long they were going to be there. She and St. Joseph were just totally, completely abandoned to the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help me to live that spirit of abandonment in the same way that you did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>