<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-04T18:00:14+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">At the School of Mary</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/at-the-school-of-mary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="At the School of Mary" /><published>2026-02-02T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-02T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/at-the-school-of-mary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/at-the-school-of-mary/"><![CDATA[<p>At the School of Mary</p>

<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul II says that if we want to “rediscover in all its richness the profound relationship between the Church and the Eucharist, we cannot neglect Our Lady, Mother and model of the Church” (John Paul II, Encyclical Letter, <em>Ecclesia de Eucharistia</em>, Point 53, April 17, 2003).</p>

<p>In the Apostolic Letter that he wrote for the Year of the Rosary called <em>The Rosary of the Virgin Mary</em>, he pointed out Our Lady as “our teacher in contemplating Christ’s face” and also, among the <em>Mysteries of Light</em> in that document, he included The Institution of the Eucharist (John Paul II, <em>ibid</em>. and Apostolic Letter, <em>Rosarium Virginis Mariae</em>, Point 21, October 16, 2002).</p>

<p>He says, “Mary can guide us towards this most holy sacrament, because she herself has a profound relationship with it. At first glance, the Gospel seems silent on the subject. The account of the institution of the Eucharist on the evening of Holy Thursday makes no mention of Our Lady.</p>

<p>“Yet we know that she was present among the Apostles who prayed ‘with one accord’ (<em>cf</em>. Acts 1:14) in the first community which gathered after the Ascension in expectation of Pentecost.</p>

<p>“…Our Lady must have been present at the Eucharistic celebrations of the first generation of Christians who were devoted to ‘the breaking of bread’ (Acts 2:42).</p>

<p>“But in addition to her sharing in the Eucharistic banquet, an indirect picture of Our Lady’s relationship with the Eucharist can be had, beginning with her interior disposition” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “Mary is a ‘woman of the Eucharist’ in her whole life. The Church, which looks to Mary as a model, is also called to imitate her in her relationship with this most holy mystery” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>We refer to the Eucharist as the mystery of faith. “If the Eucharist is a mystery of faith which so greatly transcends our understanding as to call for the sheer abandonment to the word of God, then there can be no one like Our Lady to act as our support and guide in acquiring that disposition. In repeating what Christ did at the Last Supper in obedience to his command, ‘Do this in memory of me’ (Luke 22:19), we also accept Our Lady’s invitation to obey him without hesitation: ‘Do whatever he tells you’ (John 2:5).</p>

<p>“With the same maternal concern which she showed at the wedding feast of Cana, Our Lady seems to say to us: ‘Do not waver; trust in the words of my Son. If he was able to change water into wine, he can also turn bread and wine into his body and blood, and through this mystery bestow on believers the living memorial of his Passover, thus becoming the bread of life’ (<em>Ecclesia de Eucharistia</em>, Point 54).</p>

<p>“In a certain sense, Our Lady lived her Eucharistic faith even before the institution of the Eucharist, by the very fact that she offered her virginal womb for the incarnation of God’s Word. The Eucharist, while commemorating the passion and resurrection, is also in continuity with the incarnation. At the Annunciation Mary conceived the Son of God in the physical reality of his body and blood, thus anticipating within herself what to some degree happens sacramentally in every believer who receives the Lord’s body and blood under the signs of bread and wine.</p>

<p>“…there is a profound analogy between the <em>Fiat</em> [‘let it be done’], which Mary said in reply to the angel, and the <em>Amen</em> which every believer says when receiving the body of the Lord. Mary was asked to believe that the One whom she conceived ‘through the Holy Spirit’ was ‘the Son of God’ (Luke 1:30-35). In continuity with Our Lady’s faith, in the Eucharistic mystery we are asked to believe that the same Jesus Christ, Son of God and Son of Mary, becomes present in his full humanity and divinity under the signs of bread and wine.</p>

<p>“‘Blessed is she who believed’ (Luke 1:45). Our Lady also anticipated, in the mystery of the incarnation, the Church’s Eucharistic faith. When, at the Visitation, she bore in her womb the Word made flesh, she became in some way a ‘tabernacle’—the first ‘tabernacle’ in history—in which the Son of God, still invisible to our human gaze, allowed himself to be adored by Elizabeth, radiating his light as it were through the eyes and the voice of Mary. And is not the enraptured gaze of Our Lady as she contemplated the face of the newborn Christ and cradled him in her arms that unparalleled model of love which should inspire us every time we receive Communion?” (<em>ibid</em>., Point 55).</p>

<p>“Our Lady, throughout her life at the side of Christ and not only on Calvary, made her own the sacrificial dimension of the Eucharist. When she brought the Child to the Temple in Jerusalem ‘to present him to the Lord’ (Luke 2:22), she heard the aged Simeon announce that the child would be ‘a sign of contradiction’ and that a sword would pierce her own heart (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:34–35).</p>

<p>“The tragedy of her Son’s crucifixion was thus foretold, and in some sense, Mary’s <em>Stabat Mater</em>, [standing] at the foot of the Cross, was foreshadowed. In her daily preparation for Calvary, Our Lady experienced a kind of ‘anticipated Eucharist’—one could say a ‘spiritual communion’—of desire and of offering, which would culminate in her union with her Son in his passion, and then find expression after Easter by her partaking in the Eucharist which the Apostles celebrated as the memorial of that passion.</p>

<p>“What must Our Lady have felt as she heard from the mouth of Peter, John, James, and the other Apostles the words spoken at the Last Supper: ‘This is my body which is given for you’ (Luke 22:19)? The body given up for us and made present under sacramental signs was the same body which she had conceived in her womb! For Our Lady, receiving the Eucharist must have somehow meant welcoming once more into her womb that heart which had beaten in unison with hers and reliving what she had experienced at the foot of the Cross” (<em>ibid</em>, Point 56).</p>

<p>“In the ‘memorial’ of Calvary, all that Christ accomplished by his passion and death is present. Consequently, all that Christ did with regard to his Mother for our sake is also present. To her he gave the beloved disciple, and, in him, each of us: ‘Behold your son!’ To each of us he also says: ‘Behold your mother!’ (<em>cf</em>. John 19:26-27).</p>

<p>“Experiencing the memorial of Christ’s death in the Eucharist also means continually receiving this gift. It means accepting, like John, the one who is given to us anew as Our Mother. It also means taking on a commitment to be conformed to Christ, putting ourselves at the school of his Mother and allowing her to accompany us.</p>

<p>“Our Lady is present, with the Church and as the Mother of the Church, at each of our celebrations of the [Eucharist]. If the Church and the Eucharist are inseparably united, the same ought to be said of Our Lady and the Eucharist. This is one reason why, since ancient times, the commemoration of Our Lady has always been part of the Eucharistic celebrations of the Churches of East and West.</p>

<p>“In the Eucharist, the Church is completely united to Christ and his sacrifice, and makes her own the spirit of Mary. This truth can be understood more deeply by rereading the <em>Magnificat</em> in a Eucharistic key. The Eucharist, like the Canticle of Mary, is first and foremost praise and thanksgiving. When Our Lady exclaims: ‘My soul magnifies the Lord and my spirit rejoices in God my Savior’ (Luke 1:46–47), she already bears Jesus in her womb. She praises God ‘through’ Jesus, but she also praises him ‘in’ Jesus and ‘with’ Jesus. This is itself the true ‘Eucharistic attitude.’</p>

<p>“At the same time, Our Lady recalls the wonders worked by God in salvation history in fulfillment of the promise once made to the fathers (<em>cf</em>. Luke 1:55), and proclaims the wonder that surpasses them all, the redemptive incarnation.</p>

<p>“Lastly, the <em>Magnificat</em> also reflects the eschatological tension of the Eucharist. Every time the Son of God comes again to us in the ‘poverty’ of the sacramental signs of bread and wine, the seeds of that new history wherein the mighty are ‘put down from their thrones’ and ‘those of low degree are exalted’ (<em>cf</em>. Luke 1:52), take root in the world.</p>

<p>“Our Lady sings of the ‘new heavens’ and the ‘new earth’ which find in the Eucharist their anticipation and in some sense their program and plan.</p>

<p>“The <em>Magnificat</em> expresses Our Lady’s spirituality, and there is nothing greater than this spirituality for helping us to experience the mystery of the Eucharist. The Eucharist has been given to us so that our life, like that of Our Lady, may become completely a <em>Magnificat</em>” (<em>ibid</em>., Points 57-58).</p>

<p>John Paul II said, “Several years ago I celebrated the fiftieth anniversary of my priesthood. Now I write this Encyclical on the Eucharist [on the Holy Thursday] that falls during the twenty-fifth year of my Petrine ministry.</p>

<p>“As I do so,” he said, “my heart is filled with gratitude. For over a half a century, every day…, my eyes have gazed in recollection upon the host and the chalice, where time and space in some way ‘merge’ [and] the drama of Golgotha is represented in a living way, thus revealing its mysterious ‘contemporaneity.’</p>

<p>“Each day my faith has been able to recognize,” he says, “in the consecrated bread and wine the divine Wayfarer who joined the two disciples on the road to Emmaus and opened their eyes to the light and their hearts to new hope” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 24:13-35).</p>

<p>He continues: “Allow me…to share with deep emotion, as a means of accompanying and strengthening your faith, my own testimony of faith in the Most Holy Eucharist. Here is the Church’s treasure, the heart of the world, the pledge of the fulfillment for which each man and woman, even unconsciously, yearns. A great and transcendent mystery, one that taxes our mind’s ability to pass beyond appearances.</p>

<p>“Here our senses fail us: <em>visus, tactus, gustus in te fallitur</em>, in the words of the <em>Adoro Te Devote</em>; yet faith alone, rooted in the word of Christ handed down to us by the Apostles, is sufficient for us.”</p>

<p>“Allow me,” he said, “like Peter at the end of this Eucharistic discourse in John’s Gospel, to say once more to Christ, in the name of the whole Church and in the name of each one of you: ‘Lord, to whom shall we go? You have the words of eternal life’ (John 6:68)” (<em>ibid</em>., Point 59).</p>

<p>“The Christian family’s sanctifying role is grounded in Baptism and has its highest expression in the Eucharist, to which Christian marriage is intimately connected. The Second Vatican Council drew attention to the unique relationship between the Eucharist and marriage by requesting that ‘marriage normally be celebrated within the Mass’ (Vatican II, <em>Sacrosanctum Concilium</em>, Point 78, December 4, 1963). To understand better and to live more intensely the graces and responsibilities of Christian marriage and family life, it is altogether necessary to rediscover and strengthen this relationship (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Familiaris Consortio</em>, Point 57, November 22, 1981).</p>

<p>“The Eucharist is the very source of Christian marriage. It…represents Christ’s covenant of love with the Church, sealed with his blood on the Cross (<em>cf</em>. John 19:34). In this sacrifice of the New and Eternal Covenant, Christian spouses encounter the source from which their own marriage covenant flows, is interiorly structured, and continuously renewed.</p>

<p>“As a representation of Christ’s sacrifice of love for the Church, the Eucharist is a fountain of charity. In the Eucharistic gift of charity, the Christian family finds [the] foundation and soul of its ‘communion’ and its ‘mission’: by partaking in the Eucharistic bread, the different members of the Christian family become one body, which reveals and shares in the wider unity of the Church. Their sharing in the Body of Christ that is ‘given up’ and in his Blood that is ‘shed’ becomes a never-ending source of missionary and apostolic dynamism for the Christian family” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>“In the mystery of the Redemption, that is to say, in Christ’s saving work, the Church not only shares in the Gospel of her Master through fidelity to the word and service of truth, but she also shares, through a submission filled with hope and love, in the power of his redeeming action expressed and enshrined by him in a sacramental form, especially in the Eucharist” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Redemptor Hominis</em>, Point 20, March 4, 1979).</p>

<p>The Council has told us that “the Eucharist is the center and summit of the whole of sacramental life, through which each Christian receives the saving power of the Redemption, beginning with the mystery of Baptism, in which we are buried into the death of Christ, in order to become sharers in his Resurrection (<em>cf</em>. Rom. 6:3-5)…</p>

<p>“In the light of this teaching, we see still more clearly the reason why the entire sacramental life of the Church and of each Christian reaches its summit and fullness in the Eucharist. For by Christ’s will, there is in this Sacrament a continual renewing of the mystery of the Sacrifice of himself that Christ offered to the Father on the altar of the Cross, a Sacrifice that the Father accepted, giving, in return for this total self-giving by his Son, who ‘became obedient unto death’ (Phil. 2:8), his own paternal gift, that is to say the grant of new immortal life in the resurrection, since the Father is the first source and giver of life from the beginning.</p>

<p>“That new life, which involves the bodily glorification of the crucified Christ, became an efficacious sign of the new gift granted to humanity, the gift that is the Holy Spirit, through whom the divine life that the Father has in himself and gives to his Son (<em>cf</em>. John 5:26, 1 John 5:11) is communicated to all men who are united with Christ</p>

<p>“The Eucharist is the most perfect Sacrament of this union. By celebrating and also partaking of the Eucharist we unite ourselves with Christ on earth and in heaven who intercedes for us with the Father (Heb. 9:24, 1 John 2:1) but we always do so through the redeeming act of his Sacrifice, through which he has redeemed us, so that we have been ‘bought with a price’ (1 Cor. 6:20). The ‘price’ of our redemption is likewise a further proof of the value that God himself sets on man and of our dignity in Christ.</p>

<p>“For by becoming ‘children of God’ (John 1:12), adopted sons (<em>cf</em>. Rom. 8:23), we also become in his likeness ‘a kingdom and priests’ and obtain ‘a royal priesthood’ (Rev. 5:10, 1 Pet. 2:9), that is to say we share in that unique and irreversible restoration of man and the world to the Father that was carried out once and for all by him, who is both eternal Son (<em>cf</em>. John 1:1-4,18; Matt. 3:17, 11:27, 17:5) and also true Man.</p>

<p>“The Eucharist is the Sacrament in which our new being is most completely expressed and in which Christ himself unceasingly and in an ever-new manner ‘bears witness’ in the Holy Spirit to our spirit (<em>cf</em>. 1 John 5:5-11), that each of us, as a sharer in the mystery of the Redemption, has access to the fruits of the filial reconciliation with God that he himself actuated and continually actuates among us by means of the Church’s ministry.</p>

<p>“It is an essential truth, not only of doctrine but also of life, that the Eucharist builds the Church (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 11), building it as the authentic community of the People of God, as the assembly of the faithful, bearing the same mark of unity that was shared by the Apostles and the first disciples of the Lord.</p>

<p>“The Eucharist builds ever anew this community and unity, ever building and regenerating it on the basis of the Sacrifice of Christ, since it commemorates his death on the Cross (Vatican II, <em>Sacrosantum Concilium</em>, Point 47), the price by which he redeemed us.</p>

<p>“Accordingly, in the Eucharist we touch in a way the very mystery of the Body and Blood of the Lord, as is attested by the very words used at its institution, the words that, because of that institution, have become the words with which those called to this ministry in the Church unceasingly celebrate the Eucharist.</p>

<p>“The Church lives by the Eucharist, by the fullness of this Sacrament, the stupendous content and meaning of which have often been expressed in the Church’s Magisterium from the most distant times down to our own days. … we can say with certainty that, although this teaching is sustained by the acuteness of theologians, by men of deep faith and prayer, and by ascetics and mystics in complete fidelity to the Eucharistic mystery, it still reaches no more than the threshold, since it is incapable of grasping and translating into words what the Eucharist is in all its fullness, what is expressed by it, and what is actuated by it.</p>

<p>“…the Eucharist is the ineffable Sacrament! The essential commitment and, above all, the visible grace and source of supernatural strength for the Church as the people of God is to persevere and advance constantly in Eucharistic life and Eucharistic piety, and to develop spiritually in the climate of the Eucharist. With all the greater reason, then, is it not permissible for us, in thought, life, or action, to take away from this truly most holy Sacrament its full magnitude and its essential meaning. It is at one and the same time a Sacrifice-Sacrament, a Communion-Sacrament, and a Presence-Sacrament.</p>

<p>“And, although it is true that the Eucharist always was and must continue to be the most profound revelation of the human brotherhood of Christ’s disciples and confessors, it cannot be treated merely as an ‘occasion’ for manifesting this brotherhood.</p>

<p>“When celebrating the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of the Lord, the full magnitude of the divine mystery must be respected, as must the full meaning of this sacramental sign in which Christ is really present and is received, the soul is filled with grace, and the pledge of future glory is given (<em>cf</em>. Vatican II, <em>Sacrosanctum Concilium</em>, Point 47).</p>

<p>“This is the source of the duty to carry out rigorously the liturgical rules and everything that is a manifestation of community worship offered to God himself, all the more so because in this sacramental sign he entrusts himself to us with limitless trust, as if not taking into consideration our human weakness, our unworthiness, the force of habit, routine, or even the possibility of insult.</p>

<p>“Every member of the Church, especially bishops and priests, must be vigilant,” said St. John Paul II, “in seeing that this Sacrament of love shall be at the center of the life of the People of God, so that through all the manifestations of worship due to it Christ shall be given back ‘love for love’ and truly become ‘the life of our souls’ (John 6:51,57).</p>

<p>“Nor can we, on the other hand, ever forget the words of St. Paul: ‘Let a man examine himself and so eat of the bread and drink of the cup’ (1 Cor. 11:28)” (John Paul II, <em>Redemptor Hominis</em>, <em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Let us ask Our Lady that she might lead us to always have that great reverence for the real presence of Our Lord in the Sacred Host.</p>

<p><em>I thank you my God for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the School of Mary]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Forming Saints in the Domestic Church (Bethany)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/forming-saints-in-the-domestic-church-bethany/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Forming Saints in the Domestic Church (Bethany)" /><published>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/forming-saints-in-the-domestic-church-bethany</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/forming-saints-in-the-domestic-church-bethany/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Jesus, therefore, six days before the Passover, came to Bethany, where Lazarus, whom Jesus had raised to life, had died. And they made him a supper there. Martha served while Lazarus was one of those reclining at the table with him” (John 12:1-2).</p>

<p>Today is Holy Saturday. It’s a special day in the whole of the liturgical year.</p>

<p>It’s a day of silence. The Church is in mourning for the death of Christ. There are no masses in any church anywhere in the world today, not because of the pandemic, but because this is the liturgical practice. The Church is silent.</p>

<p>We try to accompany Our Lady on this special day in her mourning for the death of her Son. While there is sorrow and sadness, there’s also hope and expectation, because we look forward to the great feast of the Resurrection—the light of Christ who’s going to come into the world to dispel all the darkness.</p>

<p>The apostles have fled. Mary is left alone with St. John.</p>

<p>Today, while Mary is the shining star of the Church, she keeps the flame of faith shining and burning brightly. For this reason, Saturday has been depicted as Our Lady’s Day throughout the history of the Church.</p>

<p>It’s a very Marian day with a special Marian flavor, and we’re here to prepare for the great feast of Easter, but also to focus on the theme of forming saints in the domestic Church.</p>

<p>A relevant topic, because on the 19th of March last week, the Holy Father convoked the Year of the Family to highlight family love. Human love and family love are a reflection of divine love, the most beautiful reality on the planet.</p>

<p>Holy Week is all about love. “Greater love than this no man has, that he lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13). “God is love” (1 John 4:8,16). Christ is love.</p>

<p>And these very special hours that we have been witnessing and living, trying to follow Christ along that pathway, witnesses to love in a very special way. It speaks to us about love.</p>

<p>In the culture that we live in, often we’re told that love is feeling. But feelings can be very deceptive. Feel the feeling, taste the feeling, hear the feeling, sense the feeling.</p>

<p>Christ on the Cross did not feel too good. He had three big nails going through Him. Feelings can be very deceptive, but Christ tells us that love is sacrifice.</p>

<p>With great reason, the Holy Father has convoked this special year to highlight family love, fostering new ways to accompany families on their path to holiness. We’re reminded that the goal of the Christian vocation, the goal of our Baptism, is holiness and apostolate, something that has a daily relevance for us throughout our lives.</p>

<p>This Year of the Family also coincides with the Year of St. Joseph, which began last December.</p>

<p>We could enlist the help of the Holy Patriarch to help us in this year with his intercession for our families, for the families of the whole world, and also that many young people might discover the beauty of undertaking the path of married life while being aware of the Christian family’s evangelizing mission.</p>

<p>The family has a mission. We’re sent. We’re all missionaries.</p>

<p>Christian parents in their Christian family have to try and witness to the great truth of family life, to make Christ present to their children, to try and live like great human beings, so the young children grow, knowing what that means, so that they see a vocation to holiness lived out on a daily basis.</p>

<p>Notice how Our Lord goes up to Jerusalem, but He finds there an atmosphere of hostility, betrayal, iniquity, hatred, envy, jealousy, all the ugly things, and so He withdraws to Bethany, to a home, to the domestic Church of Martha and Mary and Lazarus, and He feels very much at home there.</p>

<p>He’s felt at home there on many other occasions. He seeks strength there for what is about to come.</p>

<p>The hours that He spends there are perhaps reminiscent of His own home in Nazareth with Joseph and Mary. He spent thirty long years in family life, and only three years in public life.</p>

<p>Christ communicates a great sense of importance to family life, to that formative atmosphere, to the bright and cheerful home that Joseph and Mary know how to create with their virtue, with their holiness.</p>

<p>All the great things that we see Christ doing in Holy Week, carrying His Cross, falling, getting up again, persevering, not coming down off the Cross—it’s as though He learned all these things in the school of virtue that was the family home in Nazareth.</p>

<p>We could never underestimate the power of the Christian home, its formative value to form great men and women, to build the civilization of love and the culture of life that the last few popes, particularly Pope John Paul, have been talking about.</p>

<p>We can ask for the grace to have another look at our own marriage and our own family, to see how we can perhaps begin again, or enrich our family, our domestic Church, to make it a little bit more formative.</p>

<p>I know a priest here in Nairobi who used to work in Rome, and he knew many people there, and he invited an American cardinal to come here to Nairobi some years ago for a conference.</p>

<p>At that time, I was involved in what is now Eastlands College of Technology, a technical school just on the right-hand side at the end of Jogoo Road near the Donholm roundabout.</p>

<p>But at that time, it was just a small little house in Uhuru 4 near Jericho with a Mabati roof. It was a place where kids could come to study because they might not have had room in their own homes, and there were a lot of formative activities there.</p>

<p>This priest brought this American cardinal there to see this place and to have a bit of a get-together with some of the kids who grew there. There were ten or twenty kids in the get-together, very frank and very fresh with their questions.</p>

<p>I suspect they never met a cardinal before or didn’t know too much of what it meant. One of them asked him a very frank question, “Now that you’re a cardinal, can you be demoted?”</p>

<p>They didn’t hold back; they weren’t put off by human respect in the questions they were asking.</p>

<p>Then one of them asked him, “What made you become a priest?” The cardinal told a rather beautiful story.</p>

<p>He said, “When I was five years of age my father was dying of cancer.</p>

<p>“I was the youngest of five children and the priest would come once a week to bring Communion to my father, and my mother organized for us five children to be at the hall door with lighted candles.</p>

<p>“We had a Eucharistic procession from the hall door to the bedroom of my father on the second floor. Once a month, we would wait outside while my father went to Confession and then we continued with our procession.”</p>

<p>The cardinal said, “I thought: what a beautiful thing…to be a priest to bring the Blessed Eucharist to sick people, to comfort them in their souls in moments of difficulty.”</p>

<p>It was a rather beautiful story, but that’s not the major point of the story.</p>

<p>I often like to think about that mother, his mother, who doesn’t figure too much in the story, but yet she’s the one who makes it all happen. She’s a young mother with young children and with a husband dying of cancer.</p>

<p>But yet she has great faith in the Blessed Sacrament, and she organizes this Eucharistic procession in her domestic Church. Now think about that for a moment.</p>

<p>In the school where I live, there is a priest who has been the Chaplain here for twenty-two years and he says, “One of the things I have learned in twenty-two years is that children love fire.”</p>

<p>This mother gives a lighted candle to a five-year-old. He could have burned down the house, but that was a minor problem.</p>

<p>This mother didn’t know that she was forming a future cardinal prince of the Church, who one day would come to Eastlands College of Technology, no less, and share this story with little kids, which I am now sharing with you.</p>

<p>That took place on another continent on the other side of the world. Five or six decades later, here we are talking about the example of that mother on that particular occasion—how she used that opportunity to form her children in Eucharistic piety.</p>

<p>She could have had no idea of where that example, that seed of virtue, was going to end up, enlightening our hearts and minds today, and helping us to see the great formative value of a Christian home, of a mother, of a father, of the power that is there.</p>

<p>We don’t have to worry about all the evils in the world or the ways that we find the devil is having a heyday. Holy Week was a great victory for the devil in some ways, until the victory of Christ.</p>

<p>He overcame death, He overcame the devil, He overcame evil. With Christ in our lives and in our homes, we can overcome every single evil there may be in the world.</p>

<p>The transmission of family values: family values, which are family priorities. Our family comes first. The best times in our lives should be at home and with our family.</p>

<p>I heard somebody say once that a dead father is better than an absent father, because at least if the father is dead, at least the children know where he is.</p>

<p>The importance of presence in the home to form those future saints, so that they grow up seeing what real virtue is, what real holiness is.</p>

<p>I was talking to a Loreto nun here in Msongari a few months ago. She died in January, aged 99, having spent something like 73 years here in Kenya.</p>

<p>I asked her about her vocation and how did her parents react to her vocation. She had two other sisters who were in religious life.</p>

<p>She said, “My father asked me to wait a year. But my mother had no problem because she was a saint.”</p>

<p>Those words stuck with me. What a beautiful thing if our children can see at the end of our lives that their parents were saints.</p>

<p>As her coffin was being lowered into the very deep grave in St. Mary’s in Msongari, I couldn’t help but think of the grain of wheat that falls into the ground and dies, but yet yields an abundant fruit (John 12:24).</p>

<p>If we spend our lives transmitting values to our children, we will transmit values to other people.</p>

<p>This is the great treasure, the great strength that we have, the strength that can overcome every single possible evil there may be in the world.</p>

<p>From looking at this topic and looking at Bethany, where Christ felt at home, where He drew strength, where He found peace and joy, where His heart was able to relax, that heart that was going to be “pierced by a sword” just a little bit later, “blood and water were going to flow”—the fountain of the sacramental life of the Church (John 19:34)—but He finds this human strength and human friendship in that human warmth of that home.</p>

<p>There’s consolation there. There’s a good time there. There’s grace there. We all need those things.</p>

<p>Christ was perfect God, but He was also perfect man, “like us in all things but sin” (Heb. 4:15). He also enjoyed that rest for His soul that He found in that home.</p>

<p>We will form saints in our children if we recreate that atmosphere in the ordinary life that God has called us to live. Christ communicated that great sense of importance to ordinary life. We can be reminded that there is something divine there.</p>

<p>God is present there in your home, in your efforts to form your children, in the example that you give them, in your effort to be a bit more Christ-like, and to use every opportunity to form your children in virtue.</p>

<p>I heard a story recently of a mother who was driving her Standard 2 child home from school, and she got stuck in a traffic jam. <em>Matatus</em> here<em>, matatus</em> there, and she was getting very impatient, banging the steering wheel.</p>

<p>Her eight-year-old Standard 2 pipes up and says, “Mommy, today in school we had a talk about patience and the teacher told us that we have to learn to be patient. And if we’re in Standard 2, we can’t expect to be in Standard 8. We have to take one step at a time. We have to live our age. We have to do this thing now. Sometimes we have to walk instead of running. We have to plan out our activities.”</p>

<p>And he went on for five minutes, blah, blah, blah, giving his mother a talk about all the things he had learned about patience that day. The mother listened patiently.</p>

<p>Then she said, “I felt like turning the car around, going back to the school, and paying more fees.”</p>

<p>In spite of her feeling boiling on the inside, it was a great joy to see that her son had learned such wonderful lessons.</p>

<p>There can be great moments just driving in the car or at the breakfast table, or other very practical moments to transmit messages to our children. My mother used to pray the <em>Morning Offering</em> with us when she remembered at the breakfast table.</p>

<p>We never reminded her if she forgot, but if she remembered, she prayed it. But if she had never done that, I think I would never have heard the <em>Morning Offering</em>.</p>

<p>When I was in Standard 2, there was a teacher who prayed the <em>Memorare</em> every single morning for a whole year. I came from a Catholic family, but for some reason, we never prayed the <em>Memorare</em>.</p>

<p>I never heard that prayer for ten years until I came in contact with Opus Dei when I was 17. I said, “Oh, that’s the prayer that the teacher used to pray in Standard 2.”</p>

<p>I feel very grateful to him now because if he hadn’t prayed that prayer, I would never have heard it. So, use ordinary moments to pray those basic prayers with your children.</p>

<p>A father has told me recently how his two-year-old is beginning to talk. He’s trying to teach him or sing to him the <em>Prayer to St. Michael the Archangel</em>.</p>

<p>The kid can’t quite enunciate the words, but he could just about get some sounds out that you can more or less decipher that it’s the <em>Prayer to St. Michael</em> that he’s saying.</p>

<p>It’s a rather beautiful thing, that at a very early age, we teach our children these things. Teach them to turn to God, where their real hope and joy can be.</p>

<p>I often think that the prayers that a child learns around the time of their First Communion are the prayers they will say on their deathbed. The things we remember, often the greatest period of spiritual formation, are in those early years.</p>

<p>Give a lot of importance to that. Think of ways, with your spouse: How can we make our family life more formative? How could we think, possibly in these times of holidays, to do something for the very young and the very elderly?</p>

<p>If your kids haven’t phoned their grandmother recently, maybe that’s a nice thing for them to do.</p>

<p>I brought a university student to Moranga a few years ago who hadn’t seen his grandmother in two or three years. He’d been at boarding school, many things.</p>

<p>The grandmother was out of the gate of the house, looking down the road to see if he was coming, three times before we arrived. And this 85-year-old, when we arrived—she did a dance around her grandson.</p>

<p>The joy of that 80-plus-year-old lady was magnificent to behold. Sometimes some small things like a phone call can go an awful long way.</p>

<p>Likewise, the effort that you bring your family to visit, maybe an orphanage, or handicapped children, helps them to realize the gifts that God has given to them.</p>

<p>Maybe not now, but over time. It may take many decades before the penny drops. Then they realize the lesson you were trying to teach them, to thank God for everything.</p>

<p>They learn how to lift their heart and soul in thanksgiving to God at every moment of their life. They learn also to live like saints and to build that domestic Church.</p>

<p>I heard a chastity educator in California one time saying how difficult it was to teach California kids to be chaste.</p>

<p>I suppose you could say the same thing about young people all over the world. She said it was a rather hard-sell job.</p>

<p>“But,” she said, “you know, my parents never had to talk too much to us about these things. Because every time they brought home a baby, that baby became the center of our life, of our whole family. He was the most important person in the whole house.”</p>

<p>She said, “They did this eleven times, so we had many opportunities to learn those lessons.”</p>

<p>One of the greatest ways you can teach your children to be saints is in your openness to life, to bring new souls into the world—souls which will give God glory in this world, and they will then go to heaven and give Him glory forever and forever and forever.</p>

<p>I heard a Protestant theologian once who was musing on this reality. He was thinking, “That’s the purpose of the soul in the world.” The greatest thing in life must be to bring souls into the world, to give God glory forever and forever.</p>

<p>And on that basis, he came to the conclusion that contraception must be wrong. So he became a Catholic. Rather an unusual pathway of conversion, but it shows you the power of that truth.</p>

<p>To be open to life at every stage of your marriage requires great faith and great generosity. You become a saint. You don’t just talk about it; you put it into practice.</p>

<p>The happiest women I have known in my life are women who had babies in their 40s, who left everything in the hands of God.</p>

<p>Of course, He rewards them, not just in the next life, but also in this.</p>

<p>One of them told me that ten years later, their peers were looking after their grandchildren, and they were still going to the swings with their own children. Kept them young.</p>

<p>Some of the saints say that maternity makes women more beautiful. It’s one of the greatest witnesses that’s needed from Christian homes in the world at the moment.</p>

<p>For families who are not able to have children, that also opens up a wide panorama of family apostolate—to also form saints, maybe with other people’s children—to give an example of sanctity in the middle of the world, and to see that they’re called, with their mutual love, to provide an example of a bright and cheerful home for those around them; to share that home, maybe with friends, or relatives, or acquaintances.</p>

<p>We help to transform our world into a better home. We don’t know what God is wanting to do with the family formation that we give.</p>

<p>I visited a 95-year-old Irish priest in hospice in Thigio, Limuru in the last few weeks, who said his mother died when he was four. There were eight children. They were farmed out to different relatives.</p>

<p>Their father was a vet; he had to travel around the place. Three of those sons became priests, and one of the daughters went into religious life as a nun.</p>

<p>He came here as a Kiltegan missionary. He was the first priest to go to Pokot in 1952. But he said the Pokot people—they had no education, they had no medication, and they had no Revelation. He spent the next 49 and a half years solving that problem.</p>

<p>Just imagine the family that fellow was entrusted into, somehow formed him in those virtues which were to have such an impact on the people of Pokot.</p>

<p>He told me he tried to learn Pökoot, and after two months he thought he was going mad.</p>

<p>He got on his motorbike and drove 250 kilometers on a Murram road to Nakuru to talk with Bishop Dunne, who later went to Kitui.</p>

<p>The bishop asked him how long he’d been learning Pökoot. He said, “Two months, and I think I’m going mad.”</p>

<p>The Bishop said, “Ah, don’t worry. You’re only early days yet. Get back on your bike go back to where you came from and keep at it.”</p>

<p>That’s what he did, and a couple of years later he translated the New Testament into Pökoot.</p>

<p>Forming our children to be saints, to give an example of virtue to those who come after us.</p>

<p>John Paul talks about the family being “a school of deeper humanity” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Familiaris Consortio</em>, November 22, 1981 and Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et spes</em>, December 7, 1965). I love those words.</p>

<p>He had a couple of short little phrases that are so rich: the culture of life, the civilization of love, the family is the school of love, the school of virtue.</p>

<p>It’s very interesting if parents have little meetings from time to time to see how we can improve our school of virtue.</p>

<p>And now, in the holidays, it’s a great time to put new virtues into practice: teaching order, industriousness, generosity; to spend time helping other people, perhaps people less generous than themselves; or to find a way to earn some money or something.</p>

<p>The Holy Father has called the next World Meeting of Families on June 26, 2022, with the theme, <em>Family Love: A Vocation and a Path to Holiness</em>. Very relevant for this particular topic.</p>

<p>This is on the mind of the Vicar of Christ on earth; it’s ours. The family. Family love. Vocation. Calling to live like great human persons, to reach for the stars, to seek the things that are above.</p>

<p>We can ask St. Joseph to help us to really derive an awful lot of fruit from this year dedicated to the family.</p>

<p>In his letter on St. Joseph, the Holy Father says, “We can ask the Holy Patriarch to grant us the grace of graces: our conversion” (Pope Francis, Apostolic Letter, <em>Patris Corde</em>, December 8, 2020).</p>

<p>Our conversion on this Holy Saturday to tell Our Lord, ‘Lord, no more messing in my life. I want to take this calling to form saints in my children more seriously, to see it as a daily challenge, to have a concrete battle plan, so that we may be better witnesses to God, particularly to God’s love in our own environment, especially in the family, so that we transmit to other people what that means.’</p>

<p>I was at the celebration in Msongari a year or two ago of a Loreto nun who was commemorating her profession, I think, sixty years. She gave a talk at the end, after the Mass and the lunch.</p>

<p>One of the things she said that struck me was, “You know this thing we say very often, ‘God is good all the time.’”</p>

<p>She said, “I don’t like that. I don’t like it: ‘God is good all the time.’”</p>

<p>She said, “God is love.”</p>

<p>She took this little phrase and lifted it up onto a completely different level: to seek the strength we need to bring about that conversion and the conversion of the souls entrusted to us in the form of your children.</p>

<p>We just need to think in a regular way of that simple phrase, “God is love.” When we contemplate the Cross—Christ taken down from the Cross—we’re contemplating love.</p>

<p>On this day, as we try to accompany the sorrowful Mother in a special way, keeping her company with little aspirations of the <em>Hail, Holy Queen</em> throughout this recollection, being a little more silent, a little more recollected, thinking of Our Lady—we can place great hope in the future, like Our Lady did today.</p>

<p>The hope of the Resurrection, the joy that is coming, the optimism—we have all the answers. And with Mary, we can always be victorious because she is always with Christ.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Came To Cast Fire On Earth</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/i-came-to-cast-fire-on-earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Came To Cast Fire On Earth" /><published>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/i-came-to-cast-fire-on-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/i-came-to-cast-fire-on-earth/"><![CDATA[<p>I Came To Cast Fire On Earth</p>

<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in St. Luke, “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already enkindled” (Luke 12:49). We can see the divine zeal of Christ for all souls. Just like any true friend, Our Lord reveals His most intimate thoughts to His disciples. He tells them of His zeal for the salvation of all souls. He has a holy impatience to ignite and to offer His holocaust to the Father on Calvary for the sake of mankind.</p>

<p>He says, “I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am constrained until it is accomplished!” (Luke 12:50). There on the Cross the fullness of God’s love for His creatures was made manifest.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. John, “Greater love than this no man has, that he lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13). We prove that we are Christ’s friends if we struggle to follow Him.</p>

<p>St. Augustine commented, “People who believe in him are enkindled. They receive the flame of charity. That is why the Holy Spirit appeared in that form at Pentecost. We’re told in the Acts of the Apostles: ‘And there appeared to them tongues as of fire, distributed and resting on each one of them’ (Acts 2:3). Set aflame by this fire, the apostles set out across the entire world to inflame others, including their enemies.</p>

<p>“Who were the enemies? That included those who had forsaken God their Creator for the worship of man-made idols.” St. Augustine says, “The faith of such as these has been smothered to ashes. It is good for them that they be set alight by this holy flame, so that they might once again shine forth in Christ’s glory” (Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 96,6</em>).</p>

<p>This crucial task of setting the world on fire has been passed on to today’s Christians. This fire of love and peace will strengthen and purify souls.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us to go to the factories, into public life, to our own homes, to schools and universities.</p>

<p>Chiara Lubich says, “If someone were to set fires at different locations throughout a city, even though they were modest fires, they would quickly consume the whole metropolis.</p>

<p>“Likewise, if in a city, at strategic points one were to ignite the hearts of the inhabitants with the fire that Jesus brought to the world, then the goodwill of those people would quickly overrun the city, lighting it up with the love of God. The fire Jesus has brought to the world is himself. It is the fire of love. This is the love which not only unites souls to God but unites souls to one another.</p>

<p>“In each city, these souls shall emerge from families: father and mother, son and father, mother and mother-in-law. This phenomenon can take place in parish life, in organizations, in schools, in offices, anywhere.</p>

<p>“Each small flame for God necessarily kindles other flames. Divine Providence takes care to distribute these souls on fire where they can best serve the process. Through their action, many places in the world will be restored to the warmth of the love of God and renewed hope” (Chiara Lubich, <em>Meditations</em>).</p>

<p>Our apostolate in the middle of the world should spread like a flame of peace, like wildfire. Each Christian who lives their faith seriously can become a point of ignition at his or her place of work, among friends and acquaintances, wherever they may be.</p>

<p>But this phenomenon will only occur when we make concrete the advice St. Paul gave to the Philippians when he said, “Have this mind among you, which was also in Christ Jesus” (Phil. 2:5).</p>

<p>“The Apostle,” says Pope Pius XII, “challenges all Christians to live out in their lives, as much as possible, those sentiments which filled the Divine Redeemer when he offered himself up as a sacrifice. Imitate his humility and present to God Almighty all the adoration, honor, praise, and thanksgiving” (Pius XII, Encyclical, <em>Mediator Dei</em>, Point 81, November 20, 1947).</p>

<p>This offering is carried out primarily in the Mass, the unbloody renewal of the Sacrifice of Calvary.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council teaches in regard to the laity: “For all their works, prayers, and apostolic endeavors, their ordinary married and family life, their daily occupations, their physical and mental relaxation, if carried out in the Spirit, and even in the hardships of life, if patiently borne—all these become ‘spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ’ (1 Pet. 1:1)” (Vatican II, <em>Lumen Gentium</em>, 34, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>The Council continues in <em>Lumen Gentium</em>: “Together with the offering of the Lord’s body, they are most fittingly offered in the celebration of the Eucharist. As those everywhere who adore in holy activity, the laity consecrate the world itself to God” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Christian life ought to be an imitation of the life of Christ, a participation in His divine Sonship. Through this way of life, we will learn from Jesus how to relate to other people.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew, “When Jesus saw the multitude, he had compassion on them…for they were like sheep without a shepherd” (Matt. 9:36). Life held no meaning for them.</p>

<p>Jesus had compassion on these people. His love was so great that He went to the extent of giving up His life for them and us on the Cross. This is the divine love which should fill our hearts.</p>

<p>Then we too will have compassion on the people around us who perhaps have strayed from the Lord. With the help of God’s grace and our genuine friendship, hopefully we will bring them back to the Master.</p>

<p>In the Mass a surging current of divine love is transmitted from the Son to the Father through the Holy Spirit. The follower of Our Lord participates in this love because he or she is incorporated in Christ. The Christian then extends this love to other people and to all earthly realities, which are thereby sanctified and made into a fitting offering to God.</p>

<p>Our apostolate should have its roots in the Mass and should from there draw its efficacy, because the Mass is nothing less than the realization of the Redemption in our time by means of apostolic Christians.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>Friends of God</em>, “Jesus came on earth to redeem everyone because he ‘wished all men to be saved’ (1 Tim. 2:4). There is not a single soul to whom Christ is not interested. Each soul has cost him the price of his Blood (<em>cf</em>. 1 Pet. 1:18-19)” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 256).</p>

<p>If we truly imitate Our Lord’s example, we’ll never be indifferent towards any soul.</p>

<p>When a Christian participates in the Mass, their prayers should be concerned first of all with their brothers and sisters in the faith. The Christian should feel more and more closely united to them in the “bread of life” and in “the cup of eternal salvation.”</p>

<p>This is the time to pray for everyone, and especially for those who are most in need. We should grow in the spirit of charity and fraternity “because the Eucharist makes us all one. As a consequence, we treat one another as family. The Eucharist unites the children of God into one family, closely related to Christ and to one another,” says Chiara Lubich (<em>op</em>. <em>cit</em>., <em>The Eucharist</em>).</p>

<p>Following this unique encounter with Our Lord, we’ll experience the same joy as was felt by the sick in Palestine once they had been cured by Jesus. They were so overjoyed at this manifestation of God’s mercy that they went about the towns and villages of Palestine singing Our Lord’s praises.</p>

<p>When the Christian receives Communion at Mass, he should be moved to share this wonderful grace with others. Each encounter with the Lord brings with it this joy as well as the need to communicate it to other people. This was how Christianity grew so quickly in its early years. It spread like a conflagration of peace and love which no one could extinguish.</p>

<p>We could make a resolution to center our life on the Mass. Then we will find peace and serenity throughout the course of our day. We’ll want to let our friends know about the treasure of this sacrament.</p>

<p>“If we attend Mass well,” says St. Josemaría, “surely we are likely to think about Our Lord during the rest of the day, wanting to be always in his presence, ready to work as he worked and to love as he loved. And so we learn to thank Our Lord for his kindness in not limiting his presence to the time of the sacrifice of the altar. He has decided to stay with us in the Host which is reserved in the tabernacle” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 154).</p>

<p>The tabernacle should be a Bethany for us. [St. Josemaría] said it is “a quiet and pleasant place where Christ resides. A place where we can tell him about our worries, our sufferings, our desires, our joys, with the same sort of simplicity and naturalness as Martha, Mary, and Lazarus” (<em>ibid</em>.). We will find in the Tabernacle the strength we need to do Our Lord’s work.</p>

<p>In union with many other Christians (<em>cf</em>. Andrés Vásquez de Prada, <em>The Founder of Opus Dei</em>, Volume I), we can repeat those words and meditate on them frequently: “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already enkindled” (Luke 12:49). This is the fire of divine love which will bring peace and joy to souls, to families, and to society as a whole.</p>

<p>In Scripture, we’re also told about the net that the fishermen cast out. The net is like an image of the Church, containing as it does both the just and sinners. We hear a lot about the parables of the Kingdom of Heaven: the hidden treasure, the pearl of great value found by the enterprising merchant, and also the great net thrown into the sea, which brings in all kinds of fish—some good and others not so good, some bad (Matt. 13:44-52).</p>

<p>The fishermen throw the good fish into vessels. The bad fish are discarded. The net thrown into the sea is an image of the Church, which holds both the just and sinners.</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches this same idea on many occasions. His Church contains saints as well as sinners, His friends, and those others who abandon the house of the Father to waste the inheritance received in Baptism. Yet all belong to the Church, although in different ways.</p>

<p>“While ‘Christ: holy, innocent, undefiled,’ as St. Paul says to the Hebrews (Heb. 7:26), knew nothing of sin (2 Cor. 5:21), but came only to expiate the sins of people (<em>cf</em>. Heb. 2:17), the Church,” says <em>Lumen Gentium</em>, “clasping sinners to her bosom, at once holy and always in need of purification, follows constantly the path of penance and renewal” (<em>Lumen Gentium</em>, 8).</p>

<p>No matter what sins they commit, sinners continue to belong to the Church since spiritual goods still subsist in them—goods such as the indelible character received in Baptism and Confirmation, the theological virtues of faith and hope, along with the charity that reaches them by reason of all the Christians struggling to be saints.</p>

<p>Just as a sick or paralyzed part of the body receives assistance from the rest of the body, so it is with the Mystical Body of Christ.</p>

<p>One writer comments, “The Church continues to live in her children who may not be in the state of grace. The Church seeks to work against the evil that corrupts their souls. She struggles to keep them in her fold, to bring them back to life with her love. She conserves them as one conserves a treasure not easily parted from.</p>

<p>“It is not because she wants to carry around dead weight. She only hopes that through the power of patience, gentleness, and pardon, the sinner will make their return to her. It is like the withered branch which for lack of sap is allowed time to regain health and flower once more” (Charles Cardinal Journet, <em>Theology of the Church</em>).</p>

<p>The Church does not forget for one single day that she is a Mother. She continually prays for her children who are ill. She waits with infinite patience. She seeks to help them with abundant charity.</p>

<p>We try to bring to Our Lord our prayers, works, joys, and sufferings for the sake of those who belong to the Church but who do not participate fully in the life of grace. We should especially keep in mind those we happen to know personally who may need to return to the fullness of spiritual life.</p>

<p>The Church is made up of sinners, but is herself without sin. The Church should not be judged on the basis of those who don’t live up to their Christian vocation. The Church is made of sinners, and in some cases great sinners, yet she herself is free from sin. Just as one can say of Christ that He came from above and not from below, so also does the Church have a divine origin.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council says Christ “joined her to himself as his body and endowed her with the gift of the Holy Spirit for the glory of God. … This holiness of the Church is constantly shown forth in the fruits of grace which the Spirit produces in the faithful. It is expressed in many ways by the individuals who, each in his own state of life, tend to the perfection of love, thus sanctifying others” (<em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 39).</p>

<p>The Church knows that she is not a creature of this world. She is not a cultural phenomenon, nor a political institution, nor a scientific school, but a creation of the heavenly Father by means of Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>“Christ has given the Church his words and works, his life and salvation. She has been entrusted with this treasure for all generations to come” (Michael Schmaus, <em>Dogmatic Theology, Dogma 4).</em></p>

<p>Sinners belong to the Church, despite their sins. They still can return to the house of the Father, even if it is at the last moment of their lives. Our Lord still wants to spread that flame of His fire, that baptism with which He’s been baptized with. Sinners, having received Baptism, carry within themselves the hope of reconciliation which not even the most grievous of sin can erase.</p>

<p>The sin which the Church finds in her children does not belong to her, but belongs to her enemy. It would be a pity if we allowed people to judge the Church on the basis of what she is not.</p>

<p>Pope John Paul II said the Church “is a Mother through whom we are born to a new life in God. A mother should be loved. She is holy with regard to her Founder, her works, and her doctrine, but she is, nevertheless, composed of sinful men and women.</p>

<p>“It is our duty to make a positive contribution to the life of the Church, to help her progress during the way of faithful renewal. This is not accomplished by negative criticisms” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, Point 3, November 7, 1982).</p>

<p>When people speak of the so-called defects of the Church in days gone by or in the present, they betray a mistaken understanding of the nature of this supernatural institution.</p>

<p>The Acts of the Apostles were told, “Take heed to yourselves and to all the flock, in which the Holy Spirit has made you guardians, to feed the church of the Lord which he obtained with his own blood” (Acts 20:28).</p>

<p>Christ has watched over the Church from its foundation, “having cleansed her by the washing of water with the word, that he might present the church to himself in splendor, without spot or wrinkle,” says St. Paul, “or any such thing, that she might be holy and without blemish” (Eph. 5:26–27). St. Paul writes to Timothy that the Church is “the household of God, the pillar and the bulwark of truth” (1 Tim. 3:15).</p>

<p>We can be very grateful for the Church, and very proud of our Church, and love our Church very much. Let us try to be good children of God in the Church so that we can spread the flame of Christ all the more effectively.</p>

<p>“If we love the Church, there will never arise in us a morbid interest in airing, as the faults of the Mother, the weaknesses of some of her children. The Church,” says St. Josemaría, “the spouse of Christ, does not have to intone any <em>mea culpa</em>—through my fault. But we do.</p>

<p>“The only true <em>mea culpa</em> is a personal one, not the one which attacks the Church, pointing out and exaggerating the human defects which, in this holy mother, result from the presence in her of men whose actions go far astray, but which can never destroy—nor even touch—that which we call the original and constitutive holiness of the Church” (J. Escrivá, <em>In Love with the Church</em>, Point 7).</p>

<p>The Church is the source of sanctity in the world. She continually offers to men the means for drawing close to God.</p>

<p>Pius XII has said, “Certainly our Holy Mother shines out spotless in her sacraments, by means of which she brings forth her children and nourishes them; in her faith, which has never suffered contamination; in her most holy laws, by which she commands all men; and in her evangelical counsels which she proposes to all men; finally, in her heavenly gifts and charisms by means of which, with inexhaustible fecundity, she brings forth armies of martyrs and virgins and confessors” (Pius XII, <em>Mystici Corporis Christi</em>, Point 66, June 29, 1943).</p>

<p>As the fountain of sanctity, the Church has produced many saints down through the centuries. First there were the martyrs who gave their lives for the faith. Later, history records the testimony of innumerable men and women who have spent their lives for the love of God to help others in need.</p>

<p>Has there ever been a human want for which the Church has not shown a maternal solicitude? Countless parents have led heroic lives of silent sacrifice while faithfully fulfilling the demands of their vocation.</p>

<p>Similarly, there are those many men and women who strive to achieve holiness in the middle of the world by living apostolic celibacy.</p>

<p>In short, the Church is holy because, the Second Vatican Council says, “all in the Church, whether they belong to the hierarchy or are cared for by it, are called to holiness” (<em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 39).</p>

<p>By virtue of the holiness of her Founder, the Church, the Bride of Christ, is forever young and beautiful, “without spot or…blemish (Eph. 5:27). She is always worthy of divine favor. The holiness of the Church is an inherent characteristic, part of her nature, which doesn’t depend upon the number of Christians nor upon the depth of their commitment to her.</p>

<p>The Church is holy due to the constant action of the Holy Spirit and not because of the behavior of her members. St. Josemaría said, “I would also like you to consider that even if human failings were to outnumber acts of valor, the clear, undeniable mystical reality of the Church, though unperceived by the senses, would still remain. The Church would still be the Body of Christ, Our Lord himself, the action of the Holy Spirit, and the loving presence of the Father” (J, Escrivá, <em>In Love with the Church</em>, Point 22).</p>

<p>As devout members of the People of God, we can ask Our Lord to increase our desire for personal holiness so that we might be truly sons and daughters of the Church. We ask Him for that grace, that we might truly want to spread the fire, the fire of the Holy Spirit that we’ve been called to spread.</p>

<p>“For this sublime mission, aimed at the flowering of a new age of evangelization all over the world, evangelizers with a special preparation are required today.</p>

<p>“There is a need for heralds of the Gospel who are experts in humanity, who have a profound knowledge of the heart of present-day man, participating in his joys and hopes, anguish and sadness, and who are at the same time contemplatives in love with God. For this we need new saints. The great evangelizers down through history have all been saints,” said John Paul II (John Paul II, <em>Address</em>, October 11, 1985).</p>

<p>We need to implore Our Lord to increase the Church’s spirit of holiness and send us new saints to evangelize today’s world. Lord, may we be always very aware of your words: “I have come to cast fire on the earth, to spread fire, and what would I but that it be enkindled” (Luke 12:49).</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I Came To Cast Fire On Earth]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Holiness in Rest: A Sacred Pause</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-holiness-in-rest-a-sacred-pause/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Holiness in Rest: A Sacred Pause" /><published>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-01T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-holiness-in-rest-a-sacred-pause</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-holiness-in-rest-a-sacred-pause/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“The apostles rejoined Jesus and told him all that they had done and taught. And he said to them, ‘Come away to some lonely place all by yourselves and rest for a while.’ For there were so many coming and going that there was no time for them even to eat. So they went off in the boat to a lonely place where they could be by themselves” (Mark 6:30-32).</p>

<p>The Apostles come back to Our Lord. They have been out preaching and doing things. It’s a moment when they tell Him about the success of all the things they’ve been doing. They’re a little bit on the crest of a wave.</p>

<p>Our Lord could have told them: ‘Out you go again and make full use of this opportunity. Let’s really make good use of our time. Let’s really push to the limit.’</p>

<p>But Our Lord doesn’t tell them that. He said to them, “Come away by yourselves to a lonely place and rest a while” (Mark 6:31).</p>

<p>Our Lord was very convinced of the importance of rest, of what St. John Paul II has called “the sacredness of rest” (John Paul II, <em>cf</em>. Apostolic Letter, <em>Dies Domini</em>, May 31, 1998).</p>

<p>Jesus is playing for the long term. He’s not just interested in momentary or temporary success. He wants them to rest well so that they can regather their strength and their forces.</p>

<p>Also, they can rest in Him with a new spirit of contemplation, which is the basis of their strength and of their future.</p>

<p>These words, taken from the Gospel, also show Our Lord’s concern for His friends—His concern for their rest.</p>

<p>Rest is something important. It’s not just a luxury. It’s an obligation. Sometimes in our life, we need to rest. We need to rest, to recuperate.</p>

<p>We rest in order to be able to work more and to work better, to work more effectively, or to gather our thoughts or think things through, or to cast a contemplative gaze over the things we have done and discern what has been done well, what not so well, what could be done better the next time.</p>

<p>After their intense apostolic mission, the apostles feel a natural tiredness and lack of strength.</p>

<p>It’s a normal human thing to get tired. It’s a very good thing that we’re tired after our day’s work.</p>

<p>Let it be that it’s really after a day’s work that we’re tired—not tired from not doing anything very constructive.</p>

<p>Tiredness is not necessarily a bad thing. Also, when we’re tired we don’t have to go around the place telling everybody how tired we are.</p>

<p>But when they come back and tell Our Lord “everything they’ve done and taught,” Our Lord realizes immediately that they’re tired and that they need rest.</p>

<p>He shows concern for them. “They went away in the boat to a lonely place by themselves” (Mark 6:32).</p>

<p>Each of us has to try and be aware of the need of the people around us for rest, be able to discern when somebody is tired, and create that opportunity or the environment or the things that will help that person to rest. It’s a very normal thing in the family. Everybody needs rest.</p>

<p>Our Lord has made us in such a way that we need seven or seven and a half to eight hours of sleep every night. Maybe children might need a little more.</p>

<p>We come to realize that we need seven and a half hours of rest—as much as that can be sleep, if possible, but there comes a moment in our life when we realize that sleep is a gift. But still, we need to rest.</p>

<p>On other occasions, it’s Our Lord Himself who needs to rest. He’s wearied out from His journey, and so He sits down beside the well (<em>cf</em>. John 4:6).</p>

<p>One commentator has mentioned how interesting it is that St. John gives us a picture of the Messiah worn out from His labors. He sits down beside the well because He cannot take another step.</p>

<p>If Our Lord in His Sacred Humanity, “like us in all things but sin” (Heb. 4:15), felt the need for a justified rest, so also, we have to rest.</p>

<p>There might come a moment in our life when we’re told by a doctor, by a sibling, or by a parent, or by somebody who has charge of us around us that we need to take a break, we need to rest.</p>

<p>We may not be told that very often in our life but if we’re ever told that, we should pay a lot of attention and be very obedient, realizing that the people around us very often know us much better than we know ourselves. They can sense when we need to take a break.</p>

<p>Our Lord has experienced something that’s very consonant with human nature: fatigue. He had experienced it at His work during the thirty years of His hidden life, just as we do each day at our own work.</p>

<p>It’s very logical that after a day’s work, we would need to rest, or at the end of the week. Often at the end of Our Lord’s day, He was exhausted.</p>

<p>The evangelists also tell us that during a storm on the lake, Our Lord fell asleep in the stern of the boat (Matt. 8:24; Mark 4:38; Luke 8:23). He must have been worn out.</p>

<p>We get the impression that He did not suffer from insomnia. He was able to fall asleep in a very unusual place at a very unusual time, with a raging storm all around Him. He’d spent the whole day preaching and He just needed to lie down and be quiet for a while.</p>

<p>He was so tired that He didn’t wake up in spite of the waves. The apostles have to come and say<em>,</em> “Master, does it not concern you that we are perishing?” (Mark 4:38).</p>

<p>Our Lord wasn’t pretending to be asleep in order to put His disciples to the test; He was really physically worn out.</p>

<p>There may be times of real bodily weariness. At these times, Our Lord is also redeeming mankind. His weakness and His tiredness can help us to bear our own weakness and our own tiredness, to co-redeem with Him.</p>

<p>Periods of tiredness can be a time of spiritual bonanza, when we may have to go a bit slower, or we may have to rest a bit more, or go to a different place, or take part in some pastime, or even do something that we find a bit difficult to do because we love to be doing our work.</p>

<p>Sometimes we just have to get away from things and offer up that tiredness that might be physical, but it might also be mental or emotional or nervous or some other type of tiredness that might not be particularly apparent. We might need to rely on the advice of other people.</p>

<p>It’s very consoling to see Our Lord exhausted and to imagine how, in times when we’re feeling low or tired or worn out, Our Lord must be very close to us in those moments.</p>

<p>As we carry out our duties, as we generously go about our professional work, or as we unstintingly use up so much of our energy in apostolic initiatives and undertakings of service to others, it is natural that fatigue appears as an almost inseparable companion.</p>

<p>Far from complaining about this inescapable reality, a reality that is common to all of us, we have to learn to rest close to God and to exercise ourselves constantly in that way of thinking.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>The Way</em>, “Oh, Jesus! I rest in you” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 732). We could often say those words inwardly as we seek support in Him.</p>

<p>Ultimately, we rest in Christ. We rest with the Blessed Sacrament. We rest in our prayer. We rest by living in the presence of God. We rest by living well our Christian vocation.</p>

<p>We don’t take vacations from our vocation. We try to fulfill all the spiritual norms of our <em>plan of life</em>, so that we truly rest in the arms of the Master.</p>

<p>This is the authentic rest that God wants for us, abandoned into the arms of Our Father God, finding a great peace in the knowledge that Christ is looking after everything. We are carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves us.</p>

<p>These may be moments of greater trust, greater hope, greater peace, and abandonment. No one knows our tiredness better than Our Lord does, because He Himself was constantly in situations similar to our own.</p>

<p>We don’t need to make a great deal of noise about what we’re going through or let everybody know what we feel like.</p>

<p>These can be moments when we just try and have to pass unnoticed—to do what we’re told and savor all the great spiritual opportunities that this situation gives us.</p>

<p>We have to try and learn to recover our strength close to Him. Our Lord says, “Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy burdened, and I will give you rest” (Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>Rest is a gift of God, just like sleep. He gives us moments of solitude or of peace. Maybe He gives us a good book that distracts us or a good movie or good music or some of those things that have been created for us to rest ourselves for a while.</p>

<p>God gives us those things so that in Him we can find our joy. We can find that it will help us if we live charity in a purposefully pleasant way towards those around us, even if at times we might find it a little bit more difficult to do so.</p>

<p>We might be on a short fuse; we might be a little bit irritable. It’s a time for greater patience with those around us, a deeper smile, a kind word, offering up the little crosses that may come.</p>

<p>We also have to remember that the use of leisure is an activity that we’re called to sanctify. We find God in the ordinary things of every day. Sometimes those ordinary things just involve being together with other people that make us relax, or looking at the sea, or listening to some music, or reading a good book—but all the time in the presence of God or in the presence of the angels.</p>

<p>The first line of the Mass of the Angels says: “In the presence of the angels, I will sing your praises, my God” (Ps. 138:1). That includes moments of tiredness.</p>

<p>Those periods of distraction shouldn’t be isolated inertial gaps in our lives, or seen as the chance to allow ourselves to indulge in some purely selfish compensation.</p>

<p>When Our Lord sat down by the well, He was also attentive to the apostolic moment. He saw an opportunity when the woman comes to the well. He didn’t say, ‘I’m a bit too tired to talk to this lady’ or ‘Why did she come at this particular moment?’</p>

<p>The apostolic vocation that was part of Christ’s vocation was a constant in His life. It was expressed in all moments.</p>

<p>Likewise, love does not take holidays. In our moments of tiredness, we can also look for apostolic opportunities.</p>

<p>We should realize also that our tiredness is never useless. Our Lord makes use of the periods when He’s recuperating His energies in order to influence souls.</p>

<p>“Come apart by yourselves to a lonely place and rest for a while.”</p>

<p>‘Listen to me talking to you.’ Days and hours of retreat or of other forms of activities can be special moments when we’re recuperating our energies in order to influence other souls.</p>

<p>Our Lord seized upon the opportunity to move that Samaritan woman to a radical change in her life (John 4:7-29).</p>

<p>So the times of tiredness, which can be demanding, can be a cross that we offer to Our Lord for apostolic purposes. Maybe, in more intense periods of tiredness, we could offer each hour of the day—put a name or an intention on every hour, write it down—so that it’s a very intense period of offering up those sacrifices and that prayer.</p>

<p>We make sure that our moments of weariness are not useless but fired with great apostolic zeal.</p>

<p>It may be that “only after our death will we know how many sinners we have helped to save by offering up our tiredness. Only then we will understand that periods of forced inactivity and our sufferings can be of more use to our neighbor than what might seem to be our most effective deeds of service” (George Chevrot, <em>The Well of Life</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lord makes use of our sacrifice. We should never fail to offer up those times when exhaustion or illness might make us feel useless.</p>

<p>‘Here I am, I can’t do anything. I’m confined to this bed or to this chair. I can’t move or don’t have the energy to move.’ Well, never mind.</p>

<p>It can be a powerhouse of apostolic fervor. Those circumstances should not stop us from helping other people.</p>

<p>Tiredness also teaches us to be humble; to accept our limitations. Our pride and our vanity might not be very happy in leading us to realize that we have limitations.</p>

<p>These periods can teach us to be more humble, to live charity better, and to realize at those times that we can’t do everything. We are not the great person that we think we are.</p>

<p>Our Lord allows us to go through those periods sometimes, to let us see the need we have for other people, and how much we depend on other people, and how all the people that God has placed around us are souls that we need very much.</p>

<p>Allowing ourselves to be helped can be a wonderful way of practicing humility. “Here I am, Lord, because you have called me” (1 Sam. 3:5,6,8). You’ve placed me in this situation.</p>

<p>At the same time, since we all become more or less tired, we’re able to understand the words of St. Paul a little better when he says, “Bear one another’s burdens” (Gal. 6:2).</p>

<p>It’s a time to forget about ourselves and think more about other people, of their crosses, of their difficulties.</p>

<p>We can understand that any help that we give to those that we see as overworked is always a great sign of charity.</p>

<p>Weariness can help us to live a greater detachment from the many things that we would like to do, but which we just don’t manage to reach because of the limitations to our strength.</p>

<p>This is the time to turn to Our Lord and say, ‘Lord, you have to take over. You have to finish this. You’ve got to put the icing on the cake. On my own, I can’t manage it. I’m useless. I’m just a useless servant.’</p>

<p>It can also help us to grow in the virtue of fortitude and in the corresponding virtue of resilience—to hang in there, finish things well when we don’t feel like it, when we feel like giving up, to realize that we don’t always find ourselves at the peak of our strength or the very best of health when we have to work, or study, or when we have to see a difficult undertaking through to the end.</p>

<p>In all those tasks, we find highs and lows, energy and lack of energy; that’s all par for the course. It’s a given. But we have to try and go forward in the easy moments and the difficult moments, and we can learn a lot about human work in those moments.</p>

<p>A big part of the virtues we need to put into practice every day involves going on working when we’re tired, not being surprised or scandalized by the fact that we get tired. Often we don’t feel as physically well as we would like to in order to get on with those tasks.</p>

<p>That might be on a daily basis. There might be a lot of tasks we have to do that we just don’t feel like doing. But yet, justice may demand that we get those jobs done.</p>

<p>If we carry out those tasks with that spirit of unity to the cross, Our Lord will bless us in a special way.</p>

<p>The Christian considers life to be an immensely beneficial gift which doesn’t belong to any one of us, but which we have to look after and be responsible for.</p>

<p>Every day we have to try and earn our invitation to the eternal wedding feast. We have to live the years that God wants us to live and go on to complete the task that He has entrusted us with—in principle, a long stretch of life.</p>

<p>As a consequence, for God’s sake and the sake of other people, we must observe the norms of prudence in caring for our health and that of the people who in any way depend upon us.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council in <em>Gaudium et spes</em> says among these norms is the one “that leisure be properly employed to refresh the spirit and strengthen the health of mind and body” (<em>cf</em>. Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et spes</em>, Point 61, December 7, 1965).</p>

<p>We have a duty to try and keep ourselves as healthy as possible, subjecting ourselves to a schedule, dedicating sufficient hours to sleep.</p>

<p>We can’t expect Our Lord to work miracles of energy with us when we haven’t used the human means. Occasionally, we have to stop what we’re doing and go for a walk or an excursion, change our environment a little bit, so that we put order into our activity.</p>

<p>If we were to function in any other way, so long as we’re not prevented by some pressing obligation, that might reveal a certain thoughtlessness or laziness.</p>

<p>That could be very harmful. It could lead us to harm our interior life or slip into an activistic state, be more liable to lose our serenity.</p>

<p>Anyone who is even moderately ordered in the organization of their day will habitually find a few periods of prudently relaxing in the midst of the most demanding and self-sacrificing of activities.</p>

<p>We have a duty to rest: resting in order to serve God and to serve other people.</p>

<p>Sometimes you have to learn to rest. It’s not something we are born knowing. There are ways of resting.</p>

<p>If we can avoid becoming totally exhausted, then we shouldn’t fail to do so. If through some lack of planning or order, we were to come into an excessively tired state, that wouldn’t be a good thing.</p>

<p>God wants us to look after our health, and to know how to recover our strength. It’s part of the Fifth Commandment. We need to rest in order to be fit, to restore lost energy, so that all our work can be all the more effective. We need it also to serve God and other people better.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em>, we’re told, “Remember that God loves his creatures to distraction. How can a donkey work if it’s not fed or given enough rest, or if its spirit is broken by too many beatings? Well, your body is like a little donkey, and it was a donkey that was God’s chosen throne in Jerusalem, and this little donkey carries you along the divine pathways of this earth of ours.</p>

<p>“But it has to be controlled so that it doesn’t stray from God’s paths. And it has to be encouraged so that it can trot along with all the briskness and cheerfulness that you would expect from a poor beast of burden” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 137).</p>

<p>When Blessed Álvaro del Portillo was leaving Rome every summer for a few months for a change of environment, he used to tell people: “I’m going to rest the donkey. I’m going to rest the body so that the body can keep going a little bit longer.”</p>

<p>When we’re tired, it can be all the more difficult to do things well, or to do them the way that God wants us to do them. At such times we might be more liable to faults against charity, or faults at least of omission.</p>

<p>When we come back from resting a little bit, usually we look happier, more cheerful, more sprightly. We bring a joy into the lives of other people around us. That’s charity.</p>

<p>St. Jerome says in an amusing manner, “Experience shows me that when a donkey is tired it sits down at every corner.”</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Way</em> says: “To rest is not to do nothing: it is to relax in activities which demand less effort” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 357).</p>

<p>Often our leisure time can provide an opportunity for interior enrichment, to learn something new, or to read something new. It can present an occasion for doing more apostolate, for fostering a friendship. We shouldn’t confuse rest with laziness.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church has always taken an interest in the physical well-being of her children.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Gospel how occasionally Our Lord stayed and rested in the house of Martha and Mary (Luke 10:38-42).</p>

<p>St. John Paul II pointed out that “rest means leaving one’s everyday occupation, detaching oneself from the normal toil of the day, the week, and the year” (John Paul II, <em>Angelus</em>, July 20, 1980).</p>

<p>It’s important that we don’t wander around aimlessly. Our time off mustn’t just be empty time. It’s very good to have a plan, to plan family fun, to plan family rest, or to plan holiday time.</p>

<p>“Sometimes,” said St. John Paul II, “it would be good to go and enjoy nature—the mountains, the sea, the forest” (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, <em>Angelus</em>, July 20, 1980).</p>

<p>And of course, it should always be desirable for one’s leisure time to be filled with something different, a new content that nevertheless still leads to an encounter with God. We should open up the inward eyes of the soul to his presence in the world and incline our inward ear to his Word of truth (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>We can be very well aware that many nowadays will dedicate their leisure to pastimes and activities which don’t facilitate, and even on certain occasions obstruct, that encounter with Christ.</p>

<p>Far from letting ourselves be influenced by what may be considered fashionable, we should be attentive to this consideration: the same norm should guide our leisure as guides our work.</p>

<p>In those moments we should be able to show our love for God and for our neighbor, doing good things.</p>

<p>It’s never right to do things that are wrong, no matter how tired we are, or how sick we are, or what situation we may be in.</p>

<p>That may mean we choose a suitable place to go on vacation, or we choose well how to plan a journey, or how to profitably arrange a weekend activity away from work.</p>

<p>We should avoid thinking of nobody but ourselves, seeking union with Christ. We rest well by forgetting about ourselves, thinking a little more, and concerning ourselves a little more with other people.</p>

<p>Any time is good for thinking about other people, for looking after them, for helping them, for taking an interest in their hobbies.</p>

<p>Any time is a good time for showing our love. Love doesn’t allow any blank gaps.</p>

<p>Jesus rested out of obedience to the law of Moses. He rested as a result of the demands made on Him by family and friends, or because of weariness, like anybody else.</p>

<p>He never rested because He was tired of serving others. He never isolated Himself, never made Himself unavailable to people, as if to say, ‘Now it’s my turn.’</p>

<p>We should never act from selfish motives, not even when we stop to get our breath back. At those moments too, we should make sure that we’re close to God. Our leisure time is not a pagan time, to be distinct and separated from our interior life.</p>

<p>In the Gospel, Our Lord leaves us with a very special sign of His love: we should be concerned about the weariness and the health of those who live close to us.</p>

<p>We see how, when He sat down exhausted beside the well of Sychar, Our Lord gave us a powerful example. He didn’t let slip the opportunity of doing apostolate, of converting the Samaritan woman.</p>

<p>He did all this even though “Jews have no dealings with Samaritans” (John 4:9). When there is love, not even exhaustion can be an excuse for not doing apostolate.</p>

<p>We also have the example of Our Lady, who went and spent three months with her cousin Elizabeth (Luke 1:56)—a great gesture of friendship. She spent time there. She was open to that change.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to make very good use of our rest times, to plan it well—that of the family, that of our friends, our neighbors—to make it very apostolic.</p>

<p>Through that time, we can recover our strength and bring joy to many other people around us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em><br />
<br />
<em>VA</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Apostolate</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-apostolate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Apostolate" /><published>2026-01-31T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-31T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-apostolate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-apostolate/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>There was a man in Australia once who learned about how to take the apostolic aspect of his Christian vocation a little more seriously.</p>

<p>He saw that God had called him to be “a fisher of men” (Matt. 4:19).</p>

<p>In his prayer he contemplated that reality and all that it meant, to fish souls, to look for them. He saw that God had brought him in contact with spiritual formation activities that helped him to grow in his own spiritual life, in order that he would spread that around to other people.</p>

<p>He began to look at his circle of friends and acquaintances, people that he met in his profession, people he met because of other reasons in his day-to-day life.</p>

<p>He realized that one person that he had sort of struck up a friendship with was the owner of the local petrol station, where he would go to fill the tank of his car every week. This man was a Catholic, and so he invited him to come to a retreat.</p>

<p>The man had never been to a retreat, but he was willing to go, and so he went along to the retreat. Early in the retreat, he heard a meditation about apostolate, friendship, and confidence, reaching out to our friends and trying to influence our environment in that way.</p>

<p>But he thought, ‘I don’t have too much opportunity for friendship and confidence because people come into my petrol station, they fill up and then they leave. It’s a three-minute relationship.’ He decided to pass on that one.</p>

<p>But later in the retreat, there was a talk on the family and about promoting the family. The Holy Spirit began to work and give him some ideas.</p>

<p>He thought, ‘I don’t have too much opportunity to promote the family with my petrol station. It’s a rather unusual way to promote the family.’</p>

<p>But the Holy Spirit overcame these obstacles and gave him the idea: ‘I could make my petrol station into a family-friendly petrol station.’</p>

<p>He began to throw that idea around in his mind and he thought he could have little flags as he wanted to make the place a bit more attractive. He could also have magazines for the ladies to read while the tank was filling. He could have football results for the fathers. He could have slides for the children.</p>

<p>So that was his resolution from that retreat. He went home and he began to implement this resolution. He found it was very good for business. In fact, it was quite lucrative.</p>

<p>All the children wanted to go to that particular petrol station. He was very happy with his resolutions. It had changed his life a little bit. It had given him some meaning, some purpose, some apostolic influence. It had enriched his pocket a little bit. He was very happy with that retreat that he went to.</p>

<p>When he was invited to go again the following year, he readily accepted. Again, he heard a meditation about apostolate.</p>

<p>This time it was about reaching out to your peers, your professional colleagues, and all those in a higher level, “launching out into the deep” (Luke 5:4), being daring, influencing our environment.</p>

<p>Initially, he thought again that he didn’t have too much opportunity to do things like that, to reach out to his peers. ‘I think I’ll just pass on that one again.’</p>

<p>But later on, there was another talk on the family. It was about how to promote the family and help one’s peers to promote the family. And again, the Holy Spirit began to work.</p>

<p>He got the idea that maybe, he could call a meeting of all the petrol station owners in his area and share with them the idea of being a family-friendly petrol station.</p>

<p>That was his resolution from the second retreat. He implemented it and called a meeting of all of these petrol station owners in the area. The result was that they all became family-friendly petrol stations. They all began to use their petrol station in order to promote the family.</p>

<p>From a situation where he thought there was nothing to be done, the whole area looked so barren, there were no possibilities or opportunities, he ended up having an enormous influence on his environment.</p>

<p>One of the goals of our Baptism is holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>If you are a family man, St. Josemaría used to say, our “first apostolate” is within the family (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 91). Friendship with our children. Spending time with them. Being their friends. Influencing with our example, with our virtue. Trying to live like a great human being so that they see what that means and hopefully want to imitate it.</p>

<p>And then, in our profession, in our neighborhood, in our environment, trying to see the souls that God has brought us in contact with. This is the particular area of society in which God wants me to sow seeds and try and leave an impact.</p>

<p>St. Paul says this to the Corinthians: “Mark this: he who sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and he who sows bountifully will also reap bountifully. Let each one give according as he has determined in his heart, not grudgingly or as if by compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver” (2 Cor. 9:6-7).</p>

<p>Every day, every hour of our life, we have opportunities to sow seeds in the lives of other people with the things we say, with the things we do.</p>

<p>Sometimes God wants us to sit down, have a coffee or offer a drink or something, and go one-on-one with our friends and let down the drawbridge of our hearts. Share with them the things that we have come to treasure and to value. Speak to them about God and about the spiritual realities of life.</p>

<p>That’s what friendship is. It’s letting down the drawbridge of our hearts and letting other people see into our hearts and what’s inside there.</p>

<p>And when they see that, then they let down the drawbridge of their hearts and then there’s a heart-to-heart communication.</p>

<p>That’s what friendship is all about. People see that there is something in your heart that they don’t have, and hopefully, they want to have it.</p>

<p>Our Lord in the Gospel said to St. Peter, “Come, follow me, and I will make you into fishers of men” (Matt. 4:19).</p>

<p>It’s a rather unusual phrase, “fishers of men.” And yet Our Lord used it very deliberately.</p>

<p>If you think about what a fisherman is, most fishermen love their fishing. They love to be out fishing. They take very good care of their fishing. They think about the fish. They go to where the fish are. Nobody fishes from their living room.</p>

<p>I saw a fisherman once fishing from some rocks. And he got to the farthest point that he could possibly go to on the rocks.</p>

<p>He had to climb over many craggy edges. He probably cut himself a few times getting to that optimal place, because that was the best place from which to cast his line.</p>

<p>Fishermen maneuver themselves into position because their mind is on the fish, and because it’s not just for the joy of casting the line or just being there. The whole idea is to catch the fish. That’s what it’s all about. He has to think very carefully and very cleverly about what bait he will use for which type of fish.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants then in our prayer that we talk to Him about our fishing. And we talk to Him about the fish: souls. Christ died on the Cross for souls.</p>

<p>He loves it when we go to Him to talk all about our apostolate, the souls that we’re trying to deal with, the ones we’re trying to fish, we’re trying to bring closer to God.</p>

<p>Those are the souls that He’s interested in, the ones He’s placed us in contact with. That’s what it’s all about. And so, our prayer, our conversation with Him comes alive.</p>

<p>It’s like if you’re talking to somebody and they’re a fan of some football club and you hit on the right club, Chelsea or Arsenal, then the conversation comes alive.</p>

<p>The topic that Our Lord loves to talk about is souls, because that’s why He died on the Cross. So, it’s very good to bring those souls to Him one by one.</p>

<p>What do you want me to say to this one? What do you want me to say to that one? Or this son of mine? Or this daughter of mine?</p>

<p>When I sit down with them over a couple of minutes to talk about things, what should I talk to them about? All the time we’re fishing, and every opportunity is an opportunity to fish wherever God has placed us.</p>

<p>When some members of Opus Dei began to go into China many years ago, they met a man who had been in the seminary in the 1940s. The seminary was closed down with the Communist Revolution.</p>

<p>He was thrown out of the seminary, but he felt a call to evangelize. He used to try and talk to people about God, but then the police got to hear about him, and he was arrested because that was illegal. He was placed in prison.</p>

<p>He was sharing a cell with a pickpocket. He thought, if God has placed me here in this prison cell with this pickpocket, He must want me to evangelize the pickpocket. He began to give doctrine classes to the pickpocket, and the pickpocket was very impressed.</p>

<p>He’d never heard such beautiful things before about truth, about beauty, about love, about being happy in the world, the Ten Commandments, about the meaning and purpose of life.</p>

<p>He felt that he should reciprocate in some way for such a great gift this man had given to him. But the only thing that he knew how to do was pickpocket. He gave classes in pickpocketing to the other man.</p>

<p>But then the prison authorities noticed that these two were talking a lot, maybe too much. They separated them into two different cells side by side.</p>

<p>They called out the older man in the middle of the night to interrogate him, to find out what he had been speaking to the pickpocket about. And this man, during the interrogation sessions, was able to use the skills he had learned from the pickpocket.</p>

<p>He noticed there was a piece of wire on the floor. While maintaining eye contact with his interrogator, he was able to reach down with his hand without letting his right hand know what his left hand was doing.</p>

<p>He managed to get that piece of wire and slip it up his sleeve. Back at the cell later on, he was able to use the wire to pick away at the clay in between the bricks.</p>

<p>Little by little, he was able to burrow a hole into the cell beside where the pickpocket was. Now they had a channel of communication. He was able to continue the doctrine classes.</p>

<p>There came a moment when he finished the doctrine classes, and the pickpocket was ready to be baptized. Now they had another problem, another challenge. So then, he got an idea.</p>

<p>He told the pickpocket, “Look, make a loop at the end of the wire and then get the metal mug that you have for your water. Put a bit of water into it and hang it on the loop that you’ve made with the wire. Then put your head under the mug and tell me when you’re there.</p>

<p>“Then I will turn the wire, which will turn the mug, which will make the water flow. And that way you will be baptized.” That’s what happened.</p>

<p>Sometime later, that man came in contact with Opus Dei. He read the homilies of St. Josemaría in <em>Christ Is Passing By</em> and <em>Friends of God</em>. He discovered a deeper aspect of his Christian vocation. He said, “This is what I’ve been trying to live for the last twenty years.”</p>

<p>All over the place, there are opportunities. Sometimes they come to us handed on a plate. But sometimes God also wants us to make those opportunities, to create them, seize them when they come.</p>

<p>There may be people that God will place beside us at a meeting, at a conference, on a bus, or in a shop. Those will be golden opportunities to transmit some message that God wants us to transmit. Or to invite someone to join us in coming to a recollection or a retreat or some formative activity.</p>

<p>We never know how much God is depending on our initiative and correspondence and daring in those moments.</p>

<p>There’s a book by Sister Briege McKenna, available in the Pauline Bookshop, where she talks about how one day she was in the departure lounge of Dublin Airport, waiting for a plane to London at 8:00 in the morning.</p>

<p>She got chatting with the lady beside her. She asked her, “Well, are you going to visit some relatives in London?”</p>

<p>The lady said, “No, I’m going for an abortion.” Sister Briege was shocked. At 8:00 in the morning, that was the last thing she expected in the departure lounge of Dublin Airport.</p>

<p>She told the lady, “You know, that means you’re going to murder your baby.”</p>

<p>The lady said, “Well, the doctor says it’s going to be a handicapped child. And I already have a few children and I can’t manage another one, especially a handicapped one. I’ve talked to all my relatives and friends and they’re all in agreement. They all agree that God is merciful and God will understand.”</p>

<p>Sister Briege McKenna told her, “You know, you’re really going to murder your child. And don’t say that nobody ever told you because I’m telling you now.”</p>

<p>But the lady dismissed her words and didn’t want to hear anymore. The following day when she was going into the abortion clinic, the words of this nun were ringing in her ears: “You’re going to murder your child.”</p>

<p>She found she couldn’t go through with the abortion. She walked out of the abortion clinic. A few months later, she gave birth to a healthy baby boy.</p>

<p>She went back to the doctor and said, “You told me this baby was going to be handicapped.” The doctor said, “Yeah, but we all make mistakes.”</p>

<p>Then she went and she looked for Sister McKenna because she wanted to thank her. She said, “If you hadn’t told me those words in the departure lounge of Dublin Airport, I would have murdered my baby. And now look, I have this beautiful, healthy baby boy.”</p>

<p>We don’t know the influence that God wants us to have, the seeds that He wants us to sow in the lives of other people.</p>

<p>Some seeds fell on rocky ground. Some seed was choked by thorns. But some seeds fell on good ground, grew up, and yielded a hundredfold (Matt. 13:3-23).</p>

<p>God will ask us some day to account for how we’ve used the opportunities that He’s given to us. He wants us to come back to our prayer again and again, and to see what new beginnings He wants us to make, because we’re always beginning again in our apostolic task.</p>

<p>Like the fisherman who casts his line: he casts it once and he casts it twice, maybe he casts it ten times, and maybe, no fish bites. He has to come back another day. Or he has to look for another river or a different part of the ocean. But he keeps on fishing.</p>

<p>And if you observe a fisherman, you’ll see how there’s a great method in the way that he casts his line.</p>

<p>I saw another fisherman once who was fishing from a boat with a big net. He was very purposely letting the net out into the water, very gently, very methodically. He didn’t just take the net, throw it into the water, and say, ‘Here, fish! Swim into this.’ You could see that his mind was on catching the fish, on being effective, being successful.</p>

<p>We have to ask Our Lord for the grace to make our fishing effective, to lead us to the right places, to see where He wants us to go. We have to try and influence society. We have to try and change the way the world does business.</p>

<p>It’s good to ask ourselves the questions, What national and international organizations do I belong to? How am I having that apostolic impact, that Christian influence that God has called me to have?</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Romans, “How are they then to call upon him in whom they have not believed? And how are they to believe him of whom they have not heard? And how are they to hear if no one preaches? And how are men to preach unless they be sent?” (Rom. 10:14-15).</p>

<p>We have been sent: “Go you, therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:19).</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us to have the ear of this friend and that friend. To whisper certain words into the ears of those wavering friends. Perhaps to encourage them about Confession.</p>

<p>Or to share with them our own experience of the sacraments or of leading a deeper spiritual life, or taking our spiritual life a little more seriously, because we know that God has great things planned for us.</p>

<p>Our Lord is counting on us for the huge apostolic work that He wants us to do in this country at this time.</p>

<p>Like all the fishermen and all the saints who came before us, we have to try and refuse to look at the difficulties. There are always difficulties.</p>

<p>When the fisherman goes out to fish, it may be raining or foggy. He might not have the right bait this time, or he might have forgotten to bring something. But he doesn’t just go home because of that.</p>

<p>He keeps on trying. When he goes out on the boat, he uses all the means. He leaves no stone unturned to catch those fish.</p>

<p>If he fails, he thinks about it again. He comes back and tries again the next time, because that’s what it’s all about. St. Josemaría used to say, “We have to go after each soul to win it for Christ.”</p>

<p>“Treat them all with affection. Drown them all in love for Christ” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, The Forge, Point 863).</p>

<p>And it may be that the souls that cross our path or that God leads us to be in contact with have a great hunger to hear spiritual things, either waiting for some sign from God or some inspiration perhaps, to change their life, perhaps to begin again.</p>

<p>We don’t know how God is using our words and our lives and our example. But we do know that He wants us to be His instruments.</p>

<p>It’s very important that we try and increase our own sense of responsibility in the apostolate, and help our children also to think in the same way. Prepare them to be apostles. Expose them to people who have less in this world. Help them to live the corporal works of mercy. Teach them how to be generous, to be concerned for other people, with their time, their effort, to expend themselves for others.</p>

<p>Generosity is a beautiful virtue, especially in young people. Our Lord wants us to have initiative, to foster our spontaneity in searching for new friends. To bring them to Jesus Christ. To open up great horizons for them.</p>

<p>Each one of us needs to bring this topic to our prayer and say, “Lord, what do you want me to do?”</p>

<p>“You have visited the land,” we’re told in the Psalms, “and watered it. Greatly have you enriched it. God’s watercourses are filled. You have prepared the grain.</p>

<p>“Thus, have you prepared the land, drenching its furrows, breaking up its clods, softening it with showers, blessing its yield. You have crowned the year with your bounty, and your paths overflow with the rich harvest. The untilled meadows overflow with it, and rejoicing clothes the hills. The fields are garmented with flocks, and the valleys are blanketed with grain. They shout and sing for joy” (Ps. 65:9-13).</p>

<p>There’s one word that shines out in the whole of the Scriptures. That’s the word “harvest.”</p>

<p>Our Lord said, “The harvest is great, but the laborers are few” (Matt. 9:37). It’s a very beautiful word to remind ourselves frequently of: the harvest. We are here for the harvest. That’s what it’s all about.</p>

<p>That’s what our Christian vocation is all about. God wants us to deliver to the full, to sow the seeds, to cast our nets. That’s the purpose of everything.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to take this more seriously, to ask you for light. “Ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and it shall be opened” (Matt 7:7).</p>

<p>“Behold, I stand at the door and knock” (Rev. 3:20). If God has knocked on your door and brought you closer to Him, by the very fact that you’re listening to this meditation, some graces are working in your soul.</p>

<p>He wants you to hear these ideas, to put them into practice at a deeper level, to “launch out into the deep” in a new way, to find new horizons.</p>

<p>“You are the salt of the earth. But if salt loses its taste, what can make it salty again? It is good for nothing and can only be thrown out, to be trampled under people’s feet. You are the light of the world. A city built on a hilltop cannot be hidden. No one lights a lamp to put it under a tub. They put it on the lampstand where it shines for everyone in the house” (Matt. 5:13-15).</p>

<p>We cannot give what we do not have. If we want to be more effective apostles, we need to expose ourselves to formation, to grow in our apostolic vibration and apostolic formation.</p>

<p>How does God want me to function as a fisher of men? What does it mean in my profession, in my environment, in my family, with the permutations and combinations of my existence?</p>

<p>And as time goes on, we might be limited physically, or financially, or health-wise, or in a whole pile of other ways, but still, God will always want us to have some little influence, like that man in the prison cell with the pickpocket.</p>

<p>If this is where God has placed me, that’s where He wants me to cast my net.</p>

<p>Peter and the others spent the whole night fishing, we’re told, and they caught nothing. And then they see this stranger on the shore.</p>

<p>“He asked them, ‘Children, have you any fish?’ They said, ‘No.’ And he said, ‘Cast the net to the other side of the boat, and you will find some’” (John 21:3-6).</p>

<p>Peter and John could have said, ‘Look, we are professional fishermen. We know all about fishing. We know the name, the mobile, and the email of every fish in this lake. If we say there’s no fish, well then, there’s no fish.’</p>

<p>But they cast the net to the other side of the boat. They went a little deeper. “They caught such a huge shoal of fish that the net was almost breaking.” They looked again at the stranger on the shore. John is the one who says, “It is the Lord!” (John 21:6-7).</p>

<p>From the vast catch of fish that they made, they realized the source of the miracle. They reacted with faith, and they drew all the fruit.</p>

<p>In our fishing too, we can have great optimism—optimism, because we know that we’re not the ones doing the fishing. God is fishing in us and through us.</p>

<p>We can have great optimism as a consequence of our faith, great tenacity in our fishing, because we have an unshakeable hope and the daring of someone who knows that we’re fulfilling a command of God.</p>

<p>Optimism, tenacity, daring—these are all supernatural gifts that God gives to us. We try to cultivate them in prayer.</p>

<p>We lift up our sights and see the great horizons, the harvest, the fishing, and so much work to be done. God wants us every day to think about our fishing.</p>

<p>Who does God want me to touch today in some way? St. Josemaría recommended that first of all, prayer (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 82). We talk to God in prayer.</p>

<p>Before Jesus did His fishing, He withdrew to pray, and then He chose the apostles (Luke 6:12-16), and He talked to the multitudes (Luke 6:17-49), and so many other things. But His prayer came first.</p>

<p>It’s a very serious commitment that Our Lord is asking of us: “Go into the whole world” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 28:19). Preach the gospel to every creature. Be a modern apostle in your office, in your club, among your friends.</p>

<p>See how I can influence. What can I do? How can I leave a lasting impression here for the good? To raise the spiritual temperature in some way?</p>

<p>All the time, God will be with us, especially when He sees we’re trying to walk at all times with a pioneering spirit: beginning again, casting the nets, throwing out the line, making this into a daily habit so that it almost comes naturally to us, becomes the joy of our life, because I see: “This is why I am here, this is what God wants of me. It’s the basic part of my Christian vocation.”</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lady, the Queen of Apostles, who’s always there with us, guiding us in throwing out the net or casting the line, inspiring us with ideas, helping every effort to be fruitful.</p>

<p>God said, “My chosen ones do not work in vain” (Isa. 65:23). The seeds that we sow today will yield the abundant fruit tomorrow (<em>cf</em>. Gal. 6:7). We know that Our Lady will help that fruit to come.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>RK</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Purification of Our Lady</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-purification-of-our-lady/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Purification of Our Lady" /><published>2026-01-31T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-31T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-purification-of-our-lady</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-purification-of-our-lady/"><![CDATA[<p>The Purification of Our Lady</p>

<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>When the day came for them to be purified, in keeping with the Law of Moses, they took Him up to Jerusalem to present Him to the Lord. The Mosaic Law prescribed not only the offering up of the firstborn male but also the purification of the mother. Mary was not obliged by this law since she was most pure, having conceived her Son in a miraculous manner.</p>

<p>But Our Lady never sought to get out of social obligations. St. Bernard wrote, “Don’t you think that Our Lady could have complained and said, ‘What need have I of purification? Why should the authorities block my entrance into the temple when my womb has been turned into the temple of the Holy Spirit? Why can’t I go to the temple when I’ve brought to life the Lord of the temple?</p>

<p>“There has been nothing impure, nothing illicit, nothing to purify in this conception and this birth. This Child is the source of all purity. He has come to purify us from our sins. What then is there to purify in me when he has made me most pure in this immaculate birth?” (Bernard of Clairvaux, <em>Homily on the Purification of the Blessed Virgin Mary</em>).</p>

<p>Nevertheless, as in so many instances, Our Lady chose to act like any other Jewish woman of the time. She wanted to be an example of obedience and humility.</p>

<p>Our Lady had the humility to avoid drawing any attention to herself for the wonderful graces that God had bestowed on her. Even though she was the Mother of God, or perhaps because of that fact, she went to the temple just like any other woman. She guarded within her heart the treasures she had received from God.</p>

<p>Mary could have asked for special treatment. She would have definitely been more than entitled to it. But she prefers to teach us how to pass unnoticed among our contemporaries with our hearts on fire with love of God. Mary encourages us to live our lives as ordinary citizens, exercising the same rights and duties shared by our contemporaries.</p>

<p>Today we contemplate Mary on this her feast, the Fourth Joyful Mystery of the Rosary. We see Mary most pure as she submits to an obligation which she could have avoided. We look at our own behavior. How many times have we sought special treatment? How many times have we shown ingratitude to the love of God?</p>

<p>St. Josemaría has written, “You and I surely do need purification! Atonement, and more than atonement, Love. —Love as a searing iron to cauterize our souls’ uncleanness, and as a fire to kindle with divine flames the wretched tinder of our hearts” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Holy Rosary</em>, Fourth Joyful Mystery). This is the presentation we have to make to God through Our Lady.</p>

<p>The prophet Malachi says, “And presently the Lord whom you seek, and the angel of the testament whom you desire, shall come to his temple. … For he is like a refining fire, and like the fuller’s herb: and he shall sit refining and cleansing the silver, and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and shall refine them as gold, and as silver, and they shall offer sacrifices to the Lord in justice” (Mal. 3:1–3).</p>

<p>“The liturgy represents and makes present again a ‘mystery’ of Christ’s life: in the Temple, the religious center of the Jewish nation, in which animals were continually being sacrificed to be offered to God, there he makes his first entry, humble and modest, he who, according to the prophecy of Malachi, will sit as ‘a refiner and purifier,’ in particular of persons consecrated to worship and to service of God.</p>

<p>“There he makes his first entry into the Temple, he who ‘had to be made like his brethren in every respect, so that he might become a merciful and faithful high priest in the service of God, to make expiation for the sins of the people’ (Heb. 2:17)” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, Point 2, February 2, 1981).</p>

<p>Jesus comes to purify us from our sins by means of pardon and mercy.</p>

<p>This prophecy refers directly to the priests of the tribe of Levi. These priests prefigure all Christians who through Baptism become members of the royal priesthood of Christ.</p>

<p>If we allow ourselves to be cleansed and purified, we too can offer up our work and our lives in justice.</p>

<p>Today is a feast day of Our Lord who, despite His infancy, is “a light of revelation to the Gentiles” (Luke 2:32).</p>

<p>John Paul II has liked to say, “It is also a feast of Our Lady. She carries the Child in her arms. He, even in her hands, is the light of our souls, the light which illumines the darkness of knowledge and of human existence, of the intellect and of the heart.</p>

<p>“The thoughts of so many hearts are revealed when her mother’s hands carry this great divine Light, when they bring it closer to man” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, Point 3, February 2, 1979).</p>

<p>Our Lady wants to encourage us that we purify our hearts, that we make the offering of ourselves pleasing to God, that we find Christ in all the circumstances of our everyday existence. She wanted to go through with this required rite of purification, even though she didn’t have to do it, because she wanted to give us a high regard for the purification of our souls.</p>

<p>From the earliest days of Christianity, the Fathers of the Church have written of Our Lady’s purity in glowing terms. Pope Pius XII says they have called her “an iris among spines, Immaculate Virgin, forever blessed, free of all contagion of sin, tree of everlasting life, fountain most pure, free from all sin, more beautiful than beauty itself, holier than all sanctity, more exalted than all the angels and saints” (<em>cf</em>. Pius XII, Encyclical, <em>Fulgens corona</em>, Point 9, September 8, 1953).</p>

<p>Our Lady’s immaculate life is like a call for us to throw off whatever separates us from Our Lord.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em> says: “Ask the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and your Mother, to make you know yourself and weep for all those foul things that have passed through you, and which, alas, have left such dregs behind. …</p>

<p>”—And at the same time, without wishing to stop considering all that, say to him: Jesus, give me a Love that will act like a purifying fire in which my miserable flesh, my miserable heart, my miserable soul, my miserable body may be consumed and cleansed of all earthly wretchedness. And when I have been emptied of myself, fill me with yourself. May I never become attached to anything here below. May Love always sustain me” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 41).</p>

<p>We can offer everything we are through the hands of Our Lady. We can turn to her particularly in times of trial.</p>

<p>St. Paul writes, “But we carry this treasure in vessels of clay, to show that the abundance of the power is God’s and not ours” (<em>cf</em>. 2 Cor. 4:7). A vessel of clay can be broken rather easily. It can also be put together again without too much trouble. Within the merciful plans of the Lord, there is a remedy for every kind of damage.</p>

<p>The Lord only asks that we be humble, that we go to Him in sacramental Confession when necessary, that we have a firm resolve to sin no more. Our small and not-so-small weaknesses can be an excellent opportunity for us to increase our desires for reparation. Whenever we hurt someone we love, we can do our best to make up for the harm done. This is the way we should feel about hurting Jesus.</p>

<p>John Paul I said, “If children are ill, they have additional claim to be loved by their mother. And we too, if by chance we are sick with badness, on the wrong track, have yet another claim to be loved by the Lord” (John Paul I, <em>Angelus</em>, September 10, 1978).</p>

<p>We can have a great sense of peace when we contemplate all the abundant supernatural means which God has placed at our disposal for penance and purification. He has given Himself to us in the Blessed Eucharist to serve as a most powerful spiritual food. He has given us the sacrament of Confession so that when we fall, we might find forgiveness and return to the struggle. He has given us our guardian angel to guard us along the way.</p>

<p>We can also find support in our brothers in the faith through the Communion of Saints. We can learn from the good example of so many practicing Christians around us.</p>

<p>In a very special way we’re able to count on the help of Our Lady, Mother of God and Our Mother. We can have recourse to her on a regular basis, but especially when we feel worn out or a bit overwhelmed.</p>

<p>Meditating on today’s feast, St. Alphonsus Liguori explained Our Lady’s power with the use of a legend from antiquity. “Plutarch relates that Antipater wrote to Alexander the Great a long letter of accusations against Olympias, the mother of Alexander. Having read the letter he answered: ‘Does not Antipater know that one tear of my mother is enough to cancel an endless number of letters of accusation?’”</p>

<p>St. Alphonsus takes these noble words and puts them on the lips of Jesus: “Does not Lucifer know that one prayer of my mother, in favor of a sinner, is enough to make me forget all the accusations of offenses committed against me?”</p>

<p>He adds: “St. Simeon received a promise from God that he should not die until he had seen the Messiah born. … But he did not receive this grace except by means of Mary, for he did not see the Savior until he saw him in the arms of Mary. Hence, whoever wishes to find Jesus will not find him except through Our Lady. Let us go then to this divine Mother if we wish to find Jesus, and let us go with great confidence” (Alphonsus Liguori, <em>Glories of Mary</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lady is there for us also as the <em>Health of the Sick</em> and will gladly obtain for us the well-being of our bodies, especially when alleviation of our sickness is ordered to the good of our soul.</p>

<p>At other times she grants something more important than bodily health: the grace to understand that suffering, including physical pain, is an instrument of God. Permitting it, He wants us to accept it with love, and will transform it into a great good that purifies us and enables us to obtain countless benefits for the whole Church.</p>

<p>By means of sickness borne patiently and with a supernatural outlook, we obtain a good part of the treasure that awaits us in heaven, to say nothing of abundant apostolic rewards: from such humble and courageous acceptance of God’s will come decisions to dedicate oneself to God and to the salvation of many souls who, without those graces, might not find the path and the gateway to heaven.</p>

<p>Our Lady also cures the wounds left in our soul by original sin and aggravated by our personal transgressions. She will obtain remedy for our disordered concupiscence and procure strength for our weakness in doing good. She fortifies those who are wavering, raises the fallen, helps to dispel the mists of ignorance and the darkness of error.</p>

<p>She’s also the <em>Refuge of Sinners</em>. In her we find a safe harbor from the storm. After her Son, no one detests sin more than Mary does, but she does not reject sinners. Instead she welcomes them and moves them to repentance. In how many Confessions has she intervened by means of a special help?</p>

<p>She transmits the grace of light and repentance even to those who are far away; if they do not resist, they are led by her from grace to grace and finally to conversion.</p>

<p>“St. Paul says to the Ephesians: ‘Who then will be able to comprehend what is the breadth and length and height and depth’ (Eph. 3:18) of your mercy, O Virgin most blessed? It reaches forward, extending even as far as the end of time, to help all those that invoke it. Its breadth is as broad as the vast universe, so that of you too it can be said, ‘the whole earth is full of your mercy’ (Ps. 33:5)” (Bernard of Clairvaux, <em>Homily on the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary</em>).</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lady today, imploring her to have pity on us. We can tell her that we are sinners, but that we want to love her Son Jesus more and more. We can ask her to have compassion on our weaknesses and to help us overcome them.</p>

<p>She is there for our safeguard, the secure haven where we can drop anchor, sheltered from the waves and tempestuous winds. There we can refit, putting right any damage caused by temptation and our human frailty. The mercy she mediates is our protection and our peace.</p>

<p>Throughout her life, Our Lady must have been a source of consolation and support to anyone afflicted by a weight too heavy to bear alone. She must have encouraged St. Joseph on that night in Bethlehem when, as he explained the pressing need for lodging at one house after another, he found that no door would open to them. One smile from Our Lady would be enough for him to find the strength to get ready and make the most of what he had found—a stable on the outskirts of the little town (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:7).</p>

<p>She would have been a tower of strength to him in that flight into Egypt and in helping him set himself up in that country (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 2:13-15). Joseph himself was a man of fortitude, but it would have been easier for him to do what he must to fulfill the will of God when he was sustained and encouraged by Our Lady.</p>

<p>Her neighbors in Nazareth would always find upliftment and understanding in the words of Mary. The Apostles found refuge in Mary’s company when all had turned dark and meaningless after the death of Christ on the Cross. When they returned from placing the body of Jesus in the sepulcher, at a time when families in Jerusalem were getting ready to celebrate the Paschal feast, the Apostles, who had fled numb with shock and disoriented, turned almost automatically to Our Lady.</p>

<p>From then on she has never ceased to comfort those who are oppressed by sorrow. One writer says, “She has sheltered innumerable Christians from persecution, freed many souls possessed by the devil or besieged by temptations, saved countless imperiled supplicants from anxiety. She has strengthened and helped many of the dying by reminding them as they lay on their deathbeds of the infinite merits of her Son” (Réginald Garrigou-Lagrange, <em>The Mother of the Savi</em>or).</p>

<p>If ever our life has become for us a misery and we are overwhelmed by apparently insoluble difficulties, crushed by illness, daunted by seeming failure in our dedication to an apostolic task, if we are threatened by discouragement in the effort to bring up our family and dismayed at the obstacles that just keep on piling up, let us turn to Mary. We will always find solace, encouragement, and the strength to fulfill the lovable will of her Son.</p>

<p>We can slowly repeat to her: Hail, Holy Queen, Mother of Mercy. Hail our life, our sweetness and our hope. From her we shall learn to console and to hearten others in the struggle. We shall be compassionate on those who are in need of our help, in disasters, or in minor worries—people in need of encouragement here, or of condolence there—a merciful attitude which is so pleasing to Our Lord.</p>

<p>Our Lady is <em>Help of Christians</em> because, first of all, we favor those we love, and nobody has a greater love than Mary for those who belong to her Son’s family. In her we will find every grace we need to win through in the fight against temptation, in our apostolate, and in our work.</p>

<p>In the Rosary we have a “powerful weapon” (J. Escrivá, <em>Holy Rosary</em>, Foreword) with which to overcome all the obstacles we shall meet along the way.</p>

<p>Following the constant teaching of the Roman Pontiffs, many Christians throughout the world have made the daily Rosary a part of their life of piety. They recite it together as a family prayer, or alone in a church, while walking in the street, or traveling in any form of transport.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, quoting Ecclesiastes, “‘In me is to be found every grace of doctrine and of truth, every hope of life and of virtue’ (Sir. 24:25). How wise the Church has been to put these words on Our Mother’s lips so that we Christians do not forget them. She is our safety, the Love that never fails, the refuge ever open to us, the hand ever ready to caress and console” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 279).</p>

<p>Let us ask Our Lady to cleanse and purify our hearts on this feast of her Purification. We place ourselves, Mother, in your motherly hands so that you might offer us to Jesus.</p>

<p>Holy Father, through the Immaculate Heart of Mary, I offer Jesus, your beloved Son, to you. I offer myself to you through Him and with Him, in the name of all your creatures.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Purification of Our Lady]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Christian Outlook on Death</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Christian Outlook on Death" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Thessalonians, “For you yourselves know well that the day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night” (1 Thess. 5:2).</p>

<p>Our Lord Himself has said, “I am the resurrection and the life. He who believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives and believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26).</p>

<p>St. Paul to the Ephesians says, “Look carefully then how you walk, not as unwise men, but as wise, making the most of the time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>A lot of these statements in Scripture can remind us not to be blind to our final moment on earth.</p>

<p>The Church in some ways encourages us to prepare for death on a daily basis. Our Lord has said that His coming in glory will take people unawares.</p>

<p>“For as the lightning flashes and lights up the sky from one side to the other, so will the Son of Man be in his day” (Luke 17:24). Our Lord tells us that nothing can block His second coming at the end of time.</p>

<p>The disciples had a natural curiosity about when and where this would happen. “Where, Lord?” they asked Him. “Where the body is,” He replied, “there the eagles will be gathered” (Luke 17:37).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that everyone will be drawn to the Son of God at the end of time just as eagles converge on their prey.</p>

<p>The same can be said about each person’s moment of death.</p>

<p>St. Paul warns those Christians of Thessalonica that He will come ‘like a thief in the night.” It is one more call to vigilance.</p>

<p>We cannot be blind to our final moment on earth, the day of the Lord, when we will meet God face to face. St. Augustine has written that the Lord keeps the circumstances of His coming hidden so that we might always be on the alert (<em>cf</em>. St. Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 120</em>).</p>

<p>In modern culture, in certain environments, it’s not easy to speak about death and dying. In a materialistic culture, death is taboo because it suggests the end of everything.</p>

<p>It’s easy for people to forget the spiritual nature of man, that every person has a soul and that soul is immortal. It has an eternal destiny. It’s one of the most important truths of our faith, with enormous consequences.</p>

<p>But in a materialistic culture, the very mention of the subject of death can be regarded by some as a sign of bad taste. But it’s the certainty of death that illuminates our life.</p>

<p>The Church invites us to meditate frequently on the inevitability of our death so that we won’t be taken by surprise when it comes.</p>

<p>Pagan culture would have us live as though death were a distant mirage, something that only affects other people.</p>

<p>Regrettably, many who consider themselves good Christians can be unduly influenced by such a seductive approach to life. They’re led astray because they fail to come to terms with the real meaning of death.</p>

<p>Rather than see death as a friend, or even as a sister, as St. Josemaría says in <em>The Way,</em> Points 735 and 739, they view it as an enormous catastrophe, as something that will undermine all their worldly hopes and accomplishments.</p>

<p>I remember accompanying an elderly lady in another country once, at the moment of her death.</p>

<p>I was rather impressed by some of her final words. She said, ‘If I had known death was so beautiful, I would have tried to die a long time ago.’ She was a very holy woman and very well prepared for her death.</p>

<p>This earthbound approach explains why death has to be put in the closet, as it were. It’s too uncomfortable a subject to deal with. Instead of looking upon death as the key to the fullness of joy, the tendency is to see it as the end of the road, the checkout counter on what is for them a kind of terrestrial shopping spree.</p>

<p>These misguided people have lost sight of the fact that every person is in possession of an eternal soul. In <em>The Way</em>, Point 744, St. Josemaría says, “Death is nothing more than a change of lodging.”</p>

<p>The liturgy often reminds us of that truth. In the <em>Preface for the Dead</em>, it says, “Life is changed, not taken away.”</p>

<p>Life changes. It’s not something we’re deprived of.</p>

<p>Christians believe that death represents the end of an earthly pilgrimage. Believers prepare for death on a daily basis.</p>

<p>It’s through the sanctification of ordinary realities that we will win heaven as an eternal reward and the Christian who behaves accordingly will not be alarmed by death’s arrival.</p>

<p>That person will have been patiently readying themselves for this definitive encounter with the Lord. In the words of St. Cyprian, “Death is a stepping up into eternity after we have run in this earthly race” (St. Cyprian, <em>Treatise on Mortality</em>).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow,</em> Point 891, St. Josemaría says: “If at any time you feel uneasy at the thought of our sister death, because you see yourself to be such a poor creature, take heart. Heaven awaits us and consider: what will it be like when all the infinite beauty and greatness, and happiness and love of God will be poured into the poor vessel of clay that the human being is, to satisfy it eternally with the freshness of an ever new joy?”</p>

<p>Death acquires a new meaning with the death and resurrection of Christ.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “God did not make death, and He does not delight in the death of the living” (Wis. 1:13). There was no such thing as death with all its pain and suffering, before our first parents committed original sin. Death is a consequence of sin.</p>

<p>Man had been given the gift of immortality in the Garden of Paradise. But when our first parents committed that sin, they lost that gift. They lost that gift! St. Paul says, “By the sin of one man, death entered the world” (Rom. 5:12).</p>

<p>The rebellion of our first parents led to the loss of that preternatural gift. By his disobedience, Adam lost his friendship with God and that gift of immortal life.</p>

<p>Since that time, our passage to the house of the Father, our final resting place, takes us to this fateful gateway—the moment when we “depart out of this world to the Father” as quoted in St. John (John 13:1).</p>

<p>St. Paul says Jesus Christ “abolished death and brought life” (2 Tim. 1:10). He removed the essential evil from death and gave it a new meaning, making death into a stepping stone to Life.</p>

<p>His victory is shared by all who believe in Him and who participate in His Life. Our Lord has told us, “I am the resurrection and the life. He who believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives and believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26). Our Lord’s words can fill us with hope, a hope that does not disappoint.</p>

<p>Death is the enemy of the natural life of man. Christ has converted it into our friend and sister. Though the human person suffers defeat at the hands of this foe, he or she can in the end be triumphant thanks to Christ’s immortal sacrifice.</p>

<p>For a materialistic society in which pleasure and comfort reign supreme, death and even life itself are devoid of lasting value. Those who adopt a pagan lifestyle behave as if suffering, failure, and death were curses to be avoided at any cost.</p>

<p>Such people act as if Christ never achieved redemption.</p>

<p>The Psalmist says in his prayer to God: “Those who hate the righteous will be condemned” (Ps. 34:21). But “precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints” (Ps. 116:15).</p>

<p>From her earliest days, the Church has celebrated the anniversaries of the death by martyrdom of her saints. The Church likes to say that these are the <em>dies natalis</em>, the birthdays to that new Life which entails joy without end.</p>

<p>St. John tells us in the Book of Revelation, “I heard a voice from heaven saying: ‘Write this: Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord henceforth.’ ‘Blessed indeed,’ says the Spirit, ‘that they may rest from their labors, for their deeds follow them.” (Rev. 14:13).</p>

<p>We know that we will be rewarded for even the smallest service that we have done for the Lord. We’re told in St. Matthew that “whoever gives...even a cup of cold water, because he is a disciple of the Lord, shall not go without His reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>We have the joy of looking forward to every little thing being rewarded that we have done for other people in this world.</p>

<p><em>Gaudium et Spes</em> of the Second Vatican Council has said: “For after we have obeyed the Lord, and in His Spirit nurtured on earth the value of human dignity, brotherhood, and freedom, and indeed all the good fruits of our nature and enterprise, we will find them again, but freed of stain,…transfigured, when Christ hands over to the Father: ‘a kingdom eternal and universal...’” (Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et Spes,</em> Point 39).</p>

<p>All the things of the world will perish and be forgotten, but their good “deeds will follow them.”</p>

<p>We can be reminded of that phrase of Scripture which says, “Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, where dust and moth consume, and thieves break in and steal. But store up for yourselves treasures in heaven” (Matt. 6:19-20).</p>

<p>Every day, every hour, is an opportunity for us to store up for ourselves treasures in heaven.</p>

<p>Death can teach us many things about life. It can inspire us to live with only what we need, to be detached from the things we own and use, to respect the lasting merit of our good works, and to get rid of superfluous things—many good things.</p>

<p>Occasionally in your family, go through the cabinets of your children or their rooms and help them to make a decision to pass on to others what they don’t need, so that in a subtle way, they get all these messages: they are not here just to accumulate things.</p>

<p>It’s not that the one who has accumulated the most toys wins. Rather, the more we have gotten rid of things and passed them on to others will we be ready for the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>Death also teaches us to make good use of every day, to have goals, to have a plan for our spiritual life and, also for our professional and material life. Things I need to do today, with priorities, to do number one and then number two.</p>

<p>Ancient writers used to use the phrase <em>Carpe diem</em> <em>(</em>Horace<em>, Odes 1,11,17).</em> Horace, an early Latin writer, used this phrase ‘Seize the day’ to encourage people to make the most of the present moment.</p>

<p>Look around you and see if people on your mode of transport or people that you meet every day are making the most out of every moment. If they have an article or a book they’re reading in spare moments, in the little pieces of time—one writer used to call them the butts of time—the little pieces of time throughout the day when maybe nothing is happening, to have something to be reading, something to be doing, catching up on other little projects or little things to be done here and there. Using our time well.</p>

<p>These words of Horace were a pagan maxim, but we can impart a Christian meaning to it by living each day with joy as if it were our whole life. We can ask ourselves: What is the will of God for me today?</p>

<p>From the things that happened from hour to hour—ups and downs, reversals of fortune, pieces of good news, pieces of bad news—we can decipher what exactly it is that God wants me to do today and try to follow His will with a lot of peace and serenity.</p>

<p>It’s a chance that will never be repeated. Time is like a flowing divine treasure: it comes, it’s here, and then it goes, never to return.</p>

<p>During our examination of conscience, we can please Our Lord with the quantity of acts of love, of our aspirations, of our moments of talking to our guardian angel, of favors we’ve done on behalf of others, of the quiet fulfillment of our duties, of our struggle to be patient.</p>

<p>Perhaps Our Lord will convert these deeds into splendid jewels of eternal worth. “Death ends our time of meriting” (<em>cf</em>. Leo X, Bull, <em>Exsurge Domine</em>, June 15, 1520). Interesting point.</p>

<p>I know a priest who went to see a man on his deathbed. This priest was really renowned for making money, helping people to be detached. He reminded this man on his deathbed: Look, after you die, really nothing belongs to you. It all belongs to God.</p>

<p>There’s not much merit in giving away things after you die. There’s much more merit in giving away things while you are still alive. That way you gain merit—an act of generosity, charity, justice.</p>

<p>We can make a resolution not to waste the days that remain to us in our lives. We do not know when we will die.</p>

<p>Every so often we hear of people dying young, or we hear of accidents, or we hear of people having heart attacks, young people. Those are like little gentle reminders to us from the Holy Spirit that we live in the hands of God.</p>

<p>That very uncertainty helps us to be watchful, like the doorkeeper awaiting the arrival of his master (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:35-36). Hence the importance of regular sacramental Confession to be always in a state of grace. The Church has always recommended regular Confession.</p>

<p>Our examination of conscience at the end of the day can help us to recognize and discover the failings we may have had this day—failings of charity, of patience, of kindness, of justice, or failings in sensuality, failings in pride and vanity.</p>

<p>Therefore, we can build up those little details that we want to bring to Confession at the end of the week, to cleanse our soul from venial sin, and from any omissions that would indicate a lack of love.</p>

<p>Sometimes our greatest faults or sins could be our sins of omission, or our sins of neglect, things that we could have done and didn’t do, or things that we could have done much better than we did.</p>

<p>Our meditation on death can move us to work more earnestly on the great project of our own sanctification. St. Paul says to the Ephesians, <em>“</em>Look carefully then how you walk, not as unwise men but as wise, making the most of time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>We need to make up for lost time<em>.</em> … Let us take to heart that wise observation written almost twenty centuries ago. Seneca, an ancient Latin writer, said, “It’s not that we have so little time,” he said, “but that we have wasted so much of it” (Seneca<em>, De brevitate vitae,</em> 1,3). He was writing in the early centuries. Clocks and stopwatches had not yet been invented.</p>

<p>We could make an act of contrition for all the time that we may have wasted in our lives and make a resolution to make many wise decisions about our use of time.</p>

<p>We should want to have a long life so that we can give God abundant service. St. Josemaría used to say that if God has invested an awful lot in our education, in our formation, it’s very good that we give Him a good return on that investment. It makes good economic sense.</p>

<p>It’s a good thing to ask Our Lord for a long life so that we can serve more, so that hopefully we go before Our Lord with our arms full. It’s so right for us to love life since this is a gift from God.</p>

<p>I heard of a person once who was involved in fundraising for a center for young people where they would get a lot of formation, growth in holiness, and learn many other skills, and develop their personality, and develop many other virtues.</p>

<p>To try and get his friends to contribute to the growth of this youth center, a center for young people, he said, ‘Look, if you buy a brick in this place, that brick will always be there. Long after you die, that brick will still be there. It would be like an investment for the future. That brick helping that center to form young people will give great glory to God over time and all that glory will be to your benefit at the end of time, at the last judgment.’</p>

<p>There are ways that we can remind people that they have to make good use of their time and also of everything that they have, for that abundant service of God.</p>

<p>We have the grace to open horizons for them, to see those things that perhaps they haven’t seen, so that they also can go before Our Lord with their arms full.</p>

<p>If we’re faithful to our Christian vocation, when the time comes for our encounter with Our Lord we will be prepared to make a tremendous act of love for Our Father God.</p>

<p>What a beautiful thing to die with words of love on our lips. That holy woman that I just mentioned did precisely that. She went out of this world giving praise to God.</p>

<p>“As in one’s whole life, so also in one’s death. Each one should struggle to give glory to the Lord Our God” (St. Ignatius of Loyola, <em>Constitutions</em>).</p>

<p>It’s good to be aware that most people die as they have lived. The concept of last-minute deathbed conversions is very rare.</p>

<p>It’s today we have to live better. This hour. Today we have to practice the virtues. Today we have to live with a greater awareness that there is an end to all this.</p>

<p>St. Ignatius of Loyola says, “May He be honored and glorified. May other people be edified by the example of our patience and fortitude, by the testimony of our living faith, our hope, and our love for the eternal goods” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Our last moment on earth should be spent for the glory of God.</p>

<p>I remember a 19-year-old person dying in a hospital once in Asia and the doctor who was looking after him—this young fellow who had no religion, no formation, no nothing—remarked, ‘He died like a soldier.’ It’s rather a beautiful comment.</p>

<p>We’re called to die like soldiers, but “soldiers of Christ” (2 Tim. 2:3).</p>

<p>It will be a great joy when we give Our Lord the present of our professional work well done; of the apostolate that we’ve tried to do with all the opportunities that He’s given to us; of those many, many details of service to our neighbors, in our family life, in our environment, in our office, in our club, in our neighborhood; to present to Him the joy that we contributed to our family life; and the effort that we made to overcome our defects.</p>

<p>We will leave behind us works that will endure. We will take our departure from this world in a way described by a poet: “I left my love the shore and the singing current. I did not return to the bank for his love, for his love was the water” (B. Llorens, <em>A secret spring).</em></p>

<p>We know that if we live close to Our Lady all through our life, every hour and every day in the presence of Our Mother, she will also be with us. We say so frequently and throughout our life, we have said now, “at the hour of our death” (Prayer, <em>Hail Mary</em>).</p>

<p>There was a lady in Singapore whose husband passed away. But when he was alive, they would go to the happy hour every day in the local pub, and she would put on her earrings and her make-up and they’d go and have a good time.</p>

<p>Then her husband passed away, and she ended her days in a home for the elderly.</p>

<p>She had no religion, but the good nuns were converting her and teaching her the basic prayers, and she learned all of them very well.</p>

<p>During this time, when the time came for the happy hour each day, she liked to remember the good old times and to pretend that she was going to the happy hour. She’d also put on her earrings, maybe some make-up, to pretend she was accompanying her husband to the happy hour.</p>

<p>She learned all of the basic prayers, ready for her Baptism. But she couldn’t quite master the second part of the <em>Hail Mary</em> because she kept saying: Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners, now and at the happy hour of our death, Amen. But somehow, she had put her finger on the nerve.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady to accompany us in that happy hour and to help any people around us also to find Our Lady and to be with her in that very special moment.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Cup of Cold Water</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cup of Cold Water" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“If anyone can give so much as a cup of cold water to one of these little ones, because he is a disciple, then I tell you solemnly, he will most certainly not lose his reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>Giving a cup of cold water—and notice specifically how Scripture says cold water, not warm water—to someone who needs it is not going to make headlines. Most likely only the giver and the receiver will be aware of it.</p>

<p>And yet Our Lord holds up this small act of kindness as having tremendous value.</p>

<p>Even the simplest acts in which we lose ourselves for others have eternal significance. The cloth of holiness is woven in small details.</p>

<p>With this and with other examples that Our Lord gives to us, He speaks to us about the value of little things.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say, “A little act, done for love, is worth so much!” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, 814).</p>

<p>Mother Teresa has said, “A few words of kindness may be very simple and very brief, but their echoes are endless.”</p>

<p>On one occasion Our Lord sat up to the Temple treasury and He watched people putting money into the receptacle for alms. The scene takes place in one of the porticos, the so-called Treasure Chamber or Hall of Offerings. The days of the Passion were almost upon Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord didn't comment at all on the many people who contributed large amounts. But He saw a woman come up who was dressed in the typical garb of widows, and who was obviously poor (Mark 12:41).</p>

<p>She had perhaps waited for the crowd to thin out before depositing two small coins there. These coins had the least value of any in circulation at the time.</p>

<p>St. Mark explains the real value of these particular units of currency for the benefit of his non-Jewish readers, to whom his Gospel was principally addressed. He wants everyone to know how very little they were worth.</p>

<p>In men's eyes that anonymous offering had very little value. The two coins were worth just a small amount. “That coin,” St. Mark says, “was worth a quarter” (Mark 12:42). It's like a tenth of a denarius, which was the basic monetary unit; a denarius was a day's wages for a farm worker. And so, a quarter would scarcely buy anything.</p>

<p>If anyone was keeping a record of the offerings made that day in the temple, he probably would have thought it was not worth recording that widow's contribution. But we see that in fact this was the most valuable contribution of all.</p>

<p>It would be so pleasing to God that Our Lord called together His disciples, who were scattered around the place, so that they might be taught the lesson to be learned from this widow.</p>

<p>Those tiny pieces of copper could scarcely be heard falling into the treasury box. But Our Lord clearly perceived the love of this woman who said nothing but who was giving all her savings to God.</p>

<p>“Jesus said, ‘Truly I say to you, this poor widow has put in more than all those who are contributing to the treasury. For they all contributed out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty has put in everything she had, her whole living’” (Mark 12:43-44).</p>

<p>It often happens that what God considers important is very different from what men consider important. His standard of measurement and ours are not the same.</p>

<p>We are generally impressed by the big gesture, by unusual things of the kind that attract everyone's attention. But God is moved by little details filled with love—"a cup of cold water”—which are within the radius of action of everyone, even small children.</p>

<p>Of course, He's also moved by happenings that we consider to be very important, but only when they're carried out with the same spirit of rectitude of intention, of humility, and of love.</p>

<p>The apostles, who later were to be the very foundation of the Church, did not forget the lesson they were taught that day. That woman has taught all of us to touch God's heart every day in the only way that most of us can: through little things.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, Point 824, St. Josemaría says, “Have you noticed how human love consists of little things? Well, divine Love also consists of little things.”</p>

<p>In these passages of the Gospel, we learn the true value of these things. We can turn everything that happens, no matter how inconsequential it may seem, into something very pleasing to God. And because it's pleasing to Him, it's turned into something of great value. Only those things that we make pleasing to God have any true and eternal value.</p>

<p>We could consider in our prayer the vast number of opportunities that present themselves to us. We’re told by St. Francis de Sales, “Great opportunities to serve God seldom arise, but little ones are frequent; [and our Lord himself has told us that] ‘he who is faithful over a few things will be placed over many’ (Luke 16:10). Do all things in the name of God, and you will do all things well, provided you know how to fulfill your duties properly.</p>

<p>“Then, whether you eat or drink, whether you sleep, or take recreation, or turn the spit of an oven, you will profit greatly in God's sight by doing all these things, because God wishes you to do them” (St. Francis de Sales, <em>Introduction to the Devout Life</em>).</p>

<p>Often, it's the small things that make a job perfect, worthy of being offered to God: the double-checking of an email or a WhatsApp message that we write, the looking back to double-check on a room that we've just cleaned, or a floor we've just polished, or a table we've just laid, or some little professional job that we have done.</p>

<p>Perfection is in the details. It's not enough that what we're doing is good, whether it's work or prayer or football or hockey or volleyball. It also has to be well finished.</p>

<p>“For there to be virtue,” St. Thomas Aquinas teaches, “it is necessary to attend to two things: to what is being done, and also to the way it is being done” (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Quodlibet</em>, IV).</p>

<p>As far as the way it is being done is concerned, the final touches with the chisel or brush can turn that work into a masterpiece, and Our Lord wants us to work masterpieces every day.</p>

<p>On the other hand, shoddy workmanship, work which is done clumsily or carelessly, is a sign of spiritual laziness or of lukewarmness in a Christian who should be sanctifying himself through his daily work.</p>

<p>We're told in the Book of Revelation, “I know your works: you have the name of being alive, and you are dead. ... For I have not found your works perfect in the sight of my God” (Rev. 3:1-2).</p>

<p>The very nature of our Christian vocation demands that we take care of little things. A teacher who picks up a piece of paper off the floor may give a greater lesson to all his students, or to anybody who happens to be in that particular corridor or place, than all the other classes he may have given in his whole professional lifetime, because with that little gesture we teach the value of order, of tidiness, but also the value of the small things.</p>

<p>Our aim should be to imitate Our Lord during His years in Nazareth, those long years of work, of family life, of friendly relationships with His countrymen.</p>

<p>Doing little things with love for God's sake demands attention, sacrifice, and generosity. A single isolated little detail may not in itself be very important. St. Augustine says, “What is small is small, but he who is faithful in small things is great” (St. Augustine, <em>On Christian Doctrine</em>).</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>, “Love is what gives little things their value” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>The Way,</em> Point 814).</p>

<p>If this love were lacking, our endeavor to look after little things would be pointless; it would become a mania or merely Pharisaical. We would pay tithes in mint, dill and cumin—as the Pharisees do—and we would run the risk of leaving out the most essential points of the law, those of justice and of mercy.</p>

<p>Although what we have to offer may seem very little—just as the contribution of that poor widow did—it acquires a great value if you place it on the altar and unite it to the offering that Our Lord makes of Himself to the Father.</p>

<p>St. John Paul said in one of his homilies: “Our humble surrender—insignificant in itself like the oil of the widow of Sarepta, or the poor widow's mite—becomes acceptable in God's eyes through its union with the offering of Jesus” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, November 7, 1982).</p>

<p>At other times, details in our work, in our study, in our relationships with other people are the crowning of something good which would remain incomplete without those details.</p>

<p>One of the most obvious warning signs that we're starting on the path to lukewarmness is that we give little value to the details of our life of piety, to details in our work, and to little specific acts of virtue. If we ignore these symptoms, we end up paying little attention to big things as well.</p>

<p>“The misfortune is all the more grievous and incurable,” said one writer, “when we barely notice that we are sliding downwards and only slowly come to realize this … That if we are in this state, we give a mortal blow to the life of the spirit, and that can be something obvious to everyone” (Benedict Baur, <em>Frequent Confession</em>).</p>

<p>Love for God, on the other hand, is shown by our inventiveness, by our unremitting zeal, and our effort to find in everything an occasion for showing our love of God and for giving service to others.</p>

<p>Holiness is a cloth woven of little details. God is not indifferent to a love that knows how to care for small details. He's not indifferent, for example, as to whether we go to greet Him, first of all, when we go into a church or when we happen to be passing by a church.</p>

<p>He's not indifferent to the effort we make to arrive on time (better, a few minutes early) for Holy Mass, to the way we genuflect in front of Him in the tabernacle, or the way we behave or try to be recollected in His presence.</p>

<p>There was a man once who tried to do a lot of apostolate in his office, befriending as many people as he could, being close to them, trying to help them in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>He gave a lot of support to people in their marriage, in their family, tried to invite them to recollections, to retreats, to grow spiritually.</p>

<p>But there was one man in the office who refused all of his overtures. He had no time for these sorts of things.</p>

<p>But one day that man came to this other fellow and said, ‘Look, I have a big problem in my marriage. My wife is about to divorce me. Can you give me any advice?’</p>

<p>The original man was a bit surprised. He said, ‘You know, I've often tried to give you advice or reach out to you in different ways, and you never seemed very interested. Why do you come to me?’</p>

<p>The guy said, ‘Well, you're the only one that speaks about anything serious around here.’</p>

<p>The original man said, ‘Okay, let me think about it and pray about it’—which is always a good thing to say to people because they realize you're taking them seriously.</p>

<p>That evening in his prayer, he brought this topic to talk to Our Lord about it. He couldn't really see any great solutions. But for some reason, a scene in a movie with St. Josemaría came to mind, where St. Josemaría mentioned how husbands should try and bring their wives some flowers from time to time.</p>

<p>He was thinking to himself, ‘It's a bit late for flowers. That's not a very prudent sort of advice to give this fellow.’</p>

<p>But that was all he saw in his prayer. With a lot of supernatural outlook, he thought, ‘If that's all I see in my prayer, that, maybe, is what I have to transmit to this fellow.’</p>

<p>But he wasn't terribly convinced himself. It didn't seem very helpful.</p>

<p>The following day, he told his friend, ‘Look, I thought about this, and I prayed about it. My suggestion to you is that you perhaps bring some flowers to your wife.’</p>

<p>The second fellow was thinking, ‘I was really wasting my time talking to you. What a stupid piece of advice. She's about to divorce me and you're telling me to bring her flowers.’</p>

<p>He dismissed his suggestion and went off. But that evening, as he was going home, he was thinking about this and he thought, ‘Even if I get her flowers, I suppose it can't do any harm. The worst thing that could happen is that she might hit me with them.’</p>

<p>So he bought some flowers. When he got home, his wife opened the door and he handed her the flowers. She burst into tears and said, ‘This is the first time in twenty years that you have brought me flowers.’ After that, they lived happily ever after.</p>

<p>Sometimes the little things can make a huge difference.</p>

<p>Moreover, when we see somebody make a devout genuflection before the tabernacle, it's easy for us to think: that person has faith and loves God. That sign of adoration helps others to have greater faith and greater love.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI says, “It may perhaps seem to you that the Liturgy is made up of little things: the position of the body, genuflections, inclinations of the head; the way the thurible, the missal, and the cruets are to be moved. It is then that we have to recall Christ's words in the Gospel: ‘He who is faithful in a very little is faithful also in much’” (Luke 16:10).</p>

<p>“Moreover,” said St. Paul VI, “nothing is small in the Sacred Liturgy, when we think of the greatness of him to whom it is directed” (Paul VI, <em>Address</em>, May 30, 1967).</p>

<p>Our spirit of mortification usually consists in specific little sacrifices throughout the day: keeping up a persevering struggle in our particular examination of conscience, sobriety at meals, punctuality, being pleasant to people, getting up on time, not leaving our work for later even though we find it difficult or trying, having order in our work and taking care of the tools or implements and materials that we use, being grateful for whatever food is placed in front of us, not allowing ourselves whims and fancies.</p>

<p>In order to live charity in a way that becomes ever more refined and heroic, it would be necessary for us to apply this approach right down to the smallest and least important details of daily life.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in the <em>Furrow</em> says, “Your duty to be a brother to all souls will lead you to practice the ‘apostolate of little things’ without others noticing it. You will want to serve them so that for them, their way becomes agreeable” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 737).</p>

<p>At times it will mean taking a real interest in what other people are saying; at other times it will mean putting aside our own personal concerns so as to give our attention to the people we live with.</p>

<p>A little girl was talking to her father who was reading the newspaper and she said to him, ‘Daddy, you're not listening to me.’</p>

<p>Continuing to read the newspaper, he said, ‘Yes, I am. I'm hearing every word.’</p>

<p>But then she said, ‘But you're not looking at me.’</p>

<p>The child was aware, and the child wanted his full attention. A small thing, but it meant everything to the child.</p>

<p>Care of those little things will mean not getting annoyed about what are really trivia, not being touchy, making people feel welcome.</p>

<p>If those little disturbances come during the day, little things, changes of plans, or funny things go wrong, that can be a trigger to repeat our <em>Morning Offering</em>.</p>

<p>We shall tell Our Lord: I'm really serious with the <em>Offering</em> that I made to you. It's these things I wanted to offer to you.</p>

<p>We will try to help others in a way that they may not notice, or might never find out, but which lightens their burden. We try to pray to God for them when they're in need, to avoid having critical spirit towards them, and always to be grateful to them.</p>

<p>All of these things are within the reach and the scope of each one of us. And we should try and do the same where each one of the virtues is concerned.</p>

<p>If we give attention to little things, we will live each day to the full, and will know how to fill each moment with the sense of preparation for eternity. To do this, we could frequently ask Our Lady for help.</p>

<p>Our Lady, Mother of God, pray for us, now, and in every ordinary little situation of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>PKN</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Merciful Messiah</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Merciful Messiah" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’ Large crowds came to him, bringing the lame, the crippled, the blind, the dumb, and many others; and they put these down at his feet and he cured them. The crowds were astonished to hear the dumb speaking, to see the cripples whole again, the lame walking, and the blind with their sight restored” (Matt. 15:32, 30-31).</p>

<p>We’re told, “Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’” This is why the heart of Our Lord is so often moved. In His mercy, He was to follow up this episode with the wonderful miracle of the multiplication of the loaves (Matt. 15:32-39).</p>

<p>We’re reminded in these passages to turn always to the mercy of Our Lord, and to meditate on His life, so as to learn to be merciful to others.</p>

<p>The liturgy places this passage before us during Advent because of an abundance of good things and the limitless mercy which will be the signs of the coming of the Messiah.</p>

<p>“I feel sorry for all these people.” This is an overriding reason for giving ourselves to others: to be compassionate and to have mercy.</p>

<p>In order to learn how to be merciful, we have to fix our eyes on Christ, who comes “to save that which was lost” (Luke 19:10).</p>

<p>He doesn’t come to crush the broken reed or to wholly extinguish the wick that still smolders (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 12:20), but to take upon Himself our wretchedness and save us from it, and to share in their misfortune with those who suffer and are in need. Each page of the Gospel is an example of divine mercy.</p>

<p>We should meditate on the life of Jesus because, as St. Josemaría says, “[The life of] Jesus is a summary and compendium of the [story] of the divine mercy. Many other scenes of the Gospel,” he continues, “also make a deep impact on us, such as his forgiveness of the woman taken in adultery, the parables—the prodigal son, the lost sheep, the pardoned debtor—and the raising to life of the son of the widow at Naim.</p>

<p>“How many reasons based on justice could Christ have found to work as great a wonder as this last one! The only son of that poor widow had died—he who gave meaning to her life, he who would help her in her old age. Jesus did not perform his miracle out of justice, but out of compassion, because his heart was moved by the spectacle of human suffering” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 7).</p>

<p>The mercy of God is the essence of the whole history of salvation, the reason for all His saving actions.</p>

<p>God is mercy. And this divine attribute is like the engine supplying the power that energizes the life story of every human being.</p>

<p>When the apostles wanted to sum up God’s revelation, His mercy always appeared to them to be the essence of an eternal and gratuitous plan springing from God’s generosity. With good reason, the Psalmist could affirm: “The earth is full of the steadfast love of the Lord” (Ps. 33:5).</p>

<p>Mercy is constant in God’s attitude to mankind. And recourse to it is the universal remedy for all our ills, including those for which we thought there was no answer.</p>

<p>Meditating on the mercy of God should fill us with great confidence “now and at the hour of our death,” as we pray in the <em>Hail Mary</em>.</p>

<p>What a joy to be able to say to God, with St. Augustine: “All my hope lies solely in your great mercy!” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>, <em>Book 10</em>).</p>

<p>Solely in that, Lord. On your mercy rests all my hope. Not on my merits, but on your mercy.</p>

<p>In a special way, God shows His mercy towards sinners: He pardons them their sins. The Pharisees often criticize Him for this. He rebuts their criticisms saying: “It is not those who are well who have need of a physician, but those who are sick” (Matt. 9:12).</p>

<p>We who are sinners are sick of soul and need to have recourse many times to the divine mercy. In the Psalms, we say, “Show us, O Lord, your mercy; and grant us your salvation” (Ps. 85:7). The Church repeats these words continually in this liturgical season.</p>

<p>On so many occasions, every day even, we will have need to have recourse to the merciful Heart of Jesus and say: “Lord, if you will, you can make me clean” (Matt. 8:2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul in his encyclical <em>Dives in Misericordia</em> (“Rich in Mercy”), says, especially in these circumstances, “The knowledge of God, the God of mercy and benign love, is a constant and inexhaustible source of conversion, not only as a momentary interior act, but also as a stable disposition, like a state of mind. Those who come to know God in this way, those who so regard Him, cannot live without being incessantly transformed by Him.”</p>

<p>We can also say, as it is said in the Book of Sirach: “How great is the mercy of the Lord, and his forgiveness for those who turn to him!” (Sir. 17:29). Great is the divine mercy toward each one of us.</p>

<p>This can lead us to turn frequently to God, in repentance for our faults and sins, especially in that sacrament of divine mercy which we call Confession.</p>

<p>God has placed a condition for our obtaining His compassion and mercy for our offenses and weaknesses. The condition is that we too should have a heart of compassion for those around us.</p>

<p>In the parable of the good Samaritan (Luke 10:30-37), Our Lord teaches us the attitude that we should adopt towards a neighbor in distress. We’re not permitted to “pass by on the other side” in detached indifference. Rather we must “go” to him.</p>

<p>One morning many years ago, I was going to say Mass in a conference center outside Dublin. It was, maybe, a 45-minute drive. I was a little bit late, so I had my foot on the accelerator. Then I happened to see a car coming out of a side road and hitting a lorry. The front wing of the car was torn off. It was a bit dramatic.</p>

<p>I slowed down. I could see that the only damage really was to the car. Nobody was injured. There was a bit of drama, but nothing else. So, I kept going and I put my foot on the accelerator to try and catch up on the time that I had lost.</p>

<p>But after going about 100 meters, I remembered the story of the Gospel about the priest who went by on the other side of the road.</p>

<p>Listening to my conscience, I had to turn around and go back and double-check that everybody was okay, and give my phone number as a witness, and a few more things. Then I proceeded with my journey a bit more serenely than before.</p>

<p>We can all be that person who goes by on the other side of the road with all sorts of hurried excuses. St. John Paul, in his Apostolic Lette<em>r Salvifici doloris</em> (“The Salvation of Sorrow or Pain”) says: “A good Samaritan is one who stops to relieve the suffering of the other, no matter who he or she may be. This stopping is not just merely from curiosity, but rather from the desire to make ourselves available.</p>

<p>“It’s a specific interior disposition of the heart, which also has its emotional side. Good Samaritans are those who are affected by the suffering they see around them; they are genuinely moved by their neighbor’s misfortune.”</p>

<p>Each of us has to feel bad that people around us do not perhaps have the dignity or the care that they should have as human beings. And it’s not enough for us to feel bad about it. We have to try and do something about it, and infect other people with that sort of thinking, particularly our children, with our words and with our examples.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “If Christ, who knows the interior of man, emphasizes this compassion, this means that it’s important for our whole attitude towards the sufferings of others. Therefore one must cultivate this sensitivity of heart, which bears witness to compassion towards a suffering person. Sometimes this compassion remains the only or the principal expression of our love for and of our solidarity with the sufferer” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici doloris</em>, Point 28, February 11, 1984).</p>

<p>The word compassion comes from two Latin words, <em>com passio</em>, to suffer with.</p>

<p>Throughout Sacred Scripture there’s an urgency on God’s part to see that men also have the stirrings of sympathy and deep-seated feelings of mercy, that they too have this “compassion for another’s misery, which moves us to remedy it, if at all possible” (St. Augustine, <em>The City of God)</em>.</p>

<p>We can look around us and see in our home, in our office, in our workshop, in our neighborhood—is there not some person who’s handicapped, either physically or morally, or elderly, who perhaps needs urgently our time, our affection, and our attention?</p>

<p>Our Lord promises us happiness if we have a merciful heart towards others, and gives assurance that “we will obtain mercy” (Heb. 4:16) from God in the same measure as we show it to our fellow men.</p>

<p>The scope for mercy is as great as the extent of the human suffering that needs to be remedied. And, since mankind is subject to misery and calamity in the physical, intellectual, and moral order, the possible works of mercy are innumerable—as many as men have needs—though traditionally, by way of example, fourteen ‘works of mercy’ have been cited, since in them, this virtue is capable of being exercised in a special way.</p>

<p>Our attitude of compassion and mercy must, in the first place, be shown towards those who are near us—our family, our friends, our close associates—to those whom God has placed at our side, and then to those beyond who are most in need.</p>

<p>Mercy will frequently consist in our attention to the health, the recreation, and the nourishment of those whom God has commended to our care. The sick merit a special attention in terms of our company and our real interest in their illness, as we show them how and help them to offer their sufferings to God.</p>

<p>In a society dehumanized by frequent attacks on the family, more and more old people and those who are ill are left without consolation and affection. Visiting them in their loneliness is a work of mercy that has never been more necessary.</p>

<p>The time spent in keeping them company is rewarded by God in a special way: “As you did it to one of the least of these my brethren, you did it to me,” said Our Lord (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Alongside the so-called material works of mercy, we should also carry out those that are spiritual. In the first place it is our privilege and duty <em>to correct those in</em> <em>error</em> with our advice when the opportunity arises, and charitably, without ever causing offense.</p>

<p>Secondly, it is <em>to teach those who don’t know,</em> especially with regard to ignorance of religion, an ignorance which is the great enemy of God; it increases daily in alarming proportions so that catechesis has become a work of mercy of prime importance and urgency. St. Teresa of Calcutta says ignorance is the greatest poverty.</p>

<p>Next comes giving <em>counsel to the doubting</em>, honestly and with the right intention, so as to help them on their way to God. Then follows the <em>consolation of the afflicted</em>, by sharing their sorrow and encouraging them to recover their happiness in their supernatural understanding of the pain they suffer.</p>

<p><em>Pardon for those who have offended us</em>, promptly and as often as necessary, without giving excessive importance to the offense. We are advised too, <em>to give help to the needy</em>, carrying out this service generously and joyfully.</p>

<p>And finally, we have to <em>pray for the living and the dead</em>, feeling ourselves linked in a special way through the Communion of Saints to those we owe most because of family relationships, or friendship, or whatever else.</p>

<p>Our attitude of merciful benevolence towards others must extend to many different aspects of life because, says St. John Chrysostom, “nothing can make you such an imitator of Christ as your concern for others. Although you fast, although you sleep on the floor, even though, I dare to say, you kill yourself, if you are not attentive to your neighbor, you have done very little; you are very far from being an image of Christ” (St. John Chrysostom, <em>Commentary on the First Epistle to the Corinthians</em>).</p>

<p>We will ourselves obtain God’s mercy and perhaps also merit it for others in that immense depth of “mercy that extends from generation to generation,” as Our Lady prophesied to her cousin Elizabeth (Luke 1:50).</p>

<p>We can also call down the divine mercy on ourselves, who are so much in need of it.</p>

<p>As Christians, we manifest our unity of life by encouraging the works of justice and mercy. Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse the lepers...</p>

<p>From the Church’s earliest days, faithful Christians spread the faith to all parts of the world. From those first years too, vast numbers of Christians have “committed their powers and their lives to liberation from every form of oppression and to the promotion of human dignity.</p>

<p>“The experience of the saints and the example of so many works of service to one’s neighbor are an incentive and a beacon for the liberating undertakings that are needed today,” said the Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith (CDF, <em>Instruction on Christian Freedom and Liberation</em>, Point 57, March 22, 1986).</p>

<p>They are needed perhaps with an even greater urgency than in other periods of history.</p>

<p>Our faith in Christ moves us to be aware of our common involvement with the problems and shortages that other people experience, often with their ignorance and their lack of economic resources.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says this solidarity with our fellow man is not a “superficial sentiment about the evils that beset so many people, whether close to us or far away,” but “a firm and persevering determination to strive for the common good; that is to say, for the good of all and of all individuals, so that we may all be truly responsible for all persons” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Sollicitudo rei socialis</em>–The Concern of the Church for the Social Order, Point 38, December 3, 1987).</p>

<p>Faith leads us to feel a deep respect for others, for each person, and never to remain indifferent to other people’s needs.</p>

<p>Following Christ will manifest itself in deeds of justice and mercy; it will show itself too in our determination to get to know the principles of the social doctrine of the Church and to carry them out, first of all in all our surroundings, right there where we live.</p>

<p>I remember my father coming back from bringing us to swimming lessons as kids. We’d see sometimes a crocodile file of orphans who were going to a local orphanage and were coming from, maybe, the beach as well.</p>

<p>We didn’t know who these people were, what these kids were about, or what was their problem. We didn’t understand. I remember him buying ice cream for those kids, and we were still left with question marks.</p>

<p>Only many years later do you realize what that little gesture was, from a father of a family, in silence, doing that little gesture. It left its mark.</p>

<p>This period coming up to Christmas is a very interesting period, a potential period to engrave these messages in the lives of our children.</p>

<p>It should be possible to say of each one of us at the end of our lives, as it was said about Our Lord: “He went about doing good” (<em>cf</em>. Acts 10:38).</p>

<p>We have to do good within our own families, among our colleagues at work and among our friends, and even with those people whom we just chance to come across.</p>

<p>Our Lord has opportunities outlined for us. There’s a document of the Spanish Episcopal Conference, <em>Catholics in Public Life,</em>which says: “As disciples of Christ, we have to be stewards of fraternity, whatever occasions and circumstances life brings with it. When a man or woman lives the Christian spirit in all its intensity, all his or her activities and relationships reflect and communicate God’s love and the surpassing goods of the Kingdom.</p>

<p>“As Christians we need to know how to make fast and strengthen our relationships each day with our families, our friends, and our neighbors, whether we are at work or at leisure, sealing them with the seal of Christian love, which is simplicity, truthfulness, faithfulness, meekness, generosity, solidarity, and joy.”</p>

<p>We can ask for the mercy of God to be extended to our generation through Mary, Mother of Mercy, our life, our sweetness, and our hope (Prayer, <em>Hail Holy Queen</em>).</p>

<p>Now that the Feast of the Immaculate Conception is so near, our confident reliance on Our Lady will, if we have recourse to her, be more continuous and loving.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MML</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abandonment</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abandonment" /><published>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Gospel, “Can you not buy two sparrows for a penny? Yet not one falls to the ground without your Father knowing” (Matt. 10:29).</p>

<p>Our Lord uses this curious analogy of us with sparrows. It’s curious that He would want to compare us to sparrows, but yet there is a very important message there.</p>

<p>We look at a sparrow, and you blow at a sparrow, it could fall over; very fragile, very timid, not very strong. And yet God tells us that this sparrow can't do a single thing “without your Father knowing” about it and we are “of much more value than any sparrow” (Matt. 10:31).</p>

<p>Our Lord is inviting us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of trust and abandonment. This trust and abandonment, to a large extent, flows from the fact that we are children of God.</p>

<p>We celebrated a few days ago, at the beginning of the month, the Baptism of Our Lord, the institution of the Sacrament of Baptism. Through that sacrament and through all the other sacraments we get divine grace into our soul.</p>

<p>Divine grace is the presence of the Blessed Trinity within us.</p>

<p>Our Lord said we will “come and make our abode in him” (cf. John 14:23), and so when we are in the state of grace, God is in our soul. Therefore, all the fruits of God can be present in our life, in our words, in our actions.</p>

<p>Hopefully, people can somehow detect that this person is trying to lead a holy life, that they're in a state of grace, and therefore God is in control.</p>

<p>If we are not in the state of grace, if God is not in our soul in grace, then the devil may be there. Then all the fruits of the devil can be present in our life, in our works, in our actions, in the atmosphere we carry with us.</p>

<p>Because God is there within us in our soul in grace, we're told in Scripture that we become “children of God” (1 John 3:1). We're told that we're carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves us.</p>

<p>Therefore, everything that happens to us in our life, we can try to see from a supernatural perspective, and see that God is somehow in control, or He has permitted this particular thing—this joy, or sometimes this sorrow, or this contradiction, or this difficulty, or this challenge.</p>

<p>Or sometimes God can sweep the feet from under us and leave us hanging there. And when that happens it’s because He wants us to learn how to trust in Him, to have a great sense of abandonment like the sparrows.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, Our Lord says: “Look at the birds of the air: they neither sow nor reap or gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of abandonment and trust and leave things in His hands. On the one hand, He wants us to use all the human initiative that we have to solve problems.</p>

<p>When He sent the apostles out, He said: “Go ye therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:19). He didn't build chapels. He didn't build schools or hospitals. He didn't give them technology or money or all the other means to fulfill their mission.</p>

<p>He just sent them out with a few ideas. Those ideas were very important ideas, and He wanted them to convert the world with those ideas. He wanted them to be very clear that He would be acting in them and through them.</p>

<p>What He wanted was their faith, their trust, and their abandonment, that He would be at work through them.</p>

<p>Shortly after I was ordained, I was giving a retreat in the south of Spain. (I was ordained there.) There was a number of men on the retreat.</p>

<p>On the first day of the retreat, an 80-year-old man came to chat with me. Usually, people wait a few hours or a few days before they talk to the priest about their resolutions or what they've got from the retreat.</p>

<p>This man came first thing that morning and told me, “You know, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for a number of years, and the person in charge of the recollection asked me if I would come to this retreat. I said no, and I had three very good reasons for saying no.</p>

<p>“One is that I train a certain type of horse. There are some people coming these days to buy some of my horses from another country. I want to be there when they come.</p>

<p>“Secondly, there are some people coming to put drains on my house and I've been waiting for two years for them to come to put drains on my house. I want to be there also when they come.</p>

<p>“Thirdly, it's the weekend of the local fiesta, which is a big thing in Spain. Ever since I was seven, I have never missed this local feast. All my friends will be there. It’s a time to catch up. We meet, we talk, we set ourselves up for the next year. It's just unthinkable that I wouldn't be at the local fiesta.</p>

<p>“So I had three very good reasons for telling this man who was in charge of this recollection that I would not go on the retreat. And he asked me again a few weeks later, and again, I said no; and he asked me a third time, and again, I said no.”</p>

<p>But then he said, “I began to feel very uncomfortable, and the only way that I could find any peace was to finally say yes, and so here I am on this retreat very reluctantly. I came thinking about all the things I'm missing, but you know, I've only been here a couple of hours, and already I'm very glad I came.</p>

<p>“Because you see, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for the last couple of years, and I keep hearing this idea of divine filiation—that we are all children of God because God lives in our soul in grace. They talk about the life of childhood and spiritual childhood, and I've been trying to figure out what this means.</p>

<p>“Here I am, 80 years of age, and they're telling me I have to become like a child. What does that mean? Does it mean I have to put on short pants or what?</p>

<p>“Now I've come to realize what it means. I have to abandon myself into the arms of my Father God. I've got to let Him call the shots.I've got to let Him make the decisions.</p>

<p>“I've got to try and let myself be like a little child in the arms of his Father, with one hand in the hand of his Father, let God lead me and go where He leads me, irrespective of all the other human or material considerations. I've got to try and do His Will and do His thing, in fact, my Christian vocation.”</p>

<p>In those days, it was as though that man discovered “the pearl of great price” (Matt. 13:45-46).</p>

<p>There are treasures in the Gospel, great spiritual treasures. At certain stages of our life, God may reveal those treasures to us, and those treasures can be worth far more than all sorts of material things, because it's there that we can find our peace and our joy. A peace and joy that this world cannot give.</p>

<p>Therefore, there is great importance in living in the state of grace, of being close to the sacraments, of learning how to savor these great treasures that God gives us.</p>

<p>I heard of a kid once who was walking along the beach and his foot hit against a pouch of stones. He picked up the pouch of stones, and he began to take a stone, and he flung it as far as he could into the sea. He said at the same time, ‘When I grow rich, I'm going to get myself a big house.’</p>

<p>He flung another stone and said, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy myself a fine car’; and another stone, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy fine clothes’; and another stone, ‘I'm going to have great food.’</p>

<p>One by one, he threw all the stones as far as he could into the sea. When he got down to the last stone, suddenly a little sunbeam or something hit the stone and it glistened. So, he looked again. It was a diamond!</p>

<p>He'd been throwing diamonds far out into the sea, dreaming about treasures that he might never have, but he'd been throwing away the treasures that he had in his hand.</p>

<p>With this story, we have to come to try and realize that maybe we have great treasures in our lives, in our spiritual life in particular, things that we are perhaps not as aware of as we could be. We don't realize the treasures.</p>

<p>One great way of trying to get to know the treasures that we have in our life is through acts of thanksgiving.</p>

<p>If you thank God from the moment you get up in the morning until the moment you get to bed at night, for the fact that you can see, the fact that you can hear, the fact that you can walk around the place and have two arms and two legs—these are all wonderful treasures that can lead us to appreciate all the other treasures that are present every day of our life: the air that we breathe, the things that we see, the health of the people around us.</p>

<p>There are so many wonderful things to be grateful for. So we need to learn how to abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>I got a haircut last week in Nairobi, and when I came out of the place where I got it, I was driving up the street and saw a young girl crawling on all fours with a little cup, begging. Not something you often see: a young girl crawling on all fours, she had no wheelchair, she had nothing.</p>

<p>The following day, with a friend of mine, we decided to go and look for this girl and try and see if we could do something for her. We found her in a completely different place, purely by accident, crawling across a busy street with several crossings.</p>

<p>So my friend got out of the car and went to talk to her. She had no English and I don't have Swahili. They talked and she explained that she was from Migori. She was 22, she had come to Nairobi two years previously, she lived with two other people with disabilities, and somehow, she had managed to survive.</p>

<p>When she moved around Nairobi, she would hop onto a <em>matatu</em>. She got to different places from which she could beg, and she managed to carry on like this: a very cheerful lady and very happy to talk.</p>

<p>Then she came with us and we got her a wheelchair. Hopefully, she's now using that wheelchair.</p>

<p>But thinking about how that girl has survived in an unknown city far away from her home territory, and not having English, and not knowing the place, and managing to move around like that—there must be a tremendous abandonment in her, in her life, in her spirit. She went away from her own home to a strange place.</p>

<p>So sometimes with people we meet we can learn an awful lot about the spirit of abandonment, trust, of having faith in God, because we know that God has a plan for us.</p>

<p>He wants us to live out that plan. He has a mission for us. There's nothing in our life that He has not foreseen.</p>

<p>And so, as we start a new year we could try to ask Our Lord in the Blessed Sacrament that we might have a greater spirit of faith and trust and abandonment to live out those consequences of being a child of God, so that we may leave the future in His hands.</p>

<p>And if we see, as we can probably do, that when we look back, God has really taken care of so many things in our life: our primary education, our secondary education, perhaps our tertiary education, our work, our family, our children, our health—so many things that God has looked after in all sorts of special ways. We have every reason to grow in faith and trust in Him.</p>

<p>St. Thérèse of Lisieux says, “When…we feel no courage, no energy, for the practice of virtue, this is grace” (Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>Letters of Soeur Thérèse to Céline</em>, October 20, 1888). This is the moment to depend solely on Jesus.</p>

<p>There might be moments in our life when Our Lord precisely sweeps the feet from under us and leaves us hanging there. In those situations, He wants us to look up.</p>

<p>He wants us to trust completely in Him, to leave things in His hands, to learn what real hope is, what real abandonment is.</p>

<p>A farmer told me how one time he was going through his farm, and there’d been a fire on the farm. He came across all sorts of things that had been very burnt.</p>

<p>At one moment he came across a chicken that was very badly burnt, totally dead, and he gave it a good kick—this chicken that was totally dead, burnt black—but out from underneath the chicken ran four or five little chicks.</p>

<p>He said, “I suddenly remembered that phrase from Scripture: ‘I will gather you under my wing as a hen gathers her chicks’” (Matt. 23:27).</p>

<p>He said this hen saw the danger, the fire coming, she gathered her chicks. So he was very aware of the fact that Our Father God looks after us in all sorts of ways, takes care of us, preserves us from danger.</p>

<p>Sometimes we might wonder, Why? Why did this happen to my family, to my parents, to my siblings, to my children, to my work? Why do all these things specifically happen to me?</p>

<p>In certain moments, we may not appreciate that. But when time passes, sometimes we can discover there's some great divine plan behind the cross. God is at work. He has other plans that He's working out.</p>

<p>A man in another country told me once how he had a primary school education. He began to be a salesman selling pots and pans.</p>

<p>He knocked one day on the door of the president of the Ford Corporation who didn't want any pots and pans. He thought he would get his wife, but he got the husband.</p>

<p>But the husband was impressed with his sales pitch. He said, “Young man, how would you like to try selling cars? OK? So come along on Monday morning, we'll start you out selling cars.”</p>

<p>So he sold a lot of cars. He graduated to Mercedes-Benzes. He ended up importing Rolls Royces from London. He could tell you the mileage on the clock of every Rolls Royce in Asia. He made a lot of money.</p>

<p>Then he gave a present of a watch to some man in government, which is something you cannot do in that particular country. The government turned around and bankrupted him.</p>

<p>So he lost everything. He lost all his money. He lost his house. He lost his business. His wife left him. At the age of 49, he developed stage 4 cancer.</p>

<p>That's when I got to know him. He used to go to a support group in his parish for people who were recovering from cancer. This was a fairly well-to-do parish with a lot of wealthy people, and they would get together and talk week by week.</p>

<p>Then they heard of a new drug that had been made in Houston, Texas, a new cancer drug which was very expensive. One by one all these very wealthy people flew off to Houston, Texas to try out this new drug.</p>

<p>He came to me and he said, “You know, it's not fair. There’s no justice in this world. The wealthy can do all these things, and here I am, I’m bankrupt, they’ve taken away my passport, I can't leave the country, I couldn't have any money to fly, and so poor me, I can't try out this new drug.”</p>

<p>And he said, “I was complaining to God for weeks and months about how unfair this life is. Then, you know, the first one died; and then after three months, the next one died; and after six months, another one died; and now they're nearly all dead and I'm still here. So I'm saying thank you, Lord, thank you, Lord.”</p>

<p>So sometimes all the injustices of this world are the things that we find we can do. When time passes and you look back, sometimes you can see, maybe the hand of God was working in funny ways here.</p>

<p>Maybe God has me in the palm of His hand, looking after me in special ways or looking after my family.</p>

<p>There are times when there are things that maybe we'd like to have and we can't have them. God doesn't permit us to have them: luxuries or things that other people have. Maybe it's because God just wants us to trust in Him, to abandon ourselves. He has some other plan. Maybe that's not our mission.</p>

<p>When there are things in life that we find other people have, and we can't afford them and we can't have them, it may be that God is forming our soul at that moment more than at any other time.</p>

<p>Perhaps He's giving us spiritual treasures, teaching us what authentic detachment means, or teaching us authentic hope or authentic trust, which ultimately are the messages that Christ gives to us in Bethlehem.</p>

<p>Christ abandoned Himself in Bethlehem into the arms of Mary, into the arms of Joseph.</p>

<p>Sometimes that's what God wants us to do. If we were to hear tomorrow that we have some fatal disease, we can abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God. It can be totally peaceful.</p>

<p>I knew some men a couple of years ago who used to come to recollections like this. Both of them developed cancer, but they were leading very good spiritual lives.</p>

<p>They happened to find themselves in the same hospital room, and one said to the other: “Are you worried about anything? Do you feel bad about anything?” “No, I'm very peaceful.” “Me too, there’s nothing to worry about. I leave everything in the hands of God. It's a great way to live and a great way to die.”</p>

<p>It’s a wonderful thing to be able to look forward to our death because our souls are in the right state.</p>

<p>In the house where I lived, two people passed away in the last two or three months. One was 87, the other was 94. They were both looking forward to their death.</p>

<p>The 94-year-old priest in particular kept saying, “I want to die. I want to die.”</p>

<p>We brought him into the hospital at one stage, The Mater Hospital in Nairobi, and the nurse said to me, “You know, he keeps saying he wants to die, he wants to die, but everyone in this hospital wants to live. We’re wondering, is there something wrong? Is there something we should be doing?”</p>

<p>At one moment he refused all his medication and all of his food. I said to him, “Father, why don't you eat your food or take your medicine?”</p>

<p>“It's the only weapon I have to get out of this place.” So he had a great sense of humor. He died laughing. A great way to live and a great way to die. Abandonment in the moment of death, in the arms of God, because he lived a holy life.</p>

<p>Likewise, the other one, 87, saying his rosary every day, getting to Confession every week, receiving Holy Communion every day. I asked him in the last couple of days before he died, “Is there anything that you'd like?”</p>

<p>“Well, if you could find this dark chocolate, I'd be very happy.” I went to the supermarket and I found the dark chocolate. He liked a particular type of dark chocolate. So he went to heaven, enjoying himself! Great way to live, great way to die.</p>

<p>I have no worries, I’ve lived a good life, I abandon myself into the arms of my Father God, because we have tremendous things to look forward to.</p>

<p>“Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered the heart of man, the things that God has prepared for those who love him” (1 Cor. 2:9). If we live our lives focused on heaven, it's a great way to live.</p>

<p>We try to make our life on earth as heavenly as possible, but we realize that everything here is passing. It’s worth nothing, it’s fading away.</p>

<p>The things of the spirit, the things of the soul, the things that are worth having—these are the things worth acquiring, the treasures that God gives to us.</p>

<p>We look at little children, we see how they abandon themselves, and how they can get great joy out of little things.</p>

<p>Over the last few weeks, I was involved in a number of Christmas parties for poor kids. I have a friend who organizes these parties, and he gets big numbers. He brings lollipops and chapatis and sodas.</p>

<p>One time we were going to a place, and I said, Where are you going to get the children for the party? He said, You just watch.</p>

<p>So he gives two sodas to two kids. They go away. Fifty kids come within five minutes. So he gives them a lollipop, one by one.</p>

<p>Well, you see the faces of those kids light up with the lollipops and sometimes they have to struggle to get the tight wrapping off the lollipop, because it seems to be there with concrete or something. They fight to get it off. The joy on their faces, the happiness, the little things.</p>

<p>Sometimes God wants us with our childlike spirit to get great joy and happiness out of simple things. It's a great way to learn to be happy.</p>

<p>In the writings of St. Josemaría, you'll find in one place it says, “Be content with what enables you to live a simple and sober life (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 631).</p>

<p>Great advice. Who do you know in this world who is content—content with what they have, happy with what they have, thanking God for what they have.</p>

<p>A great way to live every day: Thank you, God, for the food we have on the table, for the air that I breathe, for the fact that my hands and legs work, that I can see, that I can hear. So many things that we take for granted too much.</p>

<p>We abandon every day, every hour, in our work, this project, the dreams we have for this coming year, in our workplace, in our family, in the problems we'd like to solve.</p>

<p>Maybe God has precisely given us those problems to work at solving them, not because He wants us to worry about it or be perturbed about it. He just wants us to work at them, but we know that things will work out.</p>

<p>“If you, evil as you are,” we’re told in Scripture, “know how to give good things to your children, how much more will your heavenly Father give good things to those who ask him?” (Matt. 7:11).</p>

<p>If you think back over the last few weeks, how many parents in the world did their best at Christmastime to give good things from Father Christmas to their children?</p>

<p>Maybe even if their children didn't deserve them, they still wanted to give them good things, the best they could find. Our Lord tells us, “How much more will your heavenly Father…” It's a great world for all of them.</p>

<p>Our Father God is waiting to give us all the best presents in the world, all the best treasures, but He wants us to trust in Him, to leave everything in His hands.</p>

<p>Every day of our life we can ask Our Lord for an increase in faith, an increase in hope, an increase in charity, an increase in that spirit of divine filiation, that God is my Father.</p>

<p>There may be twists and turns along the pathway of our life, but we know it will work out well in the end.</p>

<p>There was a little girl who asked Santa Claus for a thousand dolls for Christmas. Her father was an atheist.</p>

<p>She got one doll. Her father said to her, “Well, your God didn't listen to your prayer, did he?”</p>

<p>The little girl said, “Yes, He did. He said no. And that's okay. He's my Father, so it's okay for Him to say no from time to time. You're my father, you say ‘no’ pretty frequently also. That’s no big deal; that doesn't mean you don't exist.”</p>

<p>Wow, profound wisdom from a small child.</p>

<p>Sometimes, God might seem not to answer our prayer. Sometimes He says yes, sometimes He says no and sometimes He says, Wait, I’ll give that to you later. Or, Wait, because I have something better to give you, I have something greater off the line.</p>

<p>Or maybe, I don't want to give you that material thing, but I have some great spiritual thing to give you, which is worth far more than you realize, far more than a diamond. Abandonment!</p>

<p>There is a movie that came out about twenty or thirty years ago about a nun talking to a prisoner on death row. This nun is trying to convert this prisoner, helping him to repent and make his peace with God.</p>

<p>The movie is her conversation with this prisoner on death row, and at one stage she says to him: “Did you ever hear that you are a son of God?”</p>

<p>And he replied saying, “You know, in the course of my life I've been called a son of many things, but I have never been called a son of God.”</p>

<p>Well, this great reality can be something that can open our eyes, that we are truly sons of God, children of God.</p>

<p>God is my Father and therefore I can make this new beginning, this new year, with an awful lot of confidence and hope and trust that God is going to be there for me. He's going to work things out.</p>

<p>When we look back over the last year, possibly we can thank God for all the graces that He's given to us in the past year, all the things that are worked out.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was sitting in her garden, and she noticed there was a rose in the garden. Suddenly her attention began to focus on the rose, a beautiful rose.</p>

<p>She began to think how man has been able to put men on the moon, but no man can make a rose like that. That was the beginning of a profound spiritual conversion.</p>

<p>She began to focus on all the great spiritual things in her life. She’d led a very busy career woman life up to then. She became a very spiritual person.</p>

<p>In this coming year, God also wants some sort of spiritual conversion inside us, so that we live out that spiritual childhood, that abandonment, in so many ways.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to the apostles, “Do not be afraid.” On many occasions He said those words.</p>

<p>In the face of the supernatural, very often there was fear. There was the storm on the lake when He came walking to them: “Do not be afraid! It is I. Have courage, do not be afraid” (John 6:20).</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lord and ask Him that we might also respond to those words. Remember that we're worth more than many sparrows and not a single sparrow falls to the ground without Our Father God knowing it.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord that we might have this greater spirit of trust and abandonment, the trust and abandonment that we see that Our Lady had throughout her life.</p>

<p>She didn't understand what was going to happen in Bethlehem. She didn't know that they were going to go to Egypt. She didn't know how long they were going to be there. She and St. Joseph were just totally, completely abandoned to the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help me to live that spirit of abandonment in the same way that you did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>