<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:31+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Knowing When to Speak</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowing When to Speak" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in St. Mark that Jesus “was silent and made no answer” (Mark 14:61). For thirty years, Jesus had lived a life of silence. Mary and Joseph were the only ones who knew the mystery of the Son of God.</p>

<p>During His public life, when He returned to His hometown, His relatives were disconcerted by His wisdom and His miracles. They had known Him only from His exemplary life of work.</p>

<p>During the three years of His public life, we see how He withdraws into the silence of prayer, to be alone with His Father God. He withdraws from the superficial clamor of the multitude that wants to make Him their king. He performs miracles without ostentation, asking people He cures to refrain from publicizing His powers.</p>

<p>We see that one of the characteristics of the life of Christ was silence. His silence before His enemies in the Passion is very moving: “He was silent and made no answer,” we’re told (Mark 14:61). In the face of so many false accusations, He makes no defense.</p>

<p>St. Jerome comments, “Our God and Savior, who because of his mercy had redeemed the world, allows himself to be led to his death like a lamb, without a word of complaint or self-defense. The silence of Jesus obtains pardon for the protest and excuse of Adam” (Jerome, <em>Commentary on St. Mark’s Gospel</em>).</p>

<p>Jesus says nothing during the hearings before Herod and Pilate. We see Him standing silent at their preference for Barabbas in front of His hate-filled enemies.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew: “When he was accused by the chief priests and elders, he made no answer. Then Pilate said to him, ‘Do you not hear how many things they testify against you?’ But he gave him no answer, not even to a single charge, so that the governor wondered greatly” (Matt. 27:12-14).</p>

<p>The silence of Jesus in the face of human passions, before the sins which are committed every day by humanity, is not a silence of anger. It is a silence that’s full of patience and love.</p>

<p>The silence of Calvary is that of a God who comes to redeem all men by His indescribable agony of the Cross. The silence of Jesus in the tabernacle is that of a love which waits for a response. It’s the patient silence of one who treasures our attentions.</p>

<p>Christ’s silence during His earthly life represents interior strength and sense of purpose. One writer says, “Those who complain continually about their misfortunes or their bad luck should look at the example of Our Lord. Those who proclaim their problems to the four winds should consider the behavior of Christ. Those who feel compelled to explain and excuse their actions, who wait anxiously for praise or approval, should take note of Christ, who says nothing.</p>

<p>“We will imitate him when we learn to accept life’s duties and worries without sterile complaints, when we confront our personal problems without dumping them in someone else’s lap, when we face squarely the consequences of our actions, when we do our work for the glory of God without looking for earthly praise” (F. Suarez, <em>The Two Faces of Silence, Nuestro Tiempo</em>).</p>

<p>“Jesus says nothing,” we’re told in Scripture. We have to learn to say nothing on many occasions. At times vanity will have us say things which should have been kept locked in the soul.</p>

<p>The silent figure of Christ is the ever-present model to reproach empty or useless words. His example will lead us to remain silent before calumny and rumor. The Prophet Isaiah says, “In silence and in hope will be your fortitude and your courage” (Isa. 30:15). He encourages us that our fortitude is grounded in silence and in hope.</p>

<p>At the same time, Our Lord doesn’t always remain silent. He teaches us that sometimes we have to speak out when it’s necessary, with charity and with fortitude, avoiding the silence of consent.</p>

<p>There is a silence that can collaborate with lying, a silence that can cooperate with cowardice, a silence which springs from the love of comfort and the fear of complicating one’s life. You can close your eyes to what is disagreeable. You can put off making a fraternal correction that ought to be made at home or at work.</p>

<p>The word of Jesus is full of authority as He faces injustice and abuse. In St. Matthew we’re told, “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you devour widows’ houses and for a pretense you make long prayers” (Matt. 23:14).</p>

<p>St. John the Baptist was “the voice of one crying in the wilderness” (Matt. 3:3). He teaches us to say everything that must be said, even though it may seem as if we too are crying in the wilderness.</p>

<p>Our Lord will not allow our words to be wasted. It’s important that we say what has to be said, without worrying ourselves about the immediate consequences.</p>

<p>If each Christian were to speak in conformity with the faith, we would surely change the world. We can’t sit by silently in the face of such crimes of abortion and the degradation of marriage and the family. Nor can we surrender to those forces that would seek to remove God from the formation of the young.</p>

<p>We can’t be silent at attacks upon the Pope and Our Lady, or upon institutions of the Church. To be silent when we should be speaking out can be a way of collaborating with evil, because others might think that our silence means consent.</p>

<p>If Catholics were to speak out where there is need, if they were to boycott anti-Catholic publications or literature, it would be more difficult for those enterprises to prosper.</p>

<p>In our prayer today, we can ask Our Lord for the grace to speak out when necessary. At times, those occasions will be when we’re with a little group of our friends, coming or going to school or to work. In letters to the editor, we can write in praise of a good article or to criticize a bad one.</p>

<p>We should always act with charity. It’s worthwhile to remember that true charity always goes hand in hand with fortitude. We need to exercise good manners, always working with the intention of bringing souls to Jesus Christ. Yet we should act at the same time with the fortitude of Our Lord.</p>

<p>If upon realizing that his life was in danger, St. John the Baptist had remained silent or retired to the sidelines of public affairs, he would not have been beheaded by Herod. But John was not that kind of man. He was not “a reed shaken by the wind” (Matt. 11:7). He was true to his vocation and also to his principles to the end.</p>

<p>If he had remained silent, he could have lived a few more years, but his disciples would not have been the first to follow Our Lord. He would not have “prepared and made straight the way of the Lord,” as we’re told by Isaiah (Isa. 40:3). He would not have lived up to his vocation. His life would have been bereft of meaning.</p>

<p>Probably Our Lord is not asking us to suffer a martyr’s death, but He is asking for courage and fortitude in facing up to the demands of ordinary life. Perhaps He is asking us to stop watching a bad TV show or to cease putting off an apostolic conversation.</p>

<p>We can’t allow ourselves to hide behind excuses when there is a lot of apostolic work to be done. We have to act with optimism, loving the world and the good that is in it, while seeking to increase that goodness. We can do this with the example of a joyful family and of the youthful love that is born of holy purity.</p>

<p>There are other kinds of cowardly silence which we have to struggle against: the silence we might maintain with the person next to us. But God has put that person there so that we might be a beacon of light for him or for her.</p>

<p>It’s hard to imagine that we can be courageous at all in this life if we are not courageous first with ourselves, especially when we’re talking with our spiritual director, to say the things that need to be said.</p>

<p>Many of our friends, on seeing that we truly practice what we preach, will be attracted to the faith. Centuries ago, many people converted after witnessing the martyrdom of the first Christians.</p>

<p>We can learn a lot from Our Lord’s silence. We’re told in the Psalms, “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2). God lives in our midst and often in a very silent way.</p>

<p>Throughout the Old Testament, God makes known His intention of having an ongoing presence among men. The “tent of meeting” was the first temple to God in the desert. Upon the tent there came to rest a cloud which symbolized the glory of God and His presence.</p>

<p>“Then the cloud covered the tent of meeting and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle” (Ex. 40:34). The cloud was a sign of the divine presence (<em>cf</em>. Num. 12:5; 1 Kings 8:10-11).</p>

<p>Much later, the Temple of Jerusalem was the place where the Israelites worshiped God (<em>cf</em>. Ex. 23:15-17). It was the place they had been longing for while they were in the desert.</p>

<p>They would recall the enthusiasm of old when they would go to the house of the Lord, singing songs of joy and praise: “How lovely is your dwelling place, O Lord of hosts! My soul longs, yes, faints for the courts of the Lord; my heart and flesh sing for joy to the living God” (Ps. 84:1-2).</p>

<p>To be far from the sanctuary was to be deprived of true happiness. “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2).</p>

<p>In the fullness of time, the Word became flesh. In the moment of the Incarnation the power of the Most High overshadowed Our Lady (<em>cf</em>. Luke 1:35). This is an expression of the omnipotence of God.</p>

<p>Following upon the Incarnation, Our Lady, the Virgin, became the Tabernacle of God. “The Word of God dwelt among us,” we’re told in St. John (John 1:14).</p>

<p>St. John uses a Greek verb for “dwelt” which originally meant “to pitch one’s tent,” hence, to live in a place. “The careful reader of Scripture will immediately think of the tabernacle, or tent, in the period of the exodus from Egypt, where God showed his presence before all the people of Israel through certain signs of his glory, such as the cloud covering the tent.</p>

<p>“In many passages of the Old Testament it is announced that God ‘will dwell in the midst of the people’ (<em>cf</em>. Jer. 7:3; Ezek. 43:9; Sir. 24:8). These signs of God’s presence, first in the pilgrim Tent of the Ark in the desert and then in the Temple of Jerusalem, are followed by the most wonderful form of God’s presence among us—Jesus Christ, perfect God and perfect Man, in whom the ancient promise is fulfilled in a way that far exceeded men’s greatest expectations. Also the promise made through Isaiah about the ‘Emmanuel’ or ‘God with us’ (Isa. 7:14; <em>cf</em>. Matt. 1:23) is completely fulfilled through this dwelling of the Incarnate Son of God among us” (<em>The Navarre Bible</em>, St. John).</p>

<p>From that time onwards, we can say with exactitude that God lives among us. We can be next to Him every day, closer to Him than anyone might imagine possible—God truly dwelling among us.</p>

<p>From the moment of the Incarnation we can affirm that God is with us in the personal presence of Jesus Christ. As both true God and true Man, Jesus is closer to us than any other being. Jesus is “God with us.”</p>

<p>In earlier times, the Israelites would say that God was “with them.” Now we can say this in a very literal sense.</p>

<p>When Christ traveled about Palestine, He made an effort to preach in many towns. “When Jesus had finished these parables,” we’re told, “he went away from there” (Matt. 13:53). God left one town to go and meet other people.</p>

<p>When the priest consecrates the host during the Mass, he brings Christ to the altar with His Holy Humanity. He is there in the Eucharist with a special presence for as long as the sacramental species last.</p>

<p>This presence affects the Body of Christ in a direct way and the Three Persons of the Holy Trinity in an indirect way. The Word is tied to Christ’s humanity, while the Father and the Holy Spirit are related by the mutual immanence of their divine Persons (<em>cf</em>. Council of Trent, Decree, <em>De Sanctissima Eucharistia</em>).</p>

<p>Christ is really present in the Tabernacle with His Body, Blood, Soul, and Divinity. It can be said quite literally that ‘God is here, close to me.’ We could make that act of faith: “My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me.”</p>

<p>Down through the centuries the Church has developed a precise way of describing the Eucharistic presence, often requiring such exact definition to counter erroneous beliefs.</p>

<p>The Eucharistic presence is a <em>real</em> presence, a silent presence. It is not symbolic, nor does it signify or insinuate any image.</p>

<p>It is not fictitious, or merely the product of the imagination or the will. It is <em>substantial</em> because the words of the Consecration spoken by the priest change the substance of bread and the wine into the substance of the Body and Blood of Christ.</p>

<p>Paul VI says, “Every theological explanation which seeks some understanding of this mystery must, in order to be in accord with Catholic faith, maintain that in the reality itself, independently of our mind, the bread and wine have ceased to exist after the Consecration, so that it is the adorable Body and Blood of Our Lord Jesus that from then on are really before us under the sacramental species of bread and wine…” (Paul VI, Apostolic Letter, <em>Credo of the People of God</em>, Point 25, June 30, 1968).</p>

<p>In the encyclical <em>Mysterium Fidei</em>, Paul VI says, “As a result of transubstantiation, the species of bread and wine…contain a new ‘reality’ which we may justly term ‘ontological.’ Not that there lies under those species what was already there before, but something quite different; and that not only because of the faith of the Church, but in objective reality… (<em>cf</em>. Paul VI, Encyclical, <em>Mysterium Fidei,</em> Point 46, September 3, 1965).</p>

<p>Jesus is silently present in our Tabernacles whether or not we take advantage of this amazing wonder. He is there silently, with His Body and His Blood, His Soul and His Divinity. God made Man. He could not be closer.</p>

<p>The Church possesses the Author of all grace and the cause of our sanctification. We may venture to say that the Eucharistic presence of Christ is the sacramental prolongation of the Incarnation.</p>

<p>From the Tabernacle Jesus invites us to bring to Him our concerns and our petitions. In the <em>visit to the Blessed Sacrament</em> and other acts of worship offered to the Holy Eucharist, we give thanks for this great gift.</p>

<p>There we can go to find new strength, to tell Jesus that we miss Him, to tell Him that we need Him very much. “The Eucharist is reserved in the churches and oratories [to serve as] the spiritual center of a religious community or of a parish, and [indeed] of the universal Church and of all humanity, since beneath the appearance of the species, Christ is contained: the invisible Head of the Church, the Redeemer of the world, the center of all hearts, ‘by whom,’ says St. Paul, ‘all things are and by whom we exist’ (1 Cor. 8:6)” (<em>ibid</em>., Point 68).</p>

<p>It has been the constant practice of the Church to adore Christ’s silent presence in the Tabernacle. If we recall how much reverence the Israelites had for their “tent of meeting” in the desert and for the Temple at Jerusalem, which were figures or images of reality, how much more reverence should we have for Christ truly present in the Tabernacle?</p>

<p>In the first centuries of the Church, the main reason for reserving the Sacred Species was for the sake of those who were not able to get to Mass, especially the sick and the dying, and also for those in prison due to religious persecution. The Sacrament of the Lord was brought with piety and fervor so that these Christians might also receive Communion.</p>

<p>Later, faith in the real presence of Christ led to the cult of the Blessed Sacrament, and the Church authoritatively approved those practices. The Council of Trent declared, “There is, therefore, no room left for doubt that all the faithful of Christ in accordance with a custom always received in the Catholic Church offer in veneration the worship of <em>latria</em> which is due to the true God, to this most Holy Sacrament” (Council of Trent, <em>Session XIII</em>).</p>

<p>In the thirteenth century, St. Thomas Aquinas composed a Eucharistic hymn which embodies the faith of the Church in a faithful and pious manner. We should make this hymn our own so as to nourish our piety and give honor to the Blessed Sacrament.</p>

<p>The hymn states: “O Godhead hid, devoutly I adore you, Who truly are within the forms before me; To you my heart I bow with bended knee, As failing quite in contemplating thee” (Prayer in Adoration Before the Blessed Sacrament, <em>Adore te Devote</em>).</p>

<p>Here we have all the truths of the faith. We have understanding with humility and thanksgiving, amazement before the power of God, surprise at the extent of His mercy. With the confidence gained by having Him so close by, we can ask Our Lord for His grace to unite ourselves to His most holy will.</p>

<p>Next to the silent Tabernacle, we can learn how to love. There we will draw the strength necessary to remain faithful. We’ll find consolation in times of sorrow.</p>

<p>He silently waits for us and He rejoices when we are next to Him, even if only for a short while. There Jesus waits for His people who suffer the contradictions of this life. He comforts them with the warmth of His understanding and His love.</p>

<p>It is in the Tabernacle that the words of Our Lord come to life, specifically those words where He says, “Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest” (Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>We should not fail to visit Him. He is waiting for us. He has many gifts prepared for us.</p>

<p>Mary, we turn to you, Comfort of the afflicted, Cause of our joy. We ask you for the grace to learn from the silence of Our Lord in His public life, and also in the Tabernacle.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Dominic</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Dominic" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Dominic was born in Caleruega about the year 1170. He fought the Albigensian heresy with his preaching and exemplary life. He founded the Dominicans, the Order of Preachers, and spread devotion to the Holy Rosary. He died in Bologna on August 6, 1221.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the 13th century, some sects were causing great harm in the Church, especially in the south of France. During a journey St. Dominic made throughout that region in the company of his bishop, he was able to verify the damaging effects that novel doctrines were causing in the people of God, on account of deficient formation, as has so often been the case. Ignorance has brought about an awful lot of evil.</p>

<p>During his tour, the saint perceived the need to teach the truths of the faith clearly and simply. With great zeal and love for souls, he gave himself fully to the task. Shortly thereafter, he decided to found a new religious order whose aim would be the spread of Christian doctrine and its defense against error throughout Christendom.</p>

<p>In this way, the Order of Preachers was founded. The study of truths was to be one of its fundamental tenets. Ever since then, Dominicans can be found in all kinds of apostolic activities in service to the Church, bringing truth to the minds of humanity.</p>

<p>Like their founder, they put their particular charism into practice so as to illuminate the consciences of persons with the light of the Word of God. The task of transmitting the deposit of faith to everyone is currently a pressing need, as it was in St. Dominic’s day. This is a mission of the entire Church, and it is becoming more urgent than ever before.</p>

<p>Pope John Paul II periodically warned of the widespread ignorance of the most elementary truths of the faith. In an address, he said there is a contagion of numerous doctrinal errors, with detrimental consequences to souls. The lack of love and esteem for the Holy Eucharist, the neglect of confession as a sacrament vitally necessary for obtaining God’s pardon and for the formation of a person’s conscience, the disregard for our supernatural last end, and a widespread relegation of the faith to private life, stripping it of all public expression.</p>

<p>Marriage is deprived of its natural meaning and dignity. Laws permissible of abortion declare the triumph of material ease and egoism over the most sacred value of human life. A decrease in the birth rate and an aging population have led one responsible European to speak of a demographic suicide in Europe. It appears to be a serious symptom of profound spiritual impoverishment.</p>

<p>Clearly, many are oblivious to our call to friendship with God, of sin, of eternal life, of the Christian meaning of suffering. It’s plain to see that the world becomes less human to the extent that it ceases to be Christian. A wave of materialism, the loss of supernatural perspective, also affects and perhaps very profoundly the people we see around us every day and whom the Lord perhaps puts under our care for one reason or another.</p>

<p>We can consider in the presence of God today whether we are taking to heart the call of the popes to re-Christianize the world around us, in our social milieu. May we consider whether we’re making an effort to know the teachings of Jesus Christ in depth and to spread them. Do we rectify our personal, family, professional, social, and political conduct accordingly? Are we trying to invigorate those external signs of religion and Christian life that so many are bent on disregarding? A scapular, blessings at meals, and of our new house, having recourse to images of Our Lord and of Our Lady in our home and at our place of work.</p>

<p>Like so many others before him, St. Dominic depended on a powerful weapon to conquer in what at first appeared to be a losing battle. Great in the integrity of his doctrine, in the example of his virtue, and in his apostolic labors, he dauntlessly declared war on the enemies of the Church. Not by force of arms, but through burning faith in the Holy Rosary.</p>

<p>He was the first to establish and personally spread this devotion, which was later continued by his sons to the four corners of the earth. The saint required his spiritual sons to frequently make use of their preaching of this form of prayer from which he drew so much profit. On the one hand, he knew of Mary’s enormous influence with her Son, who always dispenses His graces through her hands.</p>

<p>On the other, she is so naturally inclined to mercy and kindness and so used to spontaneously helping those in need that she cannot withhold her help from all those who ask it. The Church always finds her to be our Mother in the order of grace and Mother most merciful, and has long had the custom of greeting her as such, above all through the Rosary.</p>

<p>For this reason, said Pope Benedict XV, the Roman Pontiffs have extolled devotion to the Marian Rosary with the highest praise and have enriched it with indulgences. By filial instinct, and on the explicit recommendation of the Popes, Christians have recourse to the Holy Rosary in both ordinary and extraordinary circumstances. Including public catastrophes, wars, heresies, and important family problems.</p>

<p>This powerful and perennial devotion is an excellent means of thanksgiving too. The advice of the most recent popes is constant, particularly with respect to the family Rosary. The Second Vatican Council reminded the Christian faithful to esteem those acts of piety for the Blessed Virgin which the Magisterium has recommended throughout the centuries. And Paul VI explicitly interpreted these words as referring to the Rosary.</p>

<p>Today, when humanity is so much in need, we can examine the quality of our love for and our confidence in Our Lady as expressed through this grace-laden devotion. We can ask ourselves whether we turn to our Mother in heaven with faith while we spread good doctrine around us, especially if any of those closest to us are straying from the Lord.</p>

<p>If we try to pray the Holy Rosary with love every day, St. Dominic will win many graces for ourselves and also for those whom we want to lead to Our Lord. In it, we consider the principal mysteries of our salvation, from the Annunciation of Our Lady to the Resurrection and Ascension of Our Lord into heaven, by way of His Passion and death. The first five joyful mysteries cover the hidden life of Jesus and Mary. Contemplating them will teach us to sanctify the realities of ordinary life.</p>

<p>The five sorrowful mysteries lead us to reflect on and to relive the events of the Passion. They teach us to sanctify suffering, sickness, and the cross that are present in the life of every man and woman. In the last five glorious mysteries, we meditate on the triumphs of Our Lord and of His Mother. They fill us with joy and hope as we bring to mind the glory God has reserved for us if we are faithful.</p>

<p>By reflecting on these mysteries, we go to Jesus through Mary. We rejoice with Christ as we ponder His being made man like us. We suffer patiently with Him and anticipate His glory. To ponder these truths with piety, we need to direct our prayer to the heart of her who was closest to Christ on earth, says Paul VI. In this way, we can become privy to a favorable meditation on the mysteries of the life of Our Lord.</p>

<p>The never-ending wealth of truth contained in these mysteries opens before our mind’s eye. To pray the Rosary like this, says St. Josemaría, considering the mysteries, repeating the <em>Our Father</em> and <em>Hail Mary,</em> with the praises to the Blessed Trinity and the constant invocation to the Mother of God, is a continuous act of faith, hope, and love, of adoration and reparation.</p>

<p>During the time of St. Dominic, people greeted Our Lady with the invocation of a rose, a symbol of beauty and joy. Images of her were already adorned with crowns of roses in representation of the Rosary beads. Singing to Mary as the garden of roses was common throughout Christendom. The present term “Rosary” has its origin in this custom.</p>

<p>We shouldn’t forget that each <em>Hail Mary</em> is like a rose that we offer to our Mother in heaven. May we not allow them to pass lifelessly from our lips due to lack of interest or inattentiveness. In the face of the obstacles we encounter, let us not neglect this powerful weapon. In <em>The Furrow,</em> we’re told, let us draw close to Our Lady through this devotion, when we feel the weight of our weakness most.</p>

<p>“Immaculate Virgin, I know very well that I am only a miserable wretch, and all I do is increase each day the number of my sins.” You told me the other day that was how you spoke to our Mother. And I was confident in advising you with assurance to pray the Holy Rosary. “Blessed be that monotony of <em>Hail Marys</em> which purifies the monotony of your sins.”</p>

<p>We are reminded by St. Dominic that only God can fill our heart. St. Paul says, “If then you have been raised with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God. Set your mind on the things that are above, not on the things that are on earth” (Col. 3:1–2).</p>

<p>Things of the world last a relatively short period of time, and they can’t fill the longings of the human heart. We’re told in the Book of Wisdom that the life of man on earth is brief. The greater part of it is spent in pain and suffering. Every life passes like the wind, barely a trace is left behind.</p>

<p>In the best of cases, one might amass a fortune, only for it to be left to others. What does all this pain and effort add up to? Is it all for nothing? The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “Vanity of vanities, all is vanity” (Eccles. 1:2). In the face of this emptiness and inconsistency, all this pointlessness, God is the rock of our salvation.</p>

<p>The Psalm says, “Let us come into His presence with thanksgiving, let us make a joyful noise to Him with songs of praise” (Ps. 95:2). Nevertheless, the human heart has a tremendous capacity to seek the things that are of the world, without paying any attention to the transcendent meaning of life. The human heart tends to become attached to worldly goods as the one and only goal in life, forgetting what is really important.</p>

<p>Our Lord takes advantage of a question about inheritances to teach us about the true worth of things in the light of eternity. He brings up the subject of death, of our own death, to make this point. He said, “The land of a rich man brought forth plentifully. And he thought to himself, what shall I do, for I have nowhere to store my crops?” (Luke 12:16–17).</p>

<p>And he said, “This I will do. I will pull down my barns and build larger ones. And I will say to my soul, Soul, you have ample goods laid up for many years. Take your ease. Eat, drink, be merry” (Luke 12:18–19).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that putting our hearts into the pursuit of wealth and worldly well-being is foolishness. Neither happiness, nor authentic human life itself, are founded on worldly goods. “A man’s life does not consist in the abundance of his possessions” (Luke 12:15).</p>

<p>The rich man discloses his value system in his mental dialogue. He sees himself in a very secure position because he has great resources. He bases his stability and his happiness on this wealth. For him, as for many people, living is a matter of enjoying as much pleasure as possible. That is, to do as little as need be, to eat, to drink, to have a good time. To lay up ample goods for many years. That is his ideal.</p>

<p>In his life, there’s no reference to God, much less to other people. He sees no need to share his goods with others less fortunate than himself. And how does he plan to maintain this thoroughly materialistic lifestyle? He says, “I will store up.”</p>

<p>Yet in the end, all of his calculations are for nothing. The things of this world give a fragile and insufficient security, since our lives will never be fulfilled without God. We can ask ourselves today in our prayer on this feast of St. Dominic, where is my heart? Because we know that our destination is heaven.</p>

<p>Because of that, we have to make positive and concrete acts of detachment with regard to what we own and what we use. We can ask ourselves, how much do we share our goods with the needy? How much time and wealth do we contribute to apostolic works? Taking advantage of the noble things of the earth so as to win heaven for ourselves.</p>

<p>It’s very good that we have a certain winning mentality in our life, a sporting spirit. Despite the fact that he has been overlooked, God interrupts the rich man in his ruminations to pass judgment on his chosen way of life. He says, “Fool.” Very strong word. Very strong written word, and even stronger in the words of scripture.</p>

<p>It’s not common that God calls people fools. But He says that to the rich man. “Fool, this night your soul is required of you, and the things you have prepared, whose will they be?” So is he who lays up treasure for himself and is not rich toward God (cf. Luke 12:20–21).</p>

<p>Our passage upon the earth is a time of testing. The Lord Himself has given it to us. St. Paul reminds us that “Here we have no lasting city, but we seek the city which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). On a certain day, Our Lord will come to settle accounts with us, to determine how well or ill we have administered His gifts.</p>

<p>Among His gifts that He has given to us are those of our intelligence, our health, our material goods, our capacity for friendship and leadership, our power to give joy to those around us. Our Lord will come only once. Perhaps when we least expect Him. Like, as He says Himself, a thief in the night. Like lightning flashing across the sky. He wants to find us well-prepared.</p>

<p>Tying ourselves down to the world, forgetting that our end is in heaven, can lead us to live a disoriented life of complete idiocy. “Fool” is precisely what God calls the man who lives only for the world. We certainly have to walk with our feet on the ground, taking care to safeguard our future and the future of those who depend upon us.</p>

<p>But we can’t forget that we are pilgrims. No more than actors in a show. No one is permanently made king or wealthy, since at the end of the performance, we will all find ourselves as paupers before God. All those things that we cannot carry away with us are not ours. They just belong to us, says St. John Chrysostom.</p>

<p>Worldly goods are but the means for us to attain the goal which Our Lord has pointed out to us. These goods can never become the be-all and the end-all of our existence. Our life on earth is short and limited. He says to the man, “This night your soul is required of you.”</p>

<p>We might think of death in terms of something remote, as if we’ll live forever. Yet Our Lord speaks of “this night.” Our days are numbered. We’re in the hands of God. Within a few years, maybe not that many, we’ll find ourselves face to face with Him. Meditating on our final end should motivate us to sanctify our work, redeeming the time as we strive to make up for lost time.</p>

<p>It should help us to take advantage of our circumstances in order to make reparation for sins and to become detached from earthly goods. One day, like any other day, will be our last day on earth. Today, thousands of people have died or will die in the most diverse circumstances. Those people were probably unaware that their time was up. They would have no more time to improve.</p>

<p>Some have died with their hearts immersed in things of little or no importance in terms of eternal life. Others have died who have been involved in exactly the same activities, but have kept their sights on God. It is these latter people who have come into possession of that marvelous treasure which neither dust nor moth consumes.</p>

<p>At the moment of death, the state of the soul is fixed forever. Afterwards, it is impossible to change. The destiny which awaits us is the consequence of our behavior on earth. The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “If a tree falls to the south or to the north, in the place where the tree falls, there it will lie” (Eccles. 11:3). This is the reason for Our Lord’s frequent warnings to be on watch.</p>

<p>We can learn from St. Dominic, from his life, from his quest for truth, from the great gifts and treasures that the religious order that he founded has given to the universal Church and to the world. We can pray for their ever greater fruitfulness and vocations. And ask that each of us might spread that truth in ever more fruitful ways along the course of our apostolate, and that we might take up our Rosary with greater devotion and piety every day.</p>

<p>St. Dominic, pray for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. James (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. James (2026)" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Saint James was from Bethsaida. He was the son of Zebedee and the brother of John. He is one of the three disciples to witness the Transfiguration and the agony in the garden, besides other important events of Our Lord’s public life. He and his brother’s impetuous zeal caused Our Lord to name them the sons of thunder. James developed his apostolate in Judea and Samaria, and according to tradition, he preached the Gospel in Spain. On his return to Palestine about the year 44, he became the first apostle to suffer martyrdom at the order of Herod Agrippa. His mortal remains were later brought to Santiago de Compostela in Spain, which became a popular medieval pilgrimage site and a sanctuary of the faith for all in Europe.</p>

<p>We’re told in Saint Matthew, walking by the Sea of Galilee, Jesus saw James and John, the sons of Zebedee, mending their nets, and called to them, giving the name Boanerges, which means sons of thunder (cf. Mark 3:17). It all began when a few fishermen on Lake Tiberias were called by Jesus of Nazareth to follow him. They responded to Our Lord’s call, followed him, and lived with him for nearly three years. They shared his daily life and were witnesses of his prayer, his mercy toward sinners, and those who suffer, and his power. They listened attentively to his words, the like of which they had never heard before. In the three years they spent together, the disciples experienced a reality that was to possess them forever. In a word, life with Jesus.</p>

<p>It was an experience that broke the threads of their prior existence. They had to leave everything, their family, their trade, and their possessions to follow him. In short, they were introduced to a new way of living. One day, Jesus invited James to follow him. He was the brother of John and the son of Salome, a woman who served Jesus with all she had and ultimately was present on Calvary. James knew Jesus before he was called. Together with Peter and his brother, the apostles enjoyed a special predilection from Our Lord. He was one of the three present at the Transfiguration on Mount Tabor. He was also present at the raising of the daughter of Jairus, and one of those who accompanied Our Lord in Gethsemane towards the beginning of the Passion.</p>

<p>Our Lord was so taken by the impetuous zeal of James and John that he nicknamed them Boanerges, the sons of thunder. We’re told that Jesus had finished speaking about his impending passion and death in the holy city. Saint Matthew says, “We’re going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be given over to the chief priests and the scribes, and they will condemn him to death and deliver him over to the Gentiles to be mocked and scourged and crucified, and he will be raised on the third day” (Matt. 20:18–19).</p>

<p>Our Lord feels the need to share with his disciples the innermost sentiments that fill his soul. Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee drew near to him with her sons, and bowed down at his feet to make a request. She asked him to reserve two eminent places for her sons in his seemingly imminent kingdom. Jesus turns to the brothers and asks them if they can share the same fate with him. He offers them his cup. To offer one another one’s chalice to drink from was considered a great sign of friendship in antiquity. They immediately respond, “We can.”</p>

<p>These words express generous docility. They reflect an attitude that belongs to all the young at heart and to all Christians, says John Paul II, especially those who are willing to be apostles of the good news. Our Lord accepts the generous response of the two disciples straight away, and tells them, yes, you will drink from my cup. You will participate in my sufferings, and you will complete my passion in your own bodies.</p>

<p>Sometime later, in the year 44, James was to die by decapitation. John was tried with innumerable sufferings and persecutions throughout his long life. Ever since Christ redeemed us on the cross, all Christian suffering consists in drinking from the cup of the Lord through participation in his passion, death, and resurrection. By means of our suffering, we complete in a certain way his passion that is thus prolonged in time with its saving fruits. Human suffering becomes redemptive when it’s closely associated with the ignominy that Our Lord endured. In his mercy, he lets us share in his cup.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>The Furrow</em>, in the face of difficulties, sickness, or pain, Jesus puts the same question to us: Can you drink from my cup? If we are united to him, we will respond positively and bear what is humanly disagreeable for his sake. In union with Christ, even our pain and failure are converted into joy and peace. The great Christian revolution has been to convert pain into fruitful suffering, to turn a bad thing into something good. We have deprived the devil of this weapon, and with it we can conquer eternity.</p>

<p>From the time Saint James made his not entirely ambitions known until the hour of his martyrdom, there’s a long interior development. That same zeal of his, earlier directed against the Samaritans who did not want to receive Jesus—the people would not receive him because, we’re told in Saint Luke, “His face was set towards Jerusalem” (Luke 9:53)—was later to be transformed into a zealous concern for souls. Little by little, without losing the vigor of his own personality, James learned that zeal for the divine interests cannot be violent or bitter. The glory of God alone is the only worthwhile ambition.</p>

<p>Clement of Alexandria relates how when the apostle of Spain was taken before the tribunal to be judged, his integrity was so apparent that his accuser approached him afterwards to ask his pardon. James thought about it and then embraced him, and said to him, “Peace be with you.” The two of them together then received the crown of martyrdom.</p>

<p>While meditating on the life of the Apostle James, it helps a great deal for us to see evidence of his defects and those of the other eleven that the Lord had chosen. They weren’t powerful or wise or simple. We see them at times being ambitious and argumentative. James was the first apostle to be martyred. Clearly, the help of God can work wonders in us. How thankful to God James will be in heaven for leading him along paths quite different from the ones he dreamt of earlier in his life.</p>

<p>Since Our Lord is good, infinitely wise, and loving beyond what we can realize, on many occasions he does not give us what we ask for, but what is most appropriate for us, and therefore the best. Like the other apostles, James has clear and undeniable defects and weaknesses that are clearly seen in the Gospel accounts. Nevertheless, together with these shortcomings, he had a great soul and a big heart. Jesus was always patient with him and with the others too. The master allowed them time for them to learn the lessons that he imparted with divine wisdom and affection.</p>

<p>Saint John Chrysostom says, let us examine how Our Lord’s way of questioning is equivalent to an exhortation and a stimulus. He does not say, can you bear defeat? Are you capable of shedding your blood? His words are, can you drink from the cup? To encourage them to the task, he adds, from which I am to drink. The prospect of drinking from the Lord’s very cup leads them to a more generous response. He gives the name baptism to his passion to emphasize that his sufferings would be the cause of a great purification for the whole world, says Saint John Chrysostom.</p>

<p>Our Lord has also called us. May we not give in to discouragement if our defects and weaknesses become manifest. If we approach Jesus for help, he will give us the courage to continue on our path with greater fidelity, since he is ever patient and allows us the time we need to improve.</p>

<p>In the second reading of the Mass, Saint Paul reminds us “We bear this treasure in vessels of clay so that it may be clearly seen that our power comes from God and not from ourselves” (2 Cor. 4:7). We are rather fragile creatures and not very constant. But nevertheless, we are capable of bearing in ourselves an incomparable treasure, since God works marvels in men despite their weaknesses. Just to show that it is he who acts and grants efficacy to our desires, Our Lord wants to “choose the weak to confound the strong, and the vile and scorned of the world as well as those who are not, to destroy the things that are, so that any human flesh should pride itself before the creator,” says Saint Paul (cf. 1 Cor. 1:27–29).</p>

<p>Amazingly enough, one who was formerly a persecutor of the Church of God wrote these words filled with humility. We Christians, by bearing God in our soul, can live at the same time both in heaven and on earth, divinized, but knowing that we are of the world and made of clay. An earthen pot which Our Lord has deigned to use in his service, with the frailty that is typical of such fragile material. When the vessel is cracked or broken, we will seek the seals that are put on pitchers in need of repair so that they may continue to be useful.</p>

<p>Like the prodigal son, we can say, “Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you” (Luke 15:21). God grants efficacy to those who have the humility to feel themselves as vessels of clay, the ones who bear in their own body the mortification of Jesus and who drink from the cup of the passion which Jesus drank.</p>

<p>Tradition recalls the preaching of Saint James throughout Spain. His great zeal for souls led him to the very limits of the known world. We also learn from accounts passed on to us of the difficulties he encountered in the beginnings of his evangelizing, and how Our Lady appeared to him to offer encouragement. It’s possible that we too may feel disheartened on occasion and baffled by the obstacles that obstruct our desires to bring other souls to Christ. We may also encounter misunderstanding, mockery, oppositions of all sorts, calumnies. However, we know that Our Lord will never abandon us. We will approach the Lord and be able to tell him with confidence like Saint Paul, “We are sore pressed but not destitute. We endure persecution but are not forsaken. We are cast down but never perish” (cf. 2 Cor. 4:8–9).</p>

<p>Our Lord says to his apostles, “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already kindled” (Luke 12:49). Just like any true friend, Our Lord reveals to his disciples his most intimate thoughts. He has a holy impatience to ignite the flame of charity in men’s hearts and offer his holocaust to the Father on Calvary for the sake of mankind. “I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am constrained until it is accomplished” (Luke 12:50). There on the cross, the fullness of God’s love for his creatures was made manifest. “Greater love than this no man has, than that he lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13).</p>

<p>We prove we are Christ’s friends if we struggle to follow him. Saint Augustine commented on this passage that people who believe in him are enkindled. They receive the flame of charity. That’s why the Holy Spirit appeared in this form at Pentecost. We’re told in the Acts, “There appeared to them tongues as of fire distributed and resting on each one of them” (Acts 2:3). Set aflame by this fire, the apostles set out across the entire world to inflame others, including their enemies. What enemies? says Saint Augustine. Well, those who had forsaken God their creator for the worship of man-made idols.</p>

<p>The faith of such as these has been smothered to ashes. It is good for them, says Saint Augustine, that they be set alight by this holy flame so that they may once again shine forth in Christ’s glory. This crucial task of setting the world on fire has been passed on to today’s Christians. This fire of love and peace will strengthen and purify souls. We need to go to the university, to the factories, into public life, to our homes. If one were to set fires at different locations throughout a city, even if they were modest fires, they would quickly consume the whole metropolis. Likewise, if in a city at the most separated points, one were to ignite the hearts of the inhabitants with the fire that Jesus brought to the world, then the good will of those people would quickly overrun the city, lighting it up with love for God.</p>

<p>The fire that Jesus has brought to the world is himself. It is the fire of love. This is the love which not only unites souls to God, but also unites souls to one another. In each city, these souls shall emerge from families, father and mother, son and father, mother and mother-in-law. This phenomenon can take place in parish life, in organizations, in schools, in offices, anywhere. One writer says each small flame for God necessarily kindles other flames. Divine providence takes care to distribute these souls on fire where they can best serve the process. Through their action, many places in the world will be restored to the warmth of the love of God and renewed hope.</p>

<p>Our apostolate in the middle of the world should spread like a flame of peace. Apostolate in the middle of the world should spread like wildfire. Each Christian who lives the faith seriously becomes a point of ignition at his or her place of work, among their friends and acquaintances. But this phenomenon will only occur if we make concrete the advice that Saint Paul gave to the Philippians: “Have this in mind among yourselves, which was also in Christ Jesus, who, though he was by nature God, did not consider being equal to God a thing to be clung to, but emptied himself, taking the nature of a slave and being made in the likeness of men. He became humble and obedient, even obedient to a cross” (Phil. 2:5–8).</p>

<p>Opus Dei’s author says the apostle challenges all Christians to live out in their lives as much as possible those sentiments which filled the divine Redeemer when he offered himself up as a sacrifice. Imitate his humility and present to God Almighty all the adoration, honor, praise, and thanksgiving. This offering is carried out primarily in the Mass, the unbloody renewal of the sacrifice of the cross.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council teaches us concerning the contribution of the laity. It says, for all their works, prayers, and apostolic endeavors, their ordinary married and family life, their daily occupations, their physical and mental relaxation, if carried out in the spirit, and even the hardships of life, if patiently borne—all these become spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. Together with the offering of the Lord’s body, they are most fittingly offered in the celebration of the Eucharist. Thus, as those everywhere who adore in holy activity, the laity consecrate the world itself to God (cf. <em>Lumen Gentium</em>, 34).</p>

<p>A Christian life ought to be an imitation of the life of Christ, a participation in his divine sonship. Through this way of life, we will learn from Jesus how to relate to other people. We are told in Saint Matthew that “When Jesus saw the multitude, he had compassion on them, for they were like sheep without a shepherd” (Matt. 9:36). Life held no meaning for them. Jesus had compassion on these people. His love was so great that he went to the extent of giving up his life for them and us on the cross. This is the divine love which should fill our hearts.</p>

<p>Then we too will have compassion on the people around us who perhaps have strayed from the Lord. With the help of God’s grace, our genuine friendship, hopefully, we will bring these souls back to the master. In the holy Mass, a surging current of divine love is transmitted from the Son to the Father through the Holy Spirit. The follower of Our Lord participates in this love, since he or she is incorporated into Christ. The Christian then extends this love to other people and to all earthly realities, which are thereby sanctified and made into a fitting offering to God.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>Friends of God</em>, our apostolate should have its roots in the Mass, and should from there draw its efficacy. For the Mass is nothing less than the realization of the redemption in our time by means of apostolic Christians. Jesus came on earth to redeem everyone, because he wished all men to be saved. There is not a single soul in whom Christ is not interested. Each soul has cost him the price of his blood. If we truly imitate Our Lord’s example, we can never be indifferent towards any soul.</p>

<p>When a Christian participates in the Mass, the prayers should be concerned first of all with their brothers and sisters in the faith. One writer says the Christians should feel more and more closely united to them in the bread of life and in the cup of eternal salvation. This is the time to pray for everyone, and especially for those who are most in need. We should grow in the spirit of charity and fraternity, because the Eucharist makes us all one. As a consequence, we therefore treat one another as family. The Eucharist unites the children of God into one family closely related to Christ and to one another.</p>

<p>Following this unique encounter with the Lord, we will experience the same joy as was felt by the sick in Palestine once they had been cured by Jesus. They were so overjoyed at this manifestation of God’s mercy they went about the towns and villages of Palestine singing the Lord’s praises. When a Christian receives communion at Mass, he should be moved to share this wonderful grace with others as well as the need to communicate it to other people. This was how Christianity grew so quickly in its early years. From people like Saint James, it spread like a conflagration of peace and love which no one could extinguish.</p>

<p>We could resolve to center our life upon the Mass. Then we will find peace and serenity, as well as the need to communicate it to other people. Throughout the course of our day, we will want to let our friends know about the treasure of this sacrament. If we attend Mass, as Saint Josemaría says in <em>Christ is Passing By</em>, if we attend Mass well, surely we are likely to think about Our Lord during the rest of the day, wanting to be always in his presence, ready to work as he worked, and to love as he loved.</p>

<p>We will learn to thank Our Lord for his kindness in not limiting his presence to the time of the sacrifice of the altar. He has decided to stay with us in the host which is reserved in the tabernacle. The tabernacle should be a Bethany for us, a quiet and pleasant place where Christ resides, a place where we can tell him about our worries, our sufferings, our desires, our joys, with the same sort of simplicity and naturalness as Martha, Mary, and Lazarus. We will find in the tabernacle the strength we need to do Our Lord’s work in union with many other Christians.</p>

<p>With Saint James, we could repeat the Lord’s cry, “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already kindled” (Luke 12:49). This is the fire of divine love which will bring peace and joy to souls, to families, and to society as a whole. We can also seek the intercession of Our Lady, Queen of Apostles. In her we will find the courage and the joy to proceed on our way, just like the Apostle Saint James did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Mary Magdalen (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Mary Magdalen (2026)" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Mary was originally from Magdala, a small city of Galilee on the northwest shore of Lake Tiberias. She was one of a group of women who followed Jesus and cared for him out of their own possessions.</p>

<p>Mary was present with Jesus on Calvary, and she was the second one, after Our Lady, to behold the Risen Savior on Easter morning.</p>

<p>She recognized him when Our Lord called her by name.</p>

<p>Devotion to this most constant follower of Christ spread throughout the Western world during the Middle Ages.</p>

<p>Most probably, she is not the same Mary who out of sincere contrition pours out precious ointment on Our Lord’s feet at the home of Simon the Pharisee.</p>

<p>She exemplifies our search for God at every moment.</p>

<p>In the Psalms, we read, “O God, you are my God, for you I long, for you my soul is thirsting. My soul pines for you like the dry parched earth” (Ps. 63:1).</p>

<p>We read these words in the responsorial psalm of today’s Mass.</p>

<p>They remind us of the steadfast love of Mary Magdalene. Steadfast faith.</p>

<p>After nearly twenty centuries, the refinement, fidelity, and love of this stalwart follower of Jesus are deeply moving.</p>

<p>St. John narrates for us in the gospel of the Mass, “Now this woman set out for the tomb as soon as the Sabbath rest permitted, when it was still dark, to go to find the dead body of Our Lord.”</p>

<p>Sometime previously, he had freed her of an evil spirit, and grace quickly bore fruit in her soul.</p>

<p>She followed the Master faithfully on some of his apostolic journeys and served him generously with all her possessions.</p>

<p>During the terrible moments of the crucifixion, she remained on Calvary, near the one who cured her of all that was wrong in her life.</p>

<p>Furthermore, when they laid Jesus in the tomb, she stayed close and kept him company, as we may have done at some point on the occasion of a loved one’s death.</p>

<p>St. Matthew talks about her courage. He says, “Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were seated there in front of the tomb” (Matt. 27:61).</p>

<p>When the Sabbath was over, as the first day of the week began to dawn, she sets out with the other holy women for the place where the dead body of Jesus was lying, in order to anoint it.</p>

<p>But Our Lord was no longer there. He had risen.</p>

<p>She saw the heavy stone rolled away and the tomb empty.</p>

<p>Then she began to run to Simon and the other disciple whom Jesus loved and said to them, “They have taken the Lord out of the tomb and we do not know where they have laid him” (John 20:2).</p>

<p>Peter and John went running towards the empty sepulchre.</p>

<p>St. John tells us that this moment was crucial in his life: “He saw and believed” (John 20:8).</p>

<p>Both apostles went back to their home again, but Mary stayed there, weeping, in the absence of the Master’s body.</p>

<p>With unspeakable sadness, still not believing in the resurrection, she perseveres in her vigil, not wanting to tear herself away from the place where she last saw our Savior.</p>

<p>Today, we consider the intensity of the love burning in the heart of the woman who did not leave the tomb, although the disciples had already gone away.</p>

<p>She continued to seek the one she had failed to find.</p>

<p>She sought for him in tears, and inflamed with the fire of love, was burning with longing to see the one she thought they had taken away.</p>

<p>Because Mary Magdalene remained there with the expectation of finding him, she was the only one to then encounter him.</p>

<p>Perseverance strengthens good deeds.</p>

<p>As the voice of Truth informs us, quoting St. Gregory, “Whoever perseveres to the end will be saved” (Matt. 10:22).</p>

<p>In <em>The Furrow</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Let us not stop seeking Jesus in every circumstance of our lives, even during those moments in which, if Our Lord so permits, discouragement or darkness penetrate our soul.”</p>

<p>Let us never forget that he is always very much in touch with the events of our life, though we may not be aware of him.</p>

<p>He is always close at hand.</p>

<p>“For,” as the Apostle assures us, “the Lord is near” (Phil. 4:5). <em>Dominus prope est.</em></p>

<p>“I shall walk with him, therefore, quite confidently, for the Lord is my father, and with his help I shall fulfill his most lovable will, even if I find it hard.”</p>

<p>When Jesus calls her by her name, she recognizes him, and has great joy before the Risen Christ.</p>

<p>Through her perseverance and great love in seeking him, Mary Magdalene received the grace of being the first person to whom Christ appeared.</p>

<p>At first she didn’t recognize him, despite his being right beside her.</p>

<p>St. John tells us she turned around and saw Jesus standing there, but she did not know that it was Jesus.</p>

<p>Even though he spoke to her, she didn’t immediately realize it was Christ, alive, there at her side.</p>

<p>Jesus said to her, “Woman, why are you weeping? Who is it you are seeking?” (John 20:15).</p>

<p>Her tears prevented her from seeing the Master, whom we can guess was smiling, being happy, very happy over the encounter.</p>

<p>Jesus looks at us too, as we continue to seek him out, in the midst of all the circumstances and events of our lives.</p>

<p>For Christ is the same now as then.</p>

<p>Supposing him to be the gardener, she said to him, “Sir, if you have removed him, tell me where you have laid him, and I will go and take him away” (John 20:15).</p>

<p>An unusual thing to say. Jesus was 6 feet tall, probably weighed 75 kilos, and Mary thinks she’s strong enough to carry Jesus away.</p>

<p>But then Jesus called her by her name, the way he used to. He said to her, “Mary” (John 20:16).</p>

<p>The dark clouds oppressing her heart for those past three days were all of a sudden dispersed.</p>

<p>One writer says, “How many interior sufferings, how many torments of the spirit, caused by great love and apparently without consolation, are frequently dissolved, and how often like the surf of a wave, at one word from Jesus.”</p>

<p>Like a river bursting its banks, as if it had all been a nightmare, Mary looks at him and says, “Rabboni” (John 20:16).</p>

<p>As though the connotation of this familiar term were a moving reality incapable of translation, St. John wanted to leave us the precise Hebrew word that Magdalene offered, that Magdalene often used to address Christ.</p>

<p>She sought him among the dead, comments St. Augustine, and he presented himself alive. How is it he is alive? He calls her by her name, “Mary.”</p>

<p>She responds the same instant that she hears her name spoken, “Rabboni.”</p>

<p>The gardener could have said, “Who is it you seek? Why are you crying?”</p>

<p>Mary, on the other hand, only Christ could have said it in that way. He called her by her name, the same one who called her to the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>He spoke the name “Mary.” He had written in the book of life, and she, “Rabboni,” which means “teacher.”</p>

<p>She already recognized the one who had illuminated her so that she could possibly recognize him.</p>

<p>She already saw Christ in the one whom before she perceived a gardener.</p>

<p>He said to her, “Do not touch me, for I have not yet ascended to my Father” (John 20:17).</p>

<p>Our burdens can disappear when we make an effort to discover Jesus, alive and glorious at our side, calling us by our name.</p>

<p>It’s a great joy for us to be on familiar terms with Christ, and to be able to call on him in the particular way that he knows so well.</p>

<p>Prayer, dialogue with the Lord, is our most profound blessing and the foundation of our entire life.</p>

<p>We will never stop seeking his company, even if at times we don’t perceive his presence.</p>

<p>If we persevere in prayer, he will always come out to meet us, calling us by our name.</p>

<p>Closely united to Jesus, we will recover our peace and joy.</p>

<p>One word from him will restore our hope and renew our desire to begin again.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, we’re told, “Let us never forget, in any situation, that the Lord’s triumph on the day of the Resurrection is final. Where are the soldiers the rulers put on guard? Where are the seals they affixed to the stone of the tomb? Where are those who condemned the Master? And those who crucified Jesus? He is victorious, and these poor wretches have fled away. Be filled with hope: Jesus Christ is always victorious.”</p>

<p>He conquers even in the battles of our own life. He triumphs over those defects and weaknesses of ours, which at times seem insurmountable.</p>

<p>After consoling Mary, Jesus gave her a message for the Apostles, whom he affectionately called “brothers.”</p>

<p>“Then Mary went and said to the disciples, ‘I have seen the Lord,’ and she told them all that had happened” (John 20:18).</p>

<p>Pope Francis likes to use an interesting term for Mary Magdalene at this juncture. He said, “She became the apostle of the apostles.”</p>

<p>She announces to the apostles that Christ is risen.</p>

<p>We can imagine Mary’s joy upon saying those words, “I have seen the Lord.”</p>

<p>We can imagine her joy at bringing that news to the Apostles, inflaming their own apostolic zeal, and hopefully ours also, and everyone who is to come after us.</p>

<p>This is the joy and happiness of all apostolate, worthy of the name, in which we proclaim to others in countless ways the fact that Jesus is alive today.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas comments, “This woman, who was eminently steadfast in finding out about the burial place of Christ, is prefigured every person who yearns to know divine truth, and is therefore well-disposed to pass on the knowledge of such a grace to others.”</p>

<p>Just as Mary announced it to the disciples so that she could not be reprimanded for hiding her talent.</p>

<p>The Angelic Doctor concludes, “God has not granted us this joy in order for you to hide it in the recesses of your hearts, but to share it with those who are capable of love.”</p>

<p>Whoever finds Christ finds him for everyone.</p>

<p>The news of the resurrection spread like wildfire during the first centuries. Christians were conscious of being bearers of the good news.</p>

<p>The disciples rejoiced over the one who died for us, and rose again on the third day, as he said.</p>

<p>They were happy people in the midst of a sad world. Their joy, like ours, stems from always being near the living Christ.</p>

<p>Apostolate is always the communication of this joyful message, the most cheerful message of all.</p>

<p>Today we can ask St. Mary Magdalene to gain for us a share in her loving perseverance in seeking the Lord.</p>

<p>Father, we’re told in the opening prayer of the Mass, “your Son first entrusted to Mary Magdalene the joyful news of the resurrection. By her prayers and example, may we proclaim Christ as our living Lord, and one day see him in glory.”</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Keep me as the apple of your eye, hide me in the shadow of your wings” (Ps. 17:8).</p>

<p>Our refuge and our strength lie in the love of God. We need to go to the tabernacle frequently to seek the presence of Jesus, like Mary Magdalene did.</p>

<p>On his way to the holy city, Jesus stops for a moment to express his disappointment at its rejection of his message. “Jerusalem, Jerusalem. How often I would have gathered your children together, as a hen gathers her brood under her wings, but you did not want” (Matt. 23:37).</p>

<p>Our Lord describes how he protects his own as a hen gathers her brood.</p>

<p>Jesus watches over us from the tabernacle. He is alert to the dangers that threaten us. He is ever ready to cure our wounds.</p>

<p>He continually shares his life with us. This has continually been our prayer on many occasions: “<em>Pie pellicane, Iesu Domine, me immundum munda tuo sanguine.</em>” “O loving Pelican, O Jesus Lord, unclean I am, but cleanse me in your blood.”</p>

<p>Of which a single drop, for sinners spilt, can purge the entire world from all its guilt.</p>

<p>Our Lord is our refuge and our strength. The image of this just one seeking protection from the Lord as a hen gathers her brood, is to be found repeatedly in sacred scripture.</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Keep me as the apple of your eye, hide me in the shadow of your wings, for you are my refuge, a strong tower against the enemy. Let me dwell in your tent forever. Oh, to be safe under the shelter of your wings” (Ps. 17:8; 61:3–4).</p>

<p>The prophet Isaiah employs this image to reassure the chosen people of God’s protection against the Egyptians.</p>

<p>“Like birds hovering, so the Lord of hosts will protect Jerusalem” (Isa. 31:5).</p>

<p>At the close of our earthly life, Jesus will be our judge and friend.</p>

<p>While we live on earth, his mission is to save us, to give us all the help we need.</p>

<p>From the tabernacle, Jesus protects us in a thousand ways. How can we imagine that he is indifferent towards our problems and worries?</p>

<p>Jesus has wanted to remain present throughout the world so that we might seek him more readily for friendship and assistance, and rely on him, like St. Mary Magdalene did.</p>

<p>Getting up early in the morning, while it was still dark, because she had a hole in her heart.</p>

<p>St. John Vianney says, “If we are suffering pain and discomfort, he will lighten our burden and comfort us. If we succumb to illness, either he will provide a remedy, or he will give us the strength to suffer it for the sake of eternal life. If we find ourselves at war with the devil and our passions, he will supply us with arms for the battle, so that we can resist and ultimately be victorious. If we are poor, he will enrich us with all kinds of good things in this life and in eternity.”</p>

<p>Like Mary Magdalene, we could resolve to seek his company every single day without fail.</p>

<p>St. Alphonsus says, “Those few minutes we spend in our visit will be among the most productive moments of the day.”</p>

<p>What are we to do in the presence of the Blessed Sacrament? Love him, praise him, thank him, ask of him.</p>

<p>What does a poor man do in the presence of a wealthy man? What does a sick person do in the presence of a doctor? What does a thirsty person do at the sight of a fountain of sparkling water?</p>

<p>Our confidence that we will be victorious in trial and tribulation is not founded on our own limited resources, but on the protection of Our Lord.</p>

<p>He has loved us from all eternity, to the point of sacrificing his son for our salvation.</p>

<p>Jesus remains present among us in the tabernacle. As a consequence, he may be very close to the place where we live and work. He’s ready to help us, to heal us, to give us energy for our earthly sojourn.</p>

<p>All we have to do is draw close to him. He is waiting for us.</p>

<p>Nothing should separate us from God.</p>

<p>Because, as St. Paul teaches us in scripture, “If God is for us, who is against us? He who did not spare his own Son, but gave him up for us all, will he not also give us all things with him? Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? Shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?” (Rom. 8:31–35).</p>

<p>“Nothing can separate us from God if we are determined to abide with him.”</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Clothed in grace we can cross mountains and climb the hill of our Christian duty without panting on the way.”</p>

<p>If friends of God, St. Josemaría says, “If we use these resources with a firm purpose, and beg Our Lord to grant us an everlasting hope, we will possess the infectious joy of those who know they are children of God.”</p>

<p>If God is for us, who can be against us?</p>

<p>Even though Our Lord permits us to experience strong temptations, family difficulties, sickness or reverses of any kind.</p>

<p>No trial, no matter how fierce, can separate us from Jesus.</p>

<p>By making a devout visit to the tabernacle nearest to us, we will reach out to the most powerful hand of God. We will then be able to say, “<em>Omnia possum in eo qui me confortat,</em>” “I can do all things in him who strengthens me” (Phil. 4:13).</p>

<p>“For I am sure that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, nor height, nor depth, nor anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God in Christ Jesus our Lord” (Rom. 8:38–39).</p>

<p>This is the psalm of trust and optimism, which we should make our own.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom reminds us that Paul himself had to fight against numerous adversaries. He was attacked by barbarians, his guards laid traps for him.</p>

<p>There were times, says St. John Chrysostom, when he was opposed by his own faithful in great numbers. Yet Paul was triumphant.</p>

<p>Let us not forget that the Christian who is faithful to the laws of God will win out over those who oppose him, and even over Satan himself.</p>

<p>If we stay close to Jesus in the Eucharist, we will be victorious in every engagement, though sometimes we may appear to have been overcome.</p>

<p>The tabernacle will be our strength.</p>

<p>That’s why Jesus wanted to remain with us, in a tangible way, so that we could seek his help.</p>

<p>“Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy burdened, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you, for my yoke is easy and my burden is light” (Matt. 11:28–30).</p>

<p>Jesus invites us and beckons to us every day. Our Lord, may we go to you, like Mary Magdalene did, with insistence, with perseverance, with courage, with a spirit to overcome all obstacles.</p>

<p>In that way our serenity will be rooted in Our Lord. We don’t close our eyes to reality, we look at the present and to the future with optimism, because Our Lord is by our side.</p>

<p>Life’s difficulties can, in the end, yield for us a great good. We’re never alone, in even the most overwhelming circumstances.</p>

<p>Just as we appreciate the company of a friend when things are going badly, so should we be grateful for the company of our Friend in the nearest tabernacle. We should go to him for consolation, peace, and strength.</p>

<p>What more can we want, wrote St. Teresa, than so good a friend at our side? Who will not forsake us when we are in trouble and distress, as they do who belong to the world.</p>

<p>St. Thomas More realized that his doom was sealed when he was called to testify before the Lambeth Tribunal.</p>

<p>He bade farewell at home to the people of his household, because he didn’t want them to follow him to the wharf, as was their custom. Only his son-in-law William Roper, and his favorite daughter Margaret, accompanied him on this final, short journey, together with a few servants.</p>

<p>Everyone aboard the upstream ferry was silent. After a while, More whispered into the ear of Roper, “Son Roper, I thank Our Lord the field is won.”</p>

<p>Roper later wrote that he did not comprehend the meaning of these words.</p>

<p>With the passing of time, however, he came to understand that More’s faith had given him the confidence of victory over any obstacle.</p>

<p>He knew without a shadow of a doubt that Our Lord would be with him in his ultimate battle.</p>

<p>If we seek to be close to Jesus, to be eucharistic souls, Our Lord will watch over us as a hen gathers her brood.</p>

<p>We too can be strengthened in the knowledge that the field is won.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>The Forge</em>, “Be a eucharistic soul. If the center around which your thoughts and hopes turn is the tabernacle, then my child, how abundant the fruits of your sanctity and apostolate will be.”</p>

<p>We ask Mary Magdalene to give us those desires that she had in her heart, as she set out so early to seek Jesus, not worrying about what people would think or what people would say, overcoming all the difficulties.</p>

<p>The Mother of God contemplates her Son in heaven. She’ll put the right words and desires, right words on our lips and the right desires in our hearts. If we don’t know what to say or to do, she’ll provide a prompt response to make up for all our tongue-tied clumsiness.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice.</em></p>

<p><em>My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Lost Sheep</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-lost-sheep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lost Sheep" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-lost-sheep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-lost-sheep/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Suppose a man has a hundred sheep and one of them strays; will he not leave the ninety-nine on the hillside and go in search of the stray? In truth I tell you, if he finds it, it gives him more joy than do the ninety-nine that did not stray at all. Similarly, it is never the will of your Father in heaven that one of these little ones should be lost” (Matt. 18:12-14).</p>

<p>God loves us always, even when we stray. In this parable we read about the Divine Mercy which moves the heart. A man with a hundred sheep—a large flock—loses one, probably because the sheep strayed, lagging behind the others as they looked for new pastures.</p>

<p>Our Lord asks, “Will not the shepherd leave the other ninety-nine in the fields and go to look for the lost sheep?” One might think that He could say to Himself, ‘Well, I still have ninety-nine and those ninety-nine are more important than just the one.’</p>

<p>But we’re told that he goes after the one. And St. Luke says, “When he finds it, he places it on his shoulders with joy” to return it to the flock (Luke 15:5).</p>

<p>Of all the images that the Church has promoted down through the centuries, perhaps the one that it most promotes is that of Christ carrying that sheep, that lost lamb or lost flock.</p>

<p>We could think of all the times when Our Lord has sought us out, in spite of our lack of generosity and correspondence. Even though we may not deserve His care, we stray through our own fault, He seeks us out again and again.</p>

<p>None of the sheep receives so much attention as the one that had strayed. The care that Divine Mercy pours out on sinners—on each one of us—is overwhelming.</p>

<p>How can we refuse the shoulders of the Good Shepherd if at times we lose the way? How can we not love frequent Confession, where we find Christ?</p>

<p>We have to take it for granted that we are weak and that we will stumble. It is this very weakness, when we acknowledge it, that will attract Divine Mercy, which comes to us with greater help and greater love.</p>

<p>St. Bernard says, “Jesus, our Good Shepherd, hurries to find the hundredth sheep that had lost the way. … A marvelous condescendence of God for him to seek man out. What great dignity man must have,” he says, “to be sought out by God in this way!” (Bernard, <em>Sermon for the First Week in Advent</em>).</p>

<p>We can always count on the love of Christ. Even during the worst moments of our life, He doesn’t stop loving us. We can always count on His help to return to the right path if we have lost it, to begin and begin again.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom says He keeps us fighting and “a leader on the battlefield values more the soldier who, having fallen back in flight at first, returns to the fray and attacks the enemy with valor; he values him more than he does the soldier who never ran but never showed outstanding courage” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homilies on the First Epistle to the Corinthians</em>).</p>

<p>He who never sins is not sanctified, but he is who always repents, trusting in the love God has for him, getting up and getting on with the fight.</p>

<p>To have defects is not in itself bad. The only evil lies in making a truce with them, not struggling against them, thinking that they’re part and parcel of our character or our nature.</p>

<p>Making a truce would lead to spiritual mediocrity. Our Lord doesn’t want this to happen to those who follow Him.</p>

<p>God loves each one of us in a very personal way. Jesus loves each one as he is, with his defects. His love does not lead Him to idealize man. He sees them with their paradoxes and weaknesses, with their great potential for good, and with their misery that is so often evident.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to say, “Christ knows what is in man. Only he knows!” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, October 22, 1978). He loves us the way we are.</p>

<p>Christ has a great understanding of the human heart and a great positive conception of our abilities. “His eye knows how to look beyond the veil of human passions and penetrate the inmost self of man, where man is most alone and poor” (Karl Adam, <em>Jesus Christ</em>).</p>

<p>He understands us always, and always encourages us to continue struggling. St. Josemaría liked to say, “Struggle right to the very end, until the last moment” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 429).</p>

<p>If only we could realize the personal love Christ has for each person, His care, His solicitude! God loves us. This is the great reality of our lives.</p>

<p>We’re carried in the palm of a hand of a God who loves us. He is the one who is capable of raising our spirits always, who makes us happy in spite of our sorrows and contradictions. In spite of perhaps our broken hearts or our frayed nerves, He lifts us up.</p>

<p>He loves us in spite of the deep-rooted wretchedness that is there in the human heart, in spite of all the ugly things that He said reside there.</p>

<p>“His love, in spite of everything, is incomparable. It’s unique; so maternally tender and generous that it will be inscribed forever in the memory of humanity. … His love for humanity is very different from the abstract benevolence preached by thinkers and philosophers. It’s not simply doctrine, but life” (Karl Adam, <em>Jesus Christ</em>).</p>

<p>“Where else shall we go? You have the words of eternal life” (John 6:68).</p>

<p>“His love for humanity is to suffer and to die with man. The Lord doesn’t settle for merely examining human misery and prescribing a remedy to ease it. He makes actual contact with that misery. He cannot bear to know of it without taking it upon himself,” we’re told (K. Adam, <em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>“The love of Jesus surpasses the bounds of his own heart in order to attract others to himself, or better, in order to go out of himself, identifying himself with others so as to live and suffer with them” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>He calls men brother and friend, sympathetically binds His fortune to theirs, and He looks upon anything done for another as being done for Him. “Whenever you did it to one of these, the least of my brethren, you did it for me” (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Constant are the Evangelists’ statements that He felt compassion for the people. “He had compassion on them, because they were like sheep without a shepherd” (Mark 6:34).</p>

<p>He’s moved by misfortune and pain. He cannot reject a suffering soul, not even the Syrophoenician woman who was a pagan (Mark 7:26).</p>

<p>He’s quick to attend to those who came to Him, even when doing so led others to claim that He was breaking the Sabbath (John 9:16, 5:18).</p>

<p>He mingles with publicans and sinners (Matt. 9:11; Luke 15:1-2), even though those who feel that they themselves fulfill the Law well are scandalized.</p>

<p>Not even when in agony does He fail to tell the good thief, “Today you will be with me in Paradise” (Luke 23:43).</p>

<p>His love doesn’t tolerate class distinctions. He welcomes the rich like Nicodemus, Zacchaeus, and Joseph of Arimathea, and poor folk like Bartimaeus, a beggar, who, once cured, followed Him along the way (Mark 10:46-52).</p>

<p>He attends more promptly to those with troubled bodies, and above all, those with troubled souls.</p>

<p>His concern for those most in need is not exclusive. It’s not limited to those without fortune or friends. There are evils that are common to all social classes—loneliness, lack of affection, rejection.</p>

<p>Our own life is the story of Christ’s love for us. He has looked at us with a love of predilection and has time and again sought us out when we had lost our way.</p>

<p>We ought to ask ourselves today how we are corresponding to Our Lord’s constant concern for us. What efforts do we make to receive the sacraments frequently and devoutly? Do we strive to recognize Christ in spiritual direction, when perhaps we’re corrected on some issue or put right?</p>

<p>Do we look with gratitude upon those to whom the Church has entrusted, as our pastors, the care of our souls? Do we know how to exclaim in those situations, “<em>Dominus est</em>—It is the Lord!” (John 21:7).</p>

<p>He has often looked upon us with predilection. St. Paul says, “Jesus loved me and gave himself up for me” (Gal. 2:20). This is the great truth that consoles us. He showed His love by giving His life.</p>

<p>He loves each of us as if each one was the sole object of His affections. Even if we are the only person in the whole world, Christ would still have died for us. He would have shed all of His blood for us. We should meditate often on this truth: that God loves us.</p>

<p>There was a little boy once who was asked to give some of his blood for his baby sister who needed a blood transfusion.</p>

<p>After thinking about it for a while, he agreed, although he hated needles. When the nurse linked him up to the tube that was to take his blood and the blood began to flow—they saw the blood there—he said to the nurse, “Will I begin to die soon?”</p>

<p>The nurse had to reassure him that she wasn’t going to take all of his blood; she was just going to take a little bit of his blood.</p>

<p>Christ didn’t give just a little bit of His Blood; He gave all of His Blood. This surpasses the most improbable expectations of the human heart.</p>

<p>No one—without divine Revelation—would dare to guess at or acknowledge the sublime vocation to which each and every person is called: to be God’s son or daughter, called to live a close relationship as a friend, to participate in the very Life of the three divine Persons.</p>

<p>“No longer do I call you servants…, but I have called you friends” (John 15:15).</p>

<p>Considered with earthbound eyes, it seems a dream, or scarcely credible, but it is the truth, the great truth that has to move us to correspond.</p>

<p>Christ never stops loving us, helping us, protecting us, talking to us, not even in our moments of sheer ingratitude, or after we have committed the greatest disloyalty.</p>

<p>Possibly it was during such sad circumstances that Our Lord has been most attentive to us, as this parable of the lost sheep suggests. Among the hundred sheep in the flock, only the one that was lost had the honor of resting on the shoulders of the good shepherd.</p>

<p>“I will be with you always” (Matt. 28:20). In each situation, at every moment, Our Lord tells us these words.</p>

<p>What a great consolation to spread to so many people whose hearts may be breaking from loss, from disappointment, from failure, from rejection, from loneliness.</p>

<p>And particularly, when we begin that final journey towards Him, we know that the Good Shepherd will be seeking us out.</p>

<p>Certain that Our Lord is close to us, we should be moved to begin and begin again in the interior struggle, without being disheartened by the negative experience of our defects and sins.</p>

<p>A man came to me once in another country. He had left his family, he landed in disgrace, he ended up living under a bridge.</p>

<p>But one time in his life he’d been a member of the Legion of Mary. Another member of the Legion of Mary, in her older years, began to seek out people under the bridge and bring them food and clothing, and happened to know him from thirty, forty years previously, and recognized him, and brought him to a center city confessional box where I used to hear Confessions.</p>

<p>He told me, “You know, Father, I think after all these years, Our Lady hasn’t forgotten me. She’s brought me back. And now I have cancer, I haven’t long to live, but Our Lady has brought me here to make my peace with God. I’m so very happy to be here.” It’s a very beautiful story.</p>

<p>The Good Shepherd seeks out the lost sheep; He looks after them in all sorts of ways. Every moment that we live is unique, and therefore provides us with a good opportunity to begin again and help people around us, this Lent, to begin again.</p>

<p>We can confide an awful lot in the special graces that Lent provides.</p>

<p>There are possibly people that we knew in primary school or secondary school, people that we bump into, or retired colleagues, or other people who may be far from God, and somehow, maybe, we reconnect with them. God wants to use us as instruments to bring them closer.</p>

<p>The Book of Deuteronomy says, “The Lord will go before you. He will be with you. He will not leave you or abandon you. Do not fear or be cowardly” (Deut. 31:8).</p>

<p>For many centuries, the Church placed on the lips of priests and the faithful, at the beginning of the Mass, the words of the Psalm: “I will go to the altar of God, of God who gives joy to my youth” (Ps. 43:4).</p>

<p>These words were repeated when the priests and the people were young, and when they had long since passed the years of their maturity.</p>

<p>They are the cry of the soul going straight to Christ, a soul who knows he is loved and desires love.</p>

<p>“God loves me. And John the Apostle writes: ‘Let us love God, then, since God loves us first’ (1 John 4:19). —As if this were not enough, Jesus comes to each one of us, in spite of our patent wretchedness, to ask us, as he asked Simon Peter: ‘Simon, son of John, do you love me more than these?’ (John 21:15).</p>

<p>—This is the time to reply: ‘Lord, you know all things, you know that I love you!’ (John 21:17) adding, with humility,” said St. Josemaría, “‘Help me to love you more. Increase my love!’” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 497).</p>

<p>These are aspirations that can serve us well these days. They will bring us closer to Christ. He awaits our correspondence with Him. God has great joy at the sight of our daily conversions.</p>

<p>Jesus was always with His people, even after day was done. There were many times when they wouldn’t let Him rest (<em>cf</em>. Mark 3:20). His life was totally given over to His brothers and sisters. He loved them with the greatest love that the world has ever seen (<em>cf</em>. John 13:1).</p>

<p>He was raised for our justification (<em>cf</em>. Rom 4:25) and ascended into heaven to prepare a place for us (<em>cf</em>. John 14:2). He sent the Holy Spirit to forestall our becoming orphans (<em>cf</em>. John 14:18).</p>

<p>The more we have needed Him, the more He has been among us. This Divine Mercy exceeds anything the human mind can imagine. This superabundant mercy “is proper to God and is the greatest manifestation of his omnipotence” (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, II-II, Question 30).</p>

<p>“Rejoice with me,” He would say, “I have found my sheep that was lost” (Luke 15:6).</p>

<p>St. Gregory the Great comments, “Supreme mercy will not abandon us, even when we abandon him” (Gregory the Great, <em>Homily on the Gospels</em>). The Good Shepherd never gives up on a single one of His sheep.</p>

<p>The Lord also wants to express heaven’s joy at the conversion of a single sinner: “In the same way, I tell you, there is rejoicing among the angels of God over one repentant sinner” (Luke 15:10).</p>

<p>God is delighted when we begin again after small defeats, when we struggle to correct defects in our character, when we fight to overcome any sense of discouragement.</p>

<p>He values the way we pursue our studies, the effort we put into doing our work well, our striving to begin and end on time, our avoiding making unnecessary phone calls.</p>

<p>God sees our generosity in those small habitual mortifications which perhaps no one else notices. That daily struggle keeps us close to the Lord.</p>

<p>When we begin again, each day and every day, our heart can be filled with joy—and so is the Master’s heart. Every time that we allow Jesus to enter into our life, we please God immeasurably.</p>

<p>The Sacred Heart of Jesus “overflows with joy whenever a lost soul has been recovered.” We’re told that “everyone has to join in the celebration—all the angels and the saints in heaven, as well as the just on earth, for this wonderful development” (Georges Chevrot<em>, The Gospel in the Open Air</em>).</p>

<p>“Rejoice with me,” Our Lord invites us (Luke 15:6). There’s also a special joy whenever we bring a friend or relative back to the sacrament of pardon. Our Lord awaits His brothers and sisters with open arms.</p>

<p>The Church sings in an ancient hymn: “Lord, you have worn yourself out looking for me: O that your labors will not have been in vain” (Hymn, <em>Dies irae</em>).</p>

<p>Jesus comes out to look for us, comes in search of us. He took upon Himself all the evil of the world and yet He seeks us out. He knows better than anyone the foul nature of sin; nevertheless, He’s not angry.</p>

<p>“The Just One presents to us the moving image of Divine Mercy. … To the Samaritan woman, she who had six husbands, He says simply, ‘Give me to drink’ (John 4:7). Christ knows what the soul can become—it can be a reflection of God Himself.</p>

<p>“What possibilities there are! God wants only good things for the soul” (Federico Sopeña, <em>Confession</em>).</p>

<p>Jesus draws near to the sinner with real respect. His words are always an expression of love for the individual.</p>

<p>We could think of the words Our Lord spoke to the woman caught in adultery: “Go, and do not sin again” (John 8:11). They are words of pardon, of joy, of consolation.</p>

<p>Our Lord waits for each one of us in each Confession. The Good Shepherd has such a burning desire to reclaim the lost sheep that He goes out to find it Himself.</p>

<p>As soon as He finds the lost sheep, He showers it with affection. He carries it home on His shoulders.</p>

<p>Having returned to the safety of the flock, “the lost sheep brings a great peace to the fold, even to the watchdog” (F. Sopeña, <em>Confession</em>).</p>

<p>The divine attentions lavished upon the repentant sinner are truly overwhelming. God’s pardon does not consist only in forgiving and in blotting out and the forgetting of our sins. That’s certainly a great deal in itself.</p>

<p>But along with the remission of our sins, God infuses new life into the soul. He strengthens it, fortifies it.</p>

<p>That which was dead is converted into being itself a source of life. Barren ground is made to bear abundant fruit.</p>

<p>The Lord teaches us about the immense value of a single soul. He is ready to do anything for the sake of one conversion. He’s happy at the sight of a renewed friendship!</p>

<p>We have to try and share the Lord’s concern that no one stray from the flock. If anyone has wandered away from the Lord’s fold, we have to pray that he or she will return as soon as possible.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady, Refuge of Sinners, to take care of all the lost sheep.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Parable of the Rich Man and Lazarus</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-rich-man-and-lazarus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Parable of the Rich Man and Lazarus" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-rich-man-and-lazarus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-rich-man-and-lazarus/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“There was a rich man who used to dress in purple and fine linen and feast magnificently every day. And at his gate there used to lie a poor man called Lazarus, covered with sores, who longed to fill himself with what fell from the rich man’s table. Even the dogs came and licked his sores” (Luke 16:19-21).</p>

<p>The parable warns us about an excessive concern for comfort and the things of this world, which will inevitably lead us to a neglect of God and neighbor.</p>

<p>The description of the rich man is quite superlative. He is dressed “in purple and fine linen” and his whole life could be summed up in that he feasted “magnificently every day.”</p>

<p>But then there’s a great contrast, because you have this poor man called Lazarus, who lay at his gate “covered with sores,” who was hungry, who even longed for the crumbs, but nobody gave them to him. Then we’re told, “the dogs came and licked his sores.” It’s the epitome of destitution.</p>

<p>The Gospel, in painting this picture, talks about a man who precisely fell into that trap of excessive concern for comfort. Instead of winning heaven through the use of his wealth, he lost it forever.</p>

<p>Our Lord contrasts these two extreme conditions: the vast wealth in one case and tremendous need in the other.</p>

<p>Our Lord doesn’t condemn the rich man because he is rich. It’s not a sin to be rich. Somebody who has the talent to be able to make a million dollars should try and make a million dollars, and then try and do as much good with that money as he can.</p>

<p>Christ never condemned riches. What He did condemn was the bad use of riches. Often Our Lord used the wealth of rich people. He used the tomb of Joseph of Arimathea. He got help from Nicodemus. But He never condemned riches in themselves. What He did want was that everybody would have a social conscience, social concern, for people around them.</p>

<p>The entire emphasis of the parable is on how the riches have been used. We only have expensive clothes and sumptuous daily banquets mentioned, whereas Lazarus was not even given the leftovers.</p>

<p>The rich man did nothing wrong as he amassed his fortune. The poverty of Lazarus was not his fault, at least not in a direct way. Also, he didn’t take advantage of his position to exploit Lazarus.</p>

<p>But he had this definite lifestyle. It can be summed up in those words, “he feasted magnificently.” You could say that he lived for himself as if God did not exist. He had completely forgotten the fact that we are not owners of what we have, but just administrators.</p>

<p>The rich man had a good time [to] himself. He wasn’t against God, nor did he oppress his impoverished neighbor. He was just blind to the existence of the needy person on his doorstep.</p>

<p>In some ways it was a very simple mistake. Our Lord is warning us that we can all make that mistake.</p>

<p>He lived for himself. He spared himself no expense. But his great sin was that he did not see Lazarus. He could have cared for Lazarus if he had not been so selfish. He didn’t use his wealth in any way that was in conformity with God’s desires. He didn’t know how to share.</p>

<p>How important it is for Christian parents to take advantage of situations that present themselves to teach their children not to be blind, to see needy people around them, to be generous and to share what they have, and to find that greatest joy in their life from that sharing.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Lazarus was received into heaven because of his humility and not because of his poverty. Wealth itself was not what kept the rich man from eternal bliss. His punishment was for selfishness and disloyalty” (Augustine, <em>Sermon 24</em>).</p>

<p>We’re told, “The poor man died and was carried away by the angels into the embrace of Abraham” (Luke 16:22). In this world, Lazarus had the dogs, but now he has the angels.</p>

<p>We’re also told, “The rich man also died and was buried. In his torment in hell, he looked up and saw Abraham a long way off with Lazarus in his embrace” (Luke 16:22-23).</p>

<p>The conditions of the two men are completely different. Their roles are reversed.</p>

<p>“He cried out, ‘Father Abraham, pity me and send Lazarus to dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue…’” He didn’t say, ‘Send Lazarus with the fire truck or with the hose,’ but just get him to “‘dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue...’” Any alleviation would be marvelous.</p>

<p>"’…for I am in agony in these flames.’ Abraham said, ‘My son, remember that during your life you had your fill of good things, just as Lazarus had his fill of bad. Now he is being comforted here while you are in agony’” (Luke 16:24-26).</p>

<p>Probably the rich man regrets now very much that he didn’t have better eyesight to see Lazarus. Our selfishness can be manifested in an insatiable desire to possess more and more material things. It can make people blind to the needs of their neighbors. Selfish people can come to treat others as if they were objects without value.</p>

<p>We can be reminded in this parable that we all have needy people living around us—people like Lazarus. We can’t forget to administer what we have with generosity. In addition to sharing material things, we also should be sowers of understanding, of sympathy, of friendship.</p>

<p>There’s a very nice movie called “A Christmas Carol” of 1984, based on the famous novel of Charles Dickens, which is well worth watching sometime. You’re probably familiar with the character there called Scrooge. He’s hunched over stacks of coins. He’s greedily tallying his bursting accounts as he and his employers shiver in the cold, but he is too cheap to spend money on coal to keep the office warm.</p>

<p>All Christians have to have a special sensitivity for their employees, people working under their nose. Do they have a just salary? Do they have what they need? Could they be more comfortable? Think about their family, their children.</p>

<p>Scrooge is the richest man in the city, and he keeps his wealth so securely locked away that no one, not even himself, benefits from it. No one was more successful than he was in a worldly sense. His business was prosperous. He was powerful to the point of being feared. He had the biggest mansion in town.</p>

<p>And yet what did his success do for him? It turned him into a monster. He was blind to the needs of those around him. He was blind to his own capacity for true human greatness.</p>

<p>Like the rich man in the parable, only when he saw his life from God’s perspective did things change. He saw how many opportunities for doing good that he had squandered. He saw how many people he had used or ignored, instead of loved and helped.</p>

<p>Only then was he able to begin living that life worthily. Only then did he begin to experience the joy and meaning that he’d been yearning for all along.</p>

<p>Probably not all of us are as successful in the worldly sense as the rich man in the parable. But we’re all constantly tempted to think that that kind of success is what life is really about and that can be just as dangerous. Even if we can’t have it, we want it for our children.</p>

<p>We can act as self-centered as Scrooge, even without having a comparable bank account. If in our minds we’re seeking worldly success, instead of success as God understands it, and that’s what the media culture all around us are constantly inviting us to do, we can fall into the temptation of being disciples of Scrooge instead of being disciples of Christ.</p>

<p>How well we use the goods of this life may determine whether we win or lose our entrance into heaven.</p>

<p>Our life on earth is a testing ground for our generosity. We’re told in the Acts of the Apostles, “It’s better to give than to receive” (Acts 20:35). No greater lesson can we teach our children, no greater legacy can we give them, than an example of having lived by these words. Paradoxically, we get more from giving than from receiving. What we get is heaven.</p>

<p>I used to visit an elderly 97-year-old priest here in Nairobi in the last couple of years. He was the first missionary to a place called Pokot in rural Kenya, a very isolated place.</p>

<p>He used to say that when he went there in 1952, there was no education, no medication and no revelation. He spent the next 49 years of his life building thirty-two primary schools, two secondary schools, about four hospitals, about twenty-five parishes. And he lived a long and healthy life, a very holy man, and he died a couple of weeks ago [Fr. Leo Staples, 1925-2022].</p>

<p>He went back to Ireland to celebrate the 70th anniversary of his priesthood, intending to come back here to Nairobi because he wanted to be buried here in Kenya. That was his final wish and dream. But although God may have granted him many other things, He didn’t grant him that.</p>

<p>Before he died, he had a bit of a get-together with some missionary nuns there in Ireland. He was telling them a story that before he left in May, some people from Pokot, where he had been living for 49 years, came to see him because they said they wanted to celebrate the 70th anniversary of his priestly ordination with him.</p>

<p>With them, they brought a jar of honey. This was very symbolic because among the many different projects that he started, he helped the women there to start making honey as a sort of a homemaking project, which helped them to make some money. Today there are two honey factories in that place that grew out of his initiative.</p>

<p>They brought him a jar of honey, and they said, “Father, this is the finest, sweetest, most purified honey in the whole country. And we came to bring a jar of it to tell you that what you gave us is sweeter than this honey: the Word of God that has built us up, that has helped our society to develop.”</p>

<p>Now they have educated people there. They have vocations to the priesthood. They have all sorts of things. When you look at the litany of things that that man did in the course of his life, it’s quite an impressive litany.</p>

<p>He told me his early history. His father had a good education; he became a vet. But then his mother died when he was four years of age, leaving five children. She died of tuberculosis. The father had to go and visit many farms.</p>

<p>The children were farmed out to different relatives to bring up. Three of them became priests and one became a missionary nun in Papua New Guinea. Quite an amazing story. This fellow, with that childhood marked by the cross, produced all of these fruits.</p>

<p>All of us have to try and share with others what we ourselves have been given. St. Paul says, “Be not conformed to this world, but be renewed in the spirit of your mind” (Rom. 12:2). That was Paul’s message to the first Christians in Rome.</p>

<p>When we lead selfish lives, we find it very difficult to see the needs of others. We also may find it very difficult to see God.</p>

<p>St. John Paul said, “The rich man was condemned because he did not pay attention to the other man. Because he failed to take notice of Lazarus, the person who sat at his door and longed to eat the scraps from his table” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, October 2, 1979).</p>

<p>We should be willing to give away a great deal. In these weeks and months coming up to Christmas, it’s a good time to plan these coming months. See if in my family I can put a value-added message during these coming months about generosity, about detachment, which ultimately are the messages of Bethlehem. How can I bring my family in contact with poor people more frequently, to open the eyes of my children?</p>

<p>Christians must not sit idly by as the tide of materialism sweeps over our entire culture. Nor should we become entrapped by a purely economic vision of the world.</p>

<p>There’s a document of the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith that says, “Solidarity is a direct requirement of human and supernatural brotherhood” (Joseph Ratzinger, CDF Instruction on Christian Freedom and Liberation, <em>Libertatis conscientia</em>, Point 89, March 22, 1986).</p>

<p>We have to see people around us and the dignity of every person, and the rights of every person to material things. That attitude will lead us to live that personal poverty which Our Lord called <em>blessed</em>.</p>

<p>We don’t waste food, or we don’t tolerate people around us wasting food, or throwing rubbish in public places—banana skins or plastic bottles. We care for other people, we care for the world, we care for the environment because God gave it to us.</p>

<p>This is quite different from the poverty that oppresses most of the people we know in the world. “Before this type of poverty and privation,” said St. Pope John Paul, “the Church lifts up her voice to promote the solidarity which is so urgently required” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, May 7, 1990).</p>

<p>We have to help everyone in the world to see people around them as their brothers. How can I help the people in Ukraine? And also, how can I help the people on my doorstep? They’re brothers in need of the great treasure of the faith which we possess.</p>

<p>Sometimes people around us don’t just need material things. They need our joy, our friendship. Sometimes they also need our economic assistance.</p>

<p>Mother Teresa says, “The greatest poverty is loneliness” (Mother Teresa, <em>A Simple Path</em>). We can’t remain indifferent to conditions in parts of the world where so many people are suffering for want of food.</p>

<p>The president of this country [Kenya] recently said there are 14 million hungry people in this country. People lack food, people lack education.</p>

<p>They also may be ignorant of the truths about man and about God. We can examine our conscience and see: Is my detachment a real detachment? Does it lead to any practical consequences? Our lives should be a model of temperance as far as our use of material goods is concerned.</p>

<p>It’s very good that we deny ourselves the pleasures of some fruit of the tree of good and of evil. We all need to have something that we deny ourselves: I can do without. Do we have our heart focused on the treasures that last forever, which neither thief can take nor moth can destroy? (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:33).</p>

<p>That’s why we have to encourage people or remind people around us with a certain periodicity about the need to think about eternal life. If we are faithful, we will have Christ for all eternity. Something very wonderful. Something worth dreaming about and thinking about.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “How lovely I suddenly found it, to be free from the glamor of those vanities, so that now it was a joy to renounce what I had been so much afraid to lose. But you cast them out of me, O true and supreme Loveliness, you cast them out of me and took their place instead, you who are sweeter than all pleasure, yet no mere flesh and blood; brighter than all light, yet deeper within than any secret; loftier than all honor, but not to those who are high and mighty in their own estimation” (Augustine, <em>Confessions,</em> Book IX, 1,1).</p>

<p>Generosity is a virtue of great souls who find their reward in the act of giving. A generous person knows how to give without demanding. When we give, it enlarges the heart. Our Lord sometimes asked for a little, but then He asked for a lot.</p>

<p>He told Peter, “Put out a little from the shore.” But then later on He told him, “Launch out into the deep” (Luke 5:3-4).</p>

<p>He invites us to leave our comfortable state and our egoism and to complicate our life. Heroic sanctity is tied up in following that call, “leaving all things they followed him” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 5:11).</p>

<p>In the course of our life, we have to try and maintain and strengthen our generosity. We need to maintain it because otherwise it might diminish.</p>

<p>We have the continual example of the generosity of the Child in the manger. We are called to try and imitate the generosity of Christ at the Incarnation, at the Redemption, who paid the great price of His precious blood, of which there was a superabundance. There’s a small step from lack of generosity to lukewarmness.</p>

<p>In the life of the Holy Family, we see that nobody holds anything back. St. Ignatius tells us, “To give and not to count the cost, to fight and not to heed the wounds, to toil and not to seek for rest, to labor and not to seek any reward” (<em>Prayer of St. Ignatius</em>).</p>

<p>It’s important for children to learn these lessons as soon as they have something to give. And when there is generosity and self-giving in a family, there is peace and serenity and joy, because happiness in this world is found through giving and through self-giving.</p>

<p>Christ left nothing for Himself. God loves generosity <em>(cf</em>. 2 Cor. 9:7). Stinginess or selfishness can be like a slow-acting poison. It has a deadly effect.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord in our prayer not to get too attached to the little or to the much that we may have, be it money or clothes or time or whatever, and to accept humbly our limitations and to struggle to overcome our defects.</p>

<p>At times, to be generous in that struggle, we’re asked to do the least pleasant task first, to be ready to help, whatever the circumstances may be at home, in school, in the office, in the street, and to help with an upright intention, not just because there’s something for us in it, and to help anyone who may need our help.</p>

<p>That also means that we’re ready to do favors for those who ask them of us. It was said in the early years of St. Josemaría that he tried to do favors for many people.</p>

<p>Generosity can also mean accepting people as they are, without attaching too much importance to their defects, giving a positive tone to our conversations, avoiding negative criticism, and in this way making it easier for those around us to come closer to God.</p>

<p>Generosity and not being deterred by the humbler chores that may need to be done. “We have to learn how to give ourselves,” said St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>, “to burn before God like the light placed on a lampstand to give light to those who walk in darkness, like the sanctuary lamps that burn by the altar, giving off light till their last drop is consumed.”</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>The Forge</em> also, “The Lord, the teacher of Love, is a jealous lover who asks for all we possess, for all our love. He expects us to offer him whatever we have, and to follow the path he has marked out for each one of us” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Points 44-45).</p>

<p>He wants us to be co-redeemers with Him. That is why, to help us understand this marvel, He moves the Evangelist to tell us of so many great wonders.</p>

<p>He could have produced bread from anything, but He doesn’t. He looks for human cooperation. He needs a child, a boy, a few pieces of bread and some fish (John 6:1-15). He needs you and me, and He is God. This should move us to be generous in our corresponding with His grace.</p>

<p>And always, we have the example of Our Lady, who gave herself so completely: “Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be it done unto me according to your word” (Luke 1:38)—particularly at that moment when she went to give herself and her time and her energy in helping St. Elizabeth (Luke 1:39-56).</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Parable of the Vinedressers</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-vinedressers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Parable of the Vinedressers" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-vinedressers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-parable-of-the-vinedressers/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“He went on to speak to them in parables. ‘A man planted a vineyard. He fenced it around, dug out a trough for the winepress, and built a tower. Then he leased it to tenants and went abroad.</p>

<p>‘When the time came, he sent a servant to the tenants to collect from them his share of the produce of the vineyard. But they seized the man, thrashed him, and sent him away empty-handed.</p>

<p>‘Next he sent another servant to them; him they beat about the head and treated shamefully. And he sent another, and him they killed; then a number of others, and they thrashed some and killed the rest.</p>

<p>‘Yet he had still someone left: his beloved son. He sent him to them last of all, thinking, “They will respect my son.” But those tenants said to each other, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.” So they seized him and killed him and threw him out of the vineyard’” (Mark 12:1-8).</p>

<p>In this parable of the vinedressers, Our Lord sums up the whole history of salvation.</p>

<p>He compares Israel to a choice vineyard which God surrounds with a hedge and furnishes with a winepress. He builds a watchtower in which He places a guard to protect the vineyard from thieves and wild animals.</p>

<p>God did not fail to provide all the means possible for caring for the vineyard of His heart—His people—as had already been prophesied (Isa. 5:1-7).</p>

<p>The vinedressers in the parable are the leaders of the people of Israel; the owner is God, and the vineyard is Israel, the People of God.</p>

<p>The owner sends His servants time and again to collect His due of fruit from the vineyard, but each time they are badly treated. This was the mission of the prophets.</p>

<p>Finally, He sent His Son, the Beloved, thinking that they would respect Him.</p>

<p>We are shown here the difference between Jesus—the Son—and the prophets, who were servants.</p>

<p>The parable refers to Christ's transcendental and unique Sonship, and clearly expresses the divinity of Christ.</p>

<p>The vinedressers “took him, killed him, and cast him out of the vineyard,” an explicit reference to the crucifixion, which took place outside the walls of Jerusalem.</p>

<p>Our Lord, who discreetly mentions Himself in the parable, must have spoken with great sorrow as He sees how He is to be rejected by those very people to whom He has come to bring salvation. They do not want Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord ends with the words of one of the Psalms: “The stone which the builders rejected has become the head of the corner” (Ps. 118:22).</p>

<p>The leaders of Israel understood the clearly Messianic meaning of the parable and realized that it was directed against them. So they tried to arrest Him, but once again they feared the people.</p>

<p>St. Peter was to remember Our Lord's words when He came before the Sanhedrin, and the prophecy contained in the parable had already been fulfilled.</p>

<p>“Be it known to you all,” we are told in the Acts, “and to all the people of Israel, that by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom you crucified ... This is the stone that was rejected by you builders, but which has become the head of the corner” (Acts 4:10-11).</p>

<p>Our Lord makes Himself the keystone which is the foundation and support of the whole building. This stone is essential to the Church and to each person: without it, the whole building would collapse.</p>

<p>The cornerstone affects the whole construction, our whole life—business affairs, interests, loves, time. Nothing is beyond the scope of what faith demands in the life of a Christian.</p>

<p>We are not disciples of Christ for a number of predetermined hours (for example, when we pray or when we take part in some religious service) or just on special days.</p>

<p>The profound <em>unity of life</em> that being a Christian demands causes absolutely everything in our lives to be affected by the fact that we are followers of Christ. At the same time, this does not prevent things retaining their own nature.</p>

<p>Following Christ influences the very core of our personality.</p>

<p>When someone is in love, this fact influences their whole view of things and events, however trivial they might appear. Each person is influenced by it as they walk along the street, when they are at work, in their attitude towards social relationships—and not only when they are in the company of the person that they love.</p>

<p>Being a Christian is the most important characteristic of our existence, and it has to have incomparably more influence on our lives than even human love has on the most ardent of lovers.</p>

<p>Christ is the center of our lives and of our whole being. One writer says, “Let us imagine an architect who wants to construct the vault of an apse. He has to trace the whole circumference beginning with the key point—the center.</p>

<p>“Guiding himself by this infallible norm, he then has to calculate the exact circumference and the design of the whole building. … In this way, a single point becomes the fundamental key to an imposing building” (John Cassian, <em>Conferences</em>).</p>

<p>In a similar way, God is the point of reference of our thoughts, our words, and our deeds. We should want to build our very existence in relation to Him.</p>

<p>It is Christ who gives meaning to the way His followers think and live. Our faith in Him gives us light by which to recognize the true reality of things and of events.</p>

<p>And so, it would not make sense if we were to set aside the supervening and determining fact that we are Christians whenever we have to judge a work of art or a political program, whenever we have to carry out some business deal or plan our holidays.</p>

<p>Although [the faithful follower of] Christ respects the autonomy of each discipline, the laws proper to each field of action, and the broad freedom allowed to him in everything that is a matter of opinion, he does not consider any matter at all in only one of its aspects—whether that aspect be, for example, economic, say, or artistic, or cinematographic.</p>

<p>He does not simply accept that particular undertakings or projects are good without taking a broader view of them.</p>

<p>If due subordination to God is not respected in these undertakings, in those programs, or in that work of art, only one definitive overall assessment is possible—a negative one—however good their partial values may appear to be.</p>

<p>When it comes to doing a piece of business or accepting a particular job, a good Christian should not only look at what is financially to his advantage, but he must examine other aspects too.</p>

<p>Is it licit as regards the norms of morality? Does it cause good or harm to others?</p>

<p>He tries to evaluate the benefits such a business proposition or job will contribute to society.</p>

<p>If it is morally wrong or, at best, does not give good example, any other characteristic it may have—for example, providing a good income—do not turn it into a morally sound and therefore good transaction.</p>

<p>However advantageous a business opportunity may appear, if it's not morally right it is a very bad undertaking and one that may not be entered into by any follower of Christ.</p>

<p>Error is often presented decked out in the noble garments of art, science, or freedom. But faith has to be, and indeed is, stronger than error.</p>

<p>It is the powerful light that enables us to see, lurking behind what appears to be good, the evil that lies hidden beneath the surface of an otherwise good literary work, of a beauty that conceals ugliness.</p>

<p>It is Christ who must be the cornerstone of every building.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord for His grace so that we might live in a way totally compatible and utterly coherent [with] our Christian faith.</p>

<p>In this way, we will never think of our faith as a limiting factor: ‘I can’t do this, I can’t go there.’</p>

<p>Rather it will be a light that enables us to recognize the reality of things and events, without ever forgetting that the devil will try to make an ally of human ignorance—which cannot see the complete reality contained in this literary work or in that doctrine—and of the pride and concupiscence that all of us drag along behind us.</p>

<p>Christ is the crucible that assays the gold that there is in human things.</p>

<p>Anything that does not stand up to the testing clarity of His teaching is a lie and deceptive, even though it may be adorned with the appearance of some attractive good or perfection.</p>

<p>If we make use of the criterion that this <em>unity of life</em> gives us—that of being and at all times knowing ourselves to be faithful disciples of Our Lord—we will be able to gather together many of the good things that men, who have been guided by right human criteria, have done and thought, and place them at the feet of Christ.</p>

<p>Without the light of faith, we would, as often as not, fail to detect and see through the rottenness by which we were at first deceived, since many such works do indeed possess some streak of goodness or of beauty.</p>

<p>If we want to have well-formed standards by which to discriminate and judge, while using the means to acquire them, we need to have a right will, which wants above all else to do the Will of God.</p>

<p>This explains why very ordinary simple people, plain folk of scant learning and perhaps with few natural talents, but possessed of a deep Christian faith, can have excellent criteria which enable them to form wise assessments of the various things that happen; whereas others, perhaps more highly cultured or even with far greater intellectual capacity, sometimes show a lamentable absence of sound judgment and make serious mistakes in the most elementary matters.</p>

<p><em>Unity of life</em>, a habitually Christian way of life, enables us to judge with certainty, and to discover the true human value of things. Thus, we will sanctify all noble human realities and take them to Christ.</p>

<p>We can ask ourselves: ‘In every situation, do I live in a way that is consistent with my faith and with my Christian vocation? When I make a decision, however large or small, do I keep in mind above all else what it is God wants of me?’</p>

<p>We can try to see in which specific points God is asking us to behave in a more decisively Christian way.</p>

<p>A Christian who has built his life upon the cornerstone who is Christ has his own personality, has his own way of seeing the world and its happenings.</p>

<p>He has his own scale of values in relation to the world. He has a scale of values very different to that of a pagan, who does not live by faith and who has a purely worldly conception of things.</p>

<p>One writer says a weak and lukewarm Christian faith which exerts very little influence on ordinary life “can provoke in some people that kind of inferiority complex which manifests itself in an immoderate desire to ‘humanize’ Christianity, to ‘popularize’ the Church, to make it somehow seem to conform to the value-judgments prevalent in the world at a given time” (José Orlandis, <em>What is it to be a Catholic?</em>).</p>

<p>That is why, as well as being immersed in our secular activities, as Christians we need to be immersed in God through prayer, through the sacraments, through the sanctification of our daily work.</p>

<p>We need to be faithful disciples of Christ in the middle of the world, in our ordinary everyday life, with all the constant effort and hard decisions that entails.</p>

<p>Very often it might mean refusing to do something wrong, disagreeing with the superior, taking the pathway of conscientious objection, sticking to our values, never ever willing to do something which is wrong.</p>

<p>In this way we will be able to put into practice the advice that St. Paul gave to the first Christians in Rome when he alerted them to the risks of accommodating themselves to the pagan customs of the day: “Do not be conformed to this world” (Rom. 12:2).</p>

<p>As students go through secondary school or through third-level education, this principle is something they need to imbibe because along the way, they may come up against all sorts of different challenges—challenges that demand that they take a different pathway to that which everybody else is taking, that unwillingness to participate in things that are wrong, even though they might be legal or they might be accepted behavior: “But for me I don't do those things.”</p>

<p>That refusal to conform can lead us to row against the current [and] run the risk of being misunderstood by many of our contemporaries.</p>

<p>But Christ was very misunderstood. Christ got a very bad press. We should not be worried about getting a bad press from this world, or too worried about what people may think or what people may say.</p>

<p>We are here to leave a legacy, to blaze a trail, to stand up for what is right, to live by our values.</p>

<p>A Christian has always to remember that they are the leaven (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 13:33) hidden in the lump of dough that has to be fermented by them.</p>

<p>God is the light that shines on all created reality and reveals the truth hidden within it. He is the lighthouse whose beacon-beam directs navigators on whichever sea they steer their course.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council says, “The Church...believes that the key, the center, and the purpose of the whole of man's history is to be found in its Lord and Master” (<em>cf</em>. Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et spes</em>, Point 10, December 7, 1965).</p>

<p>Twenty or thirty years ago, in the country in the world that had the lowest maternal mortality rate (which is the mortality rate for women in pregnancy from any cause) was Ireland.</p>

<p>At that time abortion was illegal, which was a bit of an embarrassment to UNICEF because the country with the lowest maternal mortality rate in the world had no abortion—more or less proving that abortion is never necessary to save the lives of women.</p>

<p>One of the professors who brought about that situation in the country, and put Christian principles into practice and scientific principles in his professional work, told me that when they were training in England in the 1940s and 1950s, when there was a difficult case—a hypertensive mother, an asthmatic mother, a diabetic mother—the treatment was to abort the baby.</p>

<p>He said, “As Catholics we couldn't participate in those things. When we came back to Ireland—Catholic country with Catholic laws— those things were illegal. We had to turn around and learn how to treat the asthmatic mother, and the diabetic mother, and bring her through pregnancy and through labor—which was all the more complicated—and deliver a healthy mother and a healthy baby at the end.”</p>

<p>He said that approach, coupled with the high birth rate there was in the country at the time, led to enormous advances in obstetrical medicine, in neonatal medicine, in the management of labor.</p>

<p>That particular hospital became a world center, blazed a trail. His punchline was, “Sometimes we can have a bit of an inferiority complex in this world because we say ‘No’ to abortion, ‘No’ to contraception, ‘No’ to euthanasia.</p>

<p>“But,” he said, “we have the truth. And when we apply the truth, in research, in science, in other areas of our professional life, then we come up with a real development.”</p>

<p>These were very powerful words from an eminent professor of obstetrics.</p>

<p>Our Lord continues to be the cornerstone of every person's life. Any building constructed without Christ is built in vain.</p>

<p>We can consider whether the faith we profess is coming to bear more and more influence on our existence, on the way we view the world and mankind, and on the way we behave.</p>

<p>We want to conduct ourselves so that through our actions, all people may really come to know Christ, to follow His doctrine, and to love Him.</p>

<p>Our Lady was praised: “‘Blessed is the womb that bore you and the breast that nourished you.’ Our Lord said: ‘Rather, blessed are they who hear the word of God and keep it’” (Luke 11:27-28).</p>

<p>Ultimately, He was raising Our Lady, lifting her up, because she was the one who most heard the Word of God and kept it.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to listen with the ear of our heart to the Word of God and to put it into practice in all of our professional affairs.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trinity Sunday (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trinity Sunday (2026)" /><published>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-28T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Today the Church celebrates the feast of the Blessed Trinity. It’s the ineffable mystery of God’s intimate life. It’s the central truth of our faith and the source of all gifts and graces. The <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> places it at the top of the hierarchy of truths in which we are invited to believe. The liturgy of the Mass invites us to a loving union with each of the three divine persons: Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. This feast was established for the Latin Church by Pope John XXII to be celebrated on the Sunday after the coming of the Holy Spirit, which is the last of the mysteries of our salvation.</p>

<p>Today is a good day to say many times, savoring it, <em>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.</em> There’s an ancient prayer to the Blessed Trinity called the <em>Trisagium Angelicum,</em> which has <em>Tibi laus, tibi gloria, tibi gratiarum actio.</em> To you be praise, to you be glory, to you be thanksgiving, world without end, O Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>Having completed the commemoration of the mysteries of salvation, from Christ’s birth in Bethlehem to the descent of the Holy Spirit at Pentecost, the liturgy now invites us to contemplate the central mystery of our faith, the Blessed Trinity. The mystery of God’s own inner life and the fountain of all gifts and graces.</p>

<p>In his infinitely wise providence, God gradually revealed to mankind his inmost being. That is, as he is in himself, and not just as the cause of created things. In the Old Testament he makes known above all his oneness, and his complete transcendence from the world as its creator and Lord. We learn that God, unlike the world, is uncreated. That he is not limited in space, he is immense. He is not limited in time, he is eternal. His power knows no limits, he is omnipotent.</p>

<p>The book of Deuteronomy says, “Know therefore this day, and lay it to your heart, that the Lord is God in heaven above and on the earth beneath; there is no other” (Deut. 4:39). The Old Testament proclaims above all the greatness of Yahweh, the one God, creator and Lord of the universe. But he is also revealed as the shepherd who seeks his flock, who looks after his own indulgently and tenderly, who forgives and forgets the frequent infidelities of the chosen people.</p>

<p>At the same time, we get glimpses of the paternity of God the Father, of the incarnation of God the Son, whose advent is foretold by the prophets, and of the action of the Holy Spirit, who vivifies all things. But it is Christ who reveals to us in all its fullness the inner workings of the Trinitarian mystery and calls us to participate in it.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew, “No one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). In St. John it is he who speaks to us of the coexistence of the Holy Spirit with the Father, and who sends him to the Church to sanctify it until the end of time. He it is who reveals to us the perfect oneness of the life of the three divine persons.</p>

<p>The mystery of the Trinity is the starting point of all revealed truth. The fountain from which proceeds supernatural life and the goal to which we are headed. We are children of the Father, brothers and co-heirs with the Son, and continually sanctified by the Holy Spirit. To make us ever more and more resemble Christ. Accordingly, we deepen in the understanding of our divine filiation and become living temples of the Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>Since it is the central mystery of the Church’s faith, the Blessed Trinity is continually invoked in the liturgy. We were baptized in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. In their name also are our sins forgiven. We begin and end many prayers by invoking the Father, through Jesus Christ, in the unity of the Holy Spirit. Often during the day, we say the prayer, <em>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.</em></p>

<p>“God is my Father,” we’re told in <em>The Forge.</em> “If you meditate on it, you will never let go of this consoling thought. Jesus is my dear friend, another thrilling discovery, who loves me with all the divine madness of his heart. The Holy Spirit is my consoler, who guides my every step along the road. Consider this often. You are God’s, and God is yours” (<em>The Forge,</em> 2).</p>

<p>The divine life in which we are called to participate is extraordinarily bounteous. The Father eternally engenders the Son, and the Father and the Son together breathe forth the Holy Spirit. This generation of the Son, and the spiration of the Holy Spirit is not something that took place at a particular moment in time and gave rise once and for all to the three divine persons. These processions, rather, as theologians call them, are eternal.</p>

<p>In the case of human generation, a father begets a son, but thereafter both father and son continue to exist independently of the act of begetting. Even if one of them later dies. The man who is father is not just father. Both before and after begetting he is man. In God, by contrast, the essence of the Father consists in giving life to the Son. This is what determines him as a divine person, really distinct from the others.</p>

<p>One author says, among human beings the son who is begotten has a separate existence from his father, but the essence of the only begotten Son of God consists precisely in being Son. It is through him, making ourselves like him by the constant impulse of the Holy Spirit, that we obtain and grow in the awareness of our divine filiation.</p>

<p>“For all who are led by the Spirit of God are children of God. For you did not receive the spirit of slavery to fall back into fear, but you have received the spirit of sonship. When we cry, ‘Abba, Father!’ it is the Spirit himself bearing witness with our spirit that we are children of God. And if children, then heirs, heirs of God and fellow heirs with Christ” (Rom. 8:14–17).</p>

<p>Among men, paternity and filiation are circumstances that fall short of defining the subject completely. But in God, paternity, filiation, and spiration constitute the entire being of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. From the moment man is first called to participate in the divine life through the grace of baptism, he is destined to participate in it ever more and more. Along this path he must journey continually.</p>

<p>From the Holy Spirit we constantly receive impulses, motions, and inspirations to encourage us to travel faster along the way that leads to God, and to revolve in an ever tighter orbit around Our Lord. Our heart now needs to distinguish and adore each one of the divine persons. The soul is, as it were, making a discovery in the supernatural life. Like a little child opening his eyes to the world about him.</p>

<p>The soul spends time lovingly with the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, and readily submits to the work of the life-giving Paraclete, who gives himself to us without the slightest merit on our part, bestowing on us his gifts and the supernatural virtues. “We have run like the deer, longing for flowing streams, thirsting, our lips parched and dry” (cf. Ps. 42:1–2). We want to drink at the source of living water. All day long, without doing anything strange, we move in this abundant, clear spring of fresh waters that leap up to eternal life.</p>

<p>“Words are not needed,” we’re told in <em>Friends of God,</em> “because the tongue cannot express this wonder. The intellect grows calm, one does not reason, one looks. And the soul breaks out once more into song. A new song, because it feels and knows it is under the loving gaze of God all day long” (<em>Friends of God,</em> 307).</p>

<p>The Blessed Trinity dwells in the Christian soul as in a temple. St. Paul explains that “God’s love has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who has been given to us” (Rom. 5:5). There, in the inner recesses of the soul, says St. Catherine of Siena, we learn to be intimate with God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit. “You, O Eternal Trinity, are a deep ocean, into which the more I penetrate, the more I discover. And the more I discover, the more I seek you.”</p>

<p><em>My God, Blessed Trinity. Draw from my poor being what most contributes to your glory, and do with me what you wish, both now and in eternity. May I no longer place between us any voluntary hindrance to your transforming action. Second by second, with a forever actual intention, I desire to offer you all that I am and all that I have. Make my poor life an intimate union with the Word incarnate, an unceasing sacrifice of glory to the Blessed Trinity.</em></p>

<p><em>My God, how I wish to glorify you. If only in exchange for my complete immolation or for any other condition, it were in my power to enkindle the hearts of all your creatures and the whole of creation in the flames of your love, how I would desire to do so. May at least my poor heart belong to you completely. May I keep nothing for myself nor for creatures. Not even a single heartbeat. May I have a burning love for all mankind. But only with you, through you, and for you.</em></p>

<p><em>I desire above all to love you with the heart of St. Joseph, with the immaculate heart of Mary, with the adorable heart of Jesus, and finally to submerge myself in that infinite ocean, that abyss of fire that consumes the Father and the Son in the unity of the Holy Spirit, and love you with your own infinite love.</em></p>

<p><em>O eternal Father, beginning and end of all things. Through the immaculate heart of Mary, I offer you Jesus your Word incarnate. And through him, with him, and in him, I want to repeat ceaselessly this cry that rises from the bottom of my soul: Father, glorify continually your Son, so that your Son may glorify you, in the unity of the Holy Spirit, forever and ever.</em></p>

<p><em>O Jesus, who said, “No one knows the Son except the Father, and no one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). Show us the Father, and we shall be satisfied.</em></p>

<p>Sister Elizabeth of the Trinity ends this prayer saying, “And you, O Spirit of love, teach us all things. And form Jesus with Mary in us until we become perfectly one in the bosom of the Father.”</p>

<p>Because of this great truth—we are children of God—we can spend our life giving thanks for this immense gift. We’re told in St. John, “But to all who received him, who believed in his name, he gave power to become children of God; who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God” (John 1:12–13).</p>

<p>God the Father “destined us in love to be his sons through Jesus Christ, according to the purpose of his will” (Eph. 1:5). God has made us his children. We will never completely understand nor value enough this incredible gift. Child of God! “See what love the Father has given us, that we should be called children of God. Beloved, we are God’s children now; it does not yet appear what we shall be” (1 John 3:1–2).</p>

<p>When we say, “I am a child of God,” we’re not using a metaphor or a pious phrase. We are children in the same way as human generation gives rise to fatherhood and sonship. Those who have been begotten by God are really his children. The Second Vatican Council states that this incomparable truth is carried out in baptism, in which, thanks to the passion and resurrection of Christ, there takes place a new birth into a new life, which did not previously exist. A new creature has emerged, by which the newly baptized person is called and really is a child of God.</p>

<p>The Council of Nicaea said divine sonship reaches its ultimate perfection in God the Son. Jesus Christ, the only begotten Son of God, born of the Father before the beginning of time. Begotten, not made, consubstantial with the Father. To highlight the essential difference between our sonship and the eternal sonship of the Son, ours is called adoptive.</p>

<p>Here below, the word adoption has a specific meaning. The new father has not given life to his son, although he sets out to educate him, supports him with his work, looks after his affairs, gives him his name, his rights of inheritance, and other privileges his natural children would have enjoyed. This might lead some people to have a somewhat confused idea about the true reality of our divine sonship. It must be understood that we are children of God, because God’s life is present in our souls in the state of grace.</p>

<p>It will help us in today’s prayer to consider that God is more our father than he whom in this life we call father, because he has given us our natural life. To refer to a Christian as a child of God is not a mere figure of speech, which brings to mind the fatherly protection or watchfulness that God exercises over him. Rather, it must be understood in the strictest sense, with the same meaning in which it is said that so-and-so is a son of such-and-such.</p>

<p>Through the act of conception, a new person comes into existence. Just as an animal gives birth to an animal of the same species, a human being gives birth to another human being, similar to the parents. Often enough there’s quite a similarity, and people are pleased to see that this or that child takes after his father, in his features, his behavior, his looks, his speech, and so on. Well, the Christian born of God is his son in the most real sense, so that he must be like his Father in heaven.</p>

<p>His condition as a son actually consists in his participation in the same nature as God. Here the words of St. Peter find their true meaning, “participants in the divine nature” (2 Pet. 1:4). Which is more than just an analogy, more than a likeness or a relationship. It implies, rather, an elevation and a transformation of human nature into a nature that is proper to a divine being.</p>

<p>There was a kid in a kindergarten school one time who was being prepared for First Holy Communion. The teacher was explaining the sacraments and explained how in baptism and in all the other sacraments we get grace and are lifted up onto a new supernatural level. That’s what grace does. Therefore we can lead a supernatural life. We’re called to lead a life on a whole new plane, with a supernatural goal.</p>

<p>The kid was amazed; he had never heard such wonderful things before. He had seen movies of Batman and Batwoman, and Spider-Man and Spider-Woman, and Superman and Superwoman. Now he hears that he is called to lead a supernatural life, that this business of baptism raises us up onto this new level. He decided that he should go home and baptize his pet dog, Rufus. He went home and got Rufus and brought him to the washroom, filled a cup with water, poured it over the head of Rufus, and said, “Now Rufus, I baptize you in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Now Rufus, you should be able to perform a supernatural action, an action above your nature. Talk to me, Rufus. Talk to me.” The story ended with Rufus beginning to talk rather clumsily, saying, “You’ll have to be patient with me while I learn to talk, because this is a whole new ball game for me.”</p>

<p>The Christian enters into a higher supernatural world, which is above his original nature, the world of God. This sense of our divine filiation and being participants in the divine nature is something incredible, something huge. It guides our relationship with God, and also with others. The Second Vatican Council said, “The Son came, sent by the Father, who chose us in him before the foundation of the world and destined us to be adopted sons, for it pleased him to restore all things in himself.”</p>

<p>Let us turn to Our Lady, daughter of God the Father, mother of God the Son, spouse of God the Holy Spirit. Mary, may you take us by the hand and lead us to be better children of God each day of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Father God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Father God" /><published>2026-02-27T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-27T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“But when you fast,” we’re told in St. Matthew, “put scent on your head and wash your face, so that no one will know that you are fasting, except your Father, who sees all that is done in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:17).</p>

<p>Our Father God is always by our side.</p>

<p>As Moses tended the flock of his father-in-law, Jethro, near Mount Horeb, the holy mountain, God appeared to him in a burning bush. There Moses was given the extraordinary task—his life’s work—of leading the chosen people out of the slavery of Egypt into the Promised Land. God confirmed him in his mission with the words, “I will be with you” (Ex. 3:1-6, 9-12).</p>

<p>In our prayer today we could repeat those words, reminding ourselves that God has told us that He will always be with us.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, He says, “Do not let your hearts be troubled” (John 14:1), “for I am with you always” (Matt. 28:20). Very consoling words.</p>

<p>Moses little imagined how closely God would be accompanying him and the people in the midst of the trials and tribulations that awaited them. In our lives too, God’s presence at every moment is something we can scarcely fathom—how He is working.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story narrating how a ray of sunlight jumped from out of the azure sky and came down, down, down to a little droplet of muddy water in a puddle. It took hold of this little droplet of muddy water and lifted it up high, high, high above the clouds and deposited it as an immaculate snowflake on a mountain top, so that as it melts it makes the valleys fertile (Fulton Sheen, <em>Sermon</em>, September 22, 1940).</p>

<p>Unbeknownst to us, God is working all the time behind the scenes. That presence of God in our life takes on an even greater definition when God sees us on the road to holiness. He’s like a father minding a toddler.</p>

<p>Every time we see a young father walking with a young baby, it’s worth taking a second look because there’s something there to learn for us about how Our Father God is taking care of us.</p>

<p>Our Lord, true God and true Man, is always reminding us in the Gospel of God’s paternal concern, since “no one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). He alone can do this.</p>

<p>The Son knows the Father in the very knowledge by which the Father knows Him. There’s no greater intimacy than that.</p>

<p>This identity of knowing and knowledge bespeaks the unity of the divine nature. In claiming it, Jesus revealed that He was God.</p>

<p>As the Son, one in substance with the Father, He is also able to reveal the Father’s relationship with and attitude towards us, and in particular, His goodness in granting us the gift of the Holy Spirit. The mystery of the Blessed Trinity is at the heart of what He had to reveal to us, and with it and in it, we find the wonder of God’s fatherhood.</p>

<p>It’s an interesting word: “wonder.” Little children wonder. Often they can’t understand the great realities, but they wonder.</p>

<p>During that last evening in the Upper Room, when Our Lord seemed to be summing up the years of self-giving and trusting revelation, He said, “I have manifested your name to the men whom you gave me” (John 17:6).</p>

<p>To manifest someone’s name really meant to reveal their mode of being. Our Lord has revealed to us the depths of the Trinitarian Mystery: the fact that God is a Father, so close to us men. Jesus is always using the title ‘Father,’ both in private conversations and in His preaching.</p>

<p>He dwells on the goodness of the Father, who rewards the slightest action and recognizes our good deeds, even the ones that no one sees.</p>

<p>“But when you give alms, your left hand must not know what your right hand is doing. Your almsgiving must be in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:3-4).</p>

<p>“But when you fast, put scent on your head and wash your face, so that no one will know you’re fasting except your Father, who sees all that is done in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:17-18).</p>

<p>He bestows bounty on the just and on the unjust. In St. Matthew we’re told, “But I say to you, love your enemies and pray for those who persecute you, so that you may be children of your Father in heaven. For he causes his sun to rise on the bad as well as the good, and sends down rain to fall on the upright and the wicked alike” (Matt. 5:44-45).</p>

<p>This loving Father is always aware of and concerned about what we need.</p>

<p>We’re told in other places in Scripture: “Ask, and it will be given to you; search, and you will find; knock, and the door will be opened to you. For everyone who asks receives, everyone who searches finds, everyone who knocks will have the door opened” (Matt. 7:7-8).</p>

<p>And elsewhere in Scripture, we’re told: “That is why I am telling you not to worry about your life and what you are to eat, nor about your body and what you are to wear. Surely life is more than food, and the body more than clothing.</p>

<p>“Look at the birds in the sky: they do not sow or reap or gather into barns. Yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not worth much more than they are? Can any of you, however much you worry, add one single cubit to your span of life?</p>

<p>“And why worry about clothing? Think of the flowers growing in the fields: they never have to work or spin. Yet I assure you that not even Solomon in all his royal robes was clothed like one of these.</p>

<p>“Now if that is how God clothes the wildflowers growing in the field, which are there today and thrown into the furnace tomorrow, will he not much more look after you, you who have so little faith? So do not worry. Do not say, ‘What are we to eat? What are we to drink? What are we to wear?’ It is the Gentiles who set their hearts on all these things.</p>

<p>“Your heavenly Father knows that you need them all. Set your hearts on his kingdom first and God’s saving justice, and all these things will be given to you as well” (Matt. 6:25-33).</p>

<p>These are very encouraging and consoling words.</p>

<p>Jesus encourages us to have the word ‘Father’ like a constant refrain on our lips, reminding ourselves that this Father is never far away, no more than a father who sees a little toddler alone and in danger. If we try to please Him, we will find Him by our side.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em> we’re told: “When you really come to love God’s Will, you will never, even in the worst state of agitation, lose sight of the fact that Our Father in heaven is always close to you, very close, right next to you, with his everlasting Love and with his unbounded affection” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 240).</p>

<p>When you’re at Mass, when you’re looking through the words of the <em>Eucharistic Prayer</em>, try and notice how frequently the word ‘Father’ appears in the liturgy. It’s like a daily reminder:</p>

<p>The way to be true children of God the Father is by imitating Christ. God didn’t just make us and then leave us, like a painter with his painting. He’s a Father to us, and He’s even brought us to be “partakers of the divine nature” (2 Pet. 1:4).</p>

<p>Beautiful phrase that we find in the letter of St. Peter worth contemplating: He’s lifted us up to be “partakers of the divine nature.” That’s why living in the state of grace is the most important goal that we should have for our life.</p>

<p>We’re told also in St. John’s Letter that the Father’s desire is “that we should be called children of God, and so we are” (1 John 3:1). Being children of God is not something we achieve on our own; it’s a gift from God. Pondering this will make us thank Him each day.</p>

<p>The sense of our divine filiation will be at the root of our joy and confidence in carrying out the mission that God has given to us. In it we find assurance in the face of difficulty and anguish.</p>

<p>“Father, my Father,” we can find ourselves saying, savoring that gentle but strong word ‘Father,’ be it at times of joy or of danger.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em>, we’re told, “Call him ‘Father’ many times a day and tell him—alone, in your heart—that you love him, that you adore him, that you feel proud and strong because you are his child” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 150).</p>

<p>It is through Christ that we share in this divine sonship, as we try to resemble Him, the firstborn among many brethren and the only begotten Son of the Father.</p>

<p>The more like Jesus we become, the more God the Father will see us as His children, if we try to work as He did, if we too have pity on the people we meet each day, if we make reparation for sin and show our thanks, as Our Lord did.</p>

<p>But we achieve this above all by imitating Christ’s prayer to His Father. This can mean bursting into praise and thanksgiving for the many expressions of God’s love that we encounter.</p>

<p>Cardinal Văn Thuận, a Vietnamese Cardinal imprisoned for many decades in solitary confinement, tells a story of how some of the prison guards that were looking after him were curious when they knew that he knew some Latin.</p>

<p>They asked him to teach them some Latin. So he taught them Latin. Then he decided to teach them the hymn, the <em>Veni Creator</em>, which is one of the most beautiful hymns to the Holy Spirit that we have in the Catholic Church.</p>

<p>And so, when the guard learned this hymn, he would come every morning singing the <em>Veni Creator</em> to open the prison cell each morning. This was like a gift from God in his solitary confinement (<em>cf</em>. Francis Xavier Nguyen Văn Thuận, <em>Testimonies of Hope</em>).</p>

<p>We can find ourselves thanking God in a special way.</p>

<p>In St. Matthew we’re told, “I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth” (Matt. 11:25). It’s very appropriate that, as the <em>Preface</em> tells us each day, that we be “always and everywhere” giving thanks to God our Father.</p>

<p>We can say, ‘Thank you for bringing this friend of mine back to the sacraments, for helping me with my family, for giving me the opportunity to open my heart in spiritual direction.’</p>

<p>St. Josemaría recommended that we should each day also thank God for all the graces of which we are not aware. There must be millions and millions of graces that God has given to us in the course of our life, which we’re not aware of at all.</p>

<p>If our minds and hearts turn to God often, in good times and in bad, then we’re living as good children should.</p>

<p>In the Psalms we’re told, “My soul, give thanks to the Lord, all my being, bless his holy name. My soul, give thanks to the Lord, and never forget all his blessings. It is he who forgives all your guilt, who heals every one of your ills, who redeems your life from the grave, who crowns you with love and compassion” (Ps. 103:1-4).</p>

<p>We could ask for the grace to see other people as Christ saw them. The world looks very different through His eyes! It is the Holy Spirit who configures us to the Master.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us, “For all who are led by the Spirit of God are children of God” (Rom. 8:14).</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom explains that it is “through the spirit that we belong to Christ, we possess him, and we vie with the angels.</p>

<p>“Through the spirit,” he says, “we crucify the flesh, we taste the joy of eternal life, we possess the pledge of the resurrection, and make sure progress on the path of virtue” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homilies on Romans, 13</em>). Divine filiation is the easiest way to reach the Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>St. Irenaeus says, “How often we have reflected on God’s mercy and how he chose to become man so that man could, in a sense, become God” (<em>cf</em>. Irenaeus, <em>Against Heresies, Book 5, Preface; Catechism of the Catholic Church, Point 460</em>), sharing His very life.</p>

<p>And so, union with Christ is a consequence of our divine filiation.</p>

<p>The sanctifying grace that we receive in the sacraments and as a reward for our good works identifies us with Christ and makes us ‘sons in the Son,’ since God the Father has only one Son and it is only ‘in Christ’ that we can attain to this divine filiation.</p>

<p>We become united and identified with Him as members of His Mystical Body, as St. Paul wrote to the Galatians: “It is no longer I who live, but Christ who lives in me” (Gal. 2:20).</p>

<p>So when we turn to the Father it is really Christ who is praying in us. When we deny ourselves something for Him, it is He who has inspired this detachment of spirit. When we try to bring someone back to the sacraments, our apostolic spirit is a reflection of Christ’s zeal for souls.</p>

<p>Our work and our sufferings complete the works and sufferings which Our Lord took on for His Mystical Body the Church. We could think of the value which our daily work and sorrows assume then in this light.</p>

<p>The interior struggle which brings us, with the help of grace, to be conformed to Christ also moves us to “have this mind among yourselves, which was also in Christ Jesus,” says St. Paul (Phil. 2:5).</p>

<p>And this in turn makes us ‘more’ children of God, so to speak. In the ordinary way, one cannot be more or less the son of one’s father, though one could be a better or a worse one.</p>

<p>In the supernatural sphere, the holier one is, the more one is a son or daughter of God, not just a better one. This is the real goal of the Christian life: a constant growth in divine filiation.</p>

<p>Our Mother Mary is the perfect example of what divine grace can achieve when it’s fully availed of. No one, excepting the sacred Humanity of Our Lord, was ever closer to God, and no created being could ever become the Daughter of God the Father that she was.</p>

<p>We can ask her to make us seek the counsel of the Holy Spirit, who will lead us to imitate Jesus. Under His influence, we’ll feel this pressing need to turn to the Father at all times, but particularly at Mass, when we address Him as Most Merciful Father in the<em>Eucharistic Prayer I</em>, in union with the sacrifice of His Son.</p>

<p>We will think of Him as Father, calling Him <em>Abba</em>, anointed as we are by the spirit of His Son who cries out, “Abba, Father!”, says St. Paul (Gal. 4:6).</p>

<p>He will also make us feel the hunger and thirst for God and for His glory, which were so apparent in His Incarnate Son.</p>

<p>The Father also receives glory from our growing more like His only begotten Son, “who by the power at work within us,” says St. Paul to the Ephesians, “is able to do far more abundantly than all we ask or think. Glory be to him” whose power working in us can do infinitely more than we can ask or imagine (Eph. 3:20-21).</p>

<p>Our Father God is always our safeguard against the difficulties and temptations that we may have to undergo. We can win every battle with Him at our side.</p>

<p>The whole history of the Incarnation opens with the words, “Do not be afraid, Mary” (Luke 1:30). In the presence of the supernatural there is often fear, but God comes to calm our fears.</p>

<p>Likewise with St. Joseph: “Do not be afraid, Joseph, son of David” (Matt. 1:20). He’s told to calm down. God comes to bring him peace.</p>

<p>And also to the shepherds, the angel says, “Do not be afraid, for I bring you good tidings of great joy which will be to all the people” (Luke 2:10). This beginning of God’s coming into the world marks a style proper to Our Lord’s presence among men.</p>

<p>Later on, when Our Lord was crossing the Sea of Galilee, the boat was swamped by the waves. St. Mark puts this event in its proper context.</p>

<p>It was the evening of the day on which Our Lord had narrated the parables of the kingdom of heaven (Mark 4:35).</p>

<p>The Gospel explains that Our Lord, tired out after hours of preaching, was asleep in the boat. The storm must have been tremendous, because the disciples, accustomed as they were to the sea, nevertheless saw themselves in great danger. And they cried out for Our Lord to save them: “Lord, save us, for we perish!” (Matt. 8:25).</p>

<p>From the start, the apostles understood why Our Lord was asleep. He must have been very tired not to have been awakened by the waves. They did everything in their power to avert the danger, rowing hard, bailing out the water. But gradually the storm began to get the better of them, and they were in imminent danger of sinking. There’s a great sense of urgency in their words: “Save us, for we are perishing.”</p>

<p>The fears that we may experience often stem from the awareness that the security of our life is based on very weak foundations. In that case, we’re forgetting an essential truth: that God is our constant security. That doesn’t mean that we are insensitive to events, but that we should have more confidence in using the human means at our disposal.</p>

<p>We must never forget that to be close to God, even when He appears to be asleep, is to be safe. When we’re confused or going through unpleasant times, God does not forget us. St. Teresa of Ávila said, “He never fails his friends” (Teresa of Ávila, <em>Life, 2,4</em>).</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presence of God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presence of God" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“The child whispered once, ‘God, speak to me.’<br />
And a meadowlark sang. The child did not hear.</p>

<p>The child yelled, ‘God, speak to me!<br />
And the thunder rolled across the sky. But the child did not listen.</p>

<p>The child looked around and said, ‘God, let me see you.’<br />
And a star shone brightly. But the child did not notice.</p>

<p>And the child shouted, ‘God, show me a miracle!’<br />
And a life was born, but the child did not know.</p>

<p>The child cried out in despair, ‘Touch me, God, let me know you are here!’<br />
Whereupon God reached down<br />
And touched the child.</p>

<p>But the child brushed the butterfly away<br />
And walked away unknowingly.”<br />
(Ravindra Kumar Karnani, <em>And the Meadowlark Sang</em>).</p>

<p>This meditation is about the <em>presence of God</em> in our life.</p>

<p>There was a priest and a professor in an ecclesiastical seminary in Rome. He’d been a popular professor of philosophy for almost thirty years. But he was also a very demanding professor.</p>

<p>He never missed a lecture, never relaxed the schedule, never gave his students free or half days, not even on special festivities or right before vacations.</p>

<p>One day he came to class, put his books on the table, smiled and announced, ‘Today we will not have class.’</p>

<p>The students were shocked. One tentatively raised his hand and asked, ‘Why not, Father?’</p>

<p>The priest answered, ‘Today I want to celebrate, because during my morning meditation, for the first time in thirty-five years, I felt the presence of God.’</p>

<p>For almost forty years, he was faithful to his daily prayer commitment without experiencing any consolation.</p>

<p>We know that God is close to us. “I am with you always, even until the end of the world” (Matt. 28:20).</p>

<p>The virtue of presence of God is the virtue whereby we remind ourselves that we are always in God’s presence—with or without any consolations, whether or not we feel Him.</p>

<p>We know with faith that Our Heavenly Father is close to us at all moments.</p>

<p>“Can a woman forget her sucking child...that she should have no compassion on the son of her womb? Even these may forget, yet I will not forget you” (Isa. 49:15).</p>

<p>“Oh, taste and see that the Lord is good!” (Ps. 34:8).</p>

<p>“The kingdom of God is within you” (Luke 17:21).</p>

<p>In all sorts of ways, Our Father God reminds us that He’s present to us all the time. He is present to us, but, as Ronald Knox says, the question is whether or not we are alive to Him, whether we notice Him, talk to Him, thank Him, appreciate His presence, and the things around us in nature.</p>

<p>“Look at the birds of the air; they neither sow or reap nor gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>When we receive supernatural grace in the sacraments, the Blessed Trinity comes to live in us in grace. We will “come and make our abode in him” (John 14:23).</p>

<p>The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are continually within us. All we need to do is turn our gaze there.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “In him we live and move and have our being” (Acts 17:28).</p>

<p>St. John Paul II liked to say that in Christ we find the meaning and the purpose of our life (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, World Youth Day, August 14, 1993). In turning to God frequently each day, we can find the meaning and the purpose of our life.</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “As the deer longs for flowing streams, so my soul longs for you, O God. My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:1-2).</p>

<p>“O God, you are my God, I seek you; my soul thirsts for you; my flesh faints for you, as in a dry and weary land, where no water is” (Ps. 63:1).</p>

<p>The Old Testament and the New Testament are full of these petitions or reminders that God is all around us and that we need Him.</p>

<p>In one of his encyclicals, Pope St. John Paul II says that there is a hole in the human heart, a chasm in the human heart, that can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>“I stretch out my hands to you,” says the Old Testament, “my soul thirsts for you like a parched land. Make haste to answer me, O Lord; my spirit fails. Hide not your face from me” (Ps. 143:6-7).</p>

<p>We could try to make a resolution to be more aware of the presence of God in the ordinary things of each day, when we know He’s waiting for us in those ordinary things that He gives us to do.</p>

<p>Growth in friendship with God requires interior recollection. The presence of the three divine Persons in our souls in grace is a living presence, which is open to our friendship: they are inviting us to get to know them and to love them. It’s up to us to correspond.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Why climb the mountains or go down into the valleys of the world looking for him who dwells within us?” (Augustine, <em>De Trinitate</em>).</p>

<p>St. Gregory tells us, “As long as our mind is giddy with carnal images, it will never be able to contemplate...because there are as many obstacles blinding it as there are thoughts pulling it here and there. Hence, for the soul to contemplate the invisible nature of God, the first step must be: let it be recollected within itself” (Gregory the Great, <em>Homilies on Ezechiel</em>).</p>

<p>We turn to our soul, to our heart, we find God within, and having that spirit of finding God within, we can also find Him without, because “there is something…divine, hidden in the most ordinary human reality” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 114).</p>

<p>God may ask some people to withdraw from the world to achieve that recollection. But for the majority of Christians—housewives, students, employees—He wants us to find Him in the midst of our daily activities, and to achieve that recollection there.</p>

<p>A young married lady told me once how their young child was getting to the stage of three or four or so, and Christmas was coming. She decided that it was time to have a crib in their home. So she got a small little crib for their flat.</p>

<p>Then the little child came along and took the different pieces of the crib and began to deposit them all over the house. She found St. Joseph under the couch, she found Our Lady behind the curtains, she found the angels in the bedroom, the shepherds were somewhere else.</p>

<p>Little by little she was able to repossess all these little pieces of the crib. But she couldn’t find the baby Jesus. She looked high up and low down, but baby Jesus was nowhere to be found.</p>

<p>A day or two later, she said, “I opened the washing machine and there was the baby Jesus sitting on top of the washing.”</p>

<p>She said, “It struck me in that moment that the Holy Spirit was speaking to me. I’ve been to many recollections and retreats where I learned a lot of formation. One of the ideas that I often heard was that we have to find God in the ordinary things of each day.</p>

<p>“When I saw the baby Jesus sitting on top of the washing, I thought, this is the message that the Holy Spirit is saying to me. This is where I have to find God each day.”</p>

<p>Then she wondered: How on earth did the baby Jesus get into the washing machine? She realized that her son had put the baby Jesus into the pocket of his trousers. The trousers went to the wash and out came the baby Jesus in the wash.</p>

<p>We keep our senses for God by means of ongoing mortification throughout the day. It’s also the way to interior contentment. We find peace in the things of God.</p>

<p>We mortify our imagination by putting aside useless thoughts; our memory, by not entertaining memories that don’t bring us closer to God; our will, by fulfilling our schedule of work and our duties, however small they may be.</p>

<p>Concentrated work, if it’s offered to God, not only does not obstruct our conversation with God, but rather, facilitates it. The same applies to our external activities: social relations, family life, leisure time, journeys.</p>

<p>Everything in life—except when superficiality predominates—has a profound, intimate dimension. It takes on that dimension when we are recollected and brings it into our friendship with God.</p>

<p>Recollection means ‘bringing together what was scattered,’ reestablishing interior order, controlling our senses as they tend towards dispersion, even in things which are good or indifferent.</p>

<p>It means having God as the center of our intentions in what we’re doing and planning.</p>

<p>The opposite to interior recollection is dissipation and superficiality. In <em>The Way</em> we’re told, “Dissipation—You stake your senses and faculties in whatever pool you meet on the way. And you can feel the results: unsettled purpose, scattered attention, deadened will, and quickened concupiscence. Subject yourself once again to a serious plan that will make you lead a Christian life, or you will never do anything worthwhile” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 375).</p>

<p>Unless we’re recollected, we cannot pay attention to God in the ordinary things of each day. The more we purify our heart and our senses, the more recollected we are, the more our soul will long for contact with God, “like the deer that yearns for running streams” (<em>cf</em>. Ps. 42:1).</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>Friends of God</em>, “Our heart then needs to distinguish and adore each one of the divine Persons. The soul is, as it were, making a discovery in the supernatural life, like an infant opening his eyes to the world about him. The soul spends time lovingly with the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, and readily submits to the work of the life-giving Paraclete, who gives himself to us without any merit on our part” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 306).</p>

<p>Our refuge and our strength lie in the love of God, expressed in the ordinary things of each day.</p>

<p>I read an article once written by a housewife who talked about how to sanctify our home life. She talked about how she would get her children and her husband off to work in the morning. I think there were eight children.</p>

<p>When they were all gone off to school and to work, she would breathe a sigh of relief, clear away the breakfast table, clean up the kitchen a little bit, and then go upstairs to make some beds.</p>

<p>She said, “Every step of the stair is an opportunity for me to tell God how much I love Him.”</p>

<p>That’s living <em>presence of God</em> in the ordinary things of each day, and using human reminders or human situations to remind us of God’s presence. Because we are creatures of matter and spirit, we need material things to remind us often of the spiritual things.</p>

<p>On His way to the Holy City, we’re told, Jesus stops for a moment to express His disappointment at its rejection of His message: “O Jerusalem, Jerusalem...How often I would have gathered your children together as a hen gathers her brood, but you did not want” (Luke 13:34).</p>

<p>Our Lord emphasizes how we have to want. We have to go in that direction, make definite resolutions.</p>

<p>A farmer in Canada once said how there was a fire on his farm, and he was surveying the damage sometime later. He came across a chicken that had been cooked in the fire in the middle of the farmyard. Obviously, the chicken was cooked to a cinder.</p>

<p>He gave it a good kick, and out from underneath the chicken ran four or five little chicks. Suddenly, he remembered this phrase of Scripture. He understood it with greater depth. “How often I would have gathered you as a hen gathers her brood.”</p>

<p>The chicken saw the danger, gathered her chicks, and gave her life in the process so that her chicks would live.</p>

<p>Jesus watches over us from the tabernacle. He’s alert to the dangers that threaten us. He’s ever ready to cure our wounds. He continually shares His life with us. He’s our refuge and our strength.</p>

<p>The Psalmist says, “Keep me as the apple of your eye; hide me in the shadow of your wings” (Ps. 17:8).</p>

<p>“For you are my refuge, a strong tower against the enemy. Let me dwell in your tent forever! Oh, to be safe under the shelter of your wings!” (Ps. 61:3-4).</p>

<p>It’s a very good thing to try and have little aspirations, little phrases that suit us for different situations, or places, or feelings, or ups and downs, that can lead us to pray. They can be phrases from well-known prayers, like “our sweetness and our hope”—a phrase we find in the <em>Hail, Holy Queen.</em></p>

<p>It could be a phrase from some words of the Mass: “Do not look on my sins, O Lord, but on the faith of your children.” “Lord, have mercy. Christ, have mercy.”</p>

<p>They could be some aspiration to Our Lady: Queen of peace, Help of Christians, Refuge of sinners, Morning Star.</p>

<p>Other little phrases that may come to mind, or words that might jump up out of the page as we do our spiritual reading or follow the Mass—the Holy Spirit will be speaking to us.</p>

<p>He’ll help us to find those words or phrases that we can use as a means of prayer during the day, that come from the depth of our soul. In this way we can stay close to Our Lord in our earthly life.</p>

<p>At the close of that life, He will be Our Judge and Our Friend. He’ll remember helping us all the time from the tabernacle.</p>

<p>Our Lord has wanted to remain present throughout the world, so that we might seek Him more readily for friendship and assistance, and turn to Him in all sorts of moments.</p>

<p>“If we’re suffering pain and discomfort, he will lighten our burden and comfort us”—perhaps reminding us that whatever we might suffer in this world, He has been there before. “And a sword has pierced his Mother’s heart” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35).</p>

<p>“If we succumb to illness, he will either provide a remedy, or he will give us the strength to suffer it for the sake of eternal life”—to offer up in that moment that pain, or that difficulty, or that piece of bad news, or that contradiction, or that broken heart.</p>

<p>“If we find ourselves at war with the devil and our passions, he’ll supply us with arms for the battle, so that we can resist and ultimately be victorious.” Virgin most faithful, Comforter of the afflicted, Mother of mercy.</p>

<p>“If we are poor, he will enrich us with all kinds of good things in this life and in eternity” (John Vianney, <em>Sermon on Maundy Thursday</em>).</p>

<p>We need to make resolutions to seek His company every single day. From the moment we wake up, even before we get out of bed, our first thought can be a thought for God:</p>

<p>‘Thank you, Lord, for the sleep that you gave me. Thank you for the fact that I have a bed to lie down in, a pillow to put my head on, and a roof over my head. Thank you for this new day. I offer it to you.’</p>

<p>And the same thing as we lie down in bed at night. It can be a good moment to repeat the morning offering, offering to Our Lord those last minutes or seconds of this gift of a day that He has given to us.</p>

<p>Our determination to live as children of God should be expressed in ordinary life: at work, at home, among our friends. In every hour of the day, we should be striving to be men and women of faith. Full-time Christians.</p>

<p>We don’t just confine our relationship with God to the few moments that we may spend inside a church. We live out our friendship with God in our workplace, in our rest and recreation, in social gatherings. We reflect Christ’s love in everything we do.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “So whether you eat or drink or whatever you do, do all for the glory of God” (1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>A lady who was not a Catholic—but later became one—heard that phrase in a class one time. She felt the Holy Spirit speaking to her. “Doing everything for the glory of God.” She said, ‘Really. that’s what the spirit of Opus Dei is all about.’</p>

<p>Then she told me that after the class she went out to her car, and it was in a bit of a mess. She thought, ‘I better start with my car—clean up the inside a little bit so it reflects more the glory of God.’</p>

<p>Then she went to her office. She was a lawyer. And as often happens in lawyers’ offices, her files were all over the place. She put them back in their proper place.</p>

<p>Her secretary came in and wondered what earthquake in reverse has hit this place. She found everything in such order. She told her, ‘I’m trying to do everything for the glory of God.’</p>

<p>Then she went home that night, and she said, ‘Every night I would watch the news with my husband. Halfway through the news, he would ask me to get him a cup of tea. Very grudgingly, I would go downstairs to make a cup of tea. But this time I had it ready for him. He asked me: What’s happened? What’s come over you?’</p>

<p>She said, ‘I’m doing everything for the glory of God.’</p>

<p>St. Basil says, “When you sit down at table, pray. When you eat your bread, give thanks to God who is so generous. If you have some wine, remember that he has created it to bring us merriment and comfort in affliction.</p>

<p>“When you’re getting dressed, give thanks to the one who gave you these clothes. When you look up at the firmament and behold the beauty of the stars above, fall down at the feet of God and adore his infinite Wisdom that is manifest in all Creation.</p>

<p>“Do the same at sunrise and sunset, when you’re asleep and when you’re awake. Give thanks to God who created all this wonder for your benefit, so that you might know, love and praise his name” (Basil, <em>Homilia in Julittam maritem</em>).</p>

<p>All the noble realities should serve to bring us to the Lord.</p>

<p>And if some nights you can’t sleep well, have recourse to your presence of God. Pray a little more. One saint used to say, ‘Last night I slept a little less, but I prayed a little more.’</p>

<p>As you move around with your children, try and teach them to live in the presence of God: to give thanks for this and thanks to God for that; to say the <em>Grace Before Meals</em>, or the <em>Angelus</em>, or other little aspirations that they come across, so that they learn to pray and learn to realize where everything comes from.</p>

<p>Confucius, the Chinese philosopher, says, “When you drink water, remember the source.” As Christians in the middle of the world we have a lot of sources to remember.</p>

<p>Someone in love thinks of their beloved twenty-hour hours a day. That’s the kind of love we should try to have for Jesus Christ. It should constitute the essence of our being, the driving force behind all our actions.</p>

<p>He is Our One and Only Lord. He is the one we want to glorify through our work well done. Jesus is our inspiration when we try to practice the social doctrine of the Church, when we strive to protect the environment.</p>

<p>This all-embracing outlook leads a Christian to make an effort to be cordial and optimistic, to be punctual at work, to make good use of time, to overcome temptations to laziness.</p>

<p>If our love of God is authentic, it will shine out from and be appreciable in every aspect of our existence.</p>

<p>The Lord does not distance Himself from us. He wants us to live in His presence.</p>

<p>We’re told at the scene of the Transfiguration: “Immediately a cloud overshadowed them” (<em>cf</em>. Mark 9:7).</p>

<p>It’s a reminder of that other cloud that accompanied the presence of God in the Old Testament: “Then the cloud,” we’re told in the Book of Exodus, “covered the tent of meeting, and the glory…filled the tabernacle” (Ex. 40:34).</p>

<p>It was the sign of divine intervention. “And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Lo, I am coming to you in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with you, and may believe you forever’” (Ex. 19:9).</p>

<p>At Mount Tabor, that cloud overshadows Christ, and the powerful voice of God the Father is heard coming from it: “This is my Son, my Chosen, listen to him” (Luke 9:35).</p>

<p>God the Father speaks through Jesus Christ to men of all ages. His voice is heard in every age, in a particular way through the teaching of the Church, who, as John Paul says in his encyclical, <em>The Redeemer of Man,</em> his first encyclical, “continually seeks ways of bringing this mystery of her Master and Lord to humanity—to the peoples, the nations, the succeeding generations, and every individual human being” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Redemptor hominis</em>, Point 7, March 4, 1979).</p>

<p>We can detect when the Holy Spirit is speaking to us. When certain words or phrases of other people, or something we read, strikes us in a special way, or something we hear in some preaching, somehow, it’s engraved in our soul.</p>

<p>Things we remember a few days later—this is the Holy Spirit speaking to us, things He wants us to remember, like a divine call.</p>

<p>Every time our phone rings, I can think of it as a divine call, a human reminder to think of God at this particular moment. Or each time we walk into a room, or each time we see an image of Our Lady, or each time we go through a traffic light—this is the ordinary life that God wants us to sanctify.</p>

<p>He wants us to find Him in the street, in the hustle and bustle, in the people around us.</p>

<p>We have to find Him when He forgives us in the Sacrament of Penance and, above all, in Holy Communion, where He is really, truly, and substantially present.</p>

<p>Normally, Our Lord doesn’t show Himself to us with any special manifestations. He wants us to seek Him out—“Seek and you will find” (Matt. 7:7)—in the ordinary, everyday things.</p>

<p>Our God is a God of consolation. Occasionally, by our side, we realize that He gives us consolations that can only have come from Him.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “She hastens to make herself known to those who desire her” (Wisd. 6:13).</p>

<p>He grants us the grace sometimes of feeling His presence. He desires that we should speak to Him as your most beloved friend. Tell Him about your feelings. One saint used to say, “Lord, I’m fed up. I’m tired.” We share with Him the deep things that are going on in our heart.</p>

<p>“Without waiting for you to come close to him, he hastens towards you,” we’re told, “when you seek his love, and he presents himself to you, granting you the graces and remedies that you need. He only waits for one word from you in order to show you that he is beside you and wants to listen to you and console you” (Alphonsus Liguori, <em>How to Converse with God</em>).</p>

<p>We’re told in the Psalms, “His ears are towards their cry” (Ps. 34:15).</p>

<p>Our Lady and St. Joseph lived continuously in the presence of God. They were alive to God in everything they did. They listened to the angels. They responded. Living in the presence of God is hope.</p>

<p>We could ask the Holy Family that they may teach us also to be attentive to the voice of God as He speaks to us in the ordinary things of each day, and that we might respond in that same wholehearted way that Joseph and Mary did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MVF</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>