<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-22T00:00:29+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">All the Glory to God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All the Glory to God" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>In the Gospel of St. Matthew, we’re told, “Be careful not to parade your uprightness in public to attract attention; otherwise you will lose all reward from your Father in heaven. So when you give alms, do not have it trumpeted before you; this is what the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets to win admiration. In truth I tell you, they have had their reward.</p>

<p>“But when you give alms, your left hand must not know what your right hand is doing; your almsgiving must be in secret, and your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:1-4).</p>

<p>In this passage of the Gospel, Our Lord talks to us about the supernatural goal of everything we do, seeing that that supernatural intention is the only really worthwhile intention to have.</p>

<p>We have to try and declare war on our love of self, when perhaps the desire to be well-regarded comes into play. We have to remember that phrase, <em>Deo omnis gloria</em>, all the glory to God.</p>

<p>“The weather pays no attention to criticism.” Meaning will never be found in the praise and adulation of others.</p>

<p>Malcolm Muggeridge liked to say that it often happens that the real reason for doing something only emerges after it has been done (Malcolm Muggeridge, <em>The Third Testament</em>). Altruism can hide a lot of pride. Conscience and conscious intent can be but the tip of the iceberg of unconscious intent.</p>

<p>After we’ve done something which we think has been done for very altruistic reasons, when the truth has to be told, we may realize a few hours or days later that yes, it was done thinking of others, but perhaps only 30 percent thinking of others; 70 percent may have been because there was ‘something in it for me.’</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord for lights to see when we don’t have the supernatural goal as clearly as we might. Often, it’s in small, subtle things which are difficult to detect.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>The Forge</em>, “You are like the little pauper who suddenly finds out that you’re the child of the King. That is why now the only thing that concerns you on this earth is the glory of your Father God, his glory in everything” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 334).</p>

<p>God’s love is manifested in the gifts that are given to us. St. Paul says, “I do not cease to give thanks for you…that the God of Our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give you the Spirit of wisdom and of revelation in the knowledge of him” (Eph. 1:16-17).</p>

<p>The intention with which we do things is one of the most important aspects of the moral act. We have to try and take care of that intention. It can affect very much the actions that we do.</p>

<p>Rational creatures give glory to God with reason and will. Irrational creatures, like a cow, a dog, a goat, give glory to God just by being. And when we practice virtues, that reflects an aspect of the divine glory, perfection.</p>

<p>[Our Lord] said, “Let your light shine before others, that they may see your good works and give glory to your Father in heaven” (Matt. 5:16).</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord that our deeds may shine, especially in charity. To want to do things well all the time can also be an expression of love of me. We have to try and get into the habit of giving the glory to God.</p>

<p>The radicality of the Christian life requires that we go beyond what is convenient or easy or comfortable. We have to try and be ready to go the extra mile.</p>

<p>And it’s good to ask ourselves occasionally: Is the glory of God the motive of all my actions? Do we repeat the <em>Morning Offering</em> frequently as we go through the day?</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to point out to people on the roof of the Cathedral of Burgos certain stone sculptures that were there on that roof, which the sculptors had made fully aware that they could not be seen from below. They were done for the glory of God (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 65).</p>

<p>He liked to talk about a chalice he once found where there was a gem hidden up underneath the base of the chalice—there for God to see, not for human eyes.</p>

<p>With the wounds of original sin, that has made it difficult to give God all the glory, because we can get distracted. The devil can keep our vision on other things. We can have a tendency to turn our work, our family life, our material things that we use, into instruments of our own glory, to seek ourselves. We might find that we become disheartened at our own failure.</p>

<p>Thus, it’s very good that we examine our intentions. What happens when we’re asked to change our plans for the day or for the week? Or when we experience something like Our Lady and St. Joseph did on their journey to Bethlehem, and then to Egypt, and then back to Nazareth?</p>

<p>We have to put this right intention into practice when we don’t look for recognition or gratitude, and be careful that our vanity doesn’t take over. We’ve got to try and work intensely even when no one may see the results, when those results may remain hidden or pass unnoticed. Maybe they will be discovered or seen or appreciated by future generations. St. Josemaría liked to say we have to plant trees in whose shade others will bask.</p>

<p>One clear manifestation of the fact that we are trying to give glory to God in all that we do is to struggle to get the norms of our <em>plan of life</em> fulfilled every day, even when it’s difficult, when there are deadlines, when there are exams, when there’s pressure.</p>

<p>Try and give priority to the things of God.</p>

<p>Or when we have to put in the extra effort to get our work done on time, or the effort to be punctual for family gatherings. When we’re giving glory to God all throughout our day, we give off the good odor of Christ.</p>

<p>I was giving a class once in another country and I happened to quote in the class a phrase from St. Paul, who says, “In all that you’re doing, in eating and in drinking, give glory to God” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>There was a lady who had been a convert to Catholicism in the class, and suddenly she was struck very much by the Holy Spirit with this phrase. She said she got a lot out of it. For her, it seemed to sum up the whole spirit of Opus Dei.</p>

<p>She told me that after the class, she went out to her car and there was a bit of a mess on the front seat, on the floor of the car, and she tidied that up a little bit because she realized she had to try and give glory to God in everything.</p>

<p>She was a lawyer, and sometimes lawyers’ offices have a lot of files all over the place. When she got to her office, she put the files back in their place, and the secretary came into the office and wondered what earthquake in reverse had hit this place. The lady said, “I’m trying to give glory to God in everything that I do.”</p>

<p>She told me that every evening she would watch the news with her husband, and halfway through the news he would ask her for a cup of tea, and she would go downstairs to get a cup of tea but sometimes, grinding her teeth. But this time she had the tea ready. He asked her, “What’s come over you?” She said, “I’m trying to give glory to God.”</p>

<p>We can find ways and means of giving glory to God in the ordinary little challenges of each day, putting virtues into practice, and having a loving service orientation with everything that we do. Not wanting to be anybody in life, in our family, in our profession; being willing to just be a nobody—because someday we will be a nobody.</p>

<p>One way of giving the glory to God as we go through the day is to repeat the <em>Morning Offering</em>: “I offer you all my thoughts, words, actions, sufferings, feelings of this day.”</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro del Portillo had a nice phrase where he used to say that with one act of love, we can make up for many lacks of love. That’s a rather encouraging thought through our day, that one act of Jesus in the Blessed Sacrament or of Our Lady can make up for all the other moments of negligence when we’ve been distracted or thinking about other things.</p>

<p>The interruptions of our day, the changes of plans, the pieces of not such good news—all these things are meant to sanctify us so that we live a certain peace in all these things.</p>

<p>Each time the phone rings or we get a WhatsApp message, it can be seen as a divine call to give glory to God in this particular moment.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, we’re told, “You are ambitious: for knowledge, for leadership, for great ventures. Good, very good. But let it be for Christ, for love” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 24).</p>

<p>In one passage of the Gospel, we’re told, “They came to Capernaum, and when he was in the house he asked them, ‘What were you discussing on the way?’ But they were silent, because on the way they had [discussed] with one another about who was the greatest.</p>

<p>“Jesus sat down and called the Twelve. And he said to them, ‘If any one of you would be first, he must be last of all and the servant of all.’ And he took a child and put him in the midst of them, and taking him in his arms, he said to them, ‘Whoever receives one such child in my name receives me, and whoever receives me, receives not me but him who sent me’” (Mark 9:33-37).</p>

<p>The disciples must have been rather ashamed when Our Lord overheard them arguing about which one of them was the greatest. That appetite for glory and greatness can be inbred in us. We can cherish the ambition to be somebody whom others admire, rather than a nobody.</p>

<p>If it’s the will of God that we are that somebody, wonderful. Give glory to God in that situation. It’s a really good human ambition to have. But at the same time, to be ready someday to be that nobody.</p>

<p>And in the face of those dramatic gestures on the part of the apostles, Our Lord made another very dramatic gesture. He embraces a child to show His disciples who really is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>“What can a little child possibly teach us about greatness? Children in the ancient world had no rights, no position, no privileges of their own. Socially, they were at the bottom of the rung, at the service of their parents, much like the household staff or domestic servants” (Don Schwager<em>, The Gospel of Luke</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lord’s lesson that He’s teaching the apostles is a pretty strong lesson.</p>

<p>There can be no share in God’s glory without the cross. All the challenges that we can have in the 21st century, things that can happen to us that we never imagined might happen to us—unemployment, financial difficulties, health problems, weight of work on our shoulders, abandoned by loved ones—these all may be characteristics of the saints of the 21st century.</p>

<p>In all those difficult situations that Our Lord may permit in our life, He wants us to learn to give Him glory in those moments; to say, “Here I am, because you have called me” (1 Sam. 3:5).</p>

<p>“That gesture of Our Lord’s elevating a little child in the presence of His disciples is very significant. … The one who is humble and lowly of heart, who, instead of asserting their rights, willingly empty themselves of pride and self-seeking glory by taking the lowly position of a servant or of a child” (Schwager, <em>ibid</em>.)—that’s the person that Christ admires.</p>

<p>Jesus Himself is our model. “Though he was by nature God, he did not consider being equal to God a thing to be clung to, but emptied himself, taking the nature of a slave and being made like unto men and appearing in the form of man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient unto death, even unto death on the cross” (Phil. 2:6-8).</p>

<p>Our Lord emptied Himself in order to give God all the glory. Often, He passed unnoticed. He shunned praise, disappeared from the people who wanted to make Him King, lowered Himself to take on our lowly nature, that He might raise us up and clothe us with His divine nature. “God opposes the proud but gives his grace to the humble” (James 4:6).</p>

<p>“If we want to be filled with God’s life and power, we need to empty ourselves of everything that stands in the way, of pride, of self-seeking glory, of vanity” (<em>cf</em>. Schwager, <em>idem</em>.).</p>

<p>God wants empty vessels so that He can fill them with His own glory, with His power, and with His love (<em>cf</em>. 2 Cor. 4:7).</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, St. Josemaría says, “<em>Deo omni gloria</em>. All the glory to God. It is an emphatic confession of our nothingness. He, Jesus, is everything. We, without him, are worth nothing: nothing. Our vainglory would be just that, vain glory; it would be a sacrilegious robbery. There should be no room for that ‘I’ anywhere” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 780).</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture that we “cannot serve two masters” (Matt. 6:24). We have to try to be giving glory to God in all that we do. Even in our prayer, we could be doing it for the wrong reasons, as we see in the parable of the Pharisee and the publican (Luke 18:9-14).</p>

<p>The Pharisee was giving glory to himself. We can be praying for the wrong reasons: to get it done, so that we can feel good, so that we can tell other people that we’ve done it. We can forget that God is waiting for us in each moment.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría had a short prayer that he used to use, which said, “Separate from me anything that separates me from you.”</p>

<p>In the living out of our Christian vocation, in our daily work, in our apostolate, in our family life, in the ordinary things of each day, we have to try and seek moments to give God all the glory, including when we might be annoyed about something, or we’re not feeling well, or we’re tired, or we made a mistake and we’re wrong, or we’ve been passed over, or not told, or not consulted, or not informed.</p>

<p>We have to try and do things for God’s glory, not just because this happens to be the most efficient way of doing things.</p>

<p>This can apply also to the small ordinary tasks in the house that need to be taken care of: making our bed, closing a door, opening a window. With St. Peter, we can try to say, “Lord, you know all things; you know that I love you” (John 21:17).</p>

<p>We give God glory when we make the effort to get the norms of our <em>plan of life</em> done. A lady stood up at a get-together with Blessed Álvaro in Dublin many years ago and she said that she had eight children, and she had to do the ironing and the washing and the marketing and the cleaning and everything in the family, a big, long list of things.</p>

<p>Then she asked, “How can I find time in my busy day to fulfill the norms of a <em>plan of life</em>?” And Blessed Álvaro said, “The litany of things that you have to do are very many. It’s true, you’re a very busy person. But,” he said, “you’ve left something out of your list. You’ve left God out of your list. If you put God into your list and you put Him first, you’ll find you’ll have time for all the other things.”</p>

<p>Giving God all the glory often means putting Him first; taking care of little things; offering our work before we do it, when we’ve finished it, in the meantime when we lift our eyes from what we’re doing, pause for a few moments, we offer it to Him again; when we make little acts of contrition during the day; when we have the joy of giving God the glory that perhaps we have denied Him in previous hours.</p>

<p>In that way, we realize that nothing gets lost. Everything works out for the good when we ask Our Lord that all our actions might be inspired by Him and might be truly brought to completion.</p>

<p>We can say: Lord, may everything I do be pleasing in your eyes. Help me to turn to you occasionally during the day, and, as it were, say a <em>Gloria</em>: “Glory to God in the highest” (Luke 2:14).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Reject any ambition for honors. Think instead about your duties, how to do them well, and the instruments you need to accomplish them.</p>

<p>”—In this way, you will not hanker for position, and if one comes you will see it just as it is: a burden to bear in the service of souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 976).</p>

<p>We can try to also be attentive to what the Holy Father is saying, what are his intentions, so that we’re grazing where he is grazing, asking for what he’s asking.</p>

<p>That desire to give God all the glory, in the final analysis, is a fruit of charity. And charity does not seek its own interests.</p>

<p>A lack of giving God glory can decrease the effectiveness of our apostolate. Pride and vanity that may rear their ugly heads can make a mess of things.</p>

<p>We can ask the Holy Spirit for lights to see where I might not be giving God the glory that is His due.</p>

<p>We’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “The understanding that so many people demand of others is that everyone should join their party” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 576).</p>

<p>In another point in <em>The Way</em>, it says, “It only takes a second. Before setting about anything, ask yourself: What does God want of me in this? Then with divine grace, do it!” (<em>ibid</em>., <em>The Way</em>, Point 778).</p>

<p>And in <em>The Forge</em>, “‘I can do all things in him who strengthens me’ (Phil. 4:13). With him, there is no possibility of failure, and this conviction gives rise to the holy ‘superiority complex’ whereby we take on things with the spirit of victory, because God grants us his strength” (<em>ibid</em>., <em>The Forge</em>, Point 337).</p>

<p>Our determination to live as children of God should be realized in ordinary life: at work, in the home, among our friends. At every hour of the day we should be striving to be men and women of faith, full-time Christians.</p>

<p>We can’t confine our relationship with God to those few moments we spend inside a church. We have to live out our friendship with God in the middle of the world, in our workplace, in our recreation, in social gatherings.</p>

<p>We should reflect Christ’s love in everything we do. St. Paul said to the Corinthians, “So, whether you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do it all to the glory of God” (1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>St. Basil, commenting on that passage, said, “When you sit down at table, pray. When you eat your bread, give thanks to God who is so generous. If you have some wine, remember that he has created it to bring us merriment and comfort in affliction. When you are getting dressed, give thanks to the one who gave you those clothes. When you look up at the firmament and behold the beauty of the stars above, fall down at the feet of God and adore his infinite Wisdom that is manifest in all Creation. Do the same at sunrise and sunset when you’re asleep and when you are awake. Give thanks to God who created all this wonder for your benefit so that you might know, love, and praise his name” (Basil of Caesarea, <em>Homily on the Martyr Julitta</em>).</p>

<p>All noble realities should serve to bring us to God, to give Him glory. When someone is in love, they think of their beloved twenty-four hours a day. That’s the sort of love we should have for Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>It should constitute the essence of our being, the driving force of all our actions. He is Our One and Only Lord. He is the one we want to glorify through our work well done.</p>

<p>Jesus is our inspiration when we try to practice the social doctrine of the Church, when we strive to protect the environment.</p>

<p>This all-embracing outlook leads a Christian to make an effort to be cordial and optimistic, to be punctual at work, to make good use of time, to overcome temptations to laziness.</p>

<p>If our love of God is authentic, it will shine out from and be appreciable in every aspect of our existence. “In all that you do,” said St. Paul, “give him glory” (<em>cf</em>. Col. 3:23).</p>

<p>A wrong intention destroys the best of actions. The deed can be well done, it can even be beneficial, but if it’s corrupted at source, it loses all its value in the eyes of God. Vanity or self-seeking can destroy what could have been a deed meriting holiness. Without a right intention, we go astray.</p>

<p>Many times, during the day, we need to remind ourselves that I am here to give God glory. On some occasions, receiving some praise is a sign of friendship and can help us along the path of goodness. But we should direct that praise towards God in all simplicity.</p>

<p>It’s one thing to receive a word of praise, a sign of being well received; it’s another thing altogether to look for praise. We must always be careful and attentive when we are praised or commended, since, as St. Gregory the Great said, “…many times our poor soul goes off the right path, as soon as it is applauded…thus it finds its delight more in being called happy than in actually being so. And that thing which should have been a reason for praising God becomes instead a cause of our separation from him” (Gregory the Great, <em>Moralia in Job).</em></p>

<p>In the Gospel, Our Lord points out the result of good deeds done without a right intention: “They have received their reward” (Matt. 6:2,5,16), He says, referring to the Pharisees, who wanted to be praised and well thought of.</p>

<p>They got what they wanted: a glance of approval, a gesture of admiration, some words of praise. Shortly, there would be nothing left but dust, and nothing at all for eternal life. A terrible failure to lose so much for so little.</p>

<p>God accepts our actions, even very small ones, if we offer them to Him with that pure intention of giving Him glory. The two small coins that the poor widow threw into the offering box of the Temple became a great treasure in heaven (Mark 12:42).</p>

<p>Our Lord contemplates our lives and has His hand outstretched each day for what we can offer Him. He accepts whatever we really do for Him. We get our own sad recompense for the rest here below.</p>

<p>“The suggestions of vanity and pride and the impulses of the flesh are not difficult to recognize,” St. Josemaría says in <em>The Way</em> (Point 788), “…and you fight and, with grace, you conquer. But the motives that inspire you, even in the holiest actions, do not seem clear; and deep down inside you hear a voice which makes you see human reasons in such a subtle way that your soul is invaded by the disturbing thought that you don’t act as you should—for pure Love, solely and exclusively to give God all his glory. React at once each time and say, ‘Lord, for myself I want nothing. All for your glory and for Love.’”</p>

<p>This was the attitude of Our Lady when she learned the plans that God had for her. “Behold, the handmaid of the Lord…”—I’m just here to serve, to do whatever it is that you want. —“Be it done unto me according to your word” (Luke 1:38).</p>

<p>The life of Our Lady was a life of continual praise and glory to God. Mary, may you help us to live in that same way.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning to Ask</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning to Ask" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“He has filled the hungry with good things, and the rich he has sent away empty” (Luke 1:53).</p>

<p>We should pray frequently about our divine filiation.</p>

<p>Our Lord had the habit of praying early in the morning and in out-of-the-way places. We’re told in St. Matthew that after sending the crowds away, “He went up into the hills by himself to pray. When evening came, he was there alone” (Matt. 14:23).</p>

<p>And in St. Mark, we’re told, “In the morning, long before daybreak, he got up and left the house and went off to a lonely place, and there he prayed” (Mark 1:35).</p>

<p>Likewise in St. Luke: “He would go off to some deserted place and pray” (Luke 5:16).</p>

<p>“Now it happened that he was praying alone and his disciples came to him. And he put the question to them: ‘Who do the crowds say that I am?’” (Luke 9:18).</p>

<p>The disciples often found Our Lord thoroughly absorbed in conversation with His Heavenly Father. We’re told also in St. Luke, “He was praying in a certain place, and when he ceased, one of his disciples said to him, ‘Lord, teach us to pray’” (Luke 11:1).</p>

<p>We are very much in need of making the same request to Our Lord: Jesus, teach me how to deal with you. Tell me what I should ask you for.</p>

<p>We should do this because we can often find ourselves in front of God without knowing what to say to Him or how we should speak to Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord answered His disciple’s request with the perfect prayer, the <em>Our Father</em>. He must have pronounced every word with care. He taught them how to put all their trust in prayer to their Father God.</p>

<p>He said, “Which of you has a friend who will go to him at midnight and say to him, ‘Friend, lend me three loaves, for a friend of mine has arrived on a journey and I have nothing to set before him.’ … I tell you, though he will not get up and give him anything because he is his friend, yet because of his insisting, he will rise and give him whatever he needs” (Luke 11:5-6,8).</p>

<p>Whenever we’re talking to God, most probably we’re asking Him for something. That’s because we’re children of God, children in need. For His part, God only wants to spend Himself on us.</p>

<p>When my mother heard us saying, “I want this, I want that,” she had a frequent phrase which she would say: “Well, you never stop wanting.” Children are like that. We never stop wanting. Our Father God knows it.</p>

<p>He says, “What father among you, if his son asks for a fish, would instead of a fish give him a serpent? Or if he asks for an egg, will give him a scorpion?” (Luke 11:11-12).</p>

<p>We should go to the tabernacle, exactly as the sick and suffering used to go to Jesus.</p>

<p>John Paul, in explaining prayer, said, “Prayer means feeling one’s own insufficiency through the various necessities which man has to face, necessities that are part of his life. Such as, for example, the need for bread to which Christ refers in the example of that man who wakes up his friend at midnight to ask him for bread. Similar necessities are numerous.</p>

<p>“The need for bread is, in a way, a symbol of all the material necessities, the necessities of the human body, the necessities of this existence which springs from the fact that man has a body. But the range of these necessities is wider” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>Humility is a prerequisite [to] confident conversation with God. We need to realize who He is and who we are. We need to realize our limitations before we can appreciate how much we depend on Our Father God.</p>

<p>John Paul says, “To learn to pray means ‘to learn the Father.’ If we learn the ‘Father’ reality in the full sense of the word, in its full dimension, we have learned everything. … To learn who the Father is means learning what absolute trust is. To learn the Father means acquiring the certainty that he absolutely cannot refuse anything.</p>

<p>“This is all said in the Gospel (Luke 11:1-13). He does not refuse you even when everything, materially and psychologically, seems to indicate refusal. He never refuses you” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>A little girl once asked Santa Claus, Father Christmas, for a thousand dolls for Christmas. Her father was an atheist. She got one doll.</p>

<p>He said to her, “Well, your God didn’t listen to your prayer, did he?” The little girl said, “Yes, he did. He said ‘No.’”</p>

<p>It was as though she was saying to her father, “God is my Father, you’re also my father. Sometimes you say ‘No.’ You don’t always say ‘Yes.’ But I know that even if He says ‘No,’ He always listens.”</p>

<p>He will never abandon us. In our conversation with God, we have to keep in mind our divine filiation and our human limitations.</p>

<p>We should ask God for spiritual and material goods insofar as they will bring us closer to Him. “For everyone who asks receives, and he who seeks finds, and to him who knocks it shall be opened” (Matt. 7:8).</p>

<p>In our prayer to God, the first things we should seek from Him are spiritual goods—the grace to love Him more each day, the grace to have an authentic desire for sanctity, the goal of our Christian vocation, the grace to do a more fruitful apostolate.</p>

<p>We should also ask God for material goods insofar as they serve to bring us closer to Him. These goods can also include good health, economic well-being, getting a job.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Pray for temporal goods in private, and rest in the knowledge that they come to us from him who knows what is best for us. Did you ask and not get what you wanted? Trust in your Father. If it would have been good for you, you would have received it.</p>

<p>“Before God, you are much as a little child is before you. All day long, the child cries his eyes out so that you will give him a knife to play with. You wisely refuse his plea and pay no attention to his wailing.</p>

<p>“When the child demands to ride your horse, you won’t let him. The child doesn’t know how to ride, and may get injured or even killed as a result.</p>

<p>“You deny him in little things, so as to preserve more important things. You want the child to grow up safely and possess all his own goods without danger” (Augustine, <em>Sermon 80</em>).</p>

<p>And so, that little girl who didn’t get a thousand dolls for Christmas—she knew that her Father God was listening. In only getting one doll, He gave her what she needed or what was important. She can be at peace, trusting her Father God.</p>

<p>And that’s how Our Lord is with us. Many times we’re like the child who doesn’t realize what he’s asking for.</p>

<p>I had a niece many years ago, and a big tree fell down close to their garden. It was all fallen down and the tree had been put in half.</p>

<p>She brought me out to the garden and pointed to the tree and said, “Can you fix that?” Little children don’t know what they’re asking for at times.</p>

<p>Our Father God always wants what’s best for us. Our happiness will always be found in our full identification with the Divine Will. ‘Lord, if you don’t want to give me this thing, then it’s okay. I realize this isn’t the time, it’s not the moment. It’s not the right thing for me.’</p>

<p>Even though what God wills may sometimes not seem so appealing from a human point of view, it necessarily leads to what is in our best interests.</p>

<p>John Paul II once recalled how impressed he was by the cheerfulness of a man he met in a hospital during the Warsaw Uprising in the Second World War.</p>

<p>He said, “This man achieved happiness by some other way because visibly, judging by his physical state from the medical point of view, there was no reason for him to be so happy, to feel so well, and to consider himself heard by God. Yet he was heard in another aspect of his humanity” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>This aspect was the identification of His human will with the Divine Will. We have to want the will of God: “Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven” (Matt. 6:10; the prayer, <em>Our Father</em>). This is the best path to follow. It’s the one prepared for us by Our Lord.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “Tell him: Lord, I want nothing other than what you want. Even those things I am asking you for at present, if they take me an inch away from your Will, don’t give them to me” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 512).</p>

<p>‘If you don’t want these things, why should I? You know best. Your Will be done.’</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture about the prayer of Abraham, his prayer for those cities who had offended God. He asked, “Will you indeed destroy the righteous with the wicked? Suppose there are fifty righteous within the city, will you then destroy the place and not spare it for the fifty righteous who are in it?” (Gen. 18:23-24).</p>

<p>Abraham tries to save the cities from destruction by giving his beloved God a hard time. He makes his case to God that even a small number of holy people are an immense treasure.</p>

<p>Our Lord takes such great pleasure in those who love Him that He is ready to forgive thousands of sinners for the sake of a handful of just people. God is willing to forget the sins and iniquities of entire cities for the sake of the love and the adoration of ten people (Gen. 18:32).</p>

<p>This is an unmistakable teaching for all of us who seek to follow Our Lord closely. We may at times be tempted to question the merit of our struggle when there are so many people around us who live without a care for God and His rights.</p>

<p>One day, Our Lord will show us the enormous effectiveness of our humble prayers, of the sacrifices made by a mother for her family’s welfare, of the sufferings offered up by a sick person for the Church, of the merit of an hour of study or work converted into prayer.</p>

<p>Yahweh was willing to save Sodom and Gomorrah for the sake of only ten just men. According to divine logic, the good works of a few people can outweigh in value the sins of thousands.</p>

<p>When we struggle to be faithful to Our Lord, we are bound to experience the joy of knowing that we are pleasing Him, for God listens attentively to our prayer.</p>

<p>We ought to pray every day for our society, a society which seems to be moving farther and farther away from its Creator. John Paul II pointed out in this regard, “I think that Abraham’s prayer and its content is very relevant for the times in which we live. Such a prayer is so necessary, to negotiate with God for every just man, to redeem the world from injustice” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>“See what love the Father has given us,” we’re told in St. John, “that we should be called children of God, and such we are” (1 John 3:1).</p>

<p>Awareness of our divine filiation gives meaning to our day. We’re told in the Psalms, “I have been set by him as a king on Zion, his holy mountain, to tell of his decrees. The Lord said to me: ‘You are my son, today I have begotten you’” (Ps. 2:6-7).</p>

<p>In <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, St. Josemaría says, “The kindness of God Our Father has given us his Son to be our king. ‘You are my son.’ The words are addressed to Christ—and to you and me if we decide to become other Christs” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 185).</p>

<p>That’s what our whole Christian life is all about: to imitate Christ, to identify ourselves with Him. We want to be good children of God in the midst of our work and our normal activities, in spite of our weaknesses.</p>

<p>Jesus came to John, just like one more person, to be baptized in the Jordan. The Holy Spirit descended upon Him, and the voice of the Father could be heard saying, “You are my beloved son” (Mark 1:9-11).</p>

<p>From all eternity, Jesus Christ is the only Son of God. “Eternally begotten of the Father…begotten, not made, of one being with the Father. Through him all things were made” (<em>Nicene Creed</em>). We say these words in the <em>Creed</em> during Mass.</p>

<p>In Him and through Him—true God and true Man—we have been made children of God and heirs to heaven.</p>

<p>Throughout the New Testament, divine filiation occupies a central position in the preaching of the Good News of Christianity. It’s presented as a reality that gives expression to God’s love for men.</p>

<p>“See what love the Father has given us,” says St. John, “that we should be called children of God; and so we are” (1 John 3:1).</p>

<p>Jesus Christ constantly revealed this truth to His disciples. He showed it to them in a direct way, by teaching them to talk to God as their Father (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 6:9).</p>

<p>“When you pray, say: ‘Father, hallowed be thy name…’” (Luke 11:2). He explains sanctity to them in terms of a son imitating his father. “Do not even the Gentiles do as much? You must therefore be perfect, just as your heavenly Father is perfect” (Matt. 5:47-48).</p>

<p>He also developed this truth of divine filiation for them through numerous parables in which God is represented as the father. One particularly moving picture is the picture of Our Father God in the parable of the prodigal son (Luke 15:11-32).</p>

<p>The Prelate of Opus Dei says, “In his infinite goodness, God created man and elevated him to the supernatural order. Through the gift of sanctifying grace, we could enter into the intimacy of the Blessed Trinity, without destroying or distorting that nature proper to us as creatures. He did this through the ineffable gift of divine filiation” (<em>cf</em>. Fernando Ocáriz, <em>God as Father</em>).</p>

<p>He makes us His children. Our divine filiation is not merely a title; it is a real elevation, an effective transformation of our inmost being. That is why “God sent his Son, born of woman…so that we might receive adoption as children. And because you are sons, God has sent the spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying ‘Abba! Father!’ So through God you are no longer a slave but a son, and if a son, then an heir” (Gal. 4:6-7).</p>

<p>Our Lord gained for us the most precious Gift, the Holy Spirit, who makes us cry out, ‘Abba! Father!’, who identifies us with Christ and makes us children of God.</p>

<p>“‘You are my Son’ (Ps. 2:7). Not a stranger,” says St. Josemaría, “not a well-treated servant, not a friend—that would be a lot already. A son!</p>

<p>“He gives us free access to treat him as sons do, with a son’s piety—and I would even say with the boldness and daring of a son whose Father cannot deny him anything” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 185).</p>

<p>“The Lord said to me, ‘You are my son, today I have begotten you’” (Ps. 2:7). These words of the Psalm 2, which refer principally to Christ, are spoken also to each one of us. They can truly make our day and give meaning to our whole life, if we once resolve—in spite of our weakness and frailty—to follow Jesus, to try to imitate Him, to identify ourselves with Him in our own particular circumstances.</p>

<p>In our ascetical struggle we will at times have to consider more deeply the consequences of our divine filiation. At times, this can become the object of our <em>particular struggle</em>.</p>

<p>One writer says, “When we are living as good children of God, we see everything that happens, including the minor occurrences of any ordinary day, in the light of faith, and we become accustomed to thinking and acting constantly in accordance with Christ’s will” (<em>cf .</em> M. Equibar, <em>Why Do the Gentiles Rage</em>?).</p>

<p>In the first place, we try to see ourselves as brothers or sisters of all the people we meet, because we are all children of the same Father. Our appreciation and respect for others will generate within us the same desire that resides in the heart of Christ—the desire for their sanctification.</p>

<p>Another writer says, “Above all, fraternal love will move us to wish that those people should come ever closer to Christ and should be more fully children of Our Father God. We will make our own the concern of Christ for the apostolate, his zeal for the Father’s glory, and the salvation of all mankind” (Bonaventure Perquin, <em>Abba Father</em>).</p>

<p>The manifestations of fraternity, rooted in spiritual childhood, will be countless throughout any one of our days. Prayers for others will remind us. Little opportunities of helping in material things will have their obvious motivation. And understanding for the defects of others will be more readily achieved if we see in them the faults of our brothers and sisters.</p>

<p>Spiritual childhood is just one more aspect of our lives. [Fr. Ocáriz] says it determines our whole supernatural character and shows us how to deal with every situation. “It is not a particular virtue that has its own acts, but the permanent condition of our being, suffusing and permeating all the other virtues” (Fernando Ocáriz, <em>op</em>. <em>cit</em>.).</p>

<p>Whatever the circumstances or the situations that affect us, we are children of God, and this firm conviction fills the whole of our life and our entire way of behaving.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “We are children of God all day long, even though we set aside special moments for considering it, so that we can fill ourselves with awareness of our divine filiation, which is the essence of true piety” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 102).</p>

<p>If we frequently consider this truth—I am a child of God—if we go deeper into its meaning, our day will be filled with peace, serenity, joy.</p>

<p>We will make a resolution to rely on God Our Father, on whom everything depends, especially when difficulties and disappointments arise, when sometimes we seem to be fighting an uphill battle (<em>cf</em>. J. Lucas, <em>We Are Children of God</em>).</p>

<p>It will be easier for us to return to Our Father’s house, like the prodigal son, if we should ever leave it through our faults and sins. We will not lose sight of this truth, that Our Father is waiting to embrace us and to give us back our dignity as His children, if ever we lose it.</p>

<p>He’s waiting to fill us with good things, with a splendid banquet, even though we may have behaved badly a thousand times and more.</p>

<p>Our prayer, just like these moments we are dedicating exclusively to God, will really be the conversation of a child with his father. The son knows that his father understands him, that he listens to him, that he gives him the whole of his attention in a way that nobody else has ever done.</p>

<p>It’s a conversation with God that’s full of trust. It moves us frequently to a prayer of petition because we’re small and needy children. It’s a conversation with God that has our life as its theme.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em> we’re told, “Everything that is on our mind and in our heart: our joys, sorrows, hopes, disappointments, successes, failures, even the most trivial happenings in our day. We will discover that Our Heavenly Father is interested in everything about us” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 245).</p>

<p>We can finish our prayer today with that resolution, that we must pray more as children of the Father. With the conviction that we have to turn to Our Lord frequently every day. Like those many sick people in the Gospels, we need to be brought to Jesus to be cured.</p>

<p>Our Lady will teach us how to have the daring of little children in our petitions. We ask her to help us to do an effective apostolate where we live and work.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JSD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Our Way to The House of Our Father</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Our Way to The House of Our Father" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in the Book of Revelation, “Then he showed me the river of the water of life, bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and of the Lamb through the middle of the street of the city; also, on either side of the river, the tree of life with its twelve kinds of fruit. … There shall no more be anything accursed, but the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it, and his servants shall worship him. They shall see his face, and his name shall be on their foreheads” (Rev. 22:1-4).</p>

<p>Scripture draws to a close where it all began: in the Garden of Eden, in Paradise. The Scriptures speak to us about our final destination: the house of the Father, our true homeland.</p>

<p>Through the rich use of symbols, God teaches us in the <em>Book of Revelation</em> about the nature of eternal life. This is the fulfillment of man’s deepest yearnings. We are to see God face to face and glorify Him forever.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to say that marriage in this world is a preparation for marriage in the next. The real marriage comes later. People who lead celibate lives in this world give witness to the fact that the real marriage comes later.</p>

<p>If we have some cross or some challenge or some difficulty, or our marriage did not work out to be everything that we dreamt of—never mind, that’s part of the preparation. We have great things to look forward to: the “eternal wedding feast” (Pope John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Evangelii gaudium</em>, Point 288, November 24, 2013).</p>

<p>In the Book of Revelation, it says this water is a symbol of the Holy Spirit who proceeds from the Father and the Son. It runs as a river from the throne of God and of the Lamb. The Name of God is to be found on the foreheads of the blessed. They belong to the Lord.</p>

<p>In heaven, “night shall be no more. They shall need no light of lamp or sun, for the Lord God will be their light, and they shall reign forever and ever” (Rev. 22:5).</p>

<p>Death is an indispensable step towards our reunion with God. Children of God should view death as a transition to eternity, a change of home, a change of place. Jumping over the pool that separates us from this and heaven.</p>

<p>Once we’re in God’s company, “night shall be no more.” To the extent that we grow in our sense of divine filiation, we should become more desirous of meeting Our loving Father.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Way</em> used to say, “Foster in your heart the glorious hope of heaven” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 668). That means we can look at death without fear, but with holy expectation.</p>

<p>“Life is a journey towards eternity,” Pope John Paul II said. “Every moment becomes precious precisely through this perspective. We live and work in time, beating within us the nostalgia for heaven” (John Paul II, <em>Address</em>, October 22, 1985).</p>

<p>Nevertheless, we’re well aware that many, many people don’t share this “nostalgia for heaven.” They may have grown accustomed to their prosperity and material comfort, as if these things were to last forever. They’ve forgotten that fundamental truth: “Here we have no lasting city, but we seek for the city which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). Our hearts were made to last for all eternity. The things of this world cannot satisfy our nature. They can therefore become an obstacle to our eternal happiness.</p>

<p>We Christians have a great love of life and of all noble earthly realities: friendship, work, joy, human love. As a consequence, we shouldn’t be surprised that the prospect of death frightens us. This is quite natural.</p>

<p>But our body and soul were created by God to be united with Him forever. In the <em>Preface</em> for Masses for the Dead, the Church prays: “Lord, for your faithful people, life is changed, not ended, and when the body of our earthly dwelling lies in death, we gain an everlasting dwelling place in heaven.”</p>

<p>The true child of God “expresses his joy in seeing at last the transcendent perfections of the Father in all his holiness. The child recognizes the condescension of Infinite Majesty in adopting him on earth, in guiding, training, sanctifying, and preparing him for heaven.</p>

<p>“He has invited that child to enter heaven, to be with his Father for all eternity. God [has had] regard for his littleness and gave him the power to glorify the Trinity forever” (Bonaventure Perquin, <em>Abba, Father</em>).</p>

<p>We have good reason to exclaim, as St. Josemaría did: “We shall never die! We will only be changing our lodgings, nothing more. In conjunction with faith and hope, we Christians also need to have this sure hope. At our death, we make only a temporary farewell. We should want to die in the spirit of those words: ‘Until we meet again’” (J. Escrivá, <em>Newsletter No. 1</em>).</p>

<p>In the Book of Daniel it says, “The saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom forever, forever and ever” (Dan. 7:18). We’ll find that everything appears new and young in heaven.</p>

<p>The <em>Book of Revelation</em> says the old universe will seem to have vanished “like a scroll that is rolled up” (Rev. 6:14). And yet heaven will not be a complete surprise for us. It is, after all, the focus of the deepest yearnings of every person, even of the most depraved sinner.</p>

<p>Heaven is the new community of the children of God who have attained to the fullness of their adoption. We will have a new heart and a new will. At the time of Christ’s glory, our bodies will be transfigured.</p>

<p>Interestingly enough, this happiness based on the vision of God will not override personal relations. We’re told by one writer, “There in heaven will be found all authentic human love: the love between spouses, the love between a father and his children, friendships, family relations, noble camaraderie…</p>

<p>“We are all traveling in this life. As the years go by, we find that more and more of our loved ones are now on the other side of that barrier.</p>

<p>“This knowledge might be a source of fear, but can also be a cause for joy. This is possible if we believe that death is the door to our true home. It leads to our definitive homeland which is inhabited by ‘all those who have gone before us marked with the sign of faith.’ Our common homeland is not a forbidding tomb, but the bosom of the Lord” (Camilo Lopez-Pardo, <em>On Life and Death</em>).</p>

<p>While here on earth, we find it quite difficult to imagine what heaven will be like. The Old Testament compares our condition in heaven to that of the Promised Land. In the Book of Isaiah it says: “They shall not hunger or thirst, neither scorching wind nor sun shall smite them, for he who has pity on them will lead them, and by springs of water will guide them” (Isa. 49:10). Our Lord frequently spoke of the incredible happiness that lies in store for us if we are faithful.</p>

<p>The soul and all its faculties, along with our glorified bodies, will be divinized, though there will still remain an infinite difference between creature and Creator. We will contemplate God as He truly is.</p>

<p>In addition, the blessed will delight in the knowledge of other people in God—for example, parents, relatives, spouse, children, and friends. St. Thomas teaches that the blessed will know in Christ everything that pertains to the beauty and integrity of the world. Because of our membership in the human community, the blessed will know the objects of Christ’s love on earth.</p>

<p>The blessed, says St. Thomas, will have a clear understanding of the truths of the faith regarding our salvation: the Incarnation, the divine maternity of Mary, the Church, grace, and the sacraments (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part I, Question 89).</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría has written: “Think how pleasing to Our Lord is the incense burnt in his honor. Think also how little the things of the earth are worth; even as they begin, they are already ending.</p>

<p>“In heaven, instead, a great Love awaits you, with no betrayals and no deceptions. The fullness of love, the fullness of beauty and greatness and knowledge. … And it will never cloy: it will satiate, yet still you will want more” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 995).</p>

<p>In heaven, we will see God, and that will fill us with great joy. The extent of this joy will be related to our holiness here on this earth.</p>

<p>Yet the mercy of God is so great that He has prepared additional motives for our joy in heaven. Theologians have termed these goods “accidental glory.” They include being in the company of Jesus Christ glorified, Mary Our Mother, St. Joseph, the angels—particularly our guardian angel—and all the saints.</p>

<p>We will have the joy of being with our loved ones: parents, brothers and sisters, friends, those people who showed us our vocation.</p>

<p>In heaven we will also be capable of acquiring new knowledge using our faculties (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, <em>op. cit</em>.).</p>

<p>The <em>Catechism of the Council of Trent</em> says we shall have the joy of seeing new souls enter heaven. We shall be able to see the progress of our friends on earth. We shall see the fruits of our apostolic efforts and sacrifices. At the time of the Last Judgment, we shall possess our resurrected and glorified body. Accidental glory can increase up to the time of the Last Judgment.</p>

<p>We have to foster the virtue of hope so that it will strengthen us in moments of difficulty. So much is at stake. We have to be vigilant in our struggle to be detached from the things of earth.</p>

<p>Our Lord has given us ample warning. In St. Luke, He says, “But take heed to yourselves lest your hearts be weighed down with dissipation and drunkenness and the cares of this life… But watch at all times, praying that you may have strength to escape all these things that will take place, and to stand before the Son of Man” (Luke 21:34,36).</p>

<p>We can also be consoled by the words of Our Lord when He says, “I go to prepare a place for you” (John 14:2). Heaven is our definitive homeland. There we will enjoy the company of Jesus and Mary. Here we are but wayfarers.</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro said, “And when the moment comes when we are to give an account to God, we will not be afraid. Death will only be a change of lodgings. It will come when God wants, being that liberation, that point of entry into the fullness of life. As the <em>Preface</em> for the Mass of the Dead says, ‘Life is changed, not taken away.’ Life changes; it does not come to an end.</p>

<p>“We have a firm hope that we will live in a new way, very united to the Blessed Virgin, as we adore the Most Holy Trinity. This is the reward that awaits us” (Álvaro del Portillo, <em>Homily</em>, August 15, 1989).</p>

<p>But Our Lord also warned us about the cities that would not be converted. He had spent a great deal of time in the cities along the shores of Lake Gennesaret. He granted countless miracles and favors to these people, and yet they would not be converted.</p>

<p>They did not know how to receive the Messiah, about whom they’d heard so much in their synagogues. This was the reason for Our Lord to complain: “Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the mighty works done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago, sitting in sackcloth and ashes. … And you, Capernaum, will you be exalted to heaven? You shall be brought down to Hades” (Luke 10:13,15).</p>

<p>Jesus had sown abundant seed, and precious little of it had borne fruit in those places. Incredible signs had been multiplied, one on top of the other, but the people were not moved to penance.</p>

<p>Without this conversion and a life of sacrifice, it was unlikely that they would recognize Christ in their midst. Tyre and Sidon were burdened with less responsibility since they had received fewer graces.</p>

<p>“The Holy Spirit says, ‘Today, when you hear his voice, do not harden your hearts…” (Heb. 3:7-8). God speaks to men and women throughout the ages. Christ continues to pass through our cities and towns, showering innumerable blessings upon us.</p>

<p>To know how to listen to His Will and fulfill it right away is of capital importance in our lives. Nothing is more important. We need to listen with great docility to the invitations that Christ gives in the heart of each individual.</p>

<p>We’re told by St. Gregory, “God is not to blame when the faith fails to spring up among men. The reason is to be found in the unreadiness of those who have heard the divine [word]” (Gregory Nazianzen, <em>Oratio catechetica magna</em>).</p>

<p>Holy Scripture calls this resistance to grace “hardness of heart” (<em>cf</em>. Ex. 4:21; Rom. 9:18). Men sometimes pose intellectual difficulties as inhibiting their growth in faith when the real problem lies in their lack of desire. Perhaps they just don’t want to abandon some bad habit. They may not be willing to struggle seriously to overcome some defect that impedes their friendship with the Lord.</p>

<p>Mortification prepares the soul to listen to the Lord and to follow His Will. St. John Mary Vianney says, “If we want to reach God, we will have to mortify the soul and all its powers” (Jean Vianney, <em>Sermon on Ash Wednesday</em>).</p>

<p>Mortification can convert our souls into the good soil that will bring the divine seed to fruition. We have to weed out and burn those thorns that tend to flourish in the soul: laziness, egoism, envy, curiosity.</p>

<p>This is why the Church recommends that we review our spirit of penance and mortification. This spirit will lead us to be more generous in our imitation of Christ on the Cross. Closely related to mortification is that happiness which we all find so necessary.</p>

<p>Anyone who intends to live their Christian faith seriously needs to put off “the old nature with its practices” (Col. 3:9).</p>

<p>One writer says this “old nature” consists in “the variety of bad inclinations we have inherited from Adam. It is the triple concupiscence which we need to control through the exercise of mortification” (Adolphe Tanquerey, <em>The Spiritual Life</em>).</p>

<p>Mortification is not recommended as a negative action. On the contrary, it’s meant to rejuvenate the soul. Mortification makes the soul better disposed to receive supernatural gifts. It also helps us to make reparation for our past sins.</p>

<p>This is why we frequently pray to Our Lord to grant us “a time of true penance, a time of reformation of our life” (<em>cf</em>. Roman Missal, <em>Formula intentionis Misae</em>). By means of the Communion of Saints we give help and strength to other members of the Mystical Body which is the Church.</p>

<p>There are three main areas for daily mortification in our ordinary lives.</p>

<p>Firstly, there’s the heartfelt and serene acceptance of the contradictions that each day brings. In most cases, this refers to the very small things that crop up unexpectedly and that force us to change our plans or adjust our expectations. An example might be a minor illness that interferes with our performance at work or that affects family life.</p>

<p>Other examples could include having to put up with inclement weather, or heavy traffic, or the difficult personality of a colleague at work. These circumstances are beyond our personal control. We have to see them as providing opportunities to love God even more. None of these problems should take away our peace and joy.</p>

<p>One writer says, “If these small contradictions are not accepted for the sake of love, they will only succeed in making people become frustrated and irritable. The great majority of our frustrations come from small contradictions which we have not accepted, rather than from major disasters.</p>

<p>The person who lies awake at night, who is gloomy, who is in a bad humor, has usually not suffered some great blow. They’ve simply been unable to turn small setbacks into encounters with God” (Ángel Garcia Dorronsoro, <em>Time to Believe</em>). Such a one loses many chances to grow in virtue.</p>

<p>In addition, when the soul gets into the habit of accepting small reverses as divine favors, it becomes better prepared to face more serious trials in union with Our Lord.</p>

<p>One writer says God came into the world “to provide a healing remedy for the root of all our rebellion and misery. He destroyed many things as useless obstacles but chose to leave pain intact. He did not take away pain, but he gave it a new meaning.</p>

<p>“He could have chosen a thousand different ways to accomplish the Redemption of the human race, but he chose the Cross. It was by this path that he has led his Mother Mary, Joseph, the apostles, and all the sons of God [closer and closer to him]. Our Lord allows evils to exist and draws good for our souls from them” (Jesús Urteaga, <em>The Defects of the Saints</em>).</p>

<p>We could make a resolution to convert setbacks of whatever type into occasions for our interior growth.</p>

<p>Another area of daily mortification lies in the conscientious carrying out of our duties: the basic material in our struggle for sanctity. It’s there that we find God’s will for us every day. We need to fulfill our duties with hard work, high standards, and much love.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría wrote that the mortification which is most pleasing to God “is to be found in order, in punctuality, in care for the small details in whatever we do. It has to do with the faithful performance of the most insignificant aspects of our vocation, even when it hurts.</p>

<p>“We need to struggle against the temptation to prefer comfort. We persevere in our work not because we feel like it, but because we know it has to be done. When we work in that frame of mind, we will work with enthusiasm and joy” (J. Escrivá, <em>Letter</em>, October 15, 1948).</p>

<p>The mother of a family will find a thousand reasons to give her home a warm and cheerful atmosphere. The student will offer up his efforts to study well. In this way, tiredness will become one more offering to Our Lord. We can examine our conduct to see whether we complain about our work, grumbling perhaps about something that should be leading us to God.</p>

<p>The third area of our mortification consists in the sacrifices that we make voluntarily in order to please Our Lord, to make ourselves better souls of prayer, in order to overcome temptation, in order to help our friends come closer to God, and ultimately to help our friends prepare for heaven. We should be looking for ways to help others seek sanctity.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Bring out your spirit of mortification in those nice touches of charity, eager to make the way of sanctity in the midst of the world attractive for everyone. Sometimes a smile can be the best proof of a spirit of penance” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 149). We could resolve to overcome our moods and our weariness with the help of our guardian angel.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Psalms: “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. As a deer longs for flowing streams, so longs my soul for you, O God. When shall I come and behold your face?” (Ps. 42:1–2). These are words that are prayed in the liturgy of the Mass.</p>

<p>The deer attempting to quench his thirst with water is the psalmist’s symbolic way of describing the desire for God resident in the heart of an upright person: a thirst and a vehement desire for God. Such is the aspiration of one who is not content to accept worldly success as the satisfaction for human ambitions.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew: “For what will it profit a man if he gains the whole world but forfeits his soul?” Our Lord’s question forces us to take a radical look at the broad horizon of our life, to which only God gives ultimate meaning.</p>

<p>In <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, St. Josemaría says the saints were men and women with a great desire to belong to God completely, in spite of their defects. We could each ask ourselves, “Have I a true desire to be a saint?”</p>

<p>The answer would most assuredly be in the affirmative: yes. But our reply should not be as to a theoretical question—because for some, holiness is “unattainable, something to do with ascetical theology, but not a real goal for them, a living reality” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 96).</p>

<p>We want to make it happen with the help of God’s grace. “So longs my soul for you, O God.” We must start by making the desire for holiness flourish in our soul, telling Our Lord that we really want to be with Him, that we have that authentic yearning for heaven, that we truly want to be on our way all the time, each day, to the house of the Father. We can ask Our Lady, Queen of Heaven, to guide our steps in a regular way.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patience in Adversity</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patience in Adversity" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“But before all this happens, you will be seized and persecuted; you will be handed over to the synagogues and to imprisonment, and brought before kings and governors for the sake of my name. That will be your opportunity to bear witness.</p>

<p>“Make up your minds not to prepare your defense, because I myself shall give you an eloquence and a wisdom that none of your opponents will be able to resist or contradict.</p>

<p>“You will be betrayed even by parents and brothers, relations, and friends, and some of you will be put to death. You will be hated universally on account of my name, but not a hair of your head will be lost. By your patience, you will win your souls” (Luke 21:12-19).</p>

<p>When Our Lord talks about the end times, He talks to us about patience.</p>

<p>He predicts the destruction of Jerusalem, which is going to come to pass some forty years later. His Second Coming will be in power and great glory.</p>

<p>In this particular passage, Our Lord warns His disciples of impending persecution. He exhorts His followers to persevere with patience, no matter what should happen: “By your endurance you will gain your lives and your souls” (Luke 21:19).</p>

<p>In the years that followed, the apostles meditated on Our Lord's warning. He told them: “A servant is not greater than his master. If they persecuted me, they will persecute you” (John 15:20).</p>

<p>Even the worst tribulation has a role to play in God's Providence. God permits contradictions because they can be the cause of greater goods. The early Roman persecutions strengthened the primitive Church and deepened her supernatural spirit.</p>

<p>All this was to fulfill what Our Lord predicted. He said, “In the world you will have tribulation; but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world” (John 16:33).</p>

<p>Life presents us with all manner of problems and trials. Some are great, but some are also of little consequence. With the help of God's grace the soul can be strengthened by every trial.</p>

<p>Certain contradictions can come from other people. There can be direct attacks, or veiled threats from people who don’t understand our calling, or there can be public opposition from a pagan culture, or from people who are declared enemies of the Church.</p>

<p>Other contradictions can have their origin in the limitations of our human nature. We might experience financial difficulties, or health problems, or grave family problems. At times we might become sick or exhausted or completely discouraged.</p>

<p>If we are to persevere in times of adversity, we need patience. We should be cheerful, no matter what happens, because we have our eyes fixed on Christ.</p>

<p>He has encouraged us to move forward, to live in His peace. Our confidence should be anchored in the fact that Christ has been triumphant.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says that patience “is the virtue that allows us to bear adversity with a serene spirit. … We should prize this serenity of soul, because it allows us to obtain greater goods” (Augustine, <em>On Patience, 2</em>).</p>

<p>The Christian should learn how to endure physical and moral hardship without complaining.</p>

<p>Usually, we are presented with many different opportunities to practice this virtue in the ordinary circumstances of everyday life.</p>

<p>There was a kid who was being driven home from school by his mother, a Standard Two or Grade Two child. There was a traffic jam and the mother was getting a bit exasperated.</p>

<p>The Standard Two child pipes up and says, ‘Today, Mommy, we got a talk about patience. The teacher told us that we're in Standard Two; we can't expect to be in Standard Eight. We have to take one day at a time and we have to accept the contradictions of everyday life.’</p>

<p>And this and that, and the child rambled on for quite a few minutes, giving his mother a talk about patience— about this virtue that he had learned in class today.</p>

<p>The mother listened patiently. When he finished, she said, ‘I felt like turning the car around and going back to the school and paying more fees.’</p>

<p>Patience is a powerful virtue. The struggle to live this virtue can relate to very mundane things: a character defect that keeps resurfacing in ourselves or in others, undertakings that don't go as we had planned, unexpected changes in schedule, bad manners of a colleague at work or on the road, people who mean well but don't understand, traffic jams, delays in public transportation, too many phone calls, forgetfulness, queues.</p>

<p>All of these are occasions for us to grow in humility and to become more refined in our charity.</p>

<p>This virtue should not be understood just to mean passivity in the face of suffering. It is a dynamic virtue. We're called to bear well the contradictions of ordinary life.</p>

<p>It is not a matter of stoically accepting the blows of outrageous fortune and accepting our fate. Patience belongs to the virtue of fortitude. It's a character strength. Fortitude is the virtue whereby we face difficulties, put up with problems.</p>

<p>When we practice patience, we strive to accept pain and trial as something coming from the hand of God. Therefore, it is good.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas says, “We therefore seek to identify our will with the Will of God. The virtue of patience enables us to endure persecution of every kind. Patience should be the foundation of our hope and joy” (<em>cf</em>. St. Thomas, <em>Commentary on the Epistle to the Hebrews 10, 35</em>).</p>

<p>There are many ways in which a Christian can practice this virtue. The first battleground can be in the area of our own behavior. It is so easy to become disheartened by our defects.</p>

<p>Patience with ourselves. Good wine improves with time. Sometimes we have to give ourselves time to grow in this virtue or get better at something else.</p>

<p>We need to exercise patience in our interior struggle based on our unshakable confidence in the love that God has for us.</p>

<p>We know He is beside us in our ups and in our downs, in our failures and in our successes, like little children. If we are trying to overcome a character defect, it won't happen overnight.</p>

<p>Our victory will ultimately be won by the cultivation of humility, of a trusting confidence in God, of greater docility.</p>

<p>St. Francis de Sales liked to remind people that we need to have patience with everyone, but first and foremost with ourselves (<em>cf</em>. St. Francis de Sales, <em>Letters</em>).</p>

<p>Whenever we have contact with other people we will encounter opportunities to exercise this virtue. This is certainly the case when we try to help people to receive spiritual formation or when we look after people who are sick.</p>

<p>We also have to exercise patience with regard to unexpected events that can happen to us or interfere with our plans: sickness, poverty, extreme heat or cold, the minor misfortunes of everyday existence, crossed telephone lines, traffic jams, or having forgotten something and left it at home, an unexpected visitor. All these little contradictions can cause us to lose our peace.</p>

<p>Yet this is where Our Lord is waiting for us, right there in the ups and downs of ordinary life. This is the raw material of our sanctity. It is where we have to try and struggle to sanctify ourselves and to sanctify others.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us that “charity is patient” (1 Cor. 13:4). Our apostolate is a clear manifestation of charity.</p>

<p>We need to be patient with other souls—patience when we don’t see the fruits from the seeds that we may have sown in our children, in our friends, in our environment.</p>

<p>Fr. Joseph de Torre in the Philippines used to say that patience is a great social force. Often, we need to give the good seed time to grow. Sometimes that is a lot of time.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us to sow His seed with a great peace of mind. We are sowing for the future, we are forming souls, we are building up great human beings.</p>

<p>We can remember that Our Lord has prepared the field beforehand. He has cultivated the earth. He has prepared the soil.</p>

<p>We can be mindful of the rhythm of the seasons. Sometimes, to plant a seed, we have got to wait for the right time and place, and that takes patience.</p>

<p>We should not give in to discouragement. Things do not change overnight. “Our hope should rest in the Lord” (Ps. 33:20). He is the one who gives the growth. He will make a tiny shoot grow into a fine ear of wheat.</p>

<p>Our Lord gives us many examples of how to practice this virtue. He was very well aware that the crowds did not grasp the full meaning of His teaching: “Seeing they do not see and hearing they do not hear, nor do they understand” (Matt. 13:13). “Too slow a wit, too dull of heart” (Luke 24:25).</p>

<p>But yet Our Lord manifests a tireless devotion to those same people. He travels the length and breadth of Palestine. He knows that someday, somehow, ‘all my words, all my efforts’ are going to yield abundant fruit.</p>

<p>This is a great example for every father and mother of a family who may think that all their effort and example is falling on deaf ears. The silent apostolate of good example in the home is never lost.</p>

<p>We see from the Gospel how the twelve apostles had their great limitations. Our Lord tells them on the eve of His Passion, “I have yet many things to say to you. But you cannot bear them now” (John 16:12).</p>

<p>Our Lord was very understanding towards His disciples. He makes allowances for their limitations. He goes the extra mile with them. He had patience with their defects and their less than perfect ways. He did not give up on them. In the years to come, those same men would be the pillars of the Church.</p>

<p>In our home, in our family, we are hopefully building pillars of the Church. Our home can be a seedbed of vocations, a domestic Church.</p>

<p>Patience and constancy are necessary for any work of spiritual formation, either aimed at ourselves or others. James Stenson, the educationalist in the States, says how parents have to repeat things 500 times for their children who only get the message on the 501st. That takes an awful lot of patience and constancy.</p>

<p>A patient person accepts the workings of God's providence and operates within that general framework. They see that maybe, this thing was not meant to work out now; maybe, this was not the fruit that God was expecting.</p>

<p>One time in the early development of Opus Dei, St. Josemaría with two or three other people made a journey overnight to a Spanish city called Villadolid to get in contact with some young people there.</p>

<p>They made a lot of phone calls. They contacted a lot of people. But nobody came to the spiritual activity that they were trying to organize, after all their efforts.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría said, ‘Look, we used all the human means. We came here. We’ve prayed. We’ve sown the seed. We haven’t lost out.’</p>

<p>They went back to Madrid happy and peaceful in spite of the fact that there seemed to be no fruits. Today there is a bustling apostolic activity in that city. We are building for the future.</p>

<p>Patience is closely allied with the virtue of humility, to accept our own defects and also, the defects of others, which may be very glaring.</p>

<p>One writer says, “A Christian who practices the manly virtue of patience won’t become disconcerted by the fact that most people are indifferent to the things of God, and the fact that most people do not think about eternity. But the truth remains that there are many good people have deep longings to encounter God. Their inner desire could be compared to a wine cellar, in which locked away is a very good wine.” Many souls are like that.</p>

<p>“The farmer must accommodate himself to the seasons and the soil. Hasn’t the Master likened the Kingdom of God to a householder who went out to hire workers for his vineyard?’ (Matt. 20:1-7)” (Jose Luis R. Sánchez de Alva, <em>The Gospel of St. John</em>).</p>

<p>If truth were told, we would have to see that Our Lord has been incredibly patient with each one of us. We have to be sure to exercise that same virtue towards others in the apostolate.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us, “Love bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things” (1 Cor. 13:7). If we live this virtue, we will be faithful. We will become holy and help others to be holy—all the people that may become entrusted to our care.</p>

<p>This virtue has a great power enclosed within it. If we are impatient with our own interior life, to return to Our Lord is often necessary.</p>

<p>“Be patient, therefore, brethren,” says St. James, “until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the farmer waits for the precious fruit of the earth, being patient over us until it receives the early and the late rain” (James 5:7).</p>

<p>It is necessary for one to know, to hope, and to struggle with persevering patience. realizing that this is what pleases God very much. He precisely places us in those sorts of situations so that we practice that virtue.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>Friends of God</em> says, “Make more acts of hope. Let me remind you that in your interior life, you will suffer defeats, and you will have ups and downs—may God make them imperceptible—because no one is free from these misfortunes. But our all-powerful and merciful Lord has granted us the precise means with which to conquer…all we have to do is to use them, resolving to begin again and again in every moment whenever necessary” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 219).</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas says, “The heart of constancy lies in love: only with love can one be patient” (<em>cf</em>. St. Thomas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part II-II, Question 136).</p>

<p>“The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a king who decided to settle his accounts with his servants. When the reckoning came, they brought him a man who owed ten thousand talents. He had no means of paying, so his master gave orders that he should be sold, together with his wife and children and all his possessions, to meet the debt. At this, the servant threw himself at the master's feet with the words, ‘Be patient with me, and I will pay the whole sum’” (Matt. 18:23-26).</p>

<p>On our way towards Our Lord, many may be the defeats that we suffer; many of these will be of no consequence, but some will. But the atonement and contrition for those will bring us even closer to God.</p>

<p>The sorrow and reparation for our sins and shortcomings are not useless moods of gloom, because they are sorrow and tears born of love.</p>

<p>It is the heavy thought of not returning as much love as Our Lord merits; it is the sorrow of returning evil for good for one who loves us so much.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord for grace to see the opportunities that He gives us to be more patient, particularly in difficult moments.</p>

<p>None of our friends should ever be able to speak to Our Lord in the words of the paralytic. We’re told in the <em>Furrow:</em> “‘I do not have anyone to help me’ (John 5:7). This—unfortunately!—could be said by many who are spiritually sick and paralytic, who could be useful—and should be useful. Lord, may I never remain indifferent to souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 212).</p>

<p>Christ has converted everything that was previously death and turned shortcomings and errors into virtue. He is the fountain of those waters that give life to everything.</p>

<p>We can examine ourselves in our prayer and see if we're sufficiently concerned about those who accompany us on our journey through life; if we are concerned about their formation; or if, on the other hand, we have gotten used to their defects as something we've come to regard as incorrigible. Are we really patient towards them?</p>

<p>It can be good to recall that with mortification we can also atone for the sins of others, and merit for them the grace of faith, of conversion, and of a greater dedication to God.</p>

<p>In Christ lies the remedy for all the evils of which humanity complains. In the Book of Ezekiel, we are told: “This water flows east down to the Arabah and to the sea; and flowing into the sea, it makes its waters wholesome. Wherever the river flows, all living creatures teeming in it will live. Fish will be very plentiful. Wherever the water goes, it brings health, and life teems wherever the river flows” (Ezek. 47:8-9).</p>

<p>Christ converts everything into life. We can ask Our Lord for that grace to be patient in all the situations He places before us, patience with every aspect of our being.</p>

<p>“The Lord said to him, ‘Go your way, for this man is to me a vessel of election, to carry my name before the Gentiles, and kings, and the children of Israel, for I will show him how great things he must suffer for my name's sake’” (Acts 9:15-16).</p>

<p>Ananias, faced with Paul, had to be patient with the plans of God for how he was being used in a certain way.</p>

<p>This virtue is the virtue that helps us to accept, for love of God, generously and peacefully, everything that is displeasing to our nature, without allowing ourselves to be depressed by the sadness which easily comes over us when we meet with disagreeable things. We can be meeting with disagreeable things on a regular basis.</p>

<p>Our Lord was patient with the Pharisees. He was patient with the people of His village who did not recognize Him. He was patient with His accusers. He was patient with the man who slapped Him in the face.</p>

<p>We should never think that God's delays are God's denials. Sometimes He says “yes,” sometimes He says “no,” and sometimes He says, “wait.” Maybe He has a better solution, or He has greater things planned for us up the way.</p>

<p>We can be patient with close and distant relatives, with the idiosyncrasies of the people that we live with who have ailments and pains and physical suffering; being subject day after day to the same work: small fastidious things, struggling in the little points.</p>

<p>It is not that we should do nothing about them. But we should not be discouraged or upset by them. We see continual examples of this virtue given by Our Lord. Patience is a sign of faith and of hope.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady, who was so patient with the plans of God, patient with St. Joseph, with the Magi, with the angels, with the shepherds, as little by little, she came to know those plans. Patience in Bethlehem and patience in Egypt: “Remain there until I tell you” (Matt. 2:13).</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to learn how to practice this virtue in ever greater ways all the time.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>UI</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fifth Sunday of St. Joseph (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-fifth-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fifth Sunday of St. Joseph (2026)" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-fifth-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-fifth-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Having at last found a place for themselves in Bethlehem, the Holy Family received the unexpected homage of the Magi with their precious gifts for the divine Child.</p>

<p>“When they had departed,” we’re told, “behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph, saying, ‘Arise, and take the child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and remain there until I tell you; for Herod will seek the child to destroy him’” (Matt. 2:13).</p>

<p>Joseph’s great joy at the visit of the Magi did not last long. He had to abandon his newfound home and business to flee to a foreign land. Herod wanted to kill the Child. Joseph’s joy was changed to dread. Once again, God was testing him.</p>

<p>Joy and sorrow are never far from one another in souls that love God. St. John Chrysostom comments on this passage: “The Lord loves his people. That’s why he mixes suffering and delight in the lives of his saints. He takes care to intersperse dangers and consolations on the tapestry of the lives of his just ones. [This] is how he dealt with Joseph” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homilies on St. Matthew’s Gospel</em>).</p>

<p>Heeding the message of the angel, the Holy Family set out at once for Egypt. They could only take with them the bare essentials.</p>

<p>One writer says, “Because Joseph was a poor man, it was easy for him to leave at a moment’s notice. His human fortune was certainly no obstacle! He had no impediments” (Léon Cristiani, <em>St. Joseph, Patron of the Universal Church</em>).</p>

<p>This brings to mind a seminar that we had for priests in the diocese of Singapore. The previous bishop had changed very few priests to different parishes during his incumbency, but a new bishop wanted to change everybody. Something like twenty-eight or thirty parish priests had to change, and some of them were in their 80s.</p>

<p>He brought in a change expert, who was an executive coach from Citibank, and he gave a talk on change to all the clergy.</p>

<p>He said, “One of the first things I say to executives when dealing with change are two words, which are: Be light.”</p>

<p>Really, he was talking about the virtue of poverty and detachment from a human perspective, because he said: “You need to be able to close your laptop and go if you get a letter at 9:00 one morning telling you, ‘We no longer need your services in this organization.’ If you’ve set up your office to look like your home and you have a picture of your children and your grandchildren and your uncle and your aunt and your grandparents, it might take you three days to dismantle your office. You need to be able to close your laptop and go. You need to be light.”</p>

<p>Useful words. Likewise, when we come to the end of our life, we also need to be able to close our laptop and go, and leave all our affairs in order for people who come to clean up after us.</p>

<p>Joseph lived this virtue very well. Heeding the message of the angel, the Holy Family set out at once for Egypt. They had very few things to take with them.</p>

<p>“Together with his walking staff, his donkey, and [his] few belongings, he escaped from Bethlehem with Mary and the Child. They passed without notice because of their evident lack of means.</p>

<p>“In addition to his life of poverty, Joseph practiced the virtues of humility and obedience in an extraordinary way. He followed the will of God without delays or complaint” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Meanwhile, many local infants who had not reached two years of age were giving their lives for Jesus in Bethlehem without even knowing it. Their martyrdom opened up for them the gates of heaven. Today, together with their mothers—surely sanctified by their enormous grief’s serving as an instrument for their salvation—they behold the Holy Family in eternal bliss.</p>

<p>St. Joseph probably had little idea of how he was going to make ends meet for the Holy Family from one day to another. Each family in the world today that may be finding it hard to make ends meet can find their consolation in Joseph and in the Holy Family, and see this reality from a supernatural perspective. It’s a divine call to practice the virtue of faith, of abandonment, of trust.</p>

<p>Joseph had to rebuild a home and also a clientele in a strange country. After a while he would have been able to give the family some financial stability. Being the kind of man he was, he would have used all the human means at his disposal. Even though he was in a foreign country, Joseph still had the joy of living with Jesus and Our Lady.</p>

<p>We don’t know for certain how long the Holy Family remained in exile, but once back in Nazareth, Joseph and Our Lady probably looked back upon that period as the “years in Egypt.” They would recall their hurried escape along with the worries and problems of their first months on foreign soil. They would also remember their joy at watching Jesus grow up into boyhood.</p>

<p>From the very start of His life, Jesus is rarely far from the Cross. Close to Him and therefore close to the Cross are those who loved Him most: Our Lady and St. Joseph.</p>

<p>The Holy Patriarch surely suffered in his life, but he humbly submitted to the divine plan, which he could not understand. One writer says, “We ought never, then, to be alarmed by contradictions, by pain, or by injustice; nor can we allow these humbling setbacks to make us lose our peace of mind. Everything has been foreseen” (Federico Suarez, <em>Joseph of Nazareth</em>).</p>

<p>The Holy Family remained in Egypt until Herod’s death (Matt. 2:14). We’re told in St. Matthew, “But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, saying, ‘Arise, and take the child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel, for those who sought the child’s life are dead’” (Matt. 2:19-20).</p>

<p>This is what Joseph did. St. Josemaría says, “In the different circumstances of his life, St. Joseph never refuses to think. He never neglects his responsibilities. On the contrary, he puts his human experience at the service of the faith.</p>

<p>“When he returns from Egypt, ‘learning that Archelaus had succeeded his father Herod as ruler of Judea, he was afraid to go there’ (Matt. 2:22). In other words, he had learned to work within the divine plan. And to confirm that he was doing the right thing, Joseph received an instruction to return to Galilee” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 42).</p>

<p>Joseph prepared the Holy Family for their return to Palestine. At first, he thought he would be going to Judea, most probably to Bethlehem.</p>

<p>Once again on this occasion, God did not spare His faithful servant anxiety or difficulty. On their way out of Egypt, Joseph learned that Archelaus, Herod’s wicked son, had assumed the throne in Judea. Joseph guarded too great a treasure to expose it to this sort of danger. “He was afraid to go there” (Matt. 2:22).</p>

<p>While reflecting on what would be best for Jesus, Joseph was told in a dream to continue onward to Galilee. We can take note that Jesus is always at the center of Joseph’s concerns. Upon their arrival in Nazareth (Matt. 2:23), the Holy Family would have renewed their acquaintance with relatives and old friends. At long last, this family could settle into a home.</p>

<p>In our prayer today, we could ask Our Lady and St. Joseph to teach us how to take advantage of difficulties and contradictions so that we may love God more. We should not be troubled to find that as we follow Our Lord ever more closely, we feel ourselves closer to the Cross as well.</p>

<p>There is a prayer that says, “O Blessed Virgin, who knew how to make the most of your time of exile, help us to serve you better in this valley of tears. Following your example, we offer to God our work, our worries, and our sorrows, so that Jesus Christ may reign in our hearts and in the hearts of our friends” (Adolphe Tanquerey, <em>The Divinization of Suffering</em>).</p>

<p>We can ask St. Joseph to help us to be strong in times of trial. We have to keep our eyes on Jesus who is always at our side. He will be our strength.</p>

<p>We can contemplate the final sorrow and joy of Joseph when Jesus was lost and then found in the Temple.</p>

<p>The Mosaic Law obliged that all Jews who could do so should go on pilgrimage to the Temple in Jerusalem during the three principal feasts of Passover, Pentecost, and the Feast of Lights. This rule covered all Jews from their twelfth birthday. If a family lived more than a day’s journey from the Temple, they need only make one pilgrimage a year.</p>

<p>The law said nothing about the participation of women in this journey, but it seems to have been customary that women accompanied their husbands. Mary and Joseph went every year to Jerusalem during the Passover.</p>

<p>When Jesus reached the age of twelve, He traveled with His parents to the Temple (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:41-42). Families who came from distant villages typically traveled in groups. Jerusalem was about three or four days’ journey from Nazareth.</p>

<p>The Passover celebration lasted for a week. At its close the family caravans would regroup outside the city walls and then begin their return home. The men often traveled in one section of the caravan while the women would be grouped in another. Children on the road would move about indiscriminately from one group to another. Husband and wife would normally meet together with their families for the evening meal.</p>

<p>When Joseph and Mary accordingly rejoined each other, they realized immediately that Jesus was missing. At first they looked for Him among the other caravan groups, but He was not to be found. No one had seen im during the return trip.</p>

<p>Joseph and Our Lady spent the following day searching anxiously among their relatives and acquaintances, but no one had any news. They would have been totally beside themselves with anxiety. What could possibly have happened? That night before they returned to Jerusalem must have been agony for them.</p>

<p>Very early on the next day, they made haste back to Bethlehem. They looked for Jesus everywhere. Where was He? What had happened? They asked people. They described the Child. No one had any idea.</p>

<p>One writer says, “They made their earnest search in a most memorable fashion: he with furrowed brow, she seemingly doubled over with sorrow. Thus they taught all of us how to behave whenever we have the misfortune to lose Jesus” (Henri-Michel Gasnier, <em>Joseph the Silent</em>).</p>

<p>[Another] writer says, “Perhaps worst of all was the apparent silence of God. She, Our Lady, the Virgin, was the Father’s favorite daughter. He, Joseph, had been chosen to care for the two of them, and he too had experienced God’s intervention in human affairs.</p>

<p>“Through the angel, he had been forewarned of the danger Jesus would run in Bethlehem. He had been urged to flee to Egypt. On moving to Judea, once more he was told to settle in Nazareth, to avoid possible evils.</p>

<p>“How is it that on this occasion there was no one to advise him? How, after two days of crying out to heaven, of incessant searching, and with ever-mounting anxiety for the child, could God remain deaf to his supplication and his suffering?” (Federico Suarez, <em>Joseph of Nazareth</em>).</p>

<p>There are times during life when God seems silent. It may seem that we have lost Him. In some instances, this happens through our own fault. In other cases, however, it’s almost as if God had deliberately hidden Himself so that we would try to find Him.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “Jesus, may I never lose you again” (J. Escrivá, <em>Holy Rosary</em>, Fourth Joyful Mystery). We could repeat this simple prayer in the depths of our hearts.</p>

<p>On the third day, when every possibility had been exhausted, suddenly they found Jesus. We can only imagine the wave of joy which must have swept over Mary and Joseph when they discovered Him.</p>

<p>They would take the Child home between the two of them so as not to lose Him again. If they did not actually fear losing Him again, at least they wanted to make up for the three days they had lived without Him.</p>

<p>In our prayer, we could say, “Jesus, may I never lose you again.” We can ask St. Joseph to help us to never lose Jesus through sin. Nor do we want to lose sight of Him through our human weakness. We can ask St. Joseph to teach us how to look for Jesus with our whole heart if we should ever suffer the misfortune of losing Him.</p>

<p>We’re told by St. Paul to the Philippians, “Make your own the mind of Jesus Christ, who, being in the form of God, did not count equality with God something to be grasped, but emptied himself, taking the form of a slave, becoming as human beings are; and being in every way like a human being, he was humbler yet, even to accepting death, death on a cross” (Phil. 2:5-8).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us to that self-emptying. St. Joseph is a great model to us of how to empty oneself, to forget about oneself, to stand on our own self-love: my likes and my dislikes, my comforts, my opinions, my reactions. Joseph gave himself completely. His life was one of total service.</p>

<p>Sometimes we might be trying to serve, but we could serve with a declaration of independence, whereas Christ invites us to put on that new person, to forget about the old person.</p>

<p>We’re also told in St. Paul that “charity endures all things” (1 Cor. 13:7). St. Joseph endured all things in the course of his life.</p>

<p>We may have to stand on our own self-love when at times we’re not appreciated or recognized, or when, like St. Joseph, life deals certain blows.</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture we receive less blows than we deserve (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:48). Sometimes we can think this is too much, but that’s our pride speaking.</p>

<p>Or at times we might find ourselves with excessive sensitivity: “This person spoke to me like this,” or “They said that,” or “They used this tone.” These are all opportunities to forget about ourself, to stand on our own self-love.</p>

<p>We’re also told in St. John, “He must increase, but I must decrease” (John 3:30).</p>

<p>In St. Matthew, Our Lord said, “Learn from me, for I am meek and humble of heart” (Matt. 11:29).</p>

<p>In St. Luke, “For everyone who raises himself up will be humbled, and the one who humbles himself will be raised up” (Luke 14:11).</p>

<p>It is as though all of these phrases of Scripture were written in the life of St. Joseph. “God resists the proud but gives his grace to the humble” (James 4:6). “Whoever loses his life will save it” (Luke 9:24).</p>

<p>“In all truth I tell you, unless a grain of wheat falls into the ground and dies, it remains only a single grain; but if it dies, it yields a rich harvest” (John 12:24).</p>

<p>Indeed, “All who are led by the Spirit of God,” says St. Paul, “are children of God” (Rom. 8:14).</p>

<p>We can examine our conscience, see if perhaps we’re easy to annoy. Help us to realize that fast temper is fast pride. Help us to rectify our intention.</p>

<p>St. Benedict says, “If humility is truth, then a significant part of its practice must involve bringing out into the daylight of another’s judgment whatever is hidden and therefore subject to delusion” (Benedict, <em>Fifth Decree of Humility</em>).</p>

<p>This can be a great encouragement in our spiritual direction to open our soul and open our heart, to let ourselves be known. In particular, to let it be known those things that we would prefer not to be known.</p>

<p>Part of that self-emptying also is to let ourselves be demanded of by our family, by our spouse, by our children, by our teachers, by our boss. We come to try and have an unconditional self-surrender.</p>

<p>We see continually in the life of St. Joseph that he allowed God to demand more from him all the time. St. Josemaría had a phrase that he liked to use: <em>siempre más</em>, “always more” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 545).</p>

<p>We can think also of the virtue of docility, able to be taught, so that we let ourselves be molded in spiritual direction. The Book of Jeremiah says we have to be “like clay in the hands of the potter” (Jer. 18:1-6), allowing other people to tell us things clearly.</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro del Portillo has said, “Let us seek only the glory of God. Let us live according to the constant lessons of the life of St. Josemaría: ‘Mine is to hide and disappear.’ Let each one fulfill the work of God, spend himself in service to the others, knowing himself to be the last. I am writing this to you,” he says, “with all the love that St. Josemaría has taught me to have for you. Let us be very humble. Let us not forget that St. Josemaría has always forewarned us that the great enemy is hidden in pride.”</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord through the intercession of St. Josemaría to give us this grace: a holy hunger to disappear, to be the last, to obey with more finesse than ever.</p>

<p>There can also be a false humility, where we think we’re humble. That virtue leads us to be open to change, to be flexible.</p>

<p>The plans of St. Joseph were always changing. The news of the angels in some ways was always unwelcome news. We could ask the Holy Spirit to come and “enkindle in us the fire of your love” that burnt in the heart of Joseph.</p>

<p>There’s a story told about an architect who constructed the first lighthouse in a place called Eddystone in England, close to Plymouth, around the year 1700. He had etched on the lamp the words: “Winstanley, the best architect in England.” Soon afterwards, a storm toppled the lighthouse into the sea.</p>

<p>Some years later, another architect, this time called Smeaton, constructed another lighthouse on the same site. Upon finishing, he had engraved on the stones the words of the Psalm: “Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain” (Ps. 127:1). That lighthouse is still standing today.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “What really makes a person—or a whole sector of society— unhappy is the anxiety-ridden, selfish search for well-being, that desire to get rid of whatever is upsetting” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 767).</p>

<p>We see how in the life of St. Joseph, he took the blows. He emptied himself for others all the time.</p>

<p>We can ask him that we might imitate him a little more each day. He, the master of the interior life” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Points 39,56), might truly be the model for our life, and that he might teach us to put human virtues into practice in concrete ways all the time.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Wisdom of Solomon</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-wisdom-of-solomon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wisdom of Solomon" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-wisdom-of-solomon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-wisdom-of-solomon/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in the First Book of Kings, “Now, Yahweh my God, you have made your servant king in succession to David, my father. But I am a very young man, unskilled in leadership. And here is your servant, surrounded with your people whom you have chosen, a people so numerous that its number cannot be counted or reckoned. So give your servant a heart to understand how to govern your people, how to discern between good and evil, for how could one otherwise govern such a great people as yours?” (1 Kings 3:7-9).</p>

<p>The passage continues, “It pleased Yahweh that Solomon should have asked for this. ‘Since you have asked for this,’ God said, ‘and not asked for long life for yourself or riches or the lives of your enemies but have asked for a discerning judgment for yourself, here and now I do what you ask. I give you a heart wise and shrewd as no one has had before and no one will have after you. What you have not asked I shall give you too: such riches and glory as no other king can match. And I shall give you a long life, if you follow my ways, keeping my laws and commandments, as your father David followed them’” (1 Kings 3:10-14).</p>

<p>The most important trait of King Solomon is his wisdom, which Our Lord will later echo in St. Matthew.</p>

<p>“On Judgment Day,” Jesus says in St. Matthew, “the Queen of the South will appear against this generation and be its condemnation, because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and look, there is something greater than Solomon here” (Matt. 12:42).</p>

<p>Our Lord highlights the wisdom of Solomon and suggests that only His wisdom, the wisdom of the Son of Man, is greater than that of Solomon.</p>

<p>The sacred author shows the origin and the manifestations of that wisdom. It’s a gift of God at the King’s request.</p>

<p>“God gave Solomon immense wisdom and understanding, and [breadth of mind like] the sand on the seashore.” We’re told that “the wisdom of Solomon surpassed the wisdom of all the sons of the east and all the wisdom of Egypt” (1 Kings 4:29-30).</p>

<p>He was wiser than anyone else, says the Book of Kings. “For he was wiser than Ethan the Ezrahite and the sons of Mahol. and Heman, Calcol, and Darda. His fame spread to all the surrounding nations. He composed 3,000 proverbs. His songs numbered 1,005. He could discourse on plants from the cedar in Lebanon to the hyssop growing on the wall. He could discourse on animals and birds and reptiles and fish. Men from all nations came to hear Solomon’s wisdom, and he received gifts from all the kings of the world who had heard of his wisdom” (1 Kings 4:31-34).</p>

<p>The more one acts with wisdom, we’re told in [Proverbs], the more that gift increases in man (<em>cf</em>. Prov. 1:5).</p>

<p>“God speaks to Solomon” also means that the Lord ratifies him as King of Israel. Solomon’s request pleases God because it is made in humility, and has, as its object, not material things, but discernment or wisdom to administer justice among the people.</p>

<p>It’s a foretaste of all the order which, according to Christ’s teaching, the prayer of petition should have.</p>

<p>In one of the Catechisms, it says, “The Master and Lord of all things himself taught and commanded what is to be asked of God, and in what order it should be done. For since prayer indicates and expresses our desires and petitions, then we ask properly and with method; and the order of the petitions follows the order of the things that are to be desired.</p>

<p>“Now, true charity teaches us to direct our whole life and to drive desires to God, who, being the supreme Good, must of necessity be loved with a supreme and special love. And God cannot be loved heartily and exclusively if his glory and honor are not preferred to all things in creation. For all goods of our own and those of others, and in short, all that is designated by the name of good, must be subordinated to the supreme Good as coming from him” (Pope Pius V, <em>The Catechism of the Council of Trent</em>).</p>

<p>From Solomon, we can learn to look again at the things that we ask of God. Often they may be material favors: things we want, things that will suit our own comfort.</p>

<p>But Our Lord is telling us that it’s very pleasing to Him if we ask for things—gifts, talents—whereby we may be of greater service to our people. “He asked for wisdom to judge my people well” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Kings 3:9).</p>

<p>It’s good to ask God for those gifts that only He can give, all the graces that we need to be a better person, a better follower of Christ, a person of greater interior life, a person of greater virtue, greater charity, greater humility, greater order; whatever it is those virtues are that we need most—maybe purity and chastity, maybe prudence, maybe justice—so that we might fill ourselves with those good things (<em>cf</em>. Eph. 1:23), so that I can be a better student, a better parent, a better mother, a better father.</p>

<p>Wisdom can be defined as “knowledge of things through their ultimate causes” (Aristotle, <em>Posterior Analytics</em>). It’s wisdom to see only good and beauty in all things, because wisdom sees God’s beauty in everything and goes to serve others.</p>

<p>“True wisdom is a participation in the mind of God” (John Paul II, <em>Audience</em>, Jan. 29, 2003). Wisdom is a divine gift and a guide of life and of the decisions of the faithful. It gives us a loving knowledge of God and of people and created things insofar as they refer to Him.</p>

<p>As someone said once, “You get knowledge in college, but wisdom comes from God.” You may have an experience some time of speaking to somebody who perhaps does not have too much education but often their words express a wisdom that is uncommon, a wisdom that can only have come from the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>Sometimes we get wisdom in the course of life. Sometimes we don’t. But it’s enlightening and inspiring to listen to people that God may place in our path who may be full of wisdom, in spite of having very little opportunity in which to acquire it.</p>

<p>Through the gift of wisdom, the Holy Spirit places this knowledge within the reach of simple souls who love God. We’re told in St. Matthew: “I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that you have hidden these things from the wise and understanding and revealed them to babes” (Matt. 11:25).</p>

<p>It’s a knowledge not learned from books but given by God who illumines and fills our mind and heart, will and understanding with love. By means of this light of love, the Christian has a more intimate and joyful knowledge of God and His mysteries.</p>

<p>There’s a Chinese proverb that says, “A single conversation across the table with a wise man is worth a month’s study of books.” In the course of our life, we have to try and gather wisdom to use our time well, to practice the virtue of humility, to give a lot of importance to our ongoing formation.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen liked to say, “Just as a mouse eating piano keys cannot understand how someone can sit at a piano stool and play Tchaikovsky, so we do not understand the wisdom of God’s ways” (Fulton J. Sheen, <em>A Word to the Intelligentsia</em>).</p>

<p>Through the world of nature and of grace, the Holy Spirit enables us to perceive and contemplate the infinite wisdom, power, and goodness of God. His nature is reflected in created things.</p>

<p>Through this gift a Christian perceives and understands that, as St. Josemaría says in <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, “all creation, the movement of the earth and the other heavenly bodies, the good actions of creatures and all the good that has been achieved in history, in short, everything, comes from God and is directed towards him” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 130).</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, Truly he will be able to say that wisdom “guided him on straight paths; she showed him the kingdom of God, and gave him knowledge of the angels” (Wisd. 10:10).</p>

<p>The Holy Spirit Himself will warn us when what is good and true in itself is in danger of becoming bad by leading us away from our last supernatural end. It could be a disordered desire for material possessions, or an attachment to these goods in a way that does not leave the heart free to serve God.</p>

<p>Christians who must sanctify themselves in the middle of the world have a particular need of this gift so as to direct all temporal activities to God, making them a means of holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>Through it a housewife discovers how her work at home is a way to God if it is done with an upright, honest intention and with a desire to please God; a student learns that study is the ordinary way to love God, to do apostolate, and to serve society; for an architect the way to God is through plans and drawings; for a nurse, her care of the sick.</p>

<p>We understand that we must love the world and temporal affairs, and come to discover the truth of those words of St. Josemaría in<em>Conversations</em>, Point 114:</p>

<p>“There is something holy, something divine, hidden in the most ordinary situations, and it is up to each one of you to discover it” (J. Escrivá, Homily, “Passionately Loving the World” in <em>Conversations</em>, Point 114).</p>

<p>We have to try and apply this truth about the gift of wisdom to our ordinary Christian vocation in the middle of the world, to our interior life, to our apostolate, our work, our spiritual direction, our sacraments.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>Conversations</em>, “When a Christian carries out with love the most insignificant everyday action, that action overflows with the transcendence of God. That is why I have told you repeatedly, and hammered away once and again at the idea, that the Christian vocation consists in making heroic verse out of the prose of each day” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 116).</p>

<p>The epic poetry that we men and women write for God is composed of the ordinary events of the day, the problems and joys that we meet along our way.</p>

<p>Like Solomon, we have to ask for the wisdom to judge well. “Age doesn’t always bring wisdom; sometimes age comes alone” (attributed to Oscar Wilde).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, Point 38, St. Josemaría says, “It is no use trying to please everyone. There will always be people who disagree, who complain. The way popular wisdom sums it up is: ‘What is good for the sheep is bad for the wolves.’”</p>

<p>In an Encyclical called “Faith and Reason,” one of the greatest Encyclicals of John Paul II, he says, “Another of the great insights of St. Thomas was his perception of the role of the Holy Spirit in the process by which knowledge matures into wisdom. From the first pages of his <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Aquinas was keen to show the primacy of the wisdom which is the gift of the Holy Spirit and which opens the way to a knowledge of divine realities.</p>

<p>“His theology allows us,” he continues, “to understand what is distinctive of wisdom in its close link with faith and knowledge of the divine. This wisdom comes to know by way of connaturality; it presupposes faith and eventually formulates its right judgment on the basis of the truth of faith itself.</p>

<p>‘The wisdom named among the gifts of the Holy Spirit is distinct from the wisdom found among the intellectual virtues. This second wisdom is acquired through study, but the first ‘comes from on high,’ as St. James puts it (James 3:17). This also distinguishes it from faith, since faith accepts divine truth as it is. But the gift of wisdom enables judgment according to divine truth” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Fides et Ratio</em>, Point 44, September 14, 1998).</p>

<p>The Holy Father continues, “It is no accident that when the sacred author comes to describe the wise man, he portrays him as one who loves and seeks the truth: ‘Happy the man who meditates on wisdom and reasons intelligently, who reflects in his heart on her ways and ponders her secrets. He pursues her like a hunter and lies in wait on her paths. He peers through her windows and listens at her doors. He camps near her house and fastens his tent-peg to her walls. He pitches his tent near her and so finds an excellent resting place; he places his children under her protection and lodges under her boughs; by her he is sheltered from the heat and he dwells in the shade of her glory’” (Sir. 14:20-27 in <em>Fides et Ratio</em>, Point 16).</p>

<p>St. Paul to the Colossians says, “The treasures of wisdom and knowledge are hidden in Christ” (Col. 2:3). The closer we become to Christ in our interior life, in our presence of God, among the ordinary daily realities of our ordinary existence, the more we’re going to find those treasures of wisdom and knowledge.</p>

<p>One writer said, “Some people drink at the fountain of knowledge; other people just gargle.”</p>

<p>The Book of Proverbs says, “A fool takes pleasure in doing wrong; the intelligent, in cultivating wisdom” (Prov. 10:23).</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord God for that grace to learn how to cultivate that wisdom on a daily basis—in our spiritual reading, in our cultural formation, in all the things that we’re exposed to, in our conversations with people, in our openness to new knowledge and new things.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Romans, “How rich and deep are the wisdom and the knowledge of God! We cannot reach to the root of his decisions or his ways” (Rom. 11:33).</p>

<p>The Book of Proverbs says, “For Yahweh himself is the giver of wisdom. From his mouth issue knowledge and understanding” (Prov. 2:6).</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom itself says, “Wisdom will never enter the soul of a wrongdoer, nor dwell in a body enslaved to sin” (Wisd. 1:4).</p>

<p>In the Gospel, Our Lord encourages us to find wisdom in daily life. We’re told, “What does it profit a man if he gains the whole world but loses his own soul?” (Mark 8:36).</p>

<p>Augustine says, “Our hearts are restless, Lord, until they rest in you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>).</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “For I decided to know nothing among you except Jesus Christ and him crucified” (1 Cor. 2:2).</p>

<p>How do we acquire the gift of wisdom? Like the other gifts of the Holy Spirit, it accompanies sanctifying grace, makes a person well disposed to receive inspirations and movements of the Holy Spirit, and “completes and perfects the virtues of those who receive them” (<em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point 1831).</p>

<p>“The spiritual person,” we’re told by St. Paul, “can assess the value of everything, and that person’s value cannot be assessed by anybody else” (1 Cor. 2:15).</p>

<p>We ask for the gift of wisdom, not only for special undertakings, but to follow God’s will, which is a continuous task for the Christian.</p>

<p>Beneath the surface of things, when we follow the Holy Family closely in the different decisions they had to make, we see how they were trying to follow God’s will in a deep way: the journey to Bethlehem, the fleeing into Egypt, the coming back to Nazareth.</p>

<p>“This discernment,” we’re told, “is nourished by the light and strength of the Holy Spirit, who evokes everywhere and in all circumstances, obedience to the faith, the joyous courage of following Jesus, and the gift of wisdom, which ‘judges all things and is judged by no one’ (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 2:15). It rests on the fidelity of the Father to his promises” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Pastores dabo vobis</em>, Point 10, March 25, 1992).</p>

<p>Through this gift, we share in Christ’s love for the people we’re in contact with. It’s relevant for our apostolate.</p>

<p>Through this gift, we see in our dealings with other people a chance to be more merciful, doing an effective apostolate, and bringing them closer to God.</p>

<p>We understand better the great need that men have to be helped on their way to Christ. Others are seen as persons in need of God, and that’s the way that Jesus sees them.</p>

<p>This gift teaches us to view events in the light of the providence of God, who is always a loving Father.</p>

<p>In <em>Christ Is Passing By,</em> Point 133, we’re told, “Among the gifts of the Holy Spirit, I would say there is one that we all need in a special way: the gift of wisdom. It makes us know God and rejoice in his presence, thereby placing us in a perspective from which we can judge accurately the situations and events of life.”</p>

<p>With the vision that this gift bestows, the soul who wishes to follow Christ closely contemplates reality from a higher perspective, because it shares in some way in the vision which God Himself has of Creation. Everything is judged with the clarity given by this gift.</p>

<p>Illumined by this gift, the saints have understood the real meaning of the events of this life, whether small or great.</p>

<p>They don’t consider illness a misfortune, nor do they rail against the sufferings they endure, because they understand that God blesses them in different ways, and frequently He blesses with the Cross.</p>

<p>Through this gift, the motions of grace will bring us and our friends and neighbors a great peace. We’ll be helped to bring joy wherever we go, and to find the right word to reconcile those who are at odds with one another. This gift ties in with the beatitude: “Blessed are the peacemakers” (Matt. 5:9).</p>

<p>Those who have peace in themselves can bring peace to others. This peace which the world cannot give (John 14:27) results from seeing all within the providential plan of God, who never for a moment forgets His children.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em>, it says, “May the Mother of God and Our Mother protect us, so that each one of us may serve the Church in the fullness of faith, with the gifts of the Holy Spirit, and with our contemplative life. May each of us joyfully honor the Lord by carrying out his duties, those which are properly his; each one of us, in his job or profession, and fulfilling the obligations of his state in life” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God,</em> Point 316).</p>

<p>Queen of Apostles, pray for us and with us, so that the Holy Spirit will descend in abundance upon His Church, and that she will shine throughout the world, ever more united, holy, catholic, and apostolic.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MVF</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Knowing When to Speak</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowing When to Speak" /><published>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in St. Mark that Jesus “was silent and made no answer” (Mark 14:61). For thirty years, Jesus had lived a life of silence. Mary and Joseph were the only ones who knew the mystery of the Son of God.</p>

<p>During His public life, when He returned to His hometown, His relatives were disconcerted by His wisdom and His miracles. They had known Him only from His exemplary life of work.</p>

<p>During the three years of His public life, we see how He withdraws into the silence of prayer, to be alone with His Father God. He withdraws from the superficial clamor of the multitude that wants to make Him their king. He performs miracles without ostentation, asking people He cures to refrain from publicizing His powers.</p>

<p>We see that one of the characteristics of the life of Christ was silence. His silence before His enemies in the Passion is very moving: “He was silent and made no answer,” we’re told (Mark 14:61). In the face of so many false accusations, He makes no defense.</p>

<p>St. Jerome comments, “Our God and Savior, who because of his mercy had redeemed the world, allows himself to be led to his death like a lamb, without a word of complaint or self-defense. The silence of Jesus obtains pardon for the protest and excuse of Adam” (Jerome, <em>Commentary on St. Mark’s Gospel</em>).</p>

<p>Jesus says nothing during the hearings before Herod and Pilate. We see Him standing silent at their preference for Barabbas in front of His hate-filled enemies.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew: “When he was accused by the chief priests and elders, he made no answer. Then Pilate said to him, ‘Do you not hear how many things they testify against you?’ But he gave him no answer, not even to a single charge, so that the governor wondered greatly” (Matt. 27:12-14).</p>

<p>The silence of Jesus in the face of human passions, before the sins which are committed every day by humanity, is not a silence of anger. It is a silence that’s full of patience and love.</p>

<p>The silence of Calvary is that of a God who comes to redeem all men by His indescribable agony of the Cross. The silence of Jesus in the tabernacle is that of a love which waits for a response. It’s the patient silence of one who treasures our attentions.</p>

<p>Christ’s silence during His earthly life represents interior strength and sense of purpose. One writer says, “Those who complain continually about their misfortunes or their bad luck should look at the example of Our Lord. Those who proclaim their problems to the four winds should consider the behavior of Christ. Those who feel compelled to explain and excuse their actions, who wait anxiously for praise or approval, should take note of Christ, who says nothing.</p>

<p>“We will imitate him when we learn to accept life’s duties and worries without sterile complaints, when we confront our personal problems without dumping them in someone else’s lap, when we face squarely the consequences of our actions, when we do our work for the glory of God without looking for earthly praise” (F. Suarez, <em>The Two Faces of Silence, Nuestro Tiempo</em>).</p>

<p>“Jesus says nothing,” we’re told in Scripture. We have to learn to say nothing on many occasions. At times vanity will have us say things which should have been kept locked in the soul.</p>

<p>The silent figure of Christ is the ever-present model to reproach empty or useless words. His example will lead us to remain silent before calumny and rumor. The Prophet Isaiah says, “In silence and in hope will be your fortitude and your courage” (Isa. 30:15). He encourages us that our fortitude is grounded in silence and in hope.</p>

<p>At the same time, Our Lord doesn’t always remain silent. He teaches us that sometimes we have to speak out when it’s necessary, with charity and with fortitude, avoiding the silence of consent.</p>

<p>There is a silence that can collaborate with lying, a silence that can cooperate with cowardice, a silence which springs from the love of comfort and the fear of complicating one’s life. You can close your eyes to what is disagreeable. You can put off making a fraternal correction that ought to be made at home or at work.</p>

<p>The word of Jesus is full of authority as He faces injustice and abuse. In St. Matthew we’re told, “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you devour widows’ houses and for a pretense you make long prayers” (Matt. 23:14).</p>

<p>St. John the Baptist was “the voice of one crying in the wilderness” (Matt. 3:3). He teaches us to say everything that must be said, even though it may seem as if we too are crying in the wilderness.</p>

<p>Our Lord will not allow our words to be wasted. It’s important that we say what has to be said, without worrying ourselves about the immediate consequences.</p>

<p>If each Christian were to speak in conformity with the faith, we would surely change the world. We can’t sit by silently in the face of such crimes of abortion and the degradation of marriage and the family. Nor can we surrender to those forces that would seek to remove God from the formation of the young.</p>

<p>We can’t be silent at attacks upon the Pope and Our Lady, or upon institutions of the Church. To be silent when we should be speaking out can be a way of collaborating with evil, because others might think that our silence means consent.</p>

<p>If Catholics were to speak out where there is need, if they were to boycott anti-Catholic publications or literature, it would be more difficult for those enterprises to prosper.</p>

<p>In our prayer today, we can ask Our Lord for the grace to speak out when necessary. At times, those occasions will be when we’re with a little group of our friends, coming or going to school or to work. In letters to the editor, we can write in praise of a good article or to criticize a bad one.</p>

<p>We should always act with charity. It’s worthwhile to remember that true charity always goes hand in hand with fortitude. We need to exercise good manners, always working with the intention of bringing souls to Jesus Christ. Yet we should act at the same time with the fortitude of Our Lord.</p>

<p>If upon realizing that his life was in danger, St. John the Baptist had remained silent or retired to the sidelines of public affairs, he would not have been beheaded by Herod. But John was not that kind of man. He was not “a reed shaken by the wind” (Matt. 11:7). He was true to his vocation and also to his principles to the end.</p>

<p>If he had remained silent, he could have lived a few more years, but his disciples would not have been the first to follow Our Lord. He would not have “prepared and made straight the way of the Lord,” as we’re told by Isaiah (Isa. 40:3). He would not have lived up to his vocation. His life would have been bereft of meaning.</p>

<p>Probably Our Lord is not asking us to suffer a martyr’s death, but He is asking for courage and fortitude in facing up to the demands of ordinary life. Perhaps He is asking us to stop watching a bad TV show or to cease putting off an apostolic conversation.</p>

<p>We can’t allow ourselves to hide behind excuses when there is a lot of apostolic work to be done. We have to act with optimism, loving the world and the good that is in it, while seeking to increase that goodness. We can do this with the example of a joyful family and of the youthful love that is born of holy purity.</p>

<p>There are other kinds of cowardly silence which we have to struggle against: the silence we might maintain with the person next to us. But God has put that person there so that we might be a beacon of light for him or for her.</p>

<p>It’s hard to imagine that we can be courageous at all in this life if we are not courageous first with ourselves, especially when we’re talking with our spiritual director, to say the things that need to be said.</p>

<p>Many of our friends, on seeing that we truly practice what we preach, will be attracted to the faith. Centuries ago, many people converted after witnessing the martyrdom of the first Christians.</p>

<p>We can learn a lot from Our Lord’s silence. We’re told in the Psalms, “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2). God lives in our midst and often in a very silent way.</p>

<p>Throughout the Old Testament, God makes known His intention of having an ongoing presence among men. The “tent of meeting” was the first temple to God in the desert. Upon the tent there came to rest a cloud which symbolized the glory of God and His presence.</p>

<p>“Then the cloud covered the tent of meeting and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle” (Ex. 40:34). The cloud was a sign of the divine presence (<em>cf</em>. Num. 12:5; 1 Kings 8:10-11).</p>

<p>Much later, the Temple of Jerusalem was the place where the Israelites worshiped God (<em>cf</em>. Ex. 23:15-17). It was the place they had been longing for while they were in the desert.</p>

<p>They would recall the enthusiasm of old when they would go to the house of the Lord, singing songs of joy and praise: “How lovely is your dwelling place, O Lord of hosts! My soul longs, yes, faints for the courts of the Lord; my heart and flesh sing for joy to the living God” (Ps. 84:1-2).</p>

<p>To be far from the sanctuary was to be deprived of true happiness. “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2).</p>

<p>In the fullness of time, the Word became flesh. In the moment of the Incarnation the power of the Most High overshadowed Our Lady (<em>cf</em>. Luke 1:35). This is an expression of the omnipotence of God.</p>

<p>Following upon the Incarnation, Our Lady, the Virgin, became the Tabernacle of God. “The Word of God dwelt among us,” we’re told in St. John (John 1:14).</p>

<p>St. John uses a Greek verb for “dwelt” which originally meant “to pitch one’s tent,” hence, to live in a place. “The careful reader of Scripture will immediately think of the tabernacle, or tent, in the period of the exodus from Egypt, where God showed his presence before all the people of Israel through certain signs of his glory, such as the cloud covering the tent.</p>

<p>“In many passages of the Old Testament it is announced that God ‘will dwell in the midst of the people’ (<em>cf</em>. Jer. 7:3; Ezek. 43:9; Sir. 24:8). These signs of God’s presence, first in the pilgrim Tent of the Ark in the desert and then in the Temple of Jerusalem, are followed by the most wonderful form of God’s presence among us—Jesus Christ, perfect God and perfect Man, in whom the ancient promise is fulfilled in a way that far exceeded men’s greatest expectations. Also the promise made through Isaiah about the ‘Emmanuel’ or ‘God with us’ (Isa. 7:14; <em>cf</em>. Matt. 1:23) is completely fulfilled through this dwelling of the Incarnate Son of God among us” (<em>The Navarre Bible</em>, St. John).</p>

<p>From that time onwards, we can say with exactitude that God lives among us. We can be next to Him every day, closer to Him than anyone might imagine possible—God truly dwelling among us.</p>

<p>From the moment of the Incarnation we can affirm that God is with us in the personal presence of Jesus Christ. As both true God and true Man, Jesus is closer to us than any other being. Jesus is “God with us.”</p>

<p>In earlier times, the Israelites would say that God was “with them.” Now we can say this in a very literal sense.</p>

<p>When Christ traveled about Palestine, He made an effort to preach in many towns. “When Jesus had finished these parables,” we’re told, “he went away from there” (Matt. 13:53). God left one town to go and meet other people.</p>

<p>When the priest consecrates the host during the Mass, he brings Christ to the altar with His Holy Humanity. He is there in the Eucharist with a special presence for as long as the sacramental species last.</p>

<p>This presence affects the Body of Christ in a direct way and the Three Persons of the Holy Trinity in an indirect way. The Word is tied to Christ’s humanity, while the Father and the Holy Spirit are related by the mutual immanence of their divine Persons (<em>cf</em>. Council of Trent, Decree, <em>De Sanctissima Eucharistia</em>).</p>

<p>Christ is really present in the Tabernacle with His Body, Blood, Soul, and Divinity. It can be said quite literally that ‘God is here, close to me.’ We could make that act of faith: “My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me.”</p>

<p>Down through the centuries the Church has developed a precise way of describing the Eucharistic presence, often requiring such exact definition to counter erroneous beliefs.</p>

<p>The Eucharistic presence is a <em>real</em> presence, a silent presence. It is not symbolic, nor does it signify or insinuate any image.</p>

<p>It is not fictitious, or merely the product of the imagination or the will. It is <em>substantial</em> because the words of the Consecration spoken by the priest change the substance of bread and the wine into the substance of the Body and Blood of Christ.</p>

<p>Paul VI says, “Every theological explanation which seeks some understanding of this mystery must, in order to be in accord with Catholic faith, maintain that in the reality itself, independently of our mind, the bread and wine have ceased to exist after the Consecration, so that it is the adorable Body and Blood of Our Lord Jesus that from then on are really before us under the sacramental species of bread and wine…” (Paul VI, Apostolic Letter, <em>Credo of the People of God</em>, Point 25, June 30, 1968).</p>

<p>In the encyclical <em>Mysterium Fidei</em>, Paul VI says, “As a result of transubstantiation, the species of bread and wine…contain a new ‘reality’ which we may justly term ‘ontological.’ Not that there lies under those species what was already there before, but something quite different; and that not only because of the faith of the Church, but in objective reality… (<em>cf</em>. Paul VI, Encyclical, <em>Mysterium Fidei,</em> Point 46, September 3, 1965).</p>

<p>Jesus is silently present in our Tabernacles whether or not we take advantage of this amazing wonder. He is there silently, with His Body and His Blood, His Soul and His Divinity. God made Man. He could not be closer.</p>

<p>The Church possesses the Author of all grace and the cause of our sanctification. We may venture to say that the Eucharistic presence of Christ is the sacramental prolongation of the Incarnation.</p>

<p>From the Tabernacle Jesus invites us to bring to Him our concerns and our petitions. In the <em>visit to the Blessed Sacrament</em> and other acts of worship offered to the Holy Eucharist, we give thanks for this great gift.</p>

<p>There we can go to find new strength, to tell Jesus that we miss Him, to tell Him that we need Him very much. “The Eucharist is reserved in the churches and oratories [to serve as] the spiritual center of a religious community or of a parish, and [indeed] of the universal Church and of all humanity, since beneath the appearance of the species, Christ is contained: the invisible Head of the Church, the Redeemer of the world, the center of all hearts, ‘by whom,’ says St. Paul, ‘all things are and by whom we exist’ (1 Cor. 8:6)” (<em>ibid</em>., Point 68).</p>

<p>It has been the constant practice of the Church to adore Christ’s silent presence in the Tabernacle. If we recall how much reverence the Israelites had for their “tent of meeting” in the desert and for the Temple at Jerusalem, which were figures or images of reality, how much more reverence should we have for Christ truly present in the Tabernacle?</p>

<p>In the first centuries of the Church, the main reason for reserving the Sacred Species was for the sake of those who were not able to get to Mass, especially the sick and the dying, and also for those in prison due to religious persecution. The Sacrament of the Lord was brought with piety and fervor so that these Christians might also receive Communion.</p>

<p>Later, faith in the real presence of Christ led to the cult of the Blessed Sacrament, and the Church authoritatively approved those practices. The Council of Trent declared, “There is, therefore, no room left for doubt that all the faithful of Christ in accordance with a custom always received in the Catholic Church offer in veneration the worship of <em>latria</em> which is due to the true God, to this most Holy Sacrament” (Council of Trent, <em>Session XIII</em>).</p>

<p>In the thirteenth century, St. Thomas Aquinas composed a Eucharistic hymn which embodies the faith of the Church in a faithful and pious manner. We should make this hymn our own so as to nourish our piety and give honor to the Blessed Sacrament.</p>

<p>The hymn states: “O Godhead hid, devoutly I adore you, Who truly are within the forms before me; To you my heart I bow with bended knee, As failing quite in contemplating thee” (Prayer in Adoration Before the Blessed Sacrament, <em>Adore te Devote</em>).</p>

<p>Here we have all the truths of the faith. We have understanding with humility and thanksgiving, amazement before the power of God, surprise at the extent of His mercy. With the confidence gained by having Him so close by, we can ask Our Lord for His grace to unite ourselves to His most holy will.</p>

<p>Next to the silent Tabernacle, we can learn how to love. There we will draw the strength necessary to remain faithful. We’ll find consolation in times of sorrow.</p>

<p>He silently waits for us and He rejoices when we are next to Him, even if only for a short while. There Jesus waits for His people who suffer the contradictions of this life. He comforts them with the warmth of His understanding and His love.</p>

<p>It is in the Tabernacle that the words of Our Lord come to life, specifically those words where He says, “Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest” (Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>We should not fail to visit Him. He is waiting for us. He has many gifts prepared for us.</p>

<p>Mary, we turn to you, Comfort of the afflicted, Cause of our joy. We ask you for the grace to learn from the silence of Our Lord in His public life, and also in the Tabernacle.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Thomas More and St. John Fisher (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-thomas-more-and-st-john-fisher-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Thomas More and St. John Fisher (2026)" /><published>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-thomas-more-and-st-john-fisher-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-thomas-more-and-st-john-fisher-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen. My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here. That you see me, that you hear me.</em></p>

<p><em>I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful.</em></p>

<p><em>My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>John Fisher was ordained a priest in 1491. He held several teaching posts at the University of Cambridge, and at the same time was responsible for the spiritual direction of Queen Margaret, the mother of Henry VIII. He later occupied the chair of theology which the queen had endowed at Cambridge.</p>

<p>Early in 1504, he was named Vice Chancellor of Cambridge University, and at the end of the year was consecrated Bishop of Rochester, the smallest and poorest diocese in England.</p>

<p>Two days later, he was appointed to office as a member of the King’s Council. Thomas More studied literature and philosophy at Oxford and law at the New Inn. In 1504, he was elected a member of parliament and held several public offices. He earned great prestige because of his knowledge of the law and his integrity.</p>

<p>Although his professional life was intensely time-consuming, he always found time for his family, which was his most important concern, and for his literary and historical studies. He published various books and essays. In 1529, he was appointed Lord Chancellor of England, in spite of having made it clear to the King that he would not agree to the dissolution of the King’s marriage.</p>

<p>Taking a full interest in the problems of his day, he dedicated himself to his work with the desire of implementing the laws and institutions of his times with a Christian approach. Both men were beheaded in 1535 for refusing to recognize the supremacy of Henry VIII over the Church in England and the annulment of the King’s marriage.</p>

<p>In England in 1534, all citizens who had come of age were ordered to take the oath unto the Act of Succession, which acknowledged the union of Henry VIII with Anne Boleyn as a marriage. The King proclaimed himself supreme head of the Church in England and denied any authority to the Pope. John Fisher, Bishop of Rochester, and Thomas More, Chancellor of the Realm, both refused to take the oath. They were imprisoned in 1534 and were beheaded the following year.</p>

<p>At a time when many acceded to the royal will, it would scarcely have been noticed if these two had taken the oath. They would have saved their lives, their property, their positions, as so many others did. Both of these men, however, were true to the faith, even to the point of martyrdom.</p>

<p>They were able to give their lives when the time came, because they were of the kind who lived their vocation day by day, giving daily witness to the faith, sometimes in matters that might have seemed of little or no consequence.</p>

<p>Thomas More is a man very close to ourselves because he was an ordinary Christian who knew how to combine, in perfect unity of life, his vocation as the father of a family, with his profession as a lawyer, and later as Lord Chancellor of England. He was at home in the world. He loved all the human realities that formed the framework of his life in the place and position where God wanted him to be.</p>

<p>At the same time, he lived such detachment from earthly things and had such love for the Cross that we can say he drew all of his strength from it. He was in the habit of meditating on a passage of the passion of Our Lord every Friday. When his children or his wife complained about ordinary difficulties and annoyances, he told them they could not expect to go to heaven on feather beds.</p>

<p>He reminded them of the sufferings Our Lord had undergone and that the servant is not greater than his master. As well as using the ordinary little pin pricks and routine mishaps of the day as a means of identifying himself with the Cross, More offered up other penances.</p>

<p>Some days he wore a hair shirt, a garment of rough cloth next to his skin. One writer says he continued this practice during his imprisonment in the Tower of London, in spite of the cold, the damp, and all the privations he had to put up with during those long months. It was here in the Cross that he found his strength.</p>

<p>We are Christians who follow Christ closely in the midst of the world and bear witness to Him, generally silently. We can ask ourselves also, do we find strength in being detached from earthly things and through the daily practice of mortification, penance, and prayer.</p>

<p>When Thomas More had to resign his post as Lord Chancellor, he gathered his family together to talk to them about the future that awaited them and how they would manage financially. He summarized his whole career, saying, “I have been brought up at Oxford, at the Inn of Chancery, at Lincoln’s Inn, and also at the King’s Court. From the lowest to the highest. Yet I now have little above one hundred pounds a year. If we are to continue together, all must become contributors. But my counsel is that it shall not be best for us to fall to the lowest fare first.”</p>

<p>Then he suggested to them a gradual descent, reminding them how it is possible to be content at every level. One writer says, if they were unable to support themselves at even the lowest level, that one at which he had managed to live while in Oxford, he said with peace and good humor, “Then we may yet with bags and wallets go a-begging together, and hoping for, for pity, some good folks will give us of their charity, and so still keep company and be merry together.” He never allowed anything to disturb the unity and peace of his family, even when he was away or in prison.</p>

<p>He lived detached from things when he had them, and with great joy when he did not possess or even have access to even the most indispensable necessities of life. He was always able to rise above circumstances. He knew how to celebrate important events even behind prison bars. A contemporary biographer tells us that while he was imprisoned in the Tower, he would dress more elegantly on important feast days, so far as his meager wardrobe would permit. He always remained cheerful and good-humored, even at the moment when he was ascending the scaffold, because he relied firmly on prayer.</p>

<p>“Good Lord, the things that I pray for,” he said, “give me your grace to labor for.” He did not expect God to give him those things that, with just a little effort on his part, he could obtain for himself. He worked all his life so as to become a lawyer of great prestige before being appointed Lord Chancellor. He never forgot, however, the need for prayer. Even though at times, and particularly in circumstances as dramatic as those leading up to his execution, it was not easy for him.</p>

<p>During those days, he wrote a long prayer in which many of the pious and moving considerations made by a man who knew he was about to die. He exclaimed, “Grant me, my Lord, a desire to be with you, not so as to avoid the calamities of this world, nor even to avoid the pains of purgatory, nor those of hell, nor to gain the joys of heaven, not out of consideration for my own profit, but simply through true love for you.”</p>

<p>St. Thomas More is always presented to us as a man of prayer. St. Josemaría says in <em>The Furrow</em>, “This enabled him to be faithful whatever the circumstances, to his commitments as a citizen and as a Christian. Thereby living a perfect unity of life. This is how we too have to be. A Catholic without prayer is the same as a soldier without arms.” We could ask ourselves, well how is my relationship with Christ?</p>

<p>Do I try to grow each day in intimacy with Him? Does my prayer influence the rest of my day? He prayed, “Give me the grace, Good Lord, to set the world at naught. To have my mind well united to you. To not depend on the changing opinions of others. So that I may think joyfully of God, and tenderly implore your help. So that I may lean on God’s strength and make an effort to love Him. So as to thank Him ceaselessly for His benefits. So as to redeem the time I have wasted.”</p>

<p>The saint wrote these words in the margin of the Book of Hours he had with him in the Tower of London. They were days in which he gave himself over completely to contemplating the Passion, and in this way to preparing himself for his own death in union with the death Christ suffered on the cross.</p>

<p>Saint Thomas’s last moments on earth were seen not only by God. His love for God had been clear to everyone around him, day by day in his family life, in his simple, pleasant manner, in the way he carried out his profession as a lawyer, in holding the highest post in the land, that of Lord Chancellor.</p>

<p>It was through fulfilling the duties of each day, some of which were important, others less important, that he sanctified himself and helped others to find God. Among many other examples of his effective apostolate, he has left us that of the apostolate he did with his son-in-law, who had fallen into the Lutheran heresy.</p>

<p>He said to his daughter, “I have borne a long time with your husband. I have reasoned and argued with him on these points of religion, and given to him my poor fatherly counsel, but I perceive none of this is able to call him home, and therefore, Meg, I will no longer dispute with him, but will give him over, and get me to God to pray for him.”</p>

<p>More’s words and prayers were effective, as soon afterwards, Roper returned to the fullness of the faith and afterwards suffered much through remaining loyal to the Catholic faith. Saint Thomas More remains among us as a living example for our conduct as Christians. He is the fruitful seed of peace and joy.</p>

<p>As was his passage on earth, at home among his family and friends, in the law courts, in the university chair, at court, in the embassies, in parliament, and in government. He is also a silent patron of England who shed his blood in defense of the unity of the Church and of the spiritual power of the Vicar of Christ.</p>

<p>One writer says, “As the blood of Christians is a germinating seed, the blood of Thomas More slowly seeps into and soaks the souls of those who approach him, drawn by his prestige, his sweetness of character, and his strength. More will be the silent apostle of the return to the faith of a whole nation.”</p>

<p>We can ask John Fisher and Thomas More to teach us to imitate them in their Christian coherence, so that we may live as God wants us to in all things, both great and small, whatever the circumstances of our lives. The opening prayer of today’s Mass says, “In the death of your martyrs, O God, we see the noblest of testimonies to the true faith. Grant we pray that strengthened by the prayers of Saint Thomas More and Saint John Fisher, we may bear witness in our lives to the faith we confess with our lips.”</p>

<p>When we contemplate the lives of these great saints, also of the English-speaking world, we could note the first necessary step in persevering to the end of the way: that desire of wanting to be a saint. We could ask them for those real and effective desires. The psalms we read, “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. As a deer longs for flowing streams, so longs my soul for you, O God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2–3).</p>

<p>The deer attempting to quench its thirst with water is the psalmist’s symbolic way of describing the desire for God present in the heart of an upright person. A thirst and vehement desire for God. Such is the aspiration of one who is not content to accept worldly success as the satisfaction for human ambitions. We’re told in Saint Matthew’s Gospel, “What will it profit a man if he gains the whole world and forfeits his life?” (Matt. 16:26).</p>

<p>Our Lord’s question forces us to take a radical look at the broad horizon of our life to which only God gives ultimate meaning. “My soul thirsts for God.” Saint Josemaría says, “The saints are not abnormally gifted people, nor have they necessarily been completely perfect since childhood. They are men and women with a great desire to belong to God completely, despite their defects.” We could each ask ourselves, “Have I a true desire to be a saint?”</p>

<p>The answer most assuredly would be in the affirmative, yes. But our reply should not be as to a theoretical question, he says, “Because for some, holiness is unattainable, something to do with ascetical theology, but not a real goal, a living reality.”</p>

<p>“We want to make it happen with the help of God’s grace. So longs my soul for you, O God.” We have to start by making the desire for holiness flourish in our own soul, telling Our Lord, “I want to be a saint, or at least when I experience my softness and weakness, I want to want to be a saint.”</p>

<p>To banish doubt and make holiness more than an empty word, we need to turn and look at Christ. The Second Vatican Council says, “The Lord Jesus, the divine teacher and model of all perfection, preached holiness of life, of which he is the author and maker, to each and every one of his disciples without distinction” (Lumen Gentium, 40).</p>

<p>“You therefore must be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect” (Matt. 5:48). He has taken the initiative. If He had not, the possibility of being a saint would never have occurred to us. Jesus put it to us as a command, “Be perfect.” It is not surprising that the Church makes sure her children hear these resounding words.</p>

<p>Therefore, all the faithful, says the Second Vatican Council, are invited and obliged to holiness and the perfection of their own state of life. Think then how deep our desire for holiness has to be. In Scripture, the prophet Daniel is “a man of desires” (Dan. 9:23).</p>

<p>It would be wonderful if we were all worthy of such a title. The first thing that souls must do if they embark on the path of holiness, says St. Teresa, is really to want to be saints, whatever may come, whatever may happen to them, however hard they may have to labor, whoever may complain of them, whether they reach their goal or die on the road.</p>

<p>In <em>The Furrow</em>, we’re told, “Allow your soul to be consumed by desires, desires for loving, for forgetting yourself, for sanctity, for heaven. Do not stop to wonder whether the time will come for seeing them accomplished, as some pseudo-advisor might suggest. Make them more fervent each day, for the Holy Spirit says that He is pleased with men of desires.”</p>

<p>“Let your desires be operative and put them into practice in your daily tasks.” We should examine our conscience to see if our desires for holiness are sincere and effective, and furthermore to see if we take them as something obligatory for a faithful Christian, as the Second Vatican Council states, in response to God’s desires.</p>

<p>This response could reveal the reason for so much apathy and weakness in our interior struggle. In <em>The Way</em>, we’re told, “You tell me yes, you want to. Very good, but do you want to as a miser longs for gold, as a mother loves her child, as a worldling craves for honors, or as a wretched sensualist seeks his pleasure?”</p>

<p>“No, then you don’t really want to.” We could try to develop these desires with the virtue of hope. One can only effectively desire something when there is a hope of attaining it. If we consider some aim to be impossible and not for us, we will not really desire it. Our theological hope rests on God.</p>

<p>Softness and lukewarmness can destroy our desires for holiness. There is need for vigilance. The conversion of Cornelius the Centurion, mentioned in today’s Mass, in the first reading, shows that God is no respecter of persons. Saint Peter explains to the others what has happened. The Holy Spirit, we’re told in the Acts, “fell upon them just as on us at the beginning” (Acts 11:15).</p>

<p>There are no limits or barriers to the power of the Holy Spirit. This is true in our case, just as it was for Cornelius, who was not a Jew by race or nation. On the one hand, we have to want to be saints, but we must also take into account that we’re told in the Psalms that, “Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labor in vain” (Ps. 127:1).</p>

<p>Humility leads us to count always above all on God’s grace. To this we add our efforts to acquire virtues and practice them continuously, and our apostolic zeal, since our concept of personal holiness should not be one which ignores others or which is indifferent to charity. That would be contradictory.</p>

<p>There is our desire to be with Christ on the Cross. That is, to be mortified, not rejecting sacrifice in small things, and if need be in big things. We should be forewarned about approaching God with reservations and without renunciation, trying to make the love of God compatible with what is not pleasing to Him.</p>

<p>We should be alert in developing our desires for holiness continually through prayer, by asking God for the ability to struggle each day, to discover in our examination of conscience the places where our love is growing cold. Saint John of the Cross says, “Desire for holiness is real when we fulfill acts of piety with refinement, not omitting them or delaying them for any reason whatever, refusing to be led by our moods and feelings.”</p>

<p>Because the soul truly in love with God never fails through laziness to do all in its power to seek God’s Son the Beloved. And having done all it could, is still not satisfied as it thinks it has done nothing. The virtue of humility enables us to avoid a sense of self-satisfaction with what we have done, and not to be content with ineffectual desires.</p>

<p>It lets us see how we can do more to show the sincerity of our desires with deeds of love, ensuring that our sins, offenses, and negligences don’t frustrate our expectations. Humility doesn’t clip the wings of our desires, but rather helps us to understand the need to have recourse to God to make them come true. With God’s grace, we can do all in our power to make virtue grow in our soul by removing obstacles, fleeing from occasions of sin, and bravely resisting temptations. We should avoid discouragement in the struggle to improve.</p>

<p>We have to count on time and on God’s grace. “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God” (Ps. 42:2). St. Josemaría says, “Is this thirst compatible with our experience of our defects and even our falls? Yes, because saints are not those who have never sinned, but those who have always got up again.” Refusal to pursue holiness and seeing ourselves full of defects is a hidden form of pride and obvious cowardice which will end up stifling our desires for God. “Feeling easily deflated,” says St. Josemaría, “and lying down under adversity is characteristic of cowardly souls lacking the firm virtue of trusting in God’s promises.”</p>

<p>Abandoning God, ceasing to struggle because of our defects when there is opposition is a serious mistake. A very subtle and dangerous temptation, which can lead us to that form of pride called pusillanimity, lack of courage and strength to bear misfortune or undertake large enterprises. We may need to rid ourselves of false illusions in wanting to be saints in a day. That would be impossible, unless God decided to perform a miracle, which He has no reason to do, since He gives us all the graces we need by ordinary means in a continuous and progressive way.</p>

<p>One writer says, “An effective desire for holiness consists in a conscious and determined effort to use the necessary means to attain holiness.” If desire is lacking, nothing can be done. One doesn’t even try. Desires alone are not enough. We must be patient then, and not try to banish in a day the many habits we have picked up in neglecting our spiritual health. “As the deer longs for flowing streams, so my soul longs for you, O God” (Ps. 42:1). We could almost hear those words on the lips and heart of St. Thomas More and Bishop John Fisher.</p>

<p>Let us try to keep our desire for God alive, to enkindle the flame of faith and hope in the fire of the love of God, enlivening our virtues and burning away our miseries. We will quench our thirst for holiness with the water that springs up to eternal life. And always our mother will be there to help us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Temptation</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/temptation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Temptation" /><published>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/temptation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/temptation/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Then Jesus was led by the Spirit into the desert, to be tempted by the devil. And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, afterwards he was hungry. And the tempter coming said to him: ‘If you be the Son of God, command that these stones be made bread.’ He answered and said: ‘It is written: not in bread alone does man live, but in every word that proceeds from the mouth of God’” (Matt. 4:1-4).</p>

<p>We find the devil mentioned very strongly in this particular moment of the Gospel.</p>

<p>Some people tend to laugh at the very suggestion of the existence of the devil, but his presence in Scripture and in the <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> is very clear. Often, it’s his most powerful weapon that people ignore him, and so he acts like a thief. But he exists and he tempted Christ.</p>

<p>He is the enemy of our redemption. He tempted and made our first parents sin. He disobeyed God and is eager to get man to do the same. He’s envious of the relationship between man and God and seeks to destroy it. Our Lord talks a lot about him, and so we can’t ignore him.</p>

<p>We have a lot of faith in God. It’s good also that we have faith in the devil. But the fact that he tempts us and bothers us on a daily basis doesn’t mean that we need to lose our peace, because we count on the help of Our Father God.</p>

<p>We can always be positive in our fight. We need not look on temptation as a burden. Our Lord Himself underwent temptation. We overcome temptation. We don’t undergo temptation.</p>

<p>We can also count on the fact that in the face of temptation we are never alone. We have the Communion of Saints.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us in these moments to acknowledge our humility, our weakness, and to run with more intensity to prayer and flee from the occasions; at the same time, counting on them, because they are part of the way to sanctity.</p>

<p>Our Lord has already triumphed. We have all the means. We can unite ourselves to His victory.</p>

<p>Every temptation that we overcome strengthens our soul and increases our grace.</p>

<p>Our Lord often was alone in solitude with God. His praying reminds us of the need we too have, to often seek those moments of solitude where we can be alone with God and pray.</p>

<p>“Count it all for joy,” says St. James, “when you fall into different temptations. Knowing that the trying of your faith works patience” (James 1:2-3).</p>

<p>There are many times in Scripture where the benefit of temptation is mentioned.</p>

<p>“Blessed is the person,” also says St. James, “that endures temptation; for when he has been proven he shall receive the crown of life” (James 1:12). Temptation is a pathway to glory and to victory.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “He that thinks himself strong enough to stand, let him take heed lest he fall” (1 Cor. 10:12).</p>

<p>“God is faithful,” says St. Paul, “who will not suffer you to be tempted above what you’re able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that you may be able to bear it” (1 Cor. 10:13).</p>

<p>The devil is the father of lies (John 8:44). Lying is behaving like a child of Satan.</p>

<p>But when we realize that we’ve invited the devil into our house or that he’s cornered us in his cave, our response has to be to run back to God with an act of contrition. Those acts of contrition can be a constant in our life.</p>

<p>Did Jesus need to be tempted? Could He be tempted?</p>

<p>In some ways He didn’t need to be tempted. He was the God-Man. But by allowing Himself to be tempted by the devil, He instructs us how to overcome those temptations.</p>

<p>Tempting means testing: trying to improve something one is not sure about. It involves the possibility that the results may go one way or another.</p>

<p>As God, Jesus could not be tempted, but the devil did not know or was not sure that He was God. It’s unlikely that the devil knew about the doctrine of the Blessed Trinity, which was first revealed to Our Lady. As God-Man, there’s no possibility of failing the test. The devil did not know this.</p>

<p>Why did the God-Man agree to this Himself?</p>

<p>Not to be strengthened, as we might need due to weakness, but it was for our instruction that He allowed Himself to be tempted as we will be tempted and tested. And that testing is not bad; otherwise, He would not have agreed to it. Great benefit can come from that.</p>

<p>St. Padre Pio said that if we knew the merit that comes from overcoming temptation, we would welcome temptations (<em>cf</em>. Padre Pio, <em>Epistolario</em>).</p>

<p>There’s a great good to be gained from it. If we are to be like Him, we will go through the same.</p>

<p>If we are trying to lead holy lives, it’s very logical that the devil will try to knock us off our perch. We’re a big target for him. He wins a great battle if he can bring us down.</p>

<p>Our Lord has come to overcome the devil. The purpose of the Incarnation in some ways was to undo all the evil that the devil had done. St. John says this in his Letter: it was “to undo all that the devil has done that the Son of God appeared” (1 John 3:8).</p>

<p>It’s appropriate that Christ arranges a meeting with the devil, a duel, so that His overcoming Satan will be a pledge to our future success. It was truly a battle of the giants.</p>

<p>In the first temptation, we’re told that the devil tempted Jesus to eat bread: “Turn these stones into loaves of bread” (Matt. 4:3).</p>

<p>After forty days, Our Lord must have been really hungry, as anyone would be. The devil picks Him out at His weakest moment, and that’s what he does to us also.</p>

<p>Now, the Lord answers him with a phrase from Scripture: “Man does not live on bread alone, but on every word that proceeds from the mouth of God” (Matt. 4:4; Deut. 8:3).</p>

<p>It’s a reminder that we are on this journey ourselves, and we also have to rely on the word of God.</p>

<p>Christ doesn’t reject or disclaim that He’s hungry, but He raises the matter to a higher level.</p>

<p>We could also remind ourselves that He is truly the Word of God and He is going to give us the Bread of Life, one of the means to overcome all temptation.</p>

<p>Christ gives us the means. He’s there with us at every moment; He doesn’t leave us alone with the devil. He’s going to give us that Eternal Bread.</p>

<p>The first temptation is a temptation to do things for our own advantage only: “turn these stones into bread.” Eat. The test is on the passions and the needs of the body. Temptation is to care only for the passing food and forget about the eternal Word.</p>

<p>“Do not labor for the food that perishes, but for that which endures to eternal life” (John 6:27). It’s a temptation to rely on one’s own strength, but happiness of life has an eternal dimension.</p>

<p>There are three stages of temptation. There’s suggestion, there’s complacency, and there’s consent. Mortal sin only exists at the level of consent.</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter how many suggestions we may have on a daily basis—to our purity, to our laziness, to our disorder, to our charity, to our obedience, our vanity, our pride, our selfishness—as long as we try not to consent to them.</p>

<p>All the most important people in sacred history have been tempted: Adam, Eve, Abraham, Moses, Peter, and Paul.</p>

<p>By rejecting the temptations of the devil, Our Lord atones for the faults of those who went before Him and those who will come after. His reaction is an example for all the temptations we may have, to greed, to gluttony, to avarice.</p>

<p>He later teaches in the <em>Our Father</em> to ask God to help us with His grace not to fall into temptation: “Lead us not into temptation” (Matt. 6:13).</p>

<p>Before beginning His work as Messiah, Our Lord prepares by prayer and fasting. That’s what the forty days of Lent are all about. The devil makes use of this opportunity. As we begin our mission, we shouldn’t be surprised that the devil has a go at us.</p>

<p>He’s physically empty. This makes Him vulnerable. He could work a miracle, but it’s not part of God’s plan. He prefers to trust in His Father.</p>

<p>We also learn from this how we have to be careful in moments of vulnerability—when we’re low, when we’re tired, when we’re discouraged.</p>

<p>The devil seems to say to Him: How can you be the Son of God and still be hungry? How can your loving heavenly Father have allowed you to be hungry? How can He love you and yet permit this contradiction?</p>

<p>The devil may say the same thing to us in modern parlance: How can you be poor and yet still loved by your heavenly Father? Or unsuccessful? Or unemployed? Or a failure? Or have cancer? Or be in this concentration camp or this jail?</p>

<p>Or your child is in jail or has this incurable disease, and God still loves you? How can you be condemned to die with an incurable sickness? Or how can you have failed your driving test and God still loves you?</p>

<p>A lady came to me once from another country and said, “Father, why is God so cruel? Why does he treat me so roughly? Why does he hate me so much?”</p>

<p>I was wondering what terrible thing had happened in her life. And she said, “I’ve just failed my driving test for the eighth time!”</p>

<p>All the contradictions of life does not mean that God does not love us. We believe with faith that Our Heavenly Father is looking after us 24/7. We have every reason to reject these subtle temptations.</p>

<p>When the devil is stripped of all his disguises, the ultimate goal of the satanic is to avoid the Cross. To avoid self-denial. Avoid standing on our pride, on our selfishness, on our egoism. Avoid any form of mortification.</p>

<p>To this temptation Christ said, “Get behind me, Satan!” (Matt. 16:23).</p>

<p>The three temptations of Christ were worldly ways of avoiding the Cross. At the beginning of His public life, the devil tries to show Christ another way of saving the world.</p>

<p>The way that Our Lord answers the devil teaches us how to deal with temptation. He also teaches us that we shouldn’t ask God for things that we can obtain with our own efforts. God wants us to use the human means.</p>

<p>And we shouldn’t just ask Him for what is exclusively for our own convenience, but rather what will help towards our holiness and that of others.</p>

<p>Jesus says: I can be poor and still be loved. I can be loved and still be hungry. I can be blessed and still be empty. I can be precious to God and still unfulfilled.</p>

<p>He invites us to look to the Word of God for our fulfillment. “Not in bread alone does man live, but on every word that proceeds from the mouth of God” (Matt. 4:4).</p>

<p>It’s an act of trust in Fatherly Providence. God will not let Him die. He led Him to the desert to prepare Him for His mission.</p>

<p>St. Gregory the Great says if we consider how Our Lord let Himself be treated in the Passion, it’s not surprising that He let Himself be treated by the devil as He did (<em>cf</em>. Gregory I, <em>Homilies on the Gospels</em>, Homily 16). It’s all a preparation for what’s to come.</p>

<p>“Then the devil took him into the holy city and set him upon the pinnacle of the temple, and said to him, ‘If you are the Son of God, cast yourself down; for it is written: He has given his angels charge over you, and in their hands they will bear you up, lest you dash your foot against the stone.’ Jesus said to him, ‘It is written again: You shall not tempt the Lord your God’” (Matt. 4:5-7; Deut. 6:16).</p>

<p>In the second temptation, the devil realizes that he hasn’t won the first time. Now he asks Him to enlist the help of the angels: “He has given his angels charge over you.” The devil quotes Sacred Scripture. Interesting.</p>

<p>The test now is the ego—to show that if one is powerful enough, that He can overcome all.</p>

<p>Christ responds, also quoting Scripture, telling him not to test God.</p>

<p>Every time we think we’re powerful enough to overcome an occasion of sin that we put ourselves in, we are testing God: ‘I’m strong enough to resist the temptation.’ ‘I can watch this movie.’ ‘I can look at this picture.’ ‘I can answer this call.’ ‘I can meet this person.’</p>

<p>When we can only find out, to our cost to us, we’re not as strong as we thought we were.</p>

<p>The Church teaches us to flee from occasions of sin. “If your hand is an occasion of sin to you, cut it off” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 5:30).</p>

<p>Christ is very radical. He doesn’t say take one long, last, lingering, loving look at your hand, and then kiss your hand goodbye, and make sure that your hand feels very good about it. Christ said, “Cut it off.”</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord for the fortitude to cut the temptations, to distance ourselves from the occasions of sin, the subtle ways in which the devil comes to us.</p>

<p>When he says to us: Don’t worry, you’re strong; you’re a child of God; nothing will happen; so many of your friends have done the same; you’re a good Christian of proven virtue; surely there’s no sin in entertaining yourself—God is there to help us. By the way, in case you forget, He has even sent His angel.</p>

<p>We have an angel to take care of us. He needs to occupy himself a little bit with our care. The devil says let him do the necessary.</p>

<p>The devil says, “He will send his angel so that you don’t get hurt” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 4:6). But over and above all this, Our Lord says, “You should not tempt the Lord your God” (Matt. 4:7; Deut. 6:16).</p>

<p>We can fly to the care of the angels for our help in moments of temptation. The <em>Prayer to St. Michael</em> is a prayer the Church recommends to say every day, particularly after Mass, and in all dangers and temptations.</p>

<p>Or the <em>Memorare</em> prayer to Our Lady when we feel things are getting hot. It’s a very good prayer to teach your children to make them aware of the devil, and to see how we shouldn’t be asking Our Lord for extraordinary help, when He wants us to avoid the occasions of sin ourselves—to see where the devil may be lurking, to see where the dangers are, to be clever. “The prudent of this world must be children of the light, not children of darkness” (Luke 16:8).</p>

<p>We know that God will help us when there’s no other way, but God is not a remedy for our laziness or our refusal to try.</p>

<p>The whole of Lent reminds us of the importance of struggle. The Old Testament says, “The life of man on earth is a struggle” (<em>cf</em>. Job 7:1). God wants us to struggle like He struggled on the way to Calvary. He fell down three times, but He got up again.</p>

<p>In this temptation the devil quotes Scripture. He sets himself up as an interpreter of Scripture. It’s a reminder to us to reject any interpretation of Scripture that is not in keeping with the teaching of the Church, stressing certain passages to the exclusion of others.</p>

<p>The Magisterium of the Church, guided by the Holy Spirit, is the one divine interpreter of Sacred Scripture. “All power in heaven and on earth has been given to me. Go you, therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:18-19). It’s the teaching power of the Church, guided by the Holy Spirit, that gives us the truth that is in Scripture.</p>

<p>The second temptation is temptation to the spectacular, the extraordinary. “Cast yourself down from the pinnacle of the temple.” Throw yourself out into the air. Do this publicity stunt. Anything to draw the crowd. Be like Superman, Batman, Spiderman.</p>

<p>The devil can also say that to us: Forget the ordinary. Be immersed in the extraordinary. Look for all sorts of extraordinary things.</p>

<p>But we know from Scripture that the ordinary passes unnoticed, like Jesus in Nazareth.</p>

<p>Some people may only believe in God and in Our Lady when they see spectacular things, miracles, apparitions, when they hear God speaking through the crowds, or when they see stigmata.</p>

<p>But Jesus bids us to look for the extraordinary in the ordinary.</p>

<p>The life of a Christian, when he has faith—when he works, when he rests, when he prays—in all moments, is always supernatural. It’s a life in which God is always present with reason enlightened by faith.</p>

<p>Our Lord rejects the [second] temptation as He did the first: “You shall not tempt the Lord your God.”</p>

<p>To tempt God is the opposite of trusting Him. We shouldn’t ask Him for extraordinary help, putting ourselves in dangerous situations: diving off some cliff into the ocean; driving when we’ve taken a drink or two; dilly-dallying with occasions of sin, with certain movies, or our phone, or people—things that we know are a danger for us.</p>

<p>We all have different temptations, different weaknesses. One man’s meat can be another man’s poison. We have to know what we have to be careful with.</p>

<p>And then there is the third temptation. “Again, the devil took him up a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and the glory of them, and said to him, ‘All these will I give you, if falling down you will adore me.’ And Jesus said to him, ‘Be gone, Satan! For it is written: The Lord your God shall you adore, and him only shall you serve.’ Then the devil left him; and behold, angels came and ministered to him” (Matt. 4:8-11).</p>

<p>The third temptation is a temptation to possessions, to have power and glory. He “showed him all the kingdoms of the world.” It’s a temptation to have material things, to social status, to power—temptation to have plenty of dreams of how great it would be to possess the world, or at least half of it.</p>

<p>But the Lord seems to say that happiness does not come from material possessions. It comes from choosing God; at times, choosing the cross, following the pathway of our Christian vocation. Not from doing things that are easy.</p>

<p>We only get momentary happiness from possessions or some material thing. But that is passing and can leave us with a bitter sadness, like that of the rich young man who “went his way sad, because he had great possessions” (Matt. 19:16-22). He clung to his riches.</p>

<p>He could have been an apostle. He could have been one of the great instruments that Our Lord used to build His Church, but he did not want.</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us to let our dreams be on what is necessary to lead a decent life. “Do not labor for the food that perishes, but for that which endures to eternal life” (John 6:27). The rest is from the evil one.</p>

<p>Don’t just focus on desiring riches, or success, or money, or power, or glory. Don’t be like people who actually adore Satan in his many forms.</p>

<p>Sometimes the devil keeps his word. He gives them riches. He provokes Christ to take on the role of an earthly Messiah, a pseudo-Messiah: Identify yourself with the world. Do what is popular. Worship me for I am its prince.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “Do not conform your mind to the ways of this world” (Rom. 12:2).</p>

<p>Christ invites us to be different—at times to clash with our environment, to stick our neck out. To be a leader. To be a conscientious objector, if necessary. To be different to everybody else.</p>

<p>There was a Dutch missionary priest in Singapore who used to tell newly baptized adults in his parish every year—there were sixty of them—“Now that you’re Catholics you have to be different. You can’t be the same as everybody else, because we’ve come to change this world. A Christian has to stand out.”</p>

<p>The devil says to the apostle: Don’t be unpopular. Don’t be different from your colleagues. Don’t clash with your environment. Take it easy.</p>

<p>It’s a temptation to reduce the God-given transcendental mission to a purely human and political one. It’s a reminder to the Church and to each one to remain faithful to its God-given mission in the world.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen used to say, “Whoever marries the spirit of the world in this generation becomes a widow in the next” (Fulton J. Sheen, <em>Sermon</em>, September 22, 1940).</p>

<p>Our Lord replies: “Be gone, Satan! For it is written, the Lord your God you shall adore and him only shall you serve” (Matt. 4:10; Deut. 6:13). There’s an uncompromising rejection of an earthly messianism. Our Lord rejects all human glory.</p>

<p>We’re reminded too that although God had the right to be treated as a God, He took the form of a slave. “He emptied himself” (Phil. 2:7).</p>

<p>We can learn from the attitude of Jesus in these trials. The absence of earthly glory and the blessings of God are not incompatible. If we struggle constantly, we’ll attain victory.</p>

<p>We’re told that “the devil left him and behold, angels came and ministered to him.” Nobody is crowned without having first conquered. The coming of the angels teaches us the interior joy given by God to the person who fights energetically.</p>

<p>Our guardian angels are powerful defenders against temptations. Teach your children to invoke their guardian angel every day.</p>

<p>It is the temptation to identify fidelity to God with success in the eyes of the world. It’s difficult to believe that we’re special and loved by God even when we’re hungry or empty or unfulfilled; when we’re not successful in the eyes of the world.</p>

<p>“We’re not tempted because we’re evil, but because we’re human. There’s nothing intrinsically evil about human nature just because the devil knocks at the door. Evil begins when we open the door and consent to the temptation. Scripture praises the man who suffers temptations.” Job went through many temptations. “When we resist temptation, we strengthen our character” (Fulton J. Sheen, <em>Life Is Worth Living).</em></p>

<p>We need to be careful with temptations so that we don’t fall away from our ideals—the ideals of holiness, of our vocation, the ideals of our apostolate. We’ve come to change the world.</p>

<p>Sometimes we could thank Our Lord for the temptations that He permits in our life. Helps us to know our weaknesses, where we need to struggle.</p>

<p>Our Lord allowed Himself to be tempted, so we can’t be surprised if we’re tempted also.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to Timothy: “He is not crowned, except he who strives lawfully” (2 Tim. 2:5). “Blessed is the person who endures temptation, for when he has been proven, he will receive the crown of life” (James 1:12).</p>

<p>Tried in temptation, virtue grows and increases in firmness (<em>cf</em>. Leo I, <em>Sermon 39</em>).</p>

<p>We know that Our Lady “crushed the head of the serpent” (Gen. 3:15). In moments of temptation, we can turn to Our Mother and ask her for all the strength that we need, to ask her for the help to realize that every urge, every craving is not necessarily a worthy one.</p>

<p>The drug addict hungers for their next high, but we know that all drugs in that sense are bad for you. Saying no to temptation seems to go against the go-for-it philosophy that many people in society promote.</p>

<p>Even our body and mind seem to fight as we deprive it of the fuel it hungers for, regardless of whether that fuel is good or bad for our spiritual and emotional welfare.</p>

<p>Mary, help me to see where my weaknesses lie, and to be wise and prudent to use that information to my best advantage.</p>

<p>The good news is that the more we say no to temptation and ungodly desires, the more we actually strengthen those weak spots. God doesn’t want us to run and hide from temptation, but to face it head on so that we may clearly see the potential pit before us.</p>

<p>Mary, help us to confess our sins, to admit our weaknesses, and to ask God for the strength and the wisdom we need to stand against all evil.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The First Martyrs of the Church of Rome</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-first-martyrs-of-the-church-of-rome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The First Martyrs of the Church of Rome" /><published>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-20T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-first-martyrs-of-the-church-of-rome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-first-martyrs-of-the-church-of-rome/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here. That you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>After Jerusalem and Antioch, Rome was the most important early Christian nucleus. Many Christians came from the Jewish colony existing in Rome. The majority came over from paganism. Today we commemorate the Christians who underwent the first persecution against the church under the emperor Nero, after the destruction of Rome by fire.</p>

<p>The Christian faith had reached Rome very quickly, which was at that time the center of the civilized world. Perhaps the first Christians in the capital of the empire were converted Jews who had come across the faith in Jerusalem itself or in some cities of Asia Minor that had been evangelized by Saint Paul. The faith was passed on from friend to friend, between workmates and relatives. The arrival of Saint Peter in about the year 43 brought about a perceptible strengthening of the little Christian community that was there. From Rome, the new religion spread to many parts of the empire.</p>

<p>The internal peace enjoyed by the imperial world at that time, the improvements in communications that facilitated travel and the rapid transmission of ideas and news, all this favored the spreading of Christianity. The Roman roads that began in the city, the great city itself, reached the most remote corners of the empire. The commercial fleets that regularly crossed the waters of the Mediterranean all helped to spread the new Christian religion throughout the length and breadth of the Roman world.</p>

<p>It’s difficult to describe the process of conversion, the sequence of experience that affected each person who embraced Christianity in first century Rome, just as it is now. Because each conversion is always a miracle of grace and of personal correspondence with God’s gift of it.</p>

<p>There’s no doubt that a decisive influence was the good example given by the Christians. What Saint Paul calls the bonus odor Christi, the good odor of Christ, which had its repercussions in the way they worked, in their joy, their charity, and their understanding for everyone. In the austerity of their lives, and in their human likableness.</p>

<p>They were men and women who tried to live their faith fully in the midst of their ordinary activities. They were now to be found in all levels of society. Daniel was young and Joseph a slave. Aquila wrought a craft. The woman who sold purple dyestuffs supervised a busy workshop. Another was a prison governor. Another a centurion like Cornelius. Saint John Chrysostom says another was in ill health like Timothy. Another was a runaway from slavery like Onesimus. Nothing proved a hindrance to any of these, but all were joyously welcomed and accepted. Both men and women, both young and old, both slaves and free men, both soldiers and civilian citizens alike.</p>

<p>The Acts of the Apostles has left us a delightful account of the hospitality shown by the Christians in Rome. They tell of the welcome given to Paul when he was brought as a prisoner to the capital. The brethren there, Saint Luke informs us, “when they heard of this, came as far as the Forum of Appius and the Three Taverns to meet us. On seeing them, Paul thanked God and took courage” (Acts 28:15). Paul felt strengthened by these demonstrations of fraternal charity.</p>

<p>The first Christians did not give up their professional or social activities. Some people were to do so, with a specific call from God, rather more than two centuries later. With their lives and their words, they considered themselves very much part of this world. Of which they were convinced they were destined to be salt and light. An early Christian writer summed up saying Christians are to the world what the soul is to the body.</p>

<p>We can examine ourselves today to see whether like those first Christians, we too give a good example to the extent that we do in fact move others to come closer to Christ. Do we edify others by our sobriety? By the way we spend money? By our unquenchable cheerfulness? By doing our work well? By keeping our word? By the way we live justice at work with our subordinates and our peers? By carrying out works of mercy, and by never having a bad word to say about anybody at all?</p>

<p>The first Christians often came up against serious obstacles and misunderstandings, which in not a few cases led to their death for defending their faith in the Master. Today on this feast we celebrate the testimony of the first Roman martyrs. Their execution was the result of the burning of Rome in the year 64. This catastrophe provided the excuse for the first great persecution. To Saint Peter and Paul, whose feast we celebrated yesterday, were added a great number of chosen ones, “who having gone under many sufferings and torments out of envy, were the best models among us,” says Saint Clement of Rome. We read this in a vivid account to be found among the earliest Christian writings.</p>

<p>The obstacles and misunderstandings encountered by those who had been converted did not inevitably lead them to martyrdom. But they often experienced in their lives what the words of the Holy Spirit warn us in scripture. Indeed, says Saint Paul to Timothy, “All who desire to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted” (2 Tim. 3:12). Sometimes the pagans’ antagonism to the followers of Christ arose because they could not bear the rich fruitfulness and splendor of devotion in the Christian daily life. At other times it arose because those who had received the faith had the duty of abstaining from the traditional religious ceremonial which was closely bound up with public life, and was even considered a test of loyalty, an open and formal proof of civic faithfulness to Rome and to the emperor.</p>

<p>Consequently, the pagans who embraced Christianity laid themselves open to misunderstandings and slanderous attacks for not conforming, for not being like the others. It’s unlikely that God will ask us to shed our blood in order to confess the Christian faith. Although if God were to allow such a trial we would ask him for the grace to enable us to give our lives in testimony of our love for him. We will however, in one way or another, meet all kinds of adversity. For being with Jesus means we shall most certainly come upon his cross.</p>

<p>“When we abandon ourselves into God’s hands, he frequently permits us to taste sorrow, loneliness, opposition, slander, defamation, ridicule, coming from both within and from outside the Church,” Saint Josemaría wrote in <em>Friends of God</em>. “This is because he wants to mold and form us into his own image and likeness. He even tolerates our being called lunatics and allows us, if we will, to be taken for fools. This is the way Jesus fashions the souls of those he loves. While at the same time never failing to give them inner calm and joy.”</p>

<p>Slander, perhaps seeing doors to promotion closed against us at work, friends or workmates who turn their backs on us, sarcastic remarks or derogatory words. If God allows them, we have to try and make use of such contradictions in order to live charity in a more heroic way. Precisely with those very people who do not have any respect for us. Perhaps out of inculpable ignorance. Our attitude can always include a just defense when necessary, especially when we have to avoid the possibility of scandal, or of injury being caused to third persons. Such situations will be a great help in enabling us to cleanse ourselves of our own sins and faults, to make reparation for those of others, to ask pardon for the offense that is made against God by them. And finally, to grow in virtue and in love of God.</p>

<p>God sometimes wants to purify us like gold in the crucible. Saint Jerome Emiliano said fire cleans gold from the dross, freeing it from impurities and greatly enhancing its value. God does the same with the good servant, who hopes and who remains constant in the midst of tribulation. If contradictions lie in our way and troubles beset us because we follow Jesus closely, we have then to be especially cheerful and give thanks to God. It makes us worthy to suffer something for him, as the apostles did. We’re told in the Acts of the Apostles, “Then they left the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer dishonor for the name” (Acts 5:41).</p>

<p>The apostles would doubtless have remembered the words of the Master, just as we meditate on them today during this feast of the first Roman martyrs. We are told in Saint Matthew, “Blessed are you when men revile you, and persecute you, and utter all kinds of evil against you falsely on my account. Rejoice and be glad, for your reward is great in heaven, for so men persecuted the prophets who went before you” (Matt. 5:11–12).</p>

<p>In spite of all ill-considered slander, infamy itself, and outbreaks of persecution, our first brothers in the faith did not fail to carry out an effective apostolate. They did not fail to tell people about Christ. The treasure they themselves had had the good fortune to find. Moreover, their calm and joyful bearing in the face of adversity, and even of death, was the very reason why many came to know the Master.</p>

<p>Tertullian says the deaths of the martyrs were the seeds of Christians. The Roman community itself, after so many men, women and children had given their lives in the course of that terrible persecution, went forward invigorated and strengthened. Years later, Tertullian wrote, “We are of but yesterday, and already we have filled the world and all your things. Cities, islands, towns, villages, hamlets, the army, the palace, the senate, the forum. We have left you only the temples.”</p>

<p>In our own sphere, in our present circumstances, if we perhaps encounter some slight difficulty to our remaining firm in the faith, we should understand that from this particular spot of bother will come a great good for all. It is at such times that we have most reason, and most need to speak with serenity about the wonder of the faith. About the immense gift of the sacraments. About the beauty of the fruits of living holy purity well. We should understand that we have elected to be on the winning side in the combat of this life, and also in that other glorious life that awaits us shortly.</p>

<p>Nothing compares with being close to Christ. Even if we had no possessions at all and had to suffer the painful illnesses of the most vile slander, so long as we possess Jesus, we possess everything. The effect of this realization should be noticeable even in our outward bearing, and in our awareness that we are at every moment, even in such circumstances, the salt of the earth and the light of the world, as the Master has told us. Referring to the philosophers of his day, Saint Justin rightly said that all the good spoken by them belongs to us Christians. Because after God, we adore and love the Word, who proceeds from the unbegotten and ineffable God himself. Indeed, for love of us he became man, so as to share in our sufferings and heal us.</p>

<p>In the opening prayer of the Mass today, we say, “Father you sanctified the church of Rome with the blood of its first martyrs. May we find strength in their courage and rejoice in their triumph.” This world of ours that we have to bring to you Jesus sometimes asks the apostles to listen attentively to his doctrine. At other times he calls them together so that he can be alone with them and explains a parable to them once again. Or shows them what lesson they should draw from something that has happened. He wants them to realize that they are being given a treasure, which is meant for the whole church, and of which later they will have to give an account.</p>

<p>“Take heed,” he says to them on one occasion. And he gives them the lesson. “To him who has will more be given, and from him who has not, even what he has will be taken away” (Mark 4:24–25). Saint John Chrysostom comments, to him who is diligent and fervent, will be given all the things that depend on God. But to him who has no love or fervor, and does not do what depends on him, what belongs to God will not be given him. For even what he thinks he has will be taken away. Not because God takes it away from him, but because he is incapable of receiving such graces.</p>

<p>“To him who has will more be given.” This is a basic teaching, says Saint Augustine, for the interior life of every Christian. To him who corresponds with grace, more grace will be given, so that he will have still more grace. But he who fails to make the inspirations, motions, and help of the Holy Spirit bear fruit will become even poorer. Those men who traded with their talents entrusted to them received a greater fortune or reward. But the man who hid his talent in the ground lost it.</p>

<p>Interior life, like love, is destined to grow. “If you say enough,” says Saint Augustine, “you are already dead.” Interior life always demands progress, correspondence, being ready to receive new graces. If you don’t go forward, you go backwards. God has promised that we will always have access to all the help we need at every moment. We’ll be able to say with the psalmist, “The Lord takes care for me” (Ps. 40:17). The difficulties, temptations, internal or external obstacles we come up against all cause us to grow. The greater the difficulty, the more the grace we receive.</p>

<p>If he permits us to experience great temptations or setbacks, he will give us proportionately still greater help to overcome them. Then all those things that seem to retard our struggle for holiness or even make succeeding in it seem impossible, will become the cause of spiritual progress and of our effectiveness in the apostolate. Saint Augustine says it’s only a lack of love, nothing less than lukewarmness, that causes the soul’s life to fall sick or die. Only a bad will, a lack of generosity towards God, can delay or prevent our union with him.</p>

<p>The vessel of faith carried to the fountain is filled according to its capacity. Christ is an inexhaustible source of help, of love, and of understanding. We can ask ourselves and examine ourselves with what capacity, with what longing do we approach him. Lord, we say to him in our prayer, make us thirst for you more and more, as the first Christians did. Make me thirst for you even more intensely than the man dying in the desert thirsts for water.</p>

<p>There are various reasons that can cause us to make scant progress in our interior life, and even to lose ground and give way to discouragement. But these reasons can be reduced to just a few. Carelessness, negligence in little things connected with service to God and friendship with him. Drawing back from the sacrifices that he asks of us. All we have to do, all we have to offer to God each day, are our little acts of faith and love. Petitions, acts of thanksgiving, thanksgiving after Mass, visit to the Blessed Sacrament and being aware that we’re going to meet Jesus Christ himself who is waiting for us. Our customary prayers throughout the day.</p>

<p>Human life is in some way a constant returning to the Father’s house. We return to our Father’s house by means of the sacrament of penance. In <em>Christ is Passing By</em>, we’re told God is waiting for us like the father in the parable, with open arms, even though we don’t deserve it. It doesn’t matter how great our debt is. Just like the prodigal son, all we have to do is open our heart, to be homesick for our Father’s house. To wonder at and rejoice in the gift which God makes us of being able to call ourselves his children, of really being his children, even though our response to him has been so poor.</p>

<p>God never abandons us. He always welcomes us, comforts us, and moves us to start again with more love, with more humility. Our weaknesses help us to seek for divine mercy and be humble. Growth in the virtue of humility means we’re able to make many steps forward in the interior life. All the virtues benefit from our being more humble. If at times we find we fail to correspond with all the graces we’ve received, if we have not been as faithful to God as he was expecting us to be, we must turn contritely to him with a contrite heart.</p>

<p>The Psalms say “Create a clean heart in me O God, and put a new and right spirit within me” (Ps. 51:10). We should often think of those things which, although they’re small, separate us from God. Then we will be moved to sorrow and contrition and be brought closer to him. In this way, our interior life emerges enriched, not only by our contending with exterior obstacles, but also by the recognition of our weakness, our mistakes, and our sins, drawing back from the sacrifices that he asks of us.</p>

<p>If we find it more difficult to begin again, our mother is always there to help us. She makes the way that leads to her son easier. We can ask her to help us with many acts of contrition. It’s interesting how the first Christians of Rome had great devotion to Our Lady, and in many streets of Rome you find a large image of Our Lady built into the building structure itself. We might find it helpful to repeat the prayer of the tax collector, “God be merciful to me a sinner” (Luke 18:13), or the prayer of King David, “A humble and contrite heart O Lord, you will not spurn” (Ps. 51:17).</p>

<p>Love grows within us and develops in the midst of our setbacks and the resistance each of us puts to that love on the inside. It also grows and develops in the face of resistance from the outside. That is, despite the many external forces that are foreign and even hostile to it. Our Lord has promised us that the help of his grace will never fail us. It all depends on our correspondence and our determination, and our willingness to start time and again without getting discouraged. The more faithful we are to grace, the more help he gives us, the easier we will find it to follow the way.</p>

<p>We’ll also find that more is being demanded of us and even greater finesse in our soul. Love always calls for more love. This interior life of ours is given a special chance to grow when we’re confronted with those adverse situations. For the soul, there is no obstacle greater than that which is created by our own wretchedness, and as a result of our carelessness and lack of love. But in those circumstances, says Saint Francis de Sales, the Holy Spirit teaches us and moves us to react in a supernatural way, with an act of contrition. God be merciful to me a sinner.</p>

<p>Saint Francis de Sales teaches us that we should feel ourselves strengthened by the silent saying of aspiratory prayers filled with love and sorrow, and desires for a deeper reconciliation, so that through them we may come to trust in his merciful heart. Acts of contrition are an effective means of spiritual progress. To ask for forgiveness is to love. It is to contemplate Christ the growing dispositions of understanding and mercy. As we are sinners, our way will be filled with acts of sorrow, of love that fill our soul with hope and renew our longing to set off again on the way to sanctity.</p>

<p>We need to return to Christ time and again without becoming discouraged or overworried. Although there may be many times when we have not responded well to love. God’s mercy is infinite and encourages us to start out again with a new determination, with renewed hope. We must be like the prodigal son. Instead of remaining far away in a foreign land, filled with shame and living in misery, he came to his senses and said “I will arise and go to my father” (Luke 15:18).</p>

<p>Let us ask Our Lord that our interior life would be nourished by the little things that we carry out with love and attention. Saint Josemaría wrote, to claim anything else would be to mistake our way. To find nothing or very little to offer to God. It’s good to remember how we find in <em>Christ is Passing By</em> the story of that character imagined by a French author, who set out to hunt lions in the corridors of his home. Naturally he didn’t find any. Our life is quite ordinary. Trying to serve God in big things would be like trying to hunt lions in the corridor. Just like the huntsman in the story, we would end up empty-handed.</p>

<p>Let us try to learn today from the example of the early Christians. We can ask Our Lady, our mother in the order of grace, mother of mercy and of forgiveness, to always enkindle in us the hope of attaining the ambitious target of becoming saints. May we place the fruits of these moments of personal prayer in your hands, with the conviction that if we correspond to grace, still more grace will be given to us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you my God for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>