<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-15T09:07:59+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Zeal for Holiness Through Marriage</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zeal for Holiness Through Marriage" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>There was a meeting of priests in Singapore one time, and we were talking about vocation. One religious missionary priest from Belgium stood up and said he learned the meaning of vocation from a young married couple in the United States, when he was on his first assignment. They were 25 years of age, they were expecting their first baby, and the baby turned out to be a Down’s baby.</p>

<p>The obstetrician said to the mother, whose name was Nancy, “Are you ready to accept this baby? I can’t tell you it’s going to be easy, but I can tell you that for every ounce of love that you put into this baby, you’re going to get a pound of love in return.”</p>

<p>Nancy said, “Yes, we’re ready to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>This elderly priest who was 28 years of age at the time said, “I was very struck by that, because nobody gets married and says, ‘I want to have a handicapped child.’ I realized that is the meaning of vocation: to be ready to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>This meditation is about zeal for holiness in marriage.</p>

<p>He said, “I began to ask myself, ‘Am I ready to accept whatever comes? Here I am, a 28-year-old priest, my first missionary assignment setting out in life. A couple of years later, I was asked to go and work in Rome, work behind a desk, and handle all of the financial, legal, and architectural aspects of our organization all over the world.</p>

<p>“One day, somebody came to me and said, ‘What are you doing here, working behind a desk in Rome? You’re supposed to be a missionary priest. Why are you not off in Brazil or Alaska someplace?’”</p>

<p>He said, “I got my answer from Nancy. I didn’t ask for this job. I don’t particularly like it. I’d much prefer to be somewhere else. But I try to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>If somebody came to our organization and said, “I’m willing to join your missionary organization as long as I can work behind a desk in Rome and do all the jobs that I want and I like” they would be told, “I’m sorry, you don’t have a vocation to our organization. Part of the deal is that you have to be ready to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>As we look to the topic of zeal for holiness in marriage, we could ask ourselves, Why did I get married? What is the purpose of marriage? What’s it all about? What is the marriage contract?</p>

<p>Our baptismal vocation tells us that the goal of our Christian vocation is holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>If we’re married, it’s because we have a vocation to be married. That’s the pathway to holiness that God wants for us. Pope St. John Paul II likes to say that we’re all called to the eternal wedding feast.</p>

<p>Marriage now is a preparation for marriage later. God wants to marry us. People who live celibate lives skip the historical reality here on earth in order to give witness to the fact that real marriage comes later.</p>

<p>So everything in our marriage is a preparation for marriage in the next.</p>

<p>There is a saying in different but similar words from St. Josemaría, who spent his whole life saying that marriage is a pathway to holiness, and holiness ultimately is love, charity. That’s what we’re called to. That’s the definition of holiness (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 91).</p>

<p>Every moment of every day, every opportunity, is a calling to holiness.</p>

<p>In our prayer today, we could ask Our Lord that we might have a zeal for that holiness. We might want the goal of our marriage ultimately to get to heaven and to bring the people around us to heaven.</p>

<p>Our Lord says, “You did not choose me. No, I chose you and I commissioned you to go out and bear fruit—fruit that will last” (John 15:16).</p>

<p>We have been chosen “before the foundation of the world” (Eph. 1:4). Every aspect of our life has been chosen: your wife, your home, your health, your work, your financial difficulties, your children. It’s all part of a great divine plan in which God wants us to participate.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul liked to say that “the Blessed Trinity is a communion of persons” (quoting the <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point 2205). He liked to say that “the family is a communion of persons” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Familiaris Consortio</em>, Nov. 22, 1981).</p>

<p>So he lifted up the family onto this Trinitarian level. Our goal is somehow to imitate the Trinity.</p>

<p>He said marriage is a life-giving communion of persons (Pope John Paul II, <em>General Audience</em>, Nov. 14, 1979). The Blessed Trinity is a life-giving communion of persons. The love of the Father for the Son gives rise to the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>The <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> says that children are the supreme gift of marriage (<em>CCC</em>, Point 1652). It’s an enormously positive statement. And because God chose us, He gives us the grace for that choice.</p>

<p>Like the apostles, we have not been chosen because of what we are, but because of what we have to become. Peter was not chosen because of what he was, but because of what he had to become, in spite of his miseries and his failures.</p>

<p>He did the same thing as Judas. He betrayed Our Lord. “Woman, I do not know him” (Luke 22:57). Then we’re told in Scripture, “The Lord turned and looked upon Peter” (Luke 22:61).</p>

<p>It’s a very poignant moment. He seeks him out with His loving glance in his lowest moment. “And Peter goes out and weeps bitterly” (Luke 22:62). It’s from this moment that he goes forward to become a great saint and a great apostle.</p>

<p>That’s God’s will for each one of us: to be a great saint and a great apostle in our marriage, with everything that comes with it, ready to accept whatever comes.</p>

<p>We can thank God very much for this vocation that He’s given to us, the purpose of our existence. We can try and find meaning in that calling—our growth in holiness, which is a growth in virtue.</p>

<p>Pope St. Paul VI said on one occasion that “the cultivation of Christian perfection must still be regarded as the richest source of the Church’s spiritual strength” (Pope Paul VI, Encyclical, <em>Ecclesiam Suam</em>, August 6, 1964).</p>

<p>Rather interesting words: “the richest source of the Church’s spiritual strength” is the domestic Church.</p>

<p>We are called to live like great human persons, a man of virtue, that sees every day as an opportunity to grow in charity, in patience, in kindness, in order, in industriousness, in punctuality, in forgetfulness of self.</p>

<p>It’s in all these virtues and the cultivation of them that we find the purpose and the meaning of our life. Now that may entail many occasions of beginning again.</p>

<p>There was a lawyer in Sydney once who used to come to retreats every year and attend Circles and recollections. One time an elderly couple came to see him. He was 86 and she was 83. He said to them, “What can I do for you?”</p>

<p>They said, “We want to get a divorce.”</p>

<p>“And why do you want to get a divorce?”</p>

<p>“Because we don’t love each other anymore.”</p>

<p>“And how long have you been married?”</p>

<p>“Forty years.”</p>

<p>So the lawyer quickly tried to remember all the points about the talk or the meditation on charity from his last retreat. He tried to give them an impromptu talk on the meaning of charity.</p>

<p>Charity is patient. Charity is kind. It’s letting the water flow under the bridge. It’s knowing how to forgive. It’s not making a mountain out of molehills. It’s moving on. It’s loving other people with their defects.</p>

<p>He went through as many points as he could remember about the virtue of charity and asked them to go away and think about it for a while.</p>

<p>They weren’t very convinced, but the husband said, “Okay, we’ll give it a go.” So they went away.</p>

<p>Three years later, the wife came back and said, “I came back because I want to thank you. My husband just passed away, but we’ve just had three of the most wonderful years of our whole life.”</p>

<p>The moral of the story is that we’re always beginning again in love.</p>

<p>Love is a mystery. God is love (1 John 4:8). As the Preface of the Sacred Heart said to us last Friday, we go to the Sacred Heart of Christ to “draw water in joy from the wells of salvation” (Isa. 12:3).</p>

<p>In the wounded heart of Christ, we learn the meaning of love: forgetfulness of self, sacrifice, and a willingness to be on the cross, to start over.</p>

<p>The devil can present sanctity to us as something unattainable.</p>

<p>Sanctity is continuously doing what God wants, not what we want.</p>

<p>There was a story of a Mexican man who, for 25 years, every Saturday afternoon, used to bring his wife to the bullfights.</p>

<p>One Saturday afternoon, the wife said, “Let’s not go to the bullfights. I’m fed up going to the bullfights.” After thinking about it, the husband said, “Okay, let’s not go to the bullfights. I never really wanted to go to the bullfights anyway.”</p>

<p>There was a man who learned how to keep his first love in first place.</p>

<p>We all know how the other loves of our life—Manchester United, golf, tennis, the local bar—all these things can move themselves up, maneuver themselves up sometimes, into first place.</p>

<p>Part of holiness is keeping our first love in first place—knowing the importance of that. It’s said that the greatest thing that a man can do for his family is to love his wife very much. The greatest thing a woman can do for her family is to love her husband very much.</p>

<p>That means we have to take care of love because if we’re not careful, the devil can rob us of it.</p>

<p>Love is expressed in details. St. Josemaría liked to say that married couples, after many years of marriage, have to keep their love young and fresh, like it was before they got married.</p>

<p>So we have to know how to sweep our spouse off their feet from time to time with little details, with surprises, with small things. People need affection. They need to be told that they’re loved, that they’re beautiful, that they’re appreciated.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas was asked, “In the quest for holiness, what’s the most important thing?” He answered: “To desire it, to want it with all our heart and soul.”</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord in our prayer today, Do I want that goal of my marriage vocation more than anything else in the world? Do I take care of it? Where am I now in that zeal for holiness? Am I looking after things? Am I taking care of things? What’s the theme of their marriage vocation at the moment?</p>

<p>If you were to sing a song, what would that song be? There was a song in the 1960s that said, “Where have all the flowers gone...long time passing?”</p>

<p>Or in the 1990s, “Once upon a time, I was falling in love, and now I’m only falling apart. There’s been a total eclipse of the heart. Once upon a time, there was light in my life.”</p>

<p>Wherever we may be, we have to try and go back and begin again, relying sometimes a little more on the grace that God gives us.</p>

<p>There are two prayers to the Holy Spirit that you’ll find in the Christian devotions. One is for the sequence of Pentecost Sunday. It’s <em>Veni Sancti Spiritus</em> and <em>Veni Creator Spiritus.</em></p>

<p>The Holy Spirit is the great sanctifier. It gives us fire, the fire of love. So it makes a lot of sense to invoke the Holy Spirit frequently or to pray those prayers, perhaps in your Thanksgiving after Mass, or other moments of the day.</p>

<p>Just as we polish up our shoes every day or two, we need to do the same with our vocation to holiness, to understand what is necessary to make our vocation grow: sacraments, formation. We need regular input: yearly retreat, monthly recollection. Maybe a weekly confession.</p>

<p>These are the systems that the saints have placed in a position to help us to attain that goal of holiness. At the same time, we have to be careful not to go to the wrong environment that can send us in the wrong direction: discos, bars, etc.</p>

<p>The holier we become, the more transparent the face of Christ becomes in us.</p>

<p>Holiness doesn’t mean that we don’t have miseries and mistakes.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was at Mass in another country and there was a French missionary priest who was preaching the homily.</p>

<p>He talked about how when he was a kid in a small town in France, there was a monastery of strict observance on the outskirts of the town and he would go there as a 10-year-old kid to help the monks in their work.</p>

<p>They had a vocation of silence, so they didn’t talk unless you talked to them, and out of charity they would answer. Sometimes he would help the monks in their work and they would have a bit of a chit-chat.</p>

<p>But he noticed over in the corner of the field near the garden there was a very holy, elderly monk who was working away very silently on his own. This man had a great aura of holiness about him.</p>

<p>One day, he went over to this elderly monk and said to him, “When I grow up I want to be like you.”</p>

<p>This holy, saintly, elderly man said, “No, don’t be like me because I have hatred in my heart.”</p>

<p>This elderly missionary priest said, “As a 10-year-old I was shocked to hear that this saintly, elderly man could have had hatred in his heart.”</p>

<p>Then he explained this because he said, “Yes, you see there’s a monk who sits beside me in the refectory and he makes a lot of noise when he’s eating. For the last thirty years, he’s been driving me up the wall.”</p>

<p>The lady who told me this story said, “You know, when I heard the priest say that, I couldn’t look at my husband because for the last thirty years, I’ve been telling him, ‘Mind your manners.’”</p>

<p>We all have our miseries—things where we can improve on. Sometimes we have to listen to what other people are saying to us because maybe they see us as we really are, the realities.</p>

<p>We have to try and engrave in our hearts that we’re called to holiness.</p>

<p>God wants me in particular to be a saint. He has created me and elevated me to the order of grace. He has redeemed me, given me many graces, and given me all the formation that I have because He loves me a lot.</p>

<p>Whether our life grows with depth in this way also depends on us. God doesn’t go against our freedom. He created us out of love. He wants us to correspond with love.</p>

<p>“Everyone wants to change the world, but few want to do it by changing themselves” (<em>cf</em>. Leo Tolstoy, <em>Pamphlets</em>).</p>

<p>The message of personal sanctification is not so much that we convert China, but that we convert ourselves. We can’t convert China if we don’t change ourselves. We want big things but we can forget about ourselves.</p>

<p>Very often, conversion comes about in and through the cross. Try to learn how to thank God for the crosses that He sends you. Our holiness is there.</p>

<p>A zeal for holiness can often be a zeal for the cross, for the will of God in my life—accepting that will. The cross may come to us in all sorts of small ways on a daily basis, but from time to time in the course of our life there may be larger crosses, greater things, possibly crosses that we never expected.</p>

<p>That’s where the wisdom of the words of that missionary priest may find their true value: to be willing to accept whatever comes.</p>

<p>If something comes along that you never expected, never thought would happen to you, a great contradiction, possibly it’s not going to change. This is your lot for the rest of your life.</p>

<p>You can be sure that is the will of God for you. That’s the pathway of your sanctification. That’s why we have to learn to love it.</p>

<p>A lady told me once who had lost a 20-year-old daughter that she had learned how to thank God for the crosses that He sends her “because,” she said, “I realized it could be worse.”</p>

<p>Ask Our Lord for a passion for sanctity. Try to renew that eagerness for sanctity with a human supernatural enthusiasm.</p>

<p>Lord, may I never lose my eagerness for holiness. May my whole life, like the whole of Creation, give you glory.</p>

<p>Our vocation to holiness is a constant in our life. It’s not a state of mind. It’s not a feeling. It doesn’t depend on our state of employment, on our finances, on our health. It has to do with our being.</p>

<p>No matter where I am or what situation I’m in, it’s here. God wants me to be holy in and through this situation.</p>

<p>“You saw it quite clearly:” said St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>, “while so many people do not know God, he has looked to you. He wants you to form a part of the foundations, a firm stone upon which the life of the Church can rest. Meditate upon this reality and you will draw many practical consequences for your ordinary behavior: the foundations, made of blocks of stone, hidden and possibly rather dull, have to be solid, not fragile. They have to serve as support for the building. If not, they’re useless” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 472).</p>

<p>Your zeal for holiness may depend on the zeal for the holiness of each one of your children in their married life. Every hour is an opportunity to give them an example, to lead by example.</p>

<p>Our vocation to holiness is a gift. It can’t be earned. You have to be chosen with a divine calling.</p>

<p>I was giving a retreat many years ago and there was an elderly teacher who I knew had a lot of health problems in his life. So I asked him, “How are things now?”</p>

<p>He said to me, “Well, Father, I’ve come to realize that happiness does not consist in doing things that are easy.”</p>

<p>I nearly fell off the chair. Such wisdom. We learn an awful lot from other people.</p>

<p>Sometimes we look for happiness in the easy things. Very often our happiness is in the problems, in the challenges, in the changes of plans, in the difficulties, in solving those things that crop up on a daily basis.</p>

<p>We find our happiness on the cross. St. Josemaría liked to say that joy and happiness in this world have their roots in the form of a cross (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 43) and God is the one who makes us holy.</p>

<p>“Committed!” says St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>. “How I love that word! We children of God freely put ourselves under an obligation to live a life of dedication to God, striving that he may have complete and absolute sovereignty over our lives” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 855).</p>

<p>There are certain areas that we always need to look out for in our marriage. One of them is communication. Communication sometimes can be a very difficult thing—to communicate charity, affection, love; to listen carefully to what other people are saying to us, especially our spouse.</p>

<p>There may be things that are difficult to say with words. To communicate, we need to be able to read other people’s body language and to know the words and gestures that only those who love know are important. When to be silent. When to listen. To be there at special times.</p>

<p>A man asked his wife one time, “Why do you let our son talk to you like that?”</p>

<p>The wife said, “Because that’s the way that you talk to me.”</p>

<p>There may be great things we have to learn: great truths, personal truths from knowing how to listen; good communication.</p>

<p>If the devil can place a barrier between us and our spouse, through communication, it’s not a great battle.</p>

<p>A couple told me many years ago how every month they take a time out—half an hour, an hour—and they sit down.</p>

<p>They write down all the things that have annoyed them in the previous few weeks, all the thoughts that have passed through their mind, the feelings—feelings of injustice, feelings of neglect, feelings of lack of kindness or attention to detail.</p>

<p>They write all those things down and then they swap papers. So they communicate in writing the things that they might otherwise have found difficult to communicate in words.</p>

<p>You need to work on communication in your marriage. When the devil can’t attack frontally, he attacks obliquely through misunderstandings, miscommunications, neglect of details.</p>

<p>You have to learn how to be a good communicator, and in particular, to communicate charity. “Charity is patient. Charity is kind” (1 Cor. 13:4). You have to try and work at being easy to live with.</p>

<p>We can all be difficult to live with. Sometimes we can think we are the most lovable creature on this planet. If ever you have a thought like that, ask your mother or your father, “Mum, was I ever unlovable?”</p>

<p>And they’ll say, “Sit down for an hour and we’ll tell you about it.”</p>

<p>We have all been the most unlovable creatures that you could possibly imagine. But God has called us to try and work at being lovable creatures, and that we have to try and show love to other people.</p>

<p>The mother is the queen of the home. We always have to try and treat our spouse as that queen, so that other people see that. They see it in our words, they see it in our actions.</p>

<p>Family values mean family priorities. Family comes first. Our marriage comes first. There may be times when we have to be home: special dates, birthdays, anniversaries, Sundays, Christmas.</p>

<p>The best moments of our life should be at home and with our family. This is the apostolate of the family. This is where we find our holiness.</p>

<p>A spirit of service is a very important thing in the home. No job should be beneath the husband to do: the washing up, to lay the table, sweep the driveway, to wash the car, to wash our clothes sometimes.</p>

<p>In this way, we prepare our children to be good husbands and good wives. Prepare them for their marriage by giving that example.</p>

<p>We can ask St. Joseph, spouse of Our Lady, that we might imitate his example in a daily way, through our silence, through our service, through our faithfulness; through our acceptance of the will of God like he did, being in the background, forgetting ourselves, being a pillar; trusting; the humble faith; being manly, being available, being full of fortitude.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that she might cultivate that desire for greater holiness in our marriage so that we can truly prepare for that eternal feast that God has wanted for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Cup of Cold Water</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cup of Cold Water" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“If anyone can give so much as a cup of cold water to one of these little ones, because he is a disciple, then I tell you solemnly, he will most certainly not lose his reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>Giving a cup of cold water—and notice specifically how Scripture says cold water, not warm water—to someone who needs it is not going to make headlines. Most likely only the giver and the receiver will be aware of it.</p>

<p>And yet Our Lord holds up this small act of kindness as having tremendous value.</p>

<p>Even the simplest acts in which we lose ourselves for others have eternal significance. The cloth of holiness is woven in small details.</p>

<p>With this and with other examples that Our Lord gives to us, He speaks to us about the value of little things.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say, “A little act, done for love, is worth so much!” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, 814).</p>

<p>Mother Teresa has said, “A few words of kindness may be very simple and very brief, but their echoes are endless.”</p>

<p>On one occasion Our Lord sat up to the Temple treasury and He watched people putting money into the receptacle for alms. The scene takes place in one of the porticos, the so-called Treasure Chamber or Hall of Offerings. The days of the Passion were almost upon Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord didn't comment at all on the many people who contributed large amounts. But He saw a woman come up who was dressed in the typical garb of widows, and who was obviously poor (Mark 12:41).</p>

<p>She had perhaps waited for the crowd to thin out before depositing two small coins there. These coins had the least value of any in circulation at the time.</p>

<p>St. Mark explains the real value of these particular units of currency for the benefit of his non-Jewish readers, to whom his Gospel was principally addressed. He wants everyone to know how very little they were worth.</p>

<p>In men's eyes that anonymous offering had very little value. The two coins were worth just a small amount. “That coin,” St. Mark says, “was worth a quarter” (Mark 12:42). It's like a tenth of a denarius, which was the basic monetary unit; a denarius was a day's wages for a farm worker. And so, a quarter would scarcely buy anything.</p>

<p>If anyone was keeping a record of the offerings made that day in the temple, he probably would have thought it was not worth recording that widow's contribution. But we see that in fact this was the most valuable contribution of all.</p>

<p>It would be so pleasing to God that Our Lord called together His disciples, who were scattered around the place, so that they might be taught the lesson to be learned from this widow.</p>

<p>Those tiny pieces of copper could scarcely be heard falling into the treasury box. But Our Lord clearly perceived the love of this woman who said nothing but who was giving all her savings to God.</p>

<p>“Jesus said, ‘Truly I say to you, this poor widow has put in more than all those who are contributing to the treasury. For they all contributed out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty has put in everything she had, her whole living’” (Mark 12:43-44).</p>

<p>It often happens that what God considers important is very different from what men consider important. His standard of measurement and ours are not the same.</p>

<p>We are generally impressed by the big gesture, by unusual things of the kind that attract everyone's attention. But God is moved by little details filled with love—"a cup of cold water”—which are within the radius of action of everyone, even small children.</p>

<p>Of course, He's also moved by happenings that we consider to be very important, but only when they're carried out with the same spirit of rectitude of intention, of humility, and of love.</p>

<p>The apostles, who later were to be the very foundation of the Church, did not forget the lesson they were taught that day. That woman has taught all of us to touch God's heart every day in the only way that most of us can: through little things.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, Point 824, St. Josemaría says, “Have you noticed how human love consists of little things? Well, divine Love also consists of little things.”</p>

<p>In these passages of the Gospel, we learn the true value of these things. We can turn everything that happens, no matter how inconsequential it may seem, into something very pleasing to God. And because it's pleasing to Him, it's turned into something of great value. Only those things that we make pleasing to God have any true and eternal value.</p>

<p>We could consider in our prayer the vast number of opportunities that present themselves to us. We’re told by St. Francis de Sales, “Great opportunities to serve God seldom arise, but little ones are frequent; [and our Lord himself has told us that] ‘he who is faithful over a few things will be placed over many’ (Luke 16:10). Do all things in the name of God, and you will do all things well, provided you know how to fulfill your duties properly.</p>

<p>“Then, whether you eat or drink, whether you sleep, or take recreation, or turn the spit of an oven, you will profit greatly in God's sight by doing all these things, because God wishes you to do them” (St. Francis de Sales, <em>Introduction to the Devout Life</em>).</p>

<p>Often, it's the small things that make a job perfect, worthy of being offered to God: the double-checking of an email or a WhatsApp message that we write, the looking back to double-check on a room that we've just cleaned, or a floor we've just polished, or a table we've just laid, or some little professional job that we have done.</p>

<p>Perfection is in the details. It's not enough that what we're doing is good, whether it's work or prayer or football or hockey or volleyball. It also has to be well finished.</p>

<p>“For there to be virtue,” St. Thomas Aquinas teaches, “it is necessary to attend to two things: to what is being done, and also to the way it is being done” (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Quodlibet</em>, IV).</p>

<p>As far as the way it is being done is concerned, the final touches with the chisel or brush can turn that work into a masterpiece, and Our Lord wants us to work masterpieces every day.</p>

<p>On the other hand, shoddy workmanship, work which is done clumsily or carelessly, is a sign of spiritual laziness or of lukewarmness in a Christian who should be sanctifying himself through his daily work.</p>

<p>We're told in the Book of Revelation, “I know your works: you have the name of being alive, and you are dead. ... For I have not found your works perfect in the sight of my God” (Rev. 3:1-2).</p>

<p>The very nature of our Christian vocation demands that we take care of little things. A teacher who picks up a piece of paper off the floor may give a greater lesson to all his students, or to anybody who happens to be in that particular corridor or place, than all the other classes he may have given in his whole professional lifetime, because with that little gesture we teach the value of order, of tidiness, but also the value of the small things.</p>

<p>Our aim should be to imitate Our Lord during His years in Nazareth, those long years of work, of family life, of friendly relationships with His countrymen.</p>

<p>Doing little things with love for God's sake demands attention, sacrifice, and generosity. A single isolated little detail may not in itself be very important. St. Augustine says, “What is small is small, but he who is faithful in small things is great” (St. Augustine, <em>On Christian Doctrine</em>).</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>, “Love is what gives little things their value” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>The Way,</em> Point 814).</p>

<p>If this love were lacking, our endeavor to look after little things would be pointless; it would become a mania or merely Pharisaical. We would pay tithes in mint, dill and cumin—as the Pharisees do—and we would run the risk of leaving out the most essential points of the law, those of justice and of mercy.</p>

<p>Although what we have to offer may seem very little—just as the contribution of that poor widow did—it acquires a great value if you place it on the altar and unite it to the offering that Our Lord makes of Himself to the Father.</p>

<p>St. John Paul said in one of his homilies: “Our humble surrender—insignificant in itself like the oil of the widow of Sarepta, or the poor widow's mite—becomes acceptable in God's eyes through its union with the offering of Jesus” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, November 7, 1982).</p>

<p>At other times, details in our work, in our study, in our relationships with other people are the crowning of something good which would remain incomplete without those details.</p>

<p>One of the most obvious warning signs that we're starting on the path to lukewarmness is that we give little value to the details of our life of piety, to details in our work, and to little specific acts of virtue. If we ignore these symptoms, we end up paying little attention to big things as well.</p>

<p>“The misfortune is all the more grievous and incurable,” said one writer, “when we barely notice that we are sliding downwards and only slowly come to realize this … That if we are in this state, we give a mortal blow to the life of the spirit, and that can be something obvious to everyone” (Benedict Baur, <em>Frequent Confession</em>).</p>

<p>Love for God, on the other hand, is shown by our inventiveness, by our unremitting zeal, and our effort to find in everything an occasion for showing our love of God and for giving service to others.</p>

<p>Holiness is a cloth woven of little details. God is not indifferent to a love that knows how to care for small details. He's not indifferent, for example, as to whether we go to greet Him, first of all, when we go into a church or when we happen to be passing by a church.</p>

<p>He's not indifferent to the effort we make to arrive on time (better, a few minutes early) for Holy Mass, to the way we genuflect in front of Him in the tabernacle, or the way we behave or try to be recollected in His presence.</p>

<p>There was a man once who tried to do a lot of apostolate in his office, befriending as many people as he could, being close to them, trying to help them in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>He gave a lot of support to people in their marriage, in their family, tried to invite them to recollections, to retreats, to grow spiritually.</p>

<p>But there was one man in the office who refused all of his overtures. He had no time for these sorts of things.</p>

<p>But one day that man came to this other fellow and said, ‘Look, I have a big problem in my marriage. My wife is about to divorce me. Can you give me any advice?’</p>

<p>The original man was a bit surprised. He said, ‘You know, I've often tried to give you advice or reach out to you in different ways, and you never seemed very interested. Why do you come to me?’</p>

<p>The guy said, ‘Well, you're the only one that speaks about anything serious around here.’</p>

<p>The original man said, ‘Okay, let me think about it and pray about it’—which is always a good thing to say to people because they realize you're taking them seriously.</p>

<p>That evening in his prayer, he brought this topic to talk to Our Lord about it. He couldn't really see any great solutions. But for some reason, a scene in a movie with St. Josemaría came to mind, where St. Josemaría mentioned how husbands should try and bring their wives some flowers from time to time.</p>

<p>He was thinking to himself, ‘It's a bit late for flowers. That's not a very prudent sort of advice to give this fellow.’</p>

<p>But that was all he saw in his prayer. With a lot of supernatural outlook, he thought, ‘If that's all I see in my prayer, that, maybe, is what I have to transmit to this fellow.’</p>

<p>But he wasn't terribly convinced himself. It didn't seem very helpful.</p>

<p>The following day, he told his friend, ‘Look, I thought about this, and I prayed about it. My suggestion to you is that you perhaps bring some flowers to your wife.’</p>

<p>The second fellow was thinking, ‘I was really wasting my time talking to you. What a stupid piece of advice. She's about to divorce me and you're telling me to bring her flowers.’</p>

<p>He dismissed his suggestion and went off. But that evening, as he was going home, he was thinking about this and he thought, ‘Even if I get her flowers, I suppose it can't do any harm. The worst thing that could happen is that she might hit me with them.’</p>

<p>So he bought some flowers. When he got home, his wife opened the door and he handed her the flowers. She burst into tears and said, ‘This is the first time in twenty years that you have brought me flowers.’ After that, they lived happily ever after.</p>

<p>Sometimes the little things can make a huge difference.</p>

<p>Moreover, when we see somebody make a devout genuflection before the tabernacle, it's easy for us to think: that person has faith and loves God. That sign of adoration helps others to have greater faith and greater love.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI says, “It may perhaps seem to you that the Liturgy is made up of little things: the position of the body, genuflections, inclinations of the head; the way the thurible, the missal, and the cruets are to be moved. It is then that we have to recall Christ's words in the Gospel: ‘He who is faithful in a very little is faithful also in much’” (Luke 16:10).</p>

<p>“Moreover,” said St. Paul VI, “nothing is small in the Sacred Liturgy, when we think of the greatness of him to whom it is directed” (Paul VI, <em>Address</em>, May 30, 1967).</p>

<p>Our spirit of mortification usually consists in specific little sacrifices throughout the day: keeping up a persevering struggle in our particular examination of conscience, sobriety at meals, punctuality, being pleasant to people, getting up on time, not leaving our work for later even though we find it difficult or trying, having order in our work and taking care of the tools or implements and materials that we use, being grateful for whatever food is placed in front of us, not allowing ourselves whims and fancies.</p>

<p>In order to live charity in a way that becomes ever more refined and heroic, it would be necessary for us to apply this approach right down to the smallest and least important details of daily life.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in the <em>Furrow</em> says, “Your duty to be a brother to all souls will lead you to practice the ‘apostolate of little things’ without others noticing it. You will want to serve them so that for them, their way becomes agreeable” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 737).</p>

<p>At times it will mean taking a real interest in what other people are saying; at other times it will mean putting aside our own personal concerns so as to give our attention to the people we live with.</p>

<p>A little girl was talking to her father who was reading the newspaper and she said to him, ‘Daddy, you're not listening to me.’</p>

<p>Continuing to read the newspaper, he said, ‘Yes, I am. I'm hearing every word.’</p>

<p>But then she said, ‘But you're not looking at me.’</p>

<p>The child was aware, and the child wanted his full attention. A small thing, but it meant everything to the child.</p>

<p>Care of those little things will mean not getting annoyed about what are really trivia, not being touchy, making people feel welcome.</p>

<p>If those little disturbances come during the day, little things, changes of plans, or funny things go wrong, that can be a trigger to repeat our <em>Morning Offering</em>.</p>

<p>We shall tell Our Lord: I'm really serious with the <em>Offering</em> that I made to you. It's these things I wanted to offer to you.</p>

<p>We will try to help others in a way that they may not notice, or might never find out, but which lightens their burden. We try to pray to God for them when they're in need, to avoid having critical spirit towards them, and always to be grateful to them.</p>

<p>All of these things are within the reach and the scope of each one of us. And we should try and do the same where each one of the virtues is concerned.</p>

<p>If we give attention to little things, we will live each day to the full, and will know how to fill each moment with the sense of preparation for eternity. To do this, we could frequently ask Our Lady for help.</p>

<p>Our Lady, Mother of God, pray for us, now, and in every ordinary little situation of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>PKN</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Merciful Messiah</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Merciful Messiah" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’ Large crowds came to him, bringing the lame, the crippled, the blind, the dumb, and many others; and they put these down at his feet and he cured them. The crowds were astonished to hear the dumb speaking, to see the cripples whole again, the lame walking, and the blind with their sight restored” (Matt. 15:32, 29-31).</p>

<p>We’re told, “Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these people.’” This is why the heart of Our Lord is so often moved. In His mercy, He was to follow up this episode with the wonderful miracle of the multiplication of the loaves (Matt. 15:32-39).</p>

<p>We're reminded in these passages to turn always to the mercy of Our Lord, and to meditate on His life, so as to learn to be merciful to others.</p>

<p>The liturgy places this passage before us during Advent because of an abundance of good things and the limitless mercy which will be the signs of the coming of the Messiah.</p>

<p>“I feel sorry for all these people.” This is an overriding reason for giving ourselves to others: to be compassionate and to have mercy.</p>

<p>In order to learn how to be merciful, we have to fix our eyes on Christ, who comes “to save that which was lost” (Luke 19:10).</p>

<p>He doesn't come to crush the broken reed or to wholly extinguish the wick that still smolders (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 12:20), but to take upon Himself our wretchedness and save us from it, and to share in their misfortune with those who suffer and are in need. Each page of the Gospel is an example of divine mercy.</p>

<p>We should meditate on the life of Jesus because, as St. Josemaría says, “[The life of] Jesus is a summary and compendium of the [story] of the divine mercy. Many other scenes of the Gospel,” he continues, “also make a deep impact on us, such as his forgiveness of the woman taken in adultery, the parables—the prodigal son, the lost sheep, the pardoned debtor—and the raising to life of the son of the widow at Naim.</p>

<p>“How many reasons based on justice could Christ have found to work as great a wonder as this last one! The only son of that poor widow had died—he who gave meaning to her life, he who would help her in her old age. Jesus did not perform his miracle out of justice, but out of compassion, because his heart was moved by the spectacle of human suffering” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 7).</p>

<p>The mercy of God is the essence of the whole history of salvation, the reason for all His saving actions.</p>

<p>God is mercy. And this divine attribute is like the engine supplying the power that energizes the life story of every human being.</p>

<p>When the apostles wanted to sum up God's revelation, His mercy always appeared to them to be the essence of an eternal and gratuitous plan springing from God's generosity. With good reason, the Psalmist could affirm: “The earth is full of the steadfast love of the Lord” (Ps. 33:5).</p>

<p>Mercy is constant in God's attitude to mankind. And recourse to it is the universal remedy for all our ills, including those for which we thought there was no answer.</p>

<p>Meditating on the mercy of God should fill us with great confidence “now and at the hour of our death,” as we pray in the <em>Hail Mary</em>. What a joy to be able to say to God, with St. Augustine: “All my hope lies solely in your great mercy!” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>, Point 6,19).</p>

<p>Solely in that, Lord. On your mercy rests all my hope. Not on my merits, but on your mercy.</p>

<p>In a special way, God shows His mercy towards sinners: He pardons them their sins. The Pharisees often criticize Him for this. He rebuts their criticisms saying: “It is not those who are well who have need of a physician, but those who are sick” (Matt. 9:12).</p>

<p>We who are sinners are sick of soul and need to have recourse many times to the divine mercy. In the Psalms, we say, “Show us, O Lord, your mercy; and grant us your salvation” (Ps. 85:7). The Church repeats these words continually in this liturgical season.</p>

<p>On so many occasions, every day even, we will have need to have recourse to the merciful Heart of Jesus and say: “Lord, if you will, you can make me clean” (Matt. 8:2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul in his encyclical <em>Dives in Misericordia</em> (Rich in Mercy), says, especially in these circumstances, “The knowledge of God, the God of mercy and benign love, is a constant and inexhaustible source of conversion, not only as a momentary interior act, but also as a stable disposition, like a state of mind. Those who come to know God in this way, those who so regard Him, cannot live without being incessantly transformed by Him.”</p>

<p>We can also say, as it is said in the Book of Sirach: “How great is the mercy of the Lord, and his forgiveness for those who turn to him!” (Sir. 17:29). Great is the divine mercy toward each one of us.</p>

<p>This can lead us to turn frequently to God, in repentance for our faults and sins, especially in that sacrament of divine mercy which we call Confession.</p>

<p>God has placed a condition for our obtaining His compassion and mercy for our offenses and weaknesses. The condition is that we too should have a heart of compassion for those around us.</p>

<p>In the parable of the good Samaritan (Luke 10:30-37), Our Lord teaches us the attitude that we should adopt towards a neighbor in distress. We're not permitted to “pass by on the other side” in detached indifference. Rather we must “go” to him.</p>

<p>One morning many years ago, I was going to say Mass in a conference center outside Dublin. It was, maybe, a 45-minute drive. I was a little bit late, so I had my foot on the accelerator. Then I happened to see a car coming out of a side road and hitting a lorry. The front wing of the car was torn off. It was a bit dramatic.</p>

<p>I slowed down. I could see that the only damage really was to the car. Nobody was injured. There was a bit of drama, but nothing else. So, I kept going and I put my foot on the accelerator to try and catch up on the time that I had lost.</p>

<p>But after going about 100 meters, I remembered the story of the Gospel about the priest who went by on the other side of the road.</p>

<p>Listening to my conscience, I had to turn around and go back and double-check that everybody was okay, and give my phone number as a witness, and a few more things. Then I proceeded with my journey a bit more serenely than before.</p>

<p>We can all be that person who goes by on the other side of the road with all sorts of hurried excuses. St. John Paul, in his Apostolic Lette<em>r Salvifici doloris</em> (“The Salvation of Sorrow or Pain”) says: “A good Samaritan is one who stops to relieve the suffering of the other, no matter who he or she may be. This stopping is not just merely from curiosity, but rather from the desire to make ourselves available.</p>

<p>“It's a specific interior disposition of the heart, which also has its emotional side. Good Samaritans are those who are affected by the suffering they see around them; they are genuinely moved by their neighbor's misfortune.”</p>

<p>Each of us has to feel bad that people around us do not perhaps have the dignity or the care that they should have as human beings. And it's not enough for us to feel bad about it. We have to try and do something about it, and infect other people with that sort of thinking, particularly our children, with our words and with our examples.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “If Christ, who knows the interior of man, emphasizes this compassion, this means that it's important for our whole attitude towards the sufferings of others. Therefore one must cultivate this sensitivity of heart, which bears witness to compassion towards a suffering person. Sometimes this compassion remains the only or the principal expression of our love for and of our solidarity with the sufferer” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici doloris</em>, Point 28, February 11, 1984).</p>

<p>The word compassion comes from two Latin words, <em>com passio</em>, to suffer with.</p>

<p>Throughout Sacred Scripture there's an urgency on God's part to see that men also have the stirrings of sympathy and deep-seated feelings of mercy, that they too have this “compassion for another's misery, which moves us to remedy it, if at all possible” (St. Augustine, <em>The City of God)</em>.</p>

<p>We can look around us and see in our home, in our office, in our workshop, in our neighborhood—is there not some person who's handicapped, either physically or morally, or elderly, who perhaps needs urgently our time, our affection, and our attention?</p>

<p>Our Lord promises us happiness if we have a merciful heart towards others, and gives assurance that “we will obtain mercy” (Heb. 4:16) from God in the same measure as we show it to our fellow men.</p>

<p>The scope for mercy is as great as the extent of the human suffering that needs to be remedied. And, since mankind is subject to misery and calamity in the physical, intellectual, and moral order, the possible works of mercy are innumerable—as many as men have needs—though traditionally, by way of example, fourteen ‘works of mercy’ have been cited, since in them, this virtue is capable of being exercised in a special way.</p>

<p>Our attitude of compassion and mercy must, in the first place, be shown towards those who are near us—our family, our friends, our close associates—to those whom God has placed at our side, and then to those beyond who are most in need.</p>

<p>Mercy will frequently consist in our attention to the health, the recreation, and the nourishment of those whom God has commended to our care. The sick merit a special attention in terms of our company and our real interest in their illness, as we show them how and help them to offer their sufferings to God.</p>

<p>In a society dehumanized by frequent attacks on the family, more and more old people and those who are ill are left without consolation and affection. Visiting them in their loneliness is a work of mercy that has never been more necessary.</p>

<p>The time spent in keeping them company is rewarded by God in a special way: “As you did it to one of the least of these my brethren, you did it to me,” said Our Lord (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Alongside the so-called material works of mercy, we should also carry out those that are spiritual. In the first place it is our privilege and duty <em>to correct those in</em> <em>error</em> with our advice when the opportunity arises, and charitably, without ever causing offense.</p>

<p>Secondly, it is <em>to teach those who don't know,</em> especially with regard to ignorance of religion, an ignorance which is the great enemy of God; it increases daily in alarming proportions so that catechesis has become a work of mercy of prime importance and urgency. St. Teresa of Calcutta says ignorance is the greatest poverty.</p>

<p>Next comes giving <em>counsel to the doubting</em>, honestly and with the right intention, so as to help them on their way to God. Then follows the <em>consolation of the afflicted</em>, by sharing their sorrow and encouraging them to recover their happiness in their supernatural understanding of the pain they suffer.</p>

<p><em>Pardon for those who have offended us</em>, promptly and as often as necessary, without giving excessive importance to the offense. We are advised too, <em>to give help to the needy</em>, carrying out this service generously and joyfully.</p>

<p>And finally, we have to <em>pray for the living and the dead</em>, feeling ourselves linked in a special way through the Communion of Saints to those we owe most because of family relationships, or friendship, or whatever else.</p>

<p>Our attitude of merciful benevolence towards others must extend to many different aspects of life because, says St. John Chrysostom, “nothing can make you such an imitator of Christ as your concern for others. Although you fast, although you sleep on the floor, even though, I dare to say, you kill yourself, if you are not attentive to your neighbor, you have done very little; you are very far from being an image of Christ” (St. John Chrysostom, <em>Commentary on the First Epistle to the Corinthians</em>).</p>

<p>We will ourselves obtain God's mercy and perhaps also merit it for others in that immense depth of “mercy that extends from generation to generation,” as Our Lady prophesied to her cousin Elizabeth (Luke 1:50).</p>

<p>We can also call down the divine mercy on ourselves, who are so much in need of it. As Christians, we manifest our unity of life by encouraging the works of justice and mercy. Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse the lepers...</p>

<p>From the Church's earliest days, faithful Christians spread the faith to all parts of the world. From those first years too, vast numbers of Christians have “committed their powers and their lives to liberation from every form of oppression and to the promotion of human dignity. The experience of the saints and the example of so many works of service to one's neighbor are an incentive and a beacon for the liberating undertakings that are needed today,” said the Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith.</p>

<p>They are needed perhaps with an even greater urgency than in other periods of history.</p>

<p>Our faith in Christ moves us to be aware of our common involvement with the problems and shortages that other people experience, often with their ignorance and their lack of economic resources.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says this solidarity with our fellow man is not a “superficial sentiment about the evils that beset so many people, whether close to us or far away,” but “a firm and persevering determination to strive for the common good; that is to say, for the good of all and of all individuals, so that we may all be truly responsible for all persons” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Sollicitudo rei socialis</em>–The Concern of the Church for the Social Order, Point 38, December 3, 1987).</p>

<p>Faith leads us to feel a deep respect for others, for each person, and never to remain indifferent to other people's needs.</p>

<p>Following Christ will manifest itself in deeds of justice and mercy; it will show itself too in our determination to get to know the principles of the social doctrine of the Church and to carry them out, first of all in all our surroundings, right there where we live.</p>

<p>I remember my father coming back from bringing us to swimming lessons as kids. We'd see sometimes a crocodile file of orphans who were going to a local orphanage and were coming from, maybe, the beach as well.</p>

<p>We didn't know who these people were, what these kids were about, or what was their problem. We didn't understand. I remember him buying ice cream for those kids, and we were still left with question marks.</p>

<p>Only many years later do you realize what that little gesture was, from a father of a family, in silence, doing that little gesture. It left its mark.</p>

<p>This period coming up to Christmas is a very interesting period, a potential period to engrave these messages in the lives of our children.</p>

<p>It should be possible to say of each one of us at the end of our lives, as it was said about Our Lord: “He went about doing good” (<em>cf</em>. Acts 10:38).</p>

<p>We have to do good within our own families, among our colleagues at work and among our friends, and even with those people whom we just chance to come across.</p>

<p>Our Lord has opportunities outlined for us. There's a document of the Spanish Episcopal Conference, <em>Catholics in Public Life,</em> which says: “As disciples of Christ, we have to be stewards of fraternity, whatever occasions and circumstances life brings with it. When a man or woman lives the Christian spirit in all its intensity, all his or her activities and relationships reflect and communicate God's love and the surpassing goods of the Kingdom.</p>

<p>“As Christians we need to know how to make fast and strengthen our relationships each day with our families, our friends, and our neighbors, whether we are at work or at leisure, sealing them with the seal of Christian love, which is simplicity, truthfulness, faithfulness, meekness, generosity, solidarity, and joy.”</p>

<p>We can ask for the mercy of God to be extended to our generation through Mary, Mother of Mercy, our life, our sweetness, and our hope.</p>

<p>Now that the Feast of the Immaculate Conception is so near, our confident reliance on Our Lady will, if we have recourse to her, be more continuous and loving.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MML</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abandonment</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abandonment" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Gospel, “Can you not buy two sparrows for a penny? Yet not one falls to the ground without your Father knowing” (Matt. 10:29).</p>

<p>Our Lord uses this curious analogy of us with sparrows. It’s curious that He would want to compare us to sparrows, but yet there is a very important message there.</p>

<p>We look at a sparrow, and you blow at a sparrow, it could fall over; very fragile, very timid, not very strong. And yet God tells us that this sparrow can't do a single thing “without your Father knowing” about it and we are “of much more value than any sparrow” (Matt. 10:31).</p>

<p>Our Lord is inviting us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of trust and abandonment. This trust and abandonment, to a large extent, flows from the fact that we are children of God.</p>

<p>We celebrated a few days ago, at the beginning of the month, the Baptism of Our Lord, the institution of the Sacrament of Baptism. Through that sacrament and through all the other sacraments we get divine grace into our soul.</p>

<p>Divine grace is the presence of the Blessed Trinity within us.</p>

<p>Our Lord said we will “come and make our abode in him” (cf. John 14:23), and so when we are in the state of grace, God is in our soul. Therefore, all the fruits of God can be present in our life, in our words, in our actions.</p>

<p>Hopefully, people can somehow detect that this person is trying to lead a holy life, that they're in a state of grace, and therefore God is in control.</p>

<p>If we are not in the state of grace, if God is not in our soul in grace, then the devil may be there. Then all the fruits of the devil can be present in our life, in our works, in our actions, in the atmosphere we carry with us.</p>

<p>Because God is there within us in our soul in grace, we're told in Scripture that we become “children of God” (1 John 3:1). We're told that we're carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves us.</p>

<p>Therefore, everything that happens to us in our life, we can try to see from a supernatural perspective, and see that God is somehow in control, or He has permitted this particular thing—this joy, or sometimes this sorrow, or this contradiction, or this difficulty, or this challenge.</p>

<p>Or sometimes God can sweep the feet from under us and leave us hanging there. And when that happens it’s because He wants us to learn how to trust in Him, to have a great sense of abandonment like the sparrows.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, Our Lord says: “Look at the birds of the air: they neither sow nor reap or gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of abandonment and trust and leave things in His hands. On the one hand, He wants us to use all the human initiative that we have to solve problems.</p>

<p>When He sent the apostles out, He said: “Go ye therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:19). He didn't build chapels. He didn't build schools or hospitals. He didn't give them technology or money or all the other means to fulfill their mission.</p>

<p>He just sent them out with a few ideas. Those ideas were very important ideas, and He wanted them to convert the world with those ideas. He wanted them to be very clear that He would be acting in them and through them.</p>

<p>What He wanted was their faith, their trust, and their abandonment, that He would be at work through them.</p>

<p>Shortly after I was ordained, I was giving a retreat in the south of Spain. (I was ordained there.) There was a number of men on the retreat.</p>

<p>On the first day of the retreat, an 80-year-old man came to chat with me. Usually, people wait a few hours or a few days before they talk to the priest about their resolutions or what they've got from the retreat.</p>

<p>This man came first thing that morning and told me, “You know, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for a number of years, and the person in charge of the recollection asked me if I would come to this retreat. I said no, and I had three very good reasons for saying no.</p>

<p>“One is that I train a certain type of horse. There are some people coming these days to buy some of my horses from another country. I want to be there when they come.</p>

<p>“Secondly, there are some people coming to put drains on my house and I've been waiting for two years for them to come to put drains on my house. I want to be there also when they come.</p>

<p>“Thirdly, it's the weekend of the local fiesta, which is a big thing in Spain. Ever since I was seven, I have never missed this local feast. All my friends will be there. It’s a time to catch up. We meet, we talk, we set ourselves up for the next year. It's just unthinkable that I wouldn't be at the local fiesta.</p>

<p>“So I had three very good reasons for telling this man who was in charge of this recollection that I would not go on the retreat. And he asked me again a few weeks later, and again, I said no; and he asked me a third time, and again, I said no.”</p>

<p>But then he said, “I began to feel very uncomfortable, and the only way that I could find any peace was to finally say yes, and so here I am on this retreat very reluctantly. I came thinking about all the things I'm missing, but you know, I've only been here a couple of hours, and already I'm very glad I came.</p>

<p>“Because you see, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for the last couple of years, and I keep hearing this idea of divine filiation—that we are all children of God because God lives in our soul in grace. They talk about the life of childhood and spiritual childhood, and I've been trying to figure out what this means.</p>

<p>“Here I am, 80 years of age, and they're telling me I have to become like a child. What does that mean? Does it mean I have to put on short pants or what?</p>

<p>“Now I've come to realize what it means. I have to abandon myself into the arms of my Father God. I've got to let Him call the shots.I've got to let Him make the decisions.</p>

<p>“I've got to try and let myself be like a little child in the arms of his Father, with one hand in the hand of his Father, let God lead me and go where He leads me, irrespective of all the other human or material considerations. I've got to try and do His Will and do His thing, in fact, my Christian vocation.”</p>

<p>In those days, it was as though that man discovered “the pearl of great price” (Matt. 13:45-46).</p>

<p>There are treasures in the Gospel, great spiritual treasures. At certain stages of our life, God may reveal those treasures to us, and those treasures can be worth far more than all sorts of material things, because it's there that we can find our peace and our joy. A peace and joy that this world cannot give.</p>

<p>Therefore, there is great importance in living in the state of grace, of being close to the sacraments, of learning how to savor these great treasures that God gives us.</p>

<p>I heard of a kid once who was walking along the beach and his foot hit against a pouch of stones. He picked up the pouch of stones, and he began to take a stone, and he flung it as far as he could into the sea. He said at the same time, ‘When I grow rich, I'm going to get myself a big house.’</p>

<p>He flung another stone and said, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy myself a fine car’; and another stone, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy fine clothes’; and another stone, ‘I'm going to have great food.’</p>

<p>One by one, he threw all the stones as far as he could into the sea. When he got down to the last stone, suddenly a little sunbeam or something hit the stone and it glistened. So, he looked again. It was a diamond!</p>

<p>He'd been throwing diamonds far out into the sea, dreaming about treasures that he might never have, but he'd been throwing away the treasures that he had in his hand.</p>

<p>With this story, we have to come to try and realize that maybe we have great treasures in our lives, in our spiritual life in particular, things that we are perhaps not as aware of as we could be. We don't realize the treasures.</p>

<p>One great way of trying to get to know the treasures that we have in our life is through acts of thanksgiving.</p>

<p>If you thank God from the moment you get up in the morning until the moment you get to bed at night, for the fact that you can see, the fact that you can hear, the fact that you can walk around the place and have two arms and two legs—these are all wonderful treasures that can lead us to appreciate all the other treasures that are present every day of our life: the air that we breathe, the things that we see, the health of the people around us.</p>

<p>There are so many wonderful things to be grateful for. So we need to learn how to abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>I got a haircut last week in Nairobi, and when I came out of the place where I got it, I was driving up the street and saw a young girl crawling on all fours with a little cup, begging. Not something you often see: a young girl crawling on all fours, she had no wheelchair, she had nothing.</p>

<p>The following day, with a friend of mine, we decided to go and look for this girl and try and see if we could do something for her. We found her in a completely different place, purely by accident, crawling across a busy street with several crossings.</p>

<p>So my friend got out of the car and went to talk to her. She had no English and I don't have Swahili. They talked and she explained that she was from Migori. She was 22, she had come to Nairobi two years previously, she lived with two other people with disabilities, and somehow, she had managed to survive.</p>

<p>When she moved around Nairobi, she would hop onto a <em>matatu</em>. She got to different places from which she could beg, and she managed to carry on like this: a very cheerful lady and very happy to talk.</p>

<p>Then she came with us and we got her a wheelchair. Hopefully, she's now using that wheelchair.</p>

<p>But thinking about how that girl has survived in an unknown city far away from her home territory, and not having English, and not knowing the place, and managing to move around like that—there must be a tremendous abandonment in her, in her life, in her spirit. She went away from her own home to a strange place.</p>

<p>So sometimes with people we meet we can learn an awful lot about the spirit of abandonment, trust, of having faith in God, because we know that God has a plan for us.</p>

<p>He wants us to live out that plan. He has a mission for us. There's nothing in our life that He has not foreseen.</p>

<p>And so, as we start a new year we could try to ask Our Lord in the Blessed Sacrament that we might have a greater spirit of faith and trust and abandonment to live out those consequences of being a child of God, so that we may leave the future in His hands.</p>

<p>And if we see, as we can probably do, that when we look back, God has really taken care of so many things in our life: our primary education, our secondary education, perhaps our tertiary education, our work, our family, our children, our health—so many things that God has looked after in all sorts of special ways. We have every reason to grow in faith and trust in Him.</p>

<p>St. Thérèse of Lisieux says, “When…we feel no courage, no energy, for the practice of virtue, this is grace” (Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>Letters of Soeur Thérèse to Céline</em>, October 20, 1888). This is the moment to depend solely on Jesus.</p>

<p>There might be moments in our life when Our Lord precisely sweeps the feet from under us and leaves us hanging there. In those situations, He wants us to look up.</p>

<p>He wants us to trust completely in Him, to leave things in His hands, to learn what real hope is, what real abandonment is.</p>

<p>A farmer told me how one time he was going through his farm, and there’d been a fire on the farm. He came across all sorts of things that had been very burnt.</p>

<p>At one moment he came across a chicken that was very badly burnt, totally dead, and he gave it a good kick—this chicken that was totally dead, burnt black—but out from underneath the chicken ran four or five little chicks.</p>

<p>He said, “I suddenly remembered that phrase from Scripture: ‘I will gather you under my wing as a hen gathers her chicks’” (Matt. 23:27).</p>

<p>He said this hen saw the danger, the fire coming, she gathered her chicks. So he was very aware of the fact that Our Father God looks after us in all sorts of ways, takes care of us, preserves us from danger.</p>

<p>Sometimes we might wonder, Why? Why did this happen to my family, to my parents, to my siblings, to my children, to my work? Why do all these things specifically happen to me?</p>

<p>In certain moments, we may not appreciate that. But when time passes, sometimes we can discover there's some great divine plan behind the cross. God is at work. He has other plans that He's working out.</p>

<p>A man in another country told me once how he had a primary school education. He began to be a salesman selling pots and pans.</p>

<p>He knocked one day on the door of the president of the Ford Corporation who didn't want any pots and pans. He thought he would get his wife, but he got the husband.</p>

<p>But the husband was impressed with his sales pitch. He said, “Young man, how would you like to try selling cars? OK? So come along on Monday morning, we'll start you out selling cars.”</p>

<p>So he sold a lot of cars. He graduated to Mercedes-Benzes. He ended up importing Rolls Royces from London. He could tell you the mileage on the clock of every Rolls Royce in Asia. He made a lot of money.</p>

<p>Then he gave a present of a watch to some man in government, which is something you cannot do in that particular country. The government turned around and bankrupted him.</p>

<p>So he lost everything. He lost all his money. He lost his house. He lost his business. His wife left him. At the age of 49, he developed stage 4 cancer.</p>

<p>That's when I got to know him. He used to go to a support group in his parish for people who were recovering from cancer. This was a fairly well-to-do parish with a lot of wealthy people, and they would get together and talk week by week.</p>

<p>Then they heard of a new drug that had been made in Houston, Texas, a new cancer drug which was very expensive. One by one all these very wealthy people flew off to Houston, Texas to try out this new drug.</p>

<p>He came to me and he said, “You know, it's not fair. There’s no justice in this world. The wealthy can do all these things, and here I am, I’m bankrupt, they’ve taken away my passport, I can't leave the country, I couldn't have any money to fly, and so poor me, I can't try out this new drug.”</p>

<p>And he said, “I was complaining to God for weeks and months about how unfair this life is. Then, you know, the first one died; and then after three months, the next one died; and after six months, another one died; and now they're nearly all dead and I'm still here. So I'm saying thank you, Lord, thank you, Lord.”</p>

<p>So sometimes all the injustices of this world are the things that we find we can do. When time passes and you look back, sometimes you can see, maybe the hand of God was working in funny ways here.</p>

<p>Maybe God has me in the palm of His hand, looking after me in special ways or looking after my family.</p>

<p>There are times when there are things that maybe we'd like to have and we can't have them. God doesn't permit us to have them: luxuries or things that other people have. Maybe it's because God just wants us to trust in Him, to abandon ourselves. He has some other plan. Maybe that's not our mission.</p>

<p>When there are things in life that we find other people have, and we can't afford them and we can't have them, it may be that God is forming our soul at that moment more than at any other time.</p>

<p>Perhaps He's giving us spiritual treasures, teaching us what authentic detachment means, or teaching us authentic hope or authentic trust, which ultimately are the messages that Christ gives to us in Bethlehem.</p>

<p>Christ abandoned Himself in Bethlehem into the arms of Mary, into the arms of Joseph.</p>

<p>Sometimes that's what God wants us to do. If we were to hear tomorrow that we have some fatal disease, we can abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God. It can be totally peaceful.</p>

<p>I knew some men a couple of years ago who used to come to recollections like this. Both of them developed cancer, but they were leading very good spiritual lives.</p>

<p>They happened to find themselves in the same hospital room, and one said to the other: “Are you worried about anything? Do you feel bad about anything?” “No, I'm very peaceful.” “Me too, there’s nothing to worry about. I leave everything in the hands of God. It's a great way to live and a great way to die.”</p>

<p>It’s a wonderful thing to be able to look forward to our death because our souls are in the right state.</p>

<p>In the house where I lived, two people passed away in the last two or three months. One was 87, the other was 94. They were both looking forward to their death.</p>

<p>The 94-year-old priest in particular kept saying, “I want to die. I want to die.”</p>

<p>We brought him into the hospital at one stage, The Mater Hospital in Nairobi, and the nurse said to me, “You know, he keeps saying he wants to die, he wants to die, but everyone in this hospital wants to live. We’re wondering, is there something wrong? Is there something we should be doing?”</p>

<p>At one moment he refused all his medication and all of his food. I said to him, “Father, why don't you eat your food or take your medicine?”</p>

<p>“It's the only weapon I have to get out of this place.” So he had a great sense of humor. He died laughing. A great way to live and a great way to die. Abandonment in the moment of death, in the arms of God, because he lived a holy life.</p>

<p>Likewise, the other one, 87, saying his rosary every day, getting to Confession every week, receiving Holy Communion every day. I asked him in the last couple of days before he died, “Is there anything that you'd like?”</p>

<p>“Well, if you could find this dark chocolate, I'd be very happy.” I went to the supermarket and I found the dark chocolate. He liked a particular type of dark chocolate. So he went to heaven, enjoying himself! Great way to live, great way to die.</p>

<p>I have no worries, I’ve lived a good life, I abandon myself into the arms of my Father God, because we have tremendous things to look forward to.</p>

<p>“Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered the heart of man, the things that God has prepared for those who love him” (1 Cor. 2:9). If we live our lives focused on heaven, it's a great way to live.</p>

<p>We try to make our life on earth as heavenly as possible, but we realize that everything here is passing. It’s worth nothing, it’s fading away.</p>

<p>The things of the spirit, the things of the soul, the things that are worth having—these are the things worth acquiring, the treasures that God gives to us.</p>

<p>We look at little children, we see how they abandon themselves, and how they can get great joy out of little things.</p>

<p>Over the last few weeks, I was involved in a number of Christmas parties for poor kids. I have a friend who organizes these parties, and he gets big numbers. He brings lollipops and chapatis and sodas.</p>

<p>One time we were going to a place, and I said, Where are you going to get the children for the party? He said, You just watch.</p>

<p>So he gives two sodas to two kids. They go away. Fifty kids come within five minutes. So he gives them a lollipop, one by one.</p>

<p>Well, you see the faces of those kids light up with the lollipops and sometimes they have to struggle to get the tight wrapping off the lollipop, because it seems to be there with concrete or something. They fight to get it off. The joy on their faces, the happiness, the little things.</p>

<p>Sometimes God wants us with our childlike spirit to get great joy and happiness out of simple things. It's a great way to learn to be happy.</p>

<p>In the writings of St. Josemaría, you'll find in one place it says, “Be content with what enables you to live a simple and sober life (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 631).</p>

<p>Great advice. Who do you know in this world who is content—content with what they have, happy with what they have, thanking God for what they have.</p>

<p>A great way to live every day: Thank you, God, for the food we have on the table, for the air that I breathe, for the fact that my hands and legs work, that I can see, that I can hear. So many things that we take for granted too much.</p>

<p>We abandon every day, every hour, in our work, this project, the dreams we have for this coming year, in our workplace, in our family, in the problems we'd like to solve.</p>

<p>Maybe God has precisely given us those problems to work at solving them, not because He wants us to worry about it or be perturbed about it. He just wants us to work at them, but we know that things will work out.</p>

<p>“If you, evil as you are,” we’re told in Scripture, “know how to give good things to your children, how much more will your heavenly Father give good things to those who ask him?” (Matt. 7:11).</p>

<p>If you think back over the last few weeks, how many parents in the world did their best at Christmastime to give good things from Father Christmas to their children?</p>

<p>Maybe even if their children didn't deserve them, they still wanted to give them good things, the best they could find. Our Lord tells us, “How much more will your heavenly Father…” It's a great world for all of them.</p>

<p>Our Father God is waiting to give us all the best presents in the world, all the best treasures, but He wants us to trust in Him, to leave everything in His hands.</p>

<p>Every day of our life we can ask Our Lord for an increase in faith, an increase in hope, an increase in charity, an increase in that spirit of divine filiation, that God is my Father.</p>

<p>There may be twists and turns along the pathway of our life, but we know it will work out well in the end.</p>

<p>There was a little girl who asked Santa Claus for a thousand dolls for Christmas. Her father was an atheist.</p>

<p>She got one doll. Her father said to her, “Well, your God didn't listen to your prayer, did he?”</p>

<p>The little girl said, “Yes, He did. He said no. And that's okay. He's my Father, so it's okay for Him to say no from time to time. You're my father, you say ‘no’ pretty frequently also. That’s no big deal; that doesn't mean you don't exist.”</p>

<p>Wow, profound wisdom from a small child.</p>

<p>Sometimes, God might seem not to answer our prayer. Sometimes He says yes, sometimes He says no and sometimes He says, Wait, I’ll give that to you later. Or, Wait, because I have something better to give you, I have something greater off the line.</p>

<p>Or maybe, I don't want to give you that material thing, but I have some great spiritual thing to give you, which is worth far more than you realize, far more than a diamond. Abandonment!</p>

<p>There is a movie that came out about twenty or thirty years ago about a nun talking to a prisoner on death row. This nun is trying to convert this prisoner, helping him to repent and make his peace with God.</p>

<p>The movie is her conversation with this prisoner on death row, and at one stage she says to him: “Did you ever hear that you are a son of God?”</p>

<p>And he replied saying, “You know, in the course of my life I've been called a son of many things, but I have never been called a son of God.”</p>

<p>Well, this great reality can be something that can open our eyes, that we are truly sons of God, children of God.</p>

<p>God is my Father and therefore I can make this new beginning, this new year, with an awful lot of confidence and hope and trust that God is going to be there for me. He's going to work things out.</p>

<p>When we look back over the last year, possibly we can thank God for all the graces that He's given to us in the past year, all the things that are worked out.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was sitting in her garden, and she noticed there was a rose in the garden. Suddenly her attention began to focus on the rose, a beautiful rose.</p>

<p>She began to think how man has been able to put men on the moon, but no man can make a rose like that. That was the beginning of a profound spiritual conversion.</p>

<p>She began to focus on all the great spiritual things in her life. She’d led a very busy career woman life up to then. She became a very spiritual person.</p>

<p>In this coming year, God also wants some sort of spiritual conversion inside us, so that we live out that spiritual childhood, that abandonment, in so many ways.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to the apostles, “Do not be afraid.” On many occasions He said those words.</p>

<p>In the face of the supernatural, very often there was fear. There was the storm on the lake when He came walking to them: “Do not be afraid! It is I. Have courage, do not be afraid” (John 6:20).</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lord and ask Him that we might also respond to those words. Remember that we're worth more than many sparrows and not a single sparrow falls to the ground without Our Father God knowing it.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord that we might have this greater spirit of trust and abandonment, the trust and abandonment that we see that Our Lady had throughout her life.</p>

<p>She didn't understand what was going to happen in Bethlehem. She didn't know that they were going to go to Egypt. She didn't know how long they were going to be there. She and St. Joseph were just totally, completely abandoned to the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help me to live that spirit of abandonment in the same way that you did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Against All Hope</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/against-all-hope/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against All Hope" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/against-all-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/against-all-hope/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Who in hope believed against hope, to the end that he might become the father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken, ‘So shall your seed be’” (Rom. 4:18).</p>

<p>St. Paul says these words in his Letter to the Romans, referring to Abraham.</p>

<p>Christian asceticism pictures man's life on earth as a journey that has its end in God. We are all like men on a journey, a wayfarer, longing to turn his steps quickly towards his definitive goal: God.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI says because of this we must all “provide ourselves with hope if we want to walk with a firm and certain step along the hard path in front of us” (Paul VI, <em>Address</em>, December 9, 1975).</p>

<p>If the traveler were to lose hope of reaching their destination, they would not continue with their journey. The only thing that keeps the traveler on his way is his trust that he will some day reach his goal.</p>

<p>As Christians we want to travel very straight and fast towards holiness—to God.</p>

<p>In human life, when a person sets themselves an objective, their hope of achieving it is based on their physical resilience, their training, and their own experience. When all is said and done, it's based on their willpower which enables them, if necessary, to draw strength from their very weakness.</p>

<p>To reach the supernatural end of our existence, we don't rely only on our own strength, but on God, who is all-powerful. He's the faithful friend who doesn't let us down.</p>

<p>I heard a story once of some people who were out sailing and a bad storm arose, and the waters were coming in, and the waves were coming over the edge of the boat. Things weren't looking good, and they were a bit stuck.</p>

<p>But then around the corner of the head of land that was close by, they saw a much bigger boat, a trawler, that was heading into the harbor to take refuge. They were able to send a signal to that bigger boat.</p>

<p>They had sent many signals to the land before, but nobody saw them. Now they sent a signal to this bigger boat, who saw the signals, and they realized that the ability of the bigger boat to be able to help them depended on the power of that bigger boat to be able to throw them a line, to be able to pull them into shore.</p>

<p>But it also depended on the goodwill of the people in the other boat, because if they were in a hurry into the harbor with their catch, or they couldn't be bothered helping these other people, they might have just passed them by.</p>

<p>But they had the power, and they had the goodwill, and they were able to throw them a line, and they were able to pull them into land. And so, they lived to tell the tale.</p>

<p>Our hope in Our Father God is based on those same two principles: He's all-powerful, He's able to do anything; and also, He's all goodness.</p>

<p>Our trust in Him and our hope in Him is well justified. To reach the supernatural end of our existence, therefore, we rely on that goodness and power of our all-lovable Father God. He's the friend who doesn't let us down.</p>

<p>His goodness and His mercy are not the same as the goodness and mercy of men, which may frequently be “like a morning cloud, like the dew that goes early away” (Hos. 6:4).</p>

<p>Thanks to the supernatural virtue of hope, a Christian can be confident that he will reach his definitive objective, which already began with Baptism in this life and will remain forever in the next.</p>

<p>This objective is not something merely provisional, not the point of departure towards a further goal, as is the case with ordinary journeys.</p>

<p>The <em>Catechism of St. Pius X</em> says through this virtue, we hope and long for that eternal life promised by God to those who love Him, together with the means needed to achieve it and the support of His omnipotent help.</p>

<p>The greater the difficulties and the weaker we are, the stronger our hope in God has to be, for the greater His help will be. His closeness to our lives will be all the more evident.</p>

<p>In his Letter to the Romans, St. Paul recalls how Abraham “believed in hope against hope, that he should become the father of many nations, as he had been told” (Rom. 4:18).</p>

<p>Pope John Paul I comments: “You will still say, ‘How can this happen?’ The answer is it can happen because it clings tightly to three truths: God is omnipotent, God loves me immensely, and God is faithful to His promises.</p>

<p>“And it is he, the God of mercy, who awakens trust within me; trust which makes me know that I am not alone, or useless, or cast aside, but rather I am a part of a salvific destiny which will end one day in Paradise” (John Paul I, <em>Address</em>, September 20, 1978).</p>

<p>Abraham did not hesitate despite his advanced years and his wife's sterility. He trusted firmly in the power and mercy of God, being fully persuaded that “God is able to do what He promises” (Rom. 4:21).</p>

<p>And we, “Aren’t we going to trust Jesus Christ,” said one author, “‘who was delivered up for our sins and rose again for our justification’ (Rom. 4:25)? How could God leave us alone to deal with the obstacles we encounter which try to prevent us living in accordance with the call we have received from him?</p>

<p>“He holds out his hand to us in many different ways: usually in our daily prayer, in our fulfillment of the plan of life that we have set ourselves, in the sacraments, and, in a special way, in the advice we receive in spiritual direction.</p>

<p>“Our Lord will never leave us alone on our journey through this world, and on which we frequently experience faintheartedness and weakness.”</p>

<p>A year or two ago there was a story in a newspaper about a family—husband and wife and two children—that were travelling along a road somewhere in Ireland. Suddenly the car went off the road and into a river. Overturned.</p>

<p>The driver, the husband, and the two children were drowned, but the mother managed to escape, even though she made many efforts to try and save the children.</p>

<p>At the funeral of her husband and two children, her family gone in a second, she stood up to speak, heartbroken. She said, “Cherish your family. Your family can be here today and gone tomorrow.”</p>

<p>She also said, "If God has left me, it's because He has a purpose for my existence.”</p>

<p>There was a woman at a very difficult moment of her life, possibly the most difficult, who had learned how to see that moment with a supernatural perspective, to have hope in God for the future when nothing seemed to make any sense.</p>

<p>Our hope of becoming saints, of faithfully doing what God expects of each one of us, depends on our accepting the hand that He holds out to us. Accepting whatever comes. Seeing this is His will.</p>

<p>Another mother in a school somewhere in Europe was collecting her children from school. She had an automatic car, and by mistake, instead of putting the gear stick into reverse, she put it into going forward.</p>

<p>The car lurched forward and hit a three- or four-year old little girl who was there at that school. She died instantly. The mother of that little girl was standing nearby.</p>

<p>Of course, both mothers were heartbroken. But the mother of the dead child was able to forgive the other mother, who was equally distraught. They had to look forward to the rest of their lives with hope, with peace.</p>

<p>This virtue is not based on our own worthiness, on our own personal situation in life, or on the absence of difficulties, but on God's will—on His will that we should reach the goal—a will which is always accompanied by all the grace and help that we can need in any possible circumstances.</p>

<p>If God allows situations to happen that lead us to put all our hope and trust in Him, because nothing seems to have worked out, nothing seems to be according to reason, it's because He wants us to put all our hope in Him, to try and see that there's some great apostolic purpose in all of those experiences.</p>

<p>It may be that in a week or two, or a month or two, or a year or two, some other person will be brought in contact with us who perhaps has experienced something similar. Because we've been there, we know what to say to them; how to give them hope and trust, even when they have to believe in hope against hope.</p>

<p>In <em>The</em> <em>Forge</em>, we're told: “Though I should walk through the valley of the shadow of death, no evil will I fear. Neither my wretchedness nor the temptations of the enemy will worry me—for you, Lord, are with me” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 194).</p>

<p>So many places in the Gospel show us time and again how God is closer to those who need Him most, inviting us to hope in spite of the obstacles, or the setbacks, or the pain.</p>

<p>He has come to cure, to forgive, to save, and not only to preserve those who are whole. He's the divine Physician who, above all, cures the sicknesses of the soul.</p>

<p>“Those who are well have no need of a physician, but those who are sick” (Mark 2:17). He says this to those who criticized Him for eating with publicans and sinners.</p>

<p>When the things of the soul are not going well, when they have lost their health—and we’re never completely well—Our Lord is ready to pour out more care, more help. He doesn't abandon the sick person, and He doesn't abandon us. He doesn't give up anybody for lost.</p>

<p>He doesn't leave us alone with our defects, with those things we can and must improve, because He calls us to sanctity, and He has the necessary graces ready for us.</p>

<p>It's only the sick person who can cause the medicines, and the actions of the Physician who can cure all ills, to be ineffective by refusing to take them.</p>

<p>The saving will of Christ for each one of His disciples—for us—is the promise that we will reach what He Himself asks of us.</p>

<p>The virtue of hope enables us to see that the difficulties of this life have a deeper meaning. They don't happen by chance, or by blind destiny, but because God wills them, or at least He permits them, in order to bring greater good from those situations.</p>

<p>That approach can help us in all the trials that God may permit in our life or those in the lives of people who are close to us.</p>

<p>That approach can help us to strengthen our trust in Him, to grow in the awareness of our divine filiation, that I am a child of God and carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves me, in spite of all appearances.</p>

<p>This is the truth. It helps us to see that we can bring about great good from those things.</p>

<p>It can help us to foster a greater detachment from our health and earthly goods, to cleanse our hearts from intentions which perhaps may not be altogether good, and to do penance for our sins and for those of all men.</p>

<p>God tells each one of us that He “prefers mercy to sacrifice” (Matt. 9:13; Hos. 6:6), and if at some moment He allows pain and suffering to overwhelm us, it's because it is good for us. There's a far more lofty reason that we at times do not understand.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says if God allows hearts to be broken, it's because He wants to enter into them a little more, wants to make them more Christ-like, to form them, to fashion them after His own heart (cf. <em>Through the Year with Fulton Sheen</em>).</p>

<p>Those heartbreaks are for our own benefit, for that of our family, our friends, the benefit of the whole Church.</p>

<p>God wants our greater good in just the same way as the mother who gives permission for an operation that will enable her child to become healthy again.</p>

<p>It's at such moments that we have to believe with a faith which is strong and to reawaken our hope, because it's only this virtue that will teach us to regard as a treasure what humanly presents itself to us as failure, or perhaps as a great misfortune.</p>

<p>These are the moments when we have to go close to the tabernacle and say slowly to Our Lord that we want everything that He wants.</p>

<p>“This is our great mistake,” writes St. Teresa, “we do not resign ourselves absolutely to the disposition of our Lord, who knows best what is for our good” (Teresa of Ávila, <em>Life</em>).</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, Point 773, it says: “Jesus, whatever you ‘want,’ I love.”</p>

<p>Whatever you allow, I, with your help, will accept as a great good, without laying down any limits or conditions. I will always thank you for everything, if you are close to me.</p>

<p>With a certain frequency, we have to call to mind our hope of ultimately being saints. St. Paul says in the Letter to the Romans that “in everything God works for the good” (Rom. 8:28).</p>

<p>We have to try and repeat that in the depths of our heart, even though we might be passing through a great physical or moral difficulty that possibly seems to have no solution.</p>

<p>A lady approached the Regional Vicar of Opus Dei in Argentina one day to thank him for having given her a prayer card to St. Josemaría. He didn't remember that occasion; he didn't remember this lady.</p>

<p>But she said, “Yes, a couple of years ago, you saw me on the street and you gave me a prayer card. At that time my husband was about to divorce me, my children were going through a bad time, I was unemployed, my husband was unemployed. Everything was going wrong in my life and you gave me that prayer card and I prayed it, and now everything has come right.”</p>

<p>Very often God permits everything for our own good. He wants us to try to overcome the way that we may tend towards selfishness, or sadness, or mainly trivial objectives.</p>

<p>We're journeying straight towards Heaven. Everything has to become an instrument to bring us closer and enable us to arrive sooner. Everything, even our weaknesses.</p>

<p>We should frequently practice the virtue of hope in all that concerns the state of our own interior life, particularly when it seems that we're not advancing, that our defects are slow in disappearing, or that we constantly make the same mistakes.</p>

<p>We might tend to see sanctity as something very distant from us; perhaps just an illusion.</p>

<p>We need to have in mind at those moments the teaching of St. John of the Cross, who says that the soul “who has the hope of heaven achieves all that is hoped for” (St. John of the Cross, <em>Poems,</em> VI).</p>

<p>This virtue can be a great driving force in our life. It's the virtue of people who keep looking up. They don't look down, particularly in difficult moments. They see the supernatural aspect of everything.</p>

<p>There are people who don't receive divine goods because they don't have the hope of receiving them, because their outlook is too human, too narrow. They don't even glimpse the greatness of the goodness of God who gives us His help, even though we don't in the least deserve it.</p>

<p>St. John of the Cross says, “To win love’s chase, I took my way, and full of hope began to fly. I soared aloft and soared so high, that in the end I had reached my prey” (<em>Idem</em>).</p>

<p>Our hope should be in God alone. It should be all embracing, childlike as God wants it to be. Children don't just believe in their parents. They hope in them for everything that they need.</p>

<p>When holiness—which is the final aim of our lives—seems far away, we shouldn't slacken in our struggle to come closer to God. We should try to have an ardent hope and to fulfil our duties, day by day, hour by hour.</p>

<p>We have to try and put into practice the advice we received in spiritual direction and the resolutions from our examinations of conscience or our last day of recollection.</p>

<p>We should try and struggle resolutely against discouragement. Some writers say discouragement is the greatest tool of the devil.</p>

<p>At a given moment we may only be able to offer Our Lord the pain and the sorrow that we feel for our defeats—on battlefronts of greater or lesser importance—and also, our renewed desire to begin again.</p>

<p>We struggle resolutely against discouragement. This would be a humble offering which is very pleasing to Our Lord.</p>

<p>Hope encourages us to begin again with cheerfulness and patience, and without getting tired.</p>

<p>We're told in the <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church,</em> “Hope is the theological virtue by which we desire the kingdom of heaven and eternal life as our happiness, placing our trust in Christ's promises and relying not on our own strength, but on the help of the grace of the Holy Spirit” (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 1817).</p>

<p>“Let us hold fast to the confession of our hope without wavering, for he who promised is faithful” (Heb. 10:23).</p>

<p>“The Holy Spirit ... He poured out upon us richly through Jesus Christ our Savior, so that we might be justified by his grace and become heirs in hope of eternal life" (Titus 3:6-7).</p>

<p>“The virtue of hope,” the <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> says, “responds to the aspiration to happiness which God has placed in the heart of every man; it takes up the hopes that inspire men's activities and purifies them so as to order them to the Kingdom of heaven; it keeps man from discouragement; it sustains him during times of abandonment; it opens up his heart in expectation of eternal beatitude. Buoyed up by hope, he is preserved from selfishness and led to the happiness that flows from charity.</p>

<p>“Christian hope takes up and fulfills the hope of the chosen people which has its origin and model in the hope of Abraham”—who in hope against hope, believed—"who was blessed abundantly by the promises of God fulfilled in Isaac, and who was purified by the test of the sacrifice. ‘Hoping against hope, he believed, and thus became the father of many nations’ (Rom. 4:18).</p>

<p>“Christian hope unfolds from the beginning of Jesus' preaching in the proclamation of the beatitudes. The beatitudes raise our hope toward heaven as the new Promised Land; they trace the path that leads through the trials that await the disciples of Jesus. But through the merits of Jesus Christ and of his Passion, God keeps us in the ‘hope that does not disappoint’ (Rom. 5:5).</p>

<p>“Hope is the ‘sure and steadfast anchor of the soul...that enters…where Jesus has gone as a forerunner on our behalf’ (Heb. 6:19-20).</p>

<p>“Hope is also a weapon that protects us in the struggle of salvation: ‘Let us ... put on the breastplate of faith and charity, and for a helmet the hope of salvation’ (1 Thess. 5:8). It affords us joy even under trial: ‘Rejoice in your hope, be patient in tribulation’ (Rom. 12:12). Hope is expressed and nourished in prayer” (<em>Catechism</em>, Points 1818-1820).</p>

<p>Prayer is the language of hope. “We can therefore hope in the glory of heaven promised by God to those who love him and do his will (cf. Rom. 8:28-30; Matt. 7:21). In every circumstance, each one of us should hope, with the grace of God, to persevere ‘to the end’ (Matt. 10:22) and to obtain the joy of heaven, as God's eternal reward for the good works accomplished with the grace of Christ.</p>

<p>“In hope, the Church prays for ‘all men to be saved’ (1 Tim. 2:4). She longs to be united with Christ, her Bridegroom, in the glory of heaven” (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 1821).</p>

<p>We are told in the <em>Catechism</em>: “Hope, O my soul, hope. You know neither the day nor the hour. Watch carefully, for everything passes quickly, even though your impatience makes doubtful what is certain, and turns a very short time into a long one.</p>

<p>“Dream that the more you struggle, the more you prove the love that you bear your God, and the more you will rejoice one day with your Beloved, in a happiness and rapture that can never end” (St. Teresa of Ávila, Excl. 15:3).</p>

<p>St. John Paul II liked to call Our Lady “the Woman of Hope” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Tertio millennio adveniente</em>, Point 48, November 10, 1994).</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady to help us to cultivate that virtue in a special way every day, particularly aware of the influx of supernatural hope into our soul each time we receive the sacraments.</p>

<p><em>I thank you my God for the good resolutions, affections and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p>OLV</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aim High</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/aim-high/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aim High" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/aim-high</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/aim-high/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“The Spirit of the Lord is upon me. He has sent me to bring good tidings to the poor, to proclaim liberty to the captives, release to the prisoners, and to announce a year of favor to the Lord” (Luke 4:18).</p>

<p>Having said these things, quoting from the Book of Isaiah (Isa. 61:1-2) in the local synagogue in His own hometown, Our Lord “rolls up the scroll, hands it back to the assistant, and sits down” (Luke 4:19). Sitting down was the traditional sign that some important teaching was about to come.</p>

<p>All the townspeople that were there were waiting with bated breath. Suddenly, Our Lord startled them by saying, “Today this Scripture passage is fulfilled in your hearing” (Luke 4:21).</p>

<p>The word which startled them was the word “today” because they'd been trained to look to the future. Salvation was something coming in the future.</p>

<p>But Our Lord talks about “today.” He is here today. He doesn't make a long-range forecast. He doesn't promise that things will be different in the future.</p>

<p>Rather, He claims the power to transform the present, to transform today. There aren't any good times coming. They are here now.</p>

<p>He declares that “the kingdom of God is among you” (Luke 17:21). Something like 80 percent of Our Lord's recorded sayings emphasize that reality, that here and now, this day, God has broken into your life, and He can break into your life.</p>

<p>Here and now is what God counts. “Today all this is fulfilled in your hearing.” Today grace abounds. Today the kingdom of God can be revealed. Today God is revealed behind every episode of your life. Not another day, but today.</p>

<p>As we start this retreat, we could contemplate those words of Our Lord and the importance of this moment.</p>

<p>We’re here listening to this retreat. It's because God has wanted us to be here, listening to this retreat. He's packaged it for you. He has a message for you. The Holy Spirit will speak to you somewhere along the line.</p>

<p>There are things God wants you to hear: eternal truths. Possibly, truths about your own life, truths about the future.</p>

<p>But all that is to happen now, today. Our Lord speaks to us about living this moment very well.</p>

<p>This retreat is a time of grace—a time that God wants us to think, to pray, to change, to make resolutions, and to see how we are living all the other todays.</p>

<p>The retreat is a time to examine our conscience, which really means to examine our life, our thoughts, our heart.</p>

<p>St. Pope John Paul II says there are three fundamental questions that every human person must keep asking themselves in their life: Where have I come from? Where am I going? What is my life all about? (cf. John Paul II, <em>Fides et Ratio</em>, September 14, 1988).</p>

<p>He says that to a large extent, the answers to those questions will determine the happiness that we achieve in this life.</p>

<p>And so, it's important to live this moment well, to realize that God is speaking to us. He has a mission for us. Something to say to us.</p>

<p>An old woman once told a story and she said, “First, I was dying to finish secondary school and start college. Then I was dying to finish college and start working. Then I was dying for the children to grow old enough to attend school so that I could return to work. Then I was dying to retire. And now, I'm dying. I suddenly realize I had forgotten to live each day.”</p>

<p>God speaks to us in the present. He invites us to make radical decisions in our lives, to use our time well, use our life well, discover the mission that He has for us.</p>

<p>He has a mission for each one of us. He wants to place before us the greatest ideals that any human person can have in their life, which are the ideals of Christ. He wants us to think about them, ponder them, go for them.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in the first point of <em>The</em> <em>Way</em>, from the chapter on Character that has changed the life of many a man, many a person, says, “Don't let your life be sterile. Be useful. Blaze a trail. Shine forth with the light of your faith and of your love.”</p>

<p>These are very dynamic words. He speaks them to young people. Make decisions now because time is passing. Don't waste your youth doing crazy things. It's one of the greatest times of your life. Live it for God. Do good things.</p>

<p>He says, “With your apostolic life, wipe out the slimy and filthy mark left by the impure sowers of hatred. Light up all the ways of the earth with the fire of Christ that you carry in your heart” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 1).</p>

<p>He is speaking to every young person on the planet, saying: Do something decent with your life.</p>

<p>In the last few weeks, I had occasion to read about or talk to some very impressive people who did really impressive things in their lives.</p>

<p>There was a Good Shepherd nun in Singapore who ran an orphanage in Burma during the Second World War. I met her a couple of decades ago.</p>

<p>There's another Sacred Heart nun who passed away this week who had a bit of a remote influence on my life as a child in a Montessori school. She then went off to teach English to seminarians in Vietnam, educated some people in China, looked back on her life with great fulfillment.</p>

<p>I was talking to a 95-year-old Kiltegan priest here in Kenya recently who was full of the joys of living, because he feels so fulfilled with what he had done in his life. He spent his time well.</p>

<p>We have a great opportunity to use this retreat to make those radical decisions that God wants us to make.</p>

<p>In a book called <em>Surprised by Joy</em>, C.S. Lewis tells the story of his conversion. He says he was raised in Northern Ireland. He was taught his prayers, but not much religion.</p>

<p>Then he went to college. He dropped out of religion altogether. He had no use for it. He became a convinced atheist.</p>

<p>But despite himself, he was bothered by the grace of today, a <em>here and now</em> tapping on his shoulder.</p>

<p>He writes, “Some days a little door would open to an unspeakable burst of joy. Then it would slam again. The door would open, then it would slam. Open and slam.”</p>

<p>Finally, one day when he was at Oxford, at Magdalen College, something happened. The one who had been pursuing him daily finally caught up with him.</p>

<p>He said, “You must picture me alone in that room in Oxford feeling…the steady unrelenting approach of Him whom I earnestly desired not to meet. … It was in the Trinity Term of 1929 that I gave in, and admitted that God was God, and I knelt and prayed: perhaps that night, the most dejected and reluctant convert in all of England.”</p>

<p>He never became a Catholic, but he talks about his time of grace. “Today the Scripture was realized in his hearing.”</p>

<p>That’s why the Gospel challenged Jesus’ neighbors. It challenges us to live and to be open to the life of Christ here and now. Not tomorrow or next year. Not when the next millennium comes. But here and now.</p>

<p>We can try to live one day at a time as a day of acceptance of what God wants us to do today.</p>

<p>We can try that every day we try to suspend all our judgments of people. Accept them for what they are so that “this Scripture can be fulfilled in our hearing.”</p>

<p>Secondly, look for the opportunity in today—this day that presents itself, even if today is not quite what we have bargained for.</p>

<p>Very often in life, we may be faced with situations or places or events that we didn't quite bargain for.</p>

<p>A graduate student had just gotten his first job, a desk job. He felt, probably quite correctly, that this job was much beneath his talents. He complained to his friend that he didn't do pencil-pushing.</p>

<p>His friend was rather unsympathetic. He just patted him on the back and said to him, “You know, the world is a better place because Michelangelo didn't say, ‘I don’t do ceilings.’</p>

<p>“You don't go through the Bible and find Moses saying, ‘I don't do rivers’ or Noah saying, ‘I don't do arks’ or Ruth saying, ‘I don't do mothers-in-law.’</p>

<p>“David doesn't say, ‘I don't do giants.’ Paul didn't say, ‘I don’t do Gentiles.’ Mary Magdalene didn't say, ‘I don't do feet.’ Jesus didn't say, ‘I don't do crosses.’”</p>

<p>We have to try and look for the opportunity today, even in things you'd rather not do and in places you'd rather not be.</p>

<p>Today's grace awaits you in the particular place where you are. This is the place where God wants you to change, to look up, to see Him acting in your life.</p>

<p>There was a story of a lady who had her husband's new car. She wasn't a very good driver. She was driving to work one day, and another man was driving to work also, and they happened to collide.</p>

<p>There was a little fender-bender occasion. They both stopped the cars and got out to survey the damage. The woman was absolutely distraught. It was her fault—she admitted it.</p>

<p>This was a new car less than two weeks out of the showroom. She dreaded going home to her husband.</p>

<p>The man felt sorry for her. Nevertheless, certain things had to be done. She had to get the license number, the registration papers, and so on.</p>

<p>She went to her car, and she reached the glove compartment to get the documents. Among the first papers to tumble out, written in her husband's distinctive handwriting, were the following words: ‘In case of an accident, remember, honey, it's you I love, not the car.’</p>

<p>The husband put things in perspective. Perspective is the long view of today's grace, maybe today's cross, today's situation, where I'm a bit lost or a bit distressed or looking for answers to questions that have brought me to this retreat.</p>

<p>Today has to be a day of acceptance of the opportunity that God gives me, without fear. Because “today this reading is fulfilled in your hearing.”</p>

<p>God calls us in the opportunity of today to a deeper personal relationship with Him.</p>

<p>There is the story of a Chinese kid who had this big, very decorative, expensive Chinese vase in their house.</p>

<p>One day this little two-year-old put his hand in the big Chinese vase. At the bottom of the vase, he found a coin.</p>

<p>He was pushing and pulling and pushing and pulling. He'd made a grip with his fist on the coin, but his fist wouldn't come out of the neck of the vase.</p>

<p>Then his parents came on the scene. They noticed the child's arm stuck in the vase and they realized he had something in his hand. They told him to let go of whatever it was that he had in his hand.</p>

<p>But he was Chinese. He had found a coin, so he wasn't going to let go. In the end, they had to break the vase.</p>

<p>They broke the vase and when they opened the child's palm, they found he had the equivalent of one shilling. A very small amount of money. For the sake of the one shilling, a very expensive vase was lost.</p>

<p>One spiritual writer says that sometimes, something similar happens in our spiritual life.</p>

<p>We can be very attached to the coins that God has in His hand: the favors I want, help me to pass this exam, help me to get my driving test, help my parents to say yes, help my boyfriend or my girlfriend to agree to what I want.</p>

<p>Sometimes, he said, we're so attached to the coins that God has in His hand, that we forget the hand that gives. We forget the hand of God in our life.</p>

<p>Instead of being so attached to the coins, he said we have to try and reach out and touch that hand, the hand of God in our life.</p>

<p>If you look back over your life, you'll see the hand of God working, who has brought you to be what you are today, who has given you your education, your Christian formation, helped you to be a bit more aware of your Christian vocation, given you so many things.</p>

<p>Now that hand of God is perhaps beckoning to you, touching you. These days of retreat are days of prayer, days of silence, days of formation. God wants us to be silent with Him.</p>

<p>Just like Jesus on many occasions withdrew into the desert alone to pray, to talk to His Father God, to find out a bit more about the jigsaw puzzle of His life, and to find out the plan of God for His life, and the will of God, each one of us has to try and imitate Our Lord’s example and to realize that God has things to say to us and wants us to change, to make resolutions, to make new conversions.</p>

<p>St. John Henry Newman talked about the importance of change in our lives and how God wants us to change often.</p>

<p>Possibly, what we need is a good Confession to lay bare our soul, to let God's grace get in there to the murky deep recesses of our souls that perhaps have not seen the light of day for years.</p>

<p>Or, to get some serious spiritual direction. We all need spiritual direction. Going anywhere in this world we need a coach. Executives need coaches. Sportsmen need coaches.</p>

<p>Anybody who wants their soul to go anywhere, to do anything today, to make use of this opportunity that God has given to them, needs a coach, a spiritual director that they go to regularly to get a few words of advice, to come away maybe with one concrete idea every time from every ten minutes.</p>

<p>If we put those little ten-minute sessions together, over a couple of months we end up with maybe ten or twenty very powerful ideas.</p>

<p>The Holy Spirit works through this means of formation. It helps us to go forward along that journey, that pilgrimage of faith which is our Christian vocation.</p>

<p>All through His life, Our Lord used the word “come.”</p>

<p>“Come, follow me, and I will make you into fishers of men” (Matt. 4:19).</p>

<p>“Master, where do you live?” “Come and see” (John 1:38-39).</p>

<p>“Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy burdened, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you…my yoke is easy, my burden is light” (Matt. 11:28-30).</p>

<p>Our Lord all the time is saying “come.” Come to a new divine intimacy. That's what this retreat is all about.</p>

<p>It's only at the end of His life that He says “go.” “Go you, therefore, teach all nations” (Matt. 28:19).</p>

<p>We have to “come” before we “go.” This retreat is all about the coming.</p>

<p>God wants us to grow spiritually. He has planted a seed in our soul at baptism. He wants it to germinate. He gives it the fertilizer of His grace of formation.</p>

<p>Of course, when you put fertilizer on a plant, on a rose bush or some other plant, you don't see it sprouting up in front of your eyes and producing a wonderful fruit or a wonderful flower. It takes time.</p>

<p>Good wine improves with time. God wants our souls to improve with time. He may have great things prepared for us, just like he had great things prepared in and through the very special life of Joseph, his very ordinary life<strong>.</strong></p>

<p>We have to try and examine our conscience and see what areas of our life need conversion.</p>

<p>Do we get drunk? Are we doing drugs? Are we indulging in things we shouldn't be indulging in? Are we a little bit too lazy? Lacking in order? Lacking in charity? Lacking in respect for other people? Lacking in honesty or integrity?</p>

<p>There was a man who was a little bit too drunk, who was coming home from a few too many drinks one night. He happened to spot a rusty nail on the ground.</p>

<p>It was a twisted, bent, rusty nail. It caught his attention, and so he bent down to pick it up. It took him a few goes before he could pick it up because he was very unsteady on his feet, but finally, he got it.</p>

<p>He was thinking: If I could straighten this out and remove the rust, it could be useful some day.</p>

<p>When he sobered up a day or so later, he began to straighten out the nail and he began to get rid of the rust with some sandpaper. As he was working on the nail, the Holy Spirit was working on his soul.</p>

<p>He began to see, “Really my life, my soul, I'm a bit like this rusty nail. What I need to do is to straighten myself out a little bit. Just like I'm straightening out this nail, I need to straighten out my life, straighten out my soul, my conscience.”</p>

<p>He realized he needed to go to a good Confession. Maybe, start a new practice of regular Confession to let the grace of God circulate in his soul.</p>

<p>Sometimes the Holy Spirit works in funny ways—leads us back to God or leads us to see things with greater clarity, things in our life that we need to straighten out, things that are not as they should be.</p>

<p>Maybe He bothers our conscience a little bit. But God also wants us to want that new change and that new conversion, to want it 100 percent.</p>

<p>There was a story of a thief who decided to go to Confession to a priest. He was a pickpocket and he wanted to confess his sins.</p>

<p>He went to confess his sins to the priest face to face. In the course of the Confession, he stole the watch of the priest. He was really an expert pickpocket.</p>

<p>At the end of the Confession, when the priest said, “Is there anything else?” he said, “Oh yes, Father, I forgot. I stole a watch.”</p>

<p>The priest said, “Well, you have to give it back.”</p>

<p>The thief said, “Father, that will be a little bit difficult. But I tell you what, I will give it to you.”</p>

<p>The priest said, “I don't want it—you've got to give it back to the owner.”</p>

<p>The thief said, “The owner doesn't want it.”</p>

<p>The priest said, “In that case, you may keep it.” The thief ended up with the watch of the priest.</p>

<p>One thing you could say about that interchange was that that guy was not very sincere. He really didn't want to change his life.</p>

<p>We can't be sorry for our sins if we're not willing to change our lives. The <em>purpose</em> <em>of</em> <em>amendment</em> has to be present in our Confession.</p>

<p>If a person goes to the priest and says, “Father, I killed fifty people last week, and if I get a chance, I'll kill another fifty next week” the priest will say, “You have to go and try and change your contrition. You have to be ready to amend your life, to change your life.”</p>

<p>Similarly, if a person comes and says, “Father, I'm using contraception” the priest has to say, “Are you willing to stop using contraception before I can give you absolution?”</p>

<p>Or “Are you willing to stop stealing?” “Are you willing to stop getting drunk?” Whatever it is, here and now, we have to be willing to change our lives.</p>

<p>That doesn't mean that I will never take a drink again for the rest of my life, or I will never kill somebody again. But here and now, I want to change my life. That is enough to get a valid absolution because that's valid contrition.</p>

<p>In Scripture, we find the Psalm saying to Our Lord, “Create a new heart in me, O God” (Ps. 51:10).</p>

<p>We come to the retreat to get a new heart. “Take out this heart of stone and give me a heart of flesh” (cf. Ezek. 36:26).</p>

<p>“A humble and contrite heart, O Lord, you will not spurn” (Ps. 51:17).</p>

<p>It has a great importance in our faith in the heart. We get a new heart by washing our souls and our hearts in the waters of Confession. The grace of God flows there and washes away our sins.</p>

<p>But we have to first of all realize that there is something there that needs to be changed.</p>

<p>There is a story of an Irish priest one time whose congregation had a lot of problems with alcoholism. He tried to give a very graphic sermon.</p>

<p>He brought a bottle of whiskey to the pulpit and also a live worm. Then in the sermon, he dropped the live worm into the whiskey.</p>

<p>He said, “I’m going to show you what this whiskey does to this worm.” The worm shriveled up and died because of the acidic nature of the whiskey. “You see, this is what the whiskey does to your insides.”</p>

<p>After the homily, he was very happy with himself; things had gone very well.</p>

<p>But back in the sacristy when he was divesting, a man came into the sacristy and said, “Father, I wonder if I could have the bottle of whiskey because, you see, I'm full of worms.”</p>

<p>One thing you can say about that man is that he was honest. He knew his insides very well. He knew his problems. He knew his weaknesses. He knew his illnesses. He knew what was there deep down inside him.</p>

<p>In the course of our retreat and of our life, we have to try and discover those deep-down things that need changing. God wants us to see them.</p>

<p>He wants us to make resolutions to change them because he wants us to be better, because that's what holiness is all about.</p>

<p>There was a farmer who had to go out to hunt for food for his family. He had three bullets in his rifle. He saw a rabbit. He shot and he missed. Then he saw a fox, and he shot and he missed.</p>

<p>And then he saw a big fat turkey up in a tree. He lifted the rifle to shoot the turkey. But then the voice of conscience deep inside him said: “Aim high, pray first, stay focused.”</p>

<p>As he was about to shoot the turkey, out of the corner of his eye he saw a deer. The deer had more meat than the turkey, so he lowered the rifle to shoot the deer. Then he heard the voice of conscience again: “Aim high, pray first, stay focused.”</p>

<p>Then he saw there was a rattlesnake between his feet and that posed the greatest danger to life and limb. He was about to shoot the rattlesnake, but then he heard the voice of conscience again saying to him: “Aim high, pray first, stay focused.”</p>

<p>He lifted up the rifle to shoot the turkey. He thought he better obey the voice of conscience. He shot the turkey. The bullet ricocheted off a bone in the turkey, hitting the deer and killing the deer.</p>

<p>The impact of shooting the rifle made him lose his balance and he stood on the snake, killed it, and fell backwards into a pond that was full of fish.</p>

<p>When he stood up from the pond, he had a dead turkey, a dead deer, a dead snake, and plenty of fish with which to feed his family.</p>

<p>The moral of the story is that we have to aim high, pray first, stay focused.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady that in this retreat, we might use our time well, reading good things, praying a lot, listening to the Holy Spirit, letting God speak to us, because He probably wants a new conversion from us these days. Because “today the Scripture has been fulfilled in our hearing.”</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to make the changes to our lives that you want us to make.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>DWM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All Saints’ Day</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-saints-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All Saints’ Day" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-saints-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-saints-day/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“My dear friends,” we are told in St. John, “we are already God's children, but what we shall be in the future has not yet been revealed. We are well aware that when he appears we shall be like him, because we shall see him as he really is. Whoever treasures this hope of him purifies himself, to be pure as he is” (1 John 3:2-3).</p>

<p>Today we celebrate the Feast of All the Saints, a feast of all those who have gone before us and who are now happy in heaven.</p>

<p>In many ways, the goal of our life is to be a November 1^st^ saint, not necessarily to have a feast day assigned to us, but to be one of those immense numbers of people in heaven, enjoying the company of God forever.</p>

<p>“Blessed are you when people abuse you and persecute you and speak all kinds of calumny against you falsely on my account. Rejoice and be glad, for your reward will be great in heaven; this is how they persecuted the prophets before you” (Matt. 5:11-12).</p>

<p>Today is a day of joy, and also a day of hope—a day of joy and hope because we look forward to the eternal wedding feast to which God has called us, which will bring us great joys. “Your reward will be great in heaven.”</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Way</em> says, “Foster in your heart the glorious hope of heaven” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 668).</p>

<p>“What does it matter,” he says, “if we suffer in this world for ten, twenty, thirty, forty years...if afterwards there is heaven forever and forever and forever?” (<em>Ibid</em>., Point 182).</p>

<p>Heaven makes everything worthwhile. We can look forward to that great reality where “eyes have not seen, nor ears heard, nor has it entered into the heart of man the things that God has prepared for those who love him” (1 Corinthians 2:9).</p>

<p>Today we celebrate those who have fought the good fight, who have finished the race, who communicate to us a message that is worthwhile: Keep on struggling. “Be you perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect” (Matt. 5:48).</p>

<p>“You must see,” said St. John, “what great love the Father has lavished on us by letting us be called God's children, which is what we are. The reason why the world does not acknowledge us is that it did not acknowledge him” (1 John 3:1).</p>

<p>In the Beatitudes, Our Lord encourages us to walk along a certain pathway, which is the pathway to heaven, to be poor of spirit, to be gentle, to hunger and thirst for righteousness, to be merciful, to be pure in heart, to be a peacemaker. All these things He suggests to us as beautiful realities.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how in the Old Testament God gave us the commandments, but in the New Testament, He gave us the Beatitudes. It's like a loving Father speaking to His children. Commandments are like a Creator speaking to those He has created.</p>

<p>Ultimately the message of today's feast day is that sanctity is within reach of everyone.</p>

<p>And we know, we've heard, from the Second Vatican Council and so many other ways, that everyone is called to holiness. The Entrance Antiphon of today's Mass says: “Let us all rejoice in the Lord and keep festival in honor of all the saints. Let us join with the angels in joyful praise to the Son of God.”</p>

<p>We're also reminded today and tomorrow of the Communion of Saints, how we are united in the Church.</p>

<p>The Church has different parts, just like the human body. There's the Church suffering in purgatory; there’s the Church triumphant in heaven; the Church militant here on earth, struggling, fighting.</p>

<p>The Blessed in heaven, we know, can help us here on earth. The truth of our faith is that those who have gone before us, who have a special relationship with us, continue with their particular concern for each one of us from heaven.</p>

<p>Our parents, our loved ones, we know, follow us very closely. Somebody said once, the distance between heaven and earth is really very small.</p>

<p>The Preface of today's Mass says: “Around your throne, the saints sing your praise forever. Their glory fills us with joy.”</p>

<p>And Our Lord reminds us of the rewards for our fidelity. “Blessed are you, for I was hungry and you gave me to eat. I was thirsty and you gave me to drink” (Matt. 25:35).</p>

<p>No small thing that we do on this earth for others and for God will be forgotten in the eyes of God.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría reminds us that all the little things we may have done in the past, our guardian angel has taken note, and on the day of judgment, he will bring out all those good deeds from his files.</p>

<p>We're encouraged because the difficulties, the miseries, the crosses—we realize these are all the pathway to holiness.</p>

<p>The saints were normal people, not superbeings. But often they did have a heroic correspondence to the graces that God gave them. Somehow, they took very seriously that phrase of Scripture: “This is the will of God, your sanctification” (1 Thess. 4:3).</p>

<p>Stories of fidelity are always very beautiful and very moving, and can be very inspiring for us.</p>

<p>We are called to the fullness of love, and we're reminded today that sanctity is accessible to everyone in all sorts of jobs and situations. Nobody is excluded.</p>

<p>There was a document of the Holy See that was being prepared in the 1940s that began to open up to the idea that people could be holy in the world. It's mentioned in a book called <em>The Canonical Path of Opus Dei</em>.</p>

<p>That document mentioned how people could be holy in most professions, but not in anything relating to commerce or finance.</p>

<p>In the succeeding twenty years, before the Second Vatican Council, the Holy Spirit worked a bit more, and we came to the great teaching of the Council about the <em>universal call to holiness</em>. There are no limits to where we can be holy, which walks of life can be holy here on earth.</p>

<p>This Feast of All the Saints has been celebrated since the eighth century. There's a great tradition in the Church of celebrating the saints.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, we're told, “It seems an excellent idea to me that you should tell the Lord often about your great and ardent desire to be a saint, even though you see yourself filled with wretchedness...—Tell him, precisely because of this!” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 419).</p>

<p>Our sights are lifted up onto great goals, great ideals. We’re reminded that it's not enough to be nice people, good guys. God wants us to be saints.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to say to his children, “I love you very much, but I want you to be holy.” There was a play on the word <em>querer</em>, to love in Spanish, and to want. “I love you very much, but I want you to be holy.”</p>

<p>We know that we have all the graces to achieve this end. “My grace is sufficient for you” (2 Cor. 12:9).</p>

<p>Through the life of St. Josemaría, we also have all the means: our plan of life, our norms, our prayer, our mortification, our examination, our living out of the virtues, our Confession, our attention to little things.</p>

<p>“Today in your prayer,” we're told in <em>The Forge</em>, “you confirmed your resolution to be a saint. I understand you when you make this more specific by adding, ‘I know I shall succeed, not because I'm sure of myself, Jesus, but because...I'm sure of you’” (<em>Ibid</em>., Point 320).</p>

<p>St. Josemaría also liked to tell us that the sanctity that God is asking of us is not an ordinary sanctity, but a canonizable sanctity.</p>

<p>He's placed the bar very high. Christ has given us so much, a great immeasurable spiritual wealth, in the spirit of Opus Dei.</p>

<p>“But those to whom much has been given, much will be demanded” (Luke 12:48).</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Forge,</em> “You are amazed to find there are many different goals that can be pursued within each field in which improvement is possible. —There are other ways within <em>the way</em>, and they help you to avoid possible routine and bring you closer to Our Lord. —Be generous: aim for the highest” (<em>Ibid</em>., Point 820).</p>

<p>We see athletes around us going for gold, preparing for the Olympics, breaking records in marathons.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us to have the same mentality as those athletes, not struggling for a perishable crown. We see people doing all sorts of amazing things to obtain that perishable crown, but we're striving for an imperishable crown.</p>

<p>“If you were consistent,” we're told in <em>The Forge</em>, “now that you've seen his light you would want to be as great a saint as you were once a sinner: and you would struggle to make those desires a reality” (<em>Ibid</em>., Point 883).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, we’re told, “You present yourself as a wonderful theoretician. But you don't give way to others even in the most insignificant trifles. I do not believe in that spirit of mortification of yours” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 990).</p>

<p>“Sanctity consists precisely in this: in struggling to be faithful throughout your life and in accepting joyfully the Will of God at the hour of death” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 990).</p>

<p>The Church tells us that the Holy Spirit is the great Sanctifier. And so, if we're striving for holiness, it makes a lot of sense that we would pray to the Holy Spirit frequently.</p>

<p>The sequence of Pentecost Sunday, the <em>Veni Creator Spiritus</em> or the <em>Veni Sancte Spiritus,</em> hymns that we find in many popular Christian devotion booklets, are very good prayers to say in your <em>Thanksgiving after Mass</em> or in other moments of the day, asking the Holy Spirit that we might truly grow along this pathway.</p>

<p>Like good athletes, we keep ourselves very fit and in shape, not allowing any trace of lukewarmness to enter.</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>, “You are lukewarm if you carry out lazily and reluctantly those things that have to do with Our Lord; if deliberately or ‘shrewdly’ you look for some way of cutting down your duties; if you think only of yourself and of your comfort; if your conversations are idle and vain; if you do not abhor venial sin; if you act from human motives” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 331).</p>

<p>Many years ago in the 1980s, I was going out to Mass in Manila one Sunday morning and I had to cross one of the main streets of the city and I didn't know that there was a marathon taking place.</p>

<p>In those days, marathons were just beginning, and I was blocked for about 10 minutes while the runners were passing.</p>

<p>But I got a bird's eye view of all the runners, and it was very interesting to see some people who were running very well, some people not so well, and others looking as though they should have stopped running in marathons about twenty years previously.</p>

<p>But you could roughly divide the runners into those three groups:</p>

<p>Those who entered the race for a bit of a joke, maybe the night before, they did no training. Very soon they got a pain in their side and had to drop out of the race.</p>

<p>Then there were those who had done some training but perhaps hadn't pushed themselves too much. Eventually, they also developed a pain in their side. But because they'd done some bit of training, they were able to keep going, although with difficulty. Those were the ones with the looks of agony on their faces.</p>

<p>The other group of runners were the ones who had taken the race seriously. They'd done a lot of good training. They went over the course beforehand. They knew where to turn left, where to turn right. They knew where the hills were, where they had to conserve their energy.</p>

<p>And they were running like champions, cruising in the middle of the road. They were going to cruise home and eventually win the race.</p>

<p>You could say that those three types of runners are roughly those that go to hell, go to purgatory, and go to heaven:</p>

<p>Those who go to hell are those who haven't taken the race seriously, have not heeded any of the calls to vigilance, to training.</p>

<p>Those who go to purgatory have, well, they've tried to do something.</p>

<p>And those who go to heaven are those who run like champions and have a little bit in hand so that they can help many other people over the finishing line.</p>

<p>In calling us to be saints, God has called us to be the third type of runner who take the race seriously, to listen to our coach very carefully, to pay attention to all the means that God gives us to triumph in the race, to take every twist and turn of the journey very carefully, to be thinking of other people in the race, and to enjoy the race.</p>

<p>The Entrance Antiphon of today's Mass says: “Let us rejoice in the Lord and keep festival in honor of all the saints. Let us join with the angels in joyful praise to the Son of God.”</p>

<p>The theme of joy is very prominent: joy for those who have run the race well, who are focused on the goal. They know where they've come from, they know where they're going, they know what the race is all about.</p>

<p>The supernatural last end of the universal redemption is signified in the Mass, the source of our sanctity for all those who practice the Beatitudes as described by Our Lord.</p>

<p>The way we run the race well is to stay close to those sacraments, to love them, to appreciate them, to get as much as we can from them.</p>

<p>The Preface of the Sacred Heart says: “We draw close to the Sacred Heart of Christ to draw water in joy from the wells of salvation” (<em>cf</em>. Isaiah 12:3). Along the pathway of the marathon, we need occasionally to draw plenty of that water.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church invites us also today to bring to mind in a special way those who have experienced difficulties and temptations similar to our own during life, and yet in the end triumphed over them.</p>

<p>The Church has recognized many saints of every age and condition. Pope John Paul II canonized hundreds of saints, more saints in his pontificate than in the whole of the rest of human history. It's one of the themes of his pontificate: pointing to that goal of holiness in our lives.</p>

<p>We remember all these saints each year and have recourse to them as intercessors for our various needs. We ask them for things. We know they have great intercessory power before God.</p>

<p>We rejoice and ask the help of this countless multitude who have reached heaven after cheerfully passing through life sowing affection and joy almost without realizing it. They've sown the good seed in the lives of so many other people.</p>

<p>They give us inspiration and encouragement of how we have to practice the virtues, and to find that holiness in the ordinary situations of each day.</p>

<p>The Church has liked to remind us that the saints were not superheroes or special people. They would have had to confront difficulties very similar to what we may have to face. They would have had to begin again and again; make a daily effort as we do.</p>

<p>The Church doesn't mention all of their names. There are too many to mention. But St. John Paul says they were “humble yet great laborers for the growth of the Kingdom of God in history” (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Christifideles laici</em>, Point 17, December 30, 1988).</p>

<p>It would be a wonderful thing when we get to the end of our life to be able to look back and say, ‘By the grace of God, I've managed to sow some seeds. This world is a better place with the fact that I have passed through,’ so that we might inspire other people to take up the baton and run with it.</p>

<p>A struggle against our passions and inordinate tendencies is necessary. We have to make a constant effort to improve.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría said, "Sanctity does not depend on one’s state of life—single, married, widower, or priest—but on our personal correspondence with the grace God grants to each one of us” (J. Escrivá, <em>In Love with the Church</em>, Point 37).</p>

<p>The Church reminds everyone that both the worker who takes up his trade or profession each morning and the mother of a family committed to the daily running of the home should sanctify themselves in all sorts of ways by fulfilling their duties faithfully (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Christifideles laici</em>, Point 15, December 30, 1988).</p>

<p>It can be consoling for us also to realize that people with whom we had dealings a short time ago are now contemplating the face of God. We continue to be united to them by profound friendship and affection through the Communion of Saints.</p>

<p>St. Teresa of Ávila had a prayer to the Blessed in heaven where she said, “O holy ones who knew how to prepare so delightful an inheritance, help us now that you are so near the fount of all holiness. Draw water for those of us who are perishing from thirst” (St. Teresa, <em>The Exclamations of the Soul to God</em>).</p>

<p>In the Preface of today's Mass we say: “Father, today we keep the festival of your holy city, the heavenly Jerusalem. Our brothers and sisters, the saints, now sing your praises forever around your throne and their glory fills us with joy. Our communion with them through your Church gives us inspiration and strength as we hasten on our pilgrimage of faith, eager to meet them.”</p>

<p>We, the faithful on earth, are the pilgrim Church on our way to heaven. While we make progress towards heaven, we need to gather up the treasure of good works we will one day present before God.</p>

<p>Today's feast day reminds us to make good use of our time, and so that advice of the Gospel that says, “Store up for yourselves treasures in heaven” (Matt. 6:20).</p>

<p>We hear a lot of people wondering about their investments, their return, and their interest. With the same focus and zeal, we could be interested in our interest that we're accruing in heaven and the good things that we do.</p>

<p>We hear the Lord's invitation clearly: “If anyone will come after me, let him take up his cross and follow me” (Matt. 16:24).</p>

<p>We know that we are called to the fullness of Christian life through our professional occupation. Work is the hinge of our sanctity. God wants us to encounter Him in our work by carrying it out with human perfection and supernatural outlook.</p>

<p>It's there in the middle of the world that we long for the presence of the Lord, whom we will one day see face to face.</p>

<p>And so, we offer up all our activities, practice charity in our dealings with others, and are generous in bringing that work that has been entrusted to us to completion. By talking with Our Father God as a friend, we can continually refine our contemplative spirit in the midst of the ordinary activities of every day.</p>

<p>“For the vast majority of men,” said St. Josemaría, “to be a saint implies sanctifying their work, sanctifying themselves in it, and sanctifying others through it. Thus they encounter God in the course of their daily lives” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 55).</p>

<p>What else did the vast host of glorified souls do? Mothers, intellectuals, manual workers—what did they do to win heaven? They just did the ordinary things; they fulfilled their work well.</p>

<p>This is of absolute importance since we are desiring to abide with God forever in heaven. If we persevere in union with Christ and make an effort to sanctify the small realities of every day that Our Lord looks upon with affection, that crown will truly be ours.</p>

<p>If at any given moment our fidelity might be lacking, we can rectify accordingly and set out once again on that path. That's our pathway on earth; sometimes falling down, like Our Lord on the way to Calvary, but always getting up again.</p>

<p>Winning heaven is the challenge we face with the grace of God each day.</p>

<p>The Blessed in heaven are not those who never fell in this life, but they're those who got up again. Possibly they got up again many times.</p>

<p>Happily, that goal of holiness involves the task in hand and often is effected precisely among the persons that God has wanted to place at our side.</p>

<p>God has said, “Love your neighbor” (Matt. 22:39). He didn't say, ‘Love your friends.’ We choose our friends, but God chooses our neighbor. And He invites us to love that neighbor.</p>

<p>We need to realize fully that our generous and holy resolve to improve constantly has an important impact on others. We need to give a lot of good example and to keep trying to be more Christ-like, to practice more virtues.</p>

<p>If through God's grace and the help of others we do reach heaven, we won't enter eternal glory alone, but we have to try and draw many others in with us.</p>

<p>Many of those who now contemplate the face of God in heaven perhaps did not have an opportunity during their time on earth to carry out great deeds. However, they did fulfill their modest daily duties as best they could.</p>

<p>On occasion, they may have made mistakes. They gave in to impatience, or laziness, or pride, or perhaps even sinned gravely.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, they repented right away and took advantage of the sacrament of Confession to begin again—the importance of the apostolate of Confession, of sharing with other people our magnificent experience of the sacrament of joy.</p>

<p>The Blessed in heaven had big hearts and led fruitful lives since they knew how to sacrifice themselves for Christ.</p>

<p>We too are very much in need of Our Lord's great mercy during our journey to heaven. Our Lord keeps us going day by day and doesn't let us falter.</p>

<p>It's a tremendous good for us to pause frequently to consider Him and the graces we have received, to cast a contemplative gaze back over our week, our month, our year.</p>

<p>A yearly retreat is a really good way to keep on the right path as the years pass by, possibly more important at certain stages of our life than others. But it keeps us on track, reminds us of the important things, helps us not to get lost in the race.</p>

<p>The Blessed in their lives never consider themselves saints. On the contrary, they are often convinced of their great need for divine mercy.</p>

<p>To a greater or lesser degree, everyone experiences sickness, or tribulation, or low energy periods in which everything entails a particular effort. Failure may come our way, but we have some successes also.</p>

<p>Perhaps at times the saints were moved to tears, but they knew and put into practice those words that Our Lord says in Scripture: “Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy burdened and I will give you rest” (Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>They found their rest in Christ. The Blessed always lean on Christ for support. They visit Him in the tabernacle to draw renewed energy from His presence there.</p>

<p>The personalities of the Blessed vary enormously, but in this life they had one distinguishing feature in common: they lived charitably with those around them.</p>

<p>Our Lord had said: “In this will everyone know that you are my disciples, if you have love for one another” (John 13:35). This is the common denominator of the saints who currently enjoy the vision of God.</p>

<p>Our Lady awaits us in heaven also. She'll offer us a hand to take us into the presence of her Son and of our faithful departed loved ones who even now watch over us.</p>

<p>Mary, Queen of all the saints, pray for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All Souls</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-souls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All Souls" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-souls</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-souls/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“For everything, there is a season,” we're told in the Book of Ecclesiastes, “and a time for every matter under heaven; a time to be born and a time to die, a time to plant and a time to pluck up what is planted” (Eccles. 3:1-2).</p>

<p>All go to one place, all are from dust, and all turn to dust again. The Liturgy of the Church also reminds us every Ash Wednesday that we are dust, and to dust we shall return (Gen. 3:19).</p>

<p>Every year the Church gives us this Commemoration of the Souls of the Faithful Departed.</p>

<p>It's a rather beautiful custom whereby the Church invites us to stop and to look back at those who have gone before us, and to remember them with supernatural charity, to pray for them if they may still be in Purgatory, that they may go to heaven.</p>

<p>I saw a painting of a priest once who was saying Mass, and under the altar there were the souls in Purgatory, and as he was saying Mass, souls were going up to heaven.</p>

<p>The Church invites us to pray for those souls in Purgatory and to learn a lot from their lives.</p>

<p>The Church has granted a plenary indulgence for anyone who visits a cemetery or place where people are buried, even if they're not Catholics, on the first eight days of November. We can get a plenary indulgence applicable to the souls in Purgatory.</p>

<p>When we commit a mortal sin, we merit eternal blame and eternal punishment. When we go to confession, the eternal blame is forgiven, and some of the eternal punishment is changed into temporal punishment (<em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Points 1472-1473).</p>

<p>When we commit a venial sin, we merit temporal blame and temporal punishment. When we go to confession, the temporal blame is forgiven, and some of the temporal punishment is taken away also.</p>

<p>At the end of our lives, there is a large amount of temporal punishment that still remains for the sins which have been forgiven.</p>

<p>We can use the little contradictions or crosses of this world: the headaches, the failures, the reverses of fortune, to satisfy for this temporal punishment while we're here on earth. And if not, we go to Purgatory to satisfy for it there.</p>

<p>A plenary indulgence is a remission of that temporal punishment that is due for the sins that have been forgiven, and we can apply that to the souls in Purgatory.</p>

<p>We can also gain a plenary indulgence on the Day of the Faithful Departed of all Souls by visiting a church and praying an <em>Our Father</em> and a <em>Creed</em>. And that can gain a plenary indulgence applicable to the souls in Purgatory.</p>

<p>It's interesting that the Church encourages us to gain these indulgences. Part of the Christian formation of children embraces the gaining of those indulgences.</p>

<p>Notice how the Church encourages us to visit a cemetery or a place where people are buried in the first eight days of November. On the other days of November, we can gain a partial indulgence by doing the same thing.</p>

<p>But why does the Church encourage us specifically to go to a cemetery? Because there are many lessons to be learned there: it's catechetical, it's formative. It focuses us a little bit on death and on the last things: Death, Judgment, Heaven, Hell, and Purgatory.</p>

<p>The vast expanse of cemeteries where everybody is at the same level and the silence of cemeteries also carry their own message.</p>

<p>We teach children about the reality of death and what death is. It is the separation of the soul from the body, but the soul goes on living.</p>

<p>The Liturgy of the Church, the Masses for the Dead, and the Preface for the Dead talk about the bright promise of immortality.</p>

<p>Death for a Christian can be a very beautiful thing. It's not something to be afraid of or seen as a punishment. It's the gateway to eternal life (<em>cf</em>. <em>Catechism</em>, Point 1021).</p>

<p>In cemeteries, children can learn about the immortality of the soul, the beautiful truth of our faith. It can be a reminder to take care of our soul through prayer, through the sacraments.</p>

<p>It's also a reminder that we have each other on loan. Someday, my mother and my father will go to be with God. It's a message we have to transmit to our children, and they have to transmit to their children. It's the law of life. It's a normal thing.</p>

<p>And since the resurrection of Christ, death is an Easter, a passage. We lay aside the bodily exterior with which we could not move into the divine atmosphere.</p>

<p>The worn and withered shells of the bodies of the dead have value only for God. They return to being dust. But we continue to live, to know, to love, without being limited by the fragility of our bodies or hindered by the shackles of sin.</p>

<p>The truth of the immortality of the soul can give great consolation and comfort when we experience the death of a loved one.</p>

<p>Death is a passage into life that man is prepared for here below, and that continues with God, without end. Death places us in the infinity of the depths of God. Through Christ, eternal life becomes tangible. Death is a passage towards Christ (<em>cf</em>. <em>Catechism</em>, Point 1005).</p>

<p>This life is an antechamber of a great happiness—the wedding feast. It's our privilege and joy to look forward to that wedding feast when everything becomes finished here in this valley of tears.</p>

<p>The soul and the body are made to be together. And so, we believe that one day there will be the resurrection of our bodies on the last day. They will enjoy the company of God forever in heaven.</p>

<p>If we live for ourselves, we are necessarily unhappy. If we live for Christ, we already have one foot in eternity. The combat ceases only with the final heartbeat. We cross the threshold to eternity.</p>

<p>Death is enlightened, entirely enlightened, by the mystery of faith. If the end stops in a hole in the ground, then life is not worth the trouble. Cemeteries lift up our gaze to look at something over, above, and beyond, greater than ourselves. It leads us to laugh at this life and to laugh at death.</p>

<p>There is a monastery of Capuchins on the Via Veneto in Rome where there are five or six chapels that are decorated from floor to ceiling, with the bones of monks from ages past: plenty of femurs and tibia and fibula and humeri. They decorate that place. Heaps of skulls, vertebrae, ribs. Embalmed monks fixed in perpetual stillness, re-clothed in their habits, imitating postures of prayer.</p>

<p>At the entrance, there is a placard that warns visitors: we were like you; you will be like us. It's very salutary from time to time to have these reminders of what is ahead so that we prepare for that.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Philippians, “The body is dead, but the spirit is living” (Rom. 8:10). St. Thérèse of Lisieux said: I do not die, I enter into life” (<em>cf</em>. St. Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>The Last Conversations).</em></p>

<p>We could consecrate our death to God. If God has chosen us out before the foundation of the world, He's also chosen the moment and the manner of our death. It's a moment of grace. We can thank God for it. It will be the best possible death that God could give us.</p>

<p>We don't have to worry about it, but just accept it with humility and prepare for it. In many ways, it's “the most important act of earthly existence. All life is made to explode, to go further—to merge with Life with a capital L, with God” (Robert Cardinal Sarah, Introduction to Nicolas Diat, <em>A Time to Die: Monks on the Threshold of Eternal Life</em>).</p>

<p>Pope Francis has recently spoken about the spiritual emptiness of the world (Pope Francis, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Querida Amazonia</em>, Point 108, February 2, 2020; <em>Angelus</em>, June 19, 2016), a materialistic world where death is a fearful reality.</p>

<p>One writer said: “Never before has the relationship to death been so impoverished as in this time of spiritual desolation, when men, in their rush to exist, seem to avoid all mystery” (Nicolas Diat, <em>A Time to Die: Monks on the Threshold of Eternal Life</em>).</p>

<p>“Denial of death pervades our present times. Modern man has an obsessive fear—‘God is dead’ (Friedrich Nietzsche, <em>The Gay Science</em>) and so is death” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>When John Paul Sartre, a French existentialist, went to visit that Capuchin monastery in the Via Veneto and saw all those dead bones, he thought it was a sick joke.</p>

<p>“The West has worked hard to bury death more deeply in the vaults of its history,” but our message to twenty-first-century man is that “he's not condemned to lonely endings, without love, in anonymous hospital rooms.”</p>

<p>St. Joseph is the patron of a happy death.</p>

<p>“A peaceful approach to death lies in humility and simplicity. When death approaches, its hand reveals its strength.”… We can be “like happy and naive children who wait with impatience to open a gift.”</p>

<p>An elderly nun in Asia told me many years ago: she was “waiting in joyful hope.” I thought that was a beautiful phrase. She was well into her 90s. She led a very fulfilled life, taking care of all sorts of orphanages and poor children in all sorts of places. She had an awful lot to look forward to.</p>

<p>“Waiting in joyful hope.” It's a phrase from the Mass. It comes just after the Our Father. We can be like happy and naive children waiting in joyful hope. “They have no doubts about the fulfillment of the promise.</p>

<p>“A spiritual life doesn't prevent us from loving the earth. On the contrary, we love it differently, and perhaps more, because the earth is more beautiful with the eyes of faith. Nature is more beautiful, souls are more beautiful, human relationships are more beautiful” (Father Michel quoted in Diat, <em>A Time to Die</em>)—because we know where we come from, where we're going, what life is all about.</p>

<p>We look forward to the eternal wedding feast, eternal happiness, where every tear will be wiped away. That bright promise of immortality—it's worth waiting for; it's worth longing for; it's worth getting there.</p>

<p>And if ever we see how God may carry away a person in the prime of life, it may be that God just wants to show men that He is the Lord of life and that we are not the masters of death. He has His reasons, and it's not given to us to understand them.</p>

<p>Death is the time for the realization of the promises of the faith. Suddenly life stops; God comes and goes away with our brother or with our sister.</p>

<p>Without God, man is an utter absurdity. And all life is a school—a school that tells us and reminds us to make good use of our time—perhaps to think about death.</p>

<p>Thinking about death is not morbid. On the contrary, it enables us to have an understanding of the meaning of life, helps us to learn to recognize the end of our road. Why be afraid?</p>

<p>The resurrection is the foundation of our faith (<em>cf</em>. <em>Catechism</em>, Points 642, 655, 989; Rom. 1:4). Real life is not on earth. Every day we must prepare to die. And the greatest way to do that is to live in the state of grace. To live the life of grace, to be close to the sacraments because we don't know what hour and what day is going to be our last. Our Lord may come like “a thief in the night” (1 Thess. 5:2, Rev. 16:15).</p>

<p>“The strength of a person's prayer throughout their life will very much influence their approach to old age and death. … The stronger the supernatural life, the greater the familiarity with the afterlife and the simpler the death” (Dom Thevenin, quoted in Diat, <em>A Time to Die</em>).</p>

<p>God is infinitely merciful, but also, we must remember that He's infinitely just. He will ask us to atone for all our sins. We all know that we're going to die so we should live life accordingly.</p>

<p>“How could men remain indefinitely in this valley of tears? We are born to meet God. … Death is the end of this school. And afterward, there comes Paradise. The person who's given their life to God and has never met Him—it's normal for them to be impatient to see Him. In the poems of St. Teresa of Ávila and St. John of the Cross, they talk about how they die from not dying.</p>

<p>“To our great regret, the Holy Spirit is not in a hurry to come for us. .. In the final months, Christ has already taken hold of the elderly. The worn-out body returns to the earth, but it is to await the glory of its resurrection. We do not know yet what our body is, its beauty, its glory, and its light. The most beautiful, by far, is yet to come” (Dom Innocent, quoted in Diat, <em>A Time to Die</em>).</p>

<p>And so, “death is a final exam that's easy to pass. And eternal life is like summer vacation. Earthly life is a simple school for understanding God…and, after the exam, we leave on other paths (Diat, <em>A Time to Die</em>).</p>

<p>The Book of the Apocalypse (Revelation) says, “Then I heard a voice from heaven saying, ‘Write this: Blessed are the dead who from now on die in the Lord.’ ‘Blessed indeed,’ says the Spirit, ‘that they may rest from their labor, for their deeds follow them’” (Rev. 14:13).</p>

<p>There's a famous poem by an English poet called James Shirley called <em>Death the Leveller</em> that says:</p>

<p>“The glories of our blood and state<br />
Are shadows, not substantial things;<br />
There is no armor against Fate;<br />
Death lays his icy hand on kings:<br />
Scepter and Crown<br />
Must tumble down,<br />
And in the dust be equal made<br />
With the poor crooked scythe and spade.</p>

<p>Some men with swords may reap the field,<br />
And plant fresh laurels where they kill:<br />
But their strong nerves at last must yield;<br />
They tame but one another still:<br />
Early or late<br />
They stoop to fate,<br />
And must give up their murmuring breath<br />
When they, pale captives, creep to death.</p>

<p>The garlands wither on your brow,<br />
Then boast no more your mighty deeds!<br />
Upon Death's purple altar now<br />
See where the victor-victim bleeds.<br />
Your heads must come<br />
To the cold tomb:<br />
Only the actions of the just<br />
Smell sweet and blossom in their dust.”</p>

<p>This day invites us to consider the souls in Purgatory, the Church suffering. The Preface of Christian Death says, “For your faithful people, life is changed, not ended. When the body of our earthly dwelling lies in death, we gain an everlasting dwelling place in heaven” (<em>Roman Missal,</em> Preface of Christian Death I).</p>

<p>We consider those souls and try to help them get into heaven. They cannot earn anymore, their time for earning is over, but they can pray for us. Devotion to the souls in Purgatory can be a very good devotion. They can do all sorts of little favors for us.</p>

<p>“We rise at your word to the glory of the Resurrection,” says the Preface of Christian Death. “Your loving kindness calls us back to life” (<em>Roman Missal,</em> Preface of Christian Death IV).</p>

<p>Purgatory is a place of purification. It's a waiting room of heaven, not a lesser hell, but a place of preparation where souls are truly cleansed of the remains of sin before entering heaven.</p>

<p>Purgatory reminds us of sin and our inclination to sin, which we acquire through original sin, and which is increased by personal sin.</p>

<p>If we haven't sufficiently atoned for any specific offenses against God during the course of our earthly life, there's a further need for reparation to be accomplished. Evil dispositions may remain rooted in our souls at the hour of our death. We should make up for all our negligences, our lack of love, our lack of refinement in dealing with Our Lord. Everything must be paid for.</p>

<p>Purgatory is the only possibility of achieving that purification.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas says, “The least pain of Purgatory is greater than the greatest pain on earth” (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Supplement, Appendix 1, Question 2).</p>

<p>So Purgatory is worth avoiding. But there is also joy there—joy because we know that heaven comes afterward. The soul in Purgatory has already won the last battle and is awaiting a more or less permanent encounter with God.</p>

<p>Perhaps think and see if you know some friend or relative who perhaps has nobody to pray for them. Think of that soul—the lost souls in Purgatory—offer your Masses for them. We can help them pass more quickly over that great divide that separates them from God by making reparation for our sins.</p>

<p>We know that Our Lady, the Mother of all souls, will look out for them in a special way. She'll take the infinite value of the Masses that we offer for them and help them to yield abundant fruit.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “The holy souls in Purgatory. Out of charity, out of justice, and out of excusable selfishness—they have such power with God!—remember them often in your sacrifices and in your prayers. May you be able to say when you speak of them, ‘My good friends, the souls in Purgatory’” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 571).</p>

<p>Our Blessed Mother, Mary, Refuge of sinners, will obtain for us the grace to act accordingly.</p>

<p>Queen of all souls, pray for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>CPG</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anchored in Hope</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/anchored-in-hope/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anchored in Hope" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/anchored-in-hope</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/anchored-in-hope/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Romans, “Be joyful in hope, persevere in hardship, keep praying regularly” (Rom. 12:12).</p>

<p>One of the sections of the document of Pope Francis for the Jubilee Year is called ‘Anchored in Hope’ (Pope Francis, Bull of Indiction of the Ordinary Jubilee of the Year 2025, <em>Spes non confundit,</em> Points 18-25, May 9, 2024).</p>

<p>It's a rather striking title. An anchor is an interesting thing. Many big ships have anchors. They're big metal things that fall into the water, that clip onto a rock or something on the base of the sea, and somehow hold that ship in position.</p>

<p>Standing in some of the parks of Singapore that line the coastline and looking out towards the sea, you see hundreds of ships. It's one of the busiest ports in the world.</p>

<p>At one point, all the ships are pointing in one direction, and then maybe a few hours later they're pointing in a different direction. I asked a naval engineer one time: ‘What is it that makes the ships move in different directions? Is it the winds?’</p>

<p>He told me to think again, as though saying that was not a very intelligent question. And when I thought again, I suggested it might be the currents.</p>

<p>He told me that was the correct answer. The currents change in different ways and so all the ships move in different ways. But yet they maintain their position because of the anchor.</p>

<p>And what is happening on the surface of the sea, that strong anchor, anchors them in that position.</p>

<p>This title reminded me of a point in <em>The Way of the Cross</em> by St. Josemaría in the Seventh Station. On the second point for contemplation, he says, “Drop anchor in your divine filiation, no matter what is happening on the surface of the sea of your life. And you will find joy, strength, optimism: victory!” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way of the Cross</em>, Seventh Station).</p>

<p>We're all called to have an anchor—a deep thing that goes deep down onto the seabed and anchors us there on some big rock.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría invited us to “drop anchor” in our divine filiation—the fact that we are children of God. And Pope Francis is saying now we have to be anchored in hope, a very beautiful phrase and use of words.</p>

<p>“Hope, together with faith and charity, makes up the triptych of the ‘theological virtues’ that express the heart of the Christian life (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 13:13; 1 Thess. 1:3).</p>

<p>“Faith, hope and love, these three remain. But the greatest of these is love” (1 Cor. 13:13).</p>

<p>St. Paul talks a lot about this virtue, about charity, about faith, about hope. We’re told God our Father is active in the faith, unsparing in love. St. Paul says, “We should be persevering in the hope that we have from Our Lord Jesus Christ” (Heb. 10:23).</p>

<p>“In their inseparable unity,” Pope Francis says, “hope is the virtue that, so to speak, gives inward direction and purpose to the life of believers. That's why St. Paul encourages us to ‘rejoice in hope, be patient in suffering, persevere in prayer’” (Rom. 12:12).</p>

<p>He says, “Surely we need to ‘abound in hope’ (<em>cf</em>. Rom. 15:13), so that we may bear credible and attractive witness to the faith and love that dwell in our hearts; that our faith may be joyful and our charity enthusiastic; and that each of us may be able to offer a smile, a small gesture of friendship, a kind look, a ready ear, a good deed, in the knowledge that, in the Spirit of Jesus, these can become, for those who receive them, rich seeds of hope.”</p>

<p>It's a very beautiful idea that Pope Francis encourages us to think about: that we have to sow seeds of hope in the lives of other people—with our words, with our example, with our lifestyle, with the whole witness of our life well lived.</p>

<p>“May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in your faith, so that in the power of the Holy Spirit, you may be rich in hope” (<em>cf</em>. Rom. 15:13).</p>

<p>The Gospel invites us to be spiritual millionaires—to be rich in certain ways.</p>

<p>In the early 1980s, forty years ago, Pope John Paul II in his [second] encyclical had an encyclical called <em>Dives in misericordia</em>–“Rich in Mercy.” Now Pope Francis is giving us a renewed call to be rich in hope.</p>

<p>What a beautiful thing if our interaction with other people, particularly in the family, with our children, with our friends, with our neighbors, with our colleagues, with our classmates, we can sow seeds of hope.</p>

<p>“Yet what is the basis of our hope?” Pope Francis asks, and he says, “To understand this, let us stop and reflect on ‘the reasons for our hope’” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Pet. 3:15). Questions which St. Peter asks in his First Letter, chapter 3.</p>

<p>“Simply proclaim the Lord Jesus Christ holy in your hearts, and always have your answer ready for people who ask you the reason for the hope that you have” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Pet. 3:15).</p>

<p>It's a logical question that people should be able to ask us the reason for our hope.</p>

<p>In the next part of the document <em>Spes non confundit</em> or “Hope Does Not Disappoint,” he says, “I believe in life everlasting” (Apostles’ Creed). This is the reason for our hope.</p>

<p>“This is what our faith professes. Christian hope finds in these words an essential foundation. I believe in life everlasting. For hope,” he says, “is ‘that theological virtue by which we desire…eternal life as our happiness’” (<em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point 1817).</p>

<p>“The Second Vatican Council says…that ‘when people are deprived of this divine support, and lack hope in eternal life, their dignity is deeply impaired, as may be seen so often today. The problems then of life and death, of guilt and suffering, remain unsolved. People are frequently thrown into despair’” (<em>cf</em>. Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et spes</em>, Point 21).</p>

<p>“We, however,” he says, “by virtue of the hope in which we were saved, can view the passage of time with the certainty that the history of humanity and our own individual history are not doomed to a dead end or a dark abyss, but rather directed to an encounter with the Lord of glory.”</p>

<p>To remind everyone we meet, somehow, of the eternal happiness to which we are called, the eternal wedding feast. The commentators of the <em>Theology of the Body</em> of John Paul II like to say that Pope John Paul is saying that God wants to marry us.</p>

<p>We are all called to the eternal wedding feast. He said marriage in this world is just a preparation for marriage in the next.</p>

<p>If something goes wrong in our marriage in this world, it's just a means of preparation for that eternal wedding feast, that eternal happiness to which we are called.</p>

<p>“We live our lives in expectation” of what is to come—"in the hope of living forever with him. In this spirit, we make [our own] that heartfelt prayer of the first Christians with which Sacred Scripture [ends]: ‘Come, Lord Jesus!’” (Rev. 22:20).</p>

<p>We live in your expectation. “The death and resurrection of Christ is the heart of our faith and the basis of our hope.”</p>

<p>St. Paul says in his First Letter to the Corinthians, “I handed on to you as of first importance what I in turn had received, that Christ died for our sins in accordance with the Scriptures, and that he was buried, and that he was raised from the dead on the third day in accordance with the Scriptures, and that he appeared to Cephas and then to the twelve” (1 Cor. 15:3-5).</p>

<p>“Christian hope consists precisely in this: that in facing death, which appears to be the end of everything, we have the certainty that, thanks to the grace of Christ imparted to us in Baptism, ‘life is changed, not ended’ (Roman Missal, <em>Preface I for the Dead</em>), forever.” Changed forever and not ended forever.</p>

<p>“Buried with Christ in Baptism, we receive in his resurrection the gift of a new life that breaks down the walls of death, making it a passage to eternity.”</p>

<p>And so, our death is just a diving board or a jumping-off board, a change of minimal things. It's a passageway to greater things.</p>

<p>“The Jubilee, however,” says Pope Francis, “offers us the opportunity to appreciate anew, and with immense gratitude, the gift of the new life that we have received in Baptism, a life capable of [transfiguring] death's drama.”</p>

<p>It’s very important for us to understand death. Very interesting and useful that every year in our retreat we perhaps hear a meditation on death.</p>

<p>We reflect on this occasionally. We're not afraid to think about it. We don't run away from it. It's not just some horror that exists there that we fear in a great way.</p>

<p>We look forward to our death, because that's the gateway to eternal life, the gateway to eternal happiness. That's something wonderful to be able to share with people we meet, people we know, particularly in difficult moments when they've lost a loved one, when everything seems to be lost—totally the contrary!</p>

<p>“What, then, will become of us after death?” asks Pope Francis. “With Jesus, beyond this threshold we will find eternal life, consisting in full communion with God as we forever contemplate and share in his infinite love.”</p>

<p>It's a great thing to look forward to. I knew a 19-year-old girl once in another country who, in her final exam after secondary school, got into Oxford; and not only that, but she got into law in Oxford. That was in December. In February, she developed leukemia. She died in July.</p>

<p>Both her parents were doctors. There came a moment when she was in the intensive care. She was on a heart monitor, intubated, on a drip, tubes everywhere, and the moment came for the doctors to tell the parents that the moment had come to turn off the respirator.</p>

<p>Her mother was prepared for this, but this child was the youngest of three, the favorite of the father, and he wasn't quite prepared for this. And so, there was a family conference called to try and help the father to come to the decision to turn off the respirator.</p>

<p>I was called in to sort of help them come to this decision, and there was a moment in our discussion when I said to the father, “What else does this world have to offer your daughter? ICUs, drips everywhere, heart monitors, respirators. This world has nothing else to offer your daughter. But what is waiting for her? Eternal happiness!”</p>

<p>I was very grateful to the Holy Spirit for that inspiration at that particular moment. I'd never quite thought about it in those terms before. Very practical.</p>

<p>This is a great thing we have to remind people of: the eternal happiness to which we are called. Death can be a moment of joy for us.</p>

<p>“With Jesus, beyond this threshold,” he said, “we will find eternal life, consisting in full communion with God as we forever contemplate and share in his infinite love. All that we now experience in hope, we shall then see in reality.”</p>

<p>I've seen many people die very holy deaths. While working in an oncology ward for six months, you see a lot of things, and to see people dying a very beautiful death is a very beautiful thing.</p>

<p>St. Joseph is the patron of a happy death. A happy and holy death is something that hopefully we can help many people around us to experience.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “When I am one with you in all my being, there will be no more pain and toil; my life shall be true life, a life wholly filled by you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>, Point X, 28).</p>

<p>Pope Francis asked the question, “What will characterize this fullness of communion? The answer is: being happy. Happiness is our human vocation. It’s a goal to which we all aspire.</p>

<p>“But what is happiness?” he asks. “What is the happiness that we await and desire? Not some fleeting pleasure, a momentary satisfaction, that, once experienced, keeps us longing for more, in a desperate quest that leaves our hearts unsated and increasingly empty.”</p>

<p>Sometimes when you look at the great soccer matches that are taking place, and the Euros that are going on at the moment, or the World Cup that comes around occasionally, if you look behind the goal at all the fans there waiting for that goal to happen, and the roar that comes when the goal takes place—it's a wonderful roar. It's a wonderful moment of exultation and happiness and glory.</p>

<p>The television cameras capture it so well. But it's also a fleeting pleasure. Unfortunately, it's over in a moment. But it's a very good thing to watch, because it's like an example of all the human pleasures that we may experience.</p>

<p>But the happiness to which we are called is not that fleeting roar of a gold in a World Cup or in a Euro or some other moment. It's something much deeper.</p>

<p>“We aspire to a happiness,” says Pope Francis, “that is definitively found in the one thing that can bring us fulfillment, which is love.”</p>

<p>We hope to love. We hope to engage and share that love with God because “God is love” (1 John 4:8,16).</p>

<p>“We will be able to say even now: I am loved, therefore I exist; and I will live forever in the love that does not disappoint, the love from which nothing can ever separate me.”</p>

<p>Those fans behind those [gold], they may never see a goal in a match. They may lose the match. Maybe it’s the end of their aspirations until, they hope, to the next round. But we can never be separated from that love.</p>

<p>Pope Francis says, “We should indeed prepare ourselves consciously and soberly for the moment when our lives will be judged.”</p>

<p>The whole of our life is a preparation. We need to take care of our spiritual life. Savor the value of every retreat, of every recollection, of every formation that we may receive, because it's all part of that preparation.</p>

<p>We have to be attentive. “Prepare ourselves consciously and soberly…” and try and invite all of our friends. Infect them with this desire to be prepared when we come to be judged.</p>

<p>“But we must always do this,” says Pope Francis, “from the standpoint of hope.”</p>

<p>We're not afraid of that judgment. We're not afraid of that moment. “The theological virtue that sustains our lives and shields them from groundless fear”—that's what our hope is.</p>

<p>If we look to the lives of saints, particularly recent saints that may speak to us a little more, we see this in their lives.</p>

<p>“The judgment of God, who is love,” St. John says in his Letter (<em>cf</em>. 1 John 4:8,16), will surely be based on love, and in particular on all that we have done or failed to do with regard to those in need, in whose midst Christ, the Judge himself, is present” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 25:31-46).</p>

<p>Every “I confess” in the Mass that we start with, we talked about those things we have done and the things we have failed to do. “Whenever you did it to one of these, the least of my brethren, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40). Christ is present there.</p>

<p>In Chapter 25 of St. Matthew we're told, “When the Son of man comes in his glory, escorted by all the angels, then he will take his seat on his throne of glory. All the nations will be assembled before him, and he will separate one from another, as a shepherd separates sheep from goats, and he will place the sheep on his right hand, and the goats on the left.</p>

<p>“Then the king will say to those in his right hand, ‘Come, you who my Father has blessed, take as your heritage the kingdom prepared for you since the foundation of the world. For when I was hungry, you gave me food, I was thirsty and you gave me drink, I was a stranger and you made me welcome’” (Matt. 25:31-35).</p>

<p>Pope Francis then goes on to talk about the Jubilee indulgence, which, “thanks to the power of prayer,” he says, “is intended in a particular way for those who have gone before us, so that they may obtain full mercy…the indulgence is a way of discovering the unlimited nature of God's mercy.</p>

<p>“Not by chance,” he says, “for the ancients, the terms ‘mercy’ and ‘indulgence’ were interchangeable, as expressions of the fullness of God's forgiveness, which knows no bounds.”</p>

<p>The Holy Father goes on to talk about—how did he talk about the sacrament of Penance? “It assures us that God wipes away our sins.</p>

<p>“We experience those powerful and comforting words of the Psalm: ‘It is he who forgives all your guilt, who heals every one of your ills, who redeems your life from the grave, who crowns you with love and compassion. The Lord is compassion and love, slow to anger and rich in mercy. … He does not treat us according to our sins, nor repay us according to our faults. For as the heavens are high above the earth, so strong is his love for those who fear him. As far as the east is from the west, so far does he remove our sins’” (Ps.103:3-4,8,10-12).</p>

<p>“The sacrament of Reconciliation,” he says, “is not only a magnificent spiritual gift, but also a decisive, essential, and fundamental step on our journey of faith.”</p>

<p>The Holy Father invites us to savor every opportunity for receiving the sacrament of Penance, of receiving the graces that flow, of savoring those short few minutes that are extended to us as a great magnificent spiritual gift on a weekly basis.</p>

<p>“There,” he says, “we allow the Lord to erase our sins, to heal our hearts, to raise us up, to embrace us, and to reveal to us his tender and compassionate countenance.</p>

<p>“There is no better way,” he says, “to know God than to let him reconcile us to himself,” as St. Paul says to the Corinthians (<em>cf</em>. 2 Cor. 5:20), “and to savor his forgiveness.</p>

<p>“Let us not neglect Confession, but rediscover the beauty of the sacrament of healing and joy, the beauty of God's forgiveness of our sins!”</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “We are the ambassadors for Christ. It is as though God were urging you through us. In the name of Christ, we appeal to you to be reconciled to God” (2 Cor. 5:20).</p>

<p>“Still, as we know from personal experience, every sin ‘leaves its mark,’” says Pope Francis. “Sin has consequences, not only outwardly in the effects of the wrong we do, but also inwardly, inasmuch as, ‘every sin, even venial, entails an unhealthy attachment to creatures, which must be purified either here on earth, or after death, in the state called Purgatory’” (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 1472).</p>

<p>And we could be reminded to offer difficult moments of our life, of our day, of our week, in atonement for the sins we have committed, or for the sins of men.</p>

<p>“Forgiveness does not change the past,” he says, “it cannot change what happened in the past, yet it can allow us to change the future and to live different lives, free of anger, animosity, and vindictiveness”—not just looking for those passing pleasures that may come.</p>

<p>“Forgiveness,” he says, “makes possible a brighter future, which enables us to look at the past with different eyes, now more serene, albeit still bearing the trace of past tears.”</p>

<p>The words of the Holy Father communicate great hope that can be there in our life.</p>

<p>“In our journey towards the Jubilee,” he says, “let us return to Scripture and realize that it speaks to us in these words.”</p>

<p>St. Paul to the Hebrews says, “May we who have taken refuge in him be strongly encouraged to seize the hope set before us. We have this hope, a sure and steadfast anchor of the soul”—anchor of the soul, beautiful words reappearing there, that word ‘anchor’—“a hope that enters the inner shrine behind the curtain, where Jesus, a forerunner on our behalf, has entered” (Heb. 6:18-20).</p>

<p>We have to stimulate that anchor. Every time we receive the sacraments—Holy Communion, Confession—we receive supernatural sacramental grace that transmits with it the virtue of the grace of hope, coming from the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>”[Those] words,” he says, “are a forceful encouragement for us never to lose the hope we have been given, to hold fast to that hope, and to find in God our refuge and our strength.”</p>

<p>“…so that [by two] unalterable factors in which God could not be lying, we who have fled to him might have a vigorous encouragement to grasp the hope held out to us” (Heb. 6:18).</p>

<p>This is the anchor of our soul. St. Paul says to the Hebrews, “The anchor our souls have reaching right through, inside the curtain where Jesus has entered as a forerunner on our behalf, having become a high priest forever of the order of Melchizedek” (Heb. 6:19-20).</p>

<p>“The image of the anchor is eloquent; it helps us to recognize the stability and security that is ours amid the troubled waters of this life, provided we entrust ourselves to the Lord Jesus. The storms that buffet us will never prevail, for we are firmly anchored in the hope born of grace, which enables us to live in Christ and to overcome sin, fear, and death.”</p>

<p>It’s very appropriate for us to drop anchor in our divine affiliation, to contemplate it frequently.</p>

<p>“This hope,” says Pope Francis, “which transcends life's fleeting pleasures and the achievement of our immediate goals, makes us rise above our trials and difficulties, and inspires us to keep pressing forward, never losing sight of the grandeur of the heavenly goal to which we have been called.”</p>

<p>“The coming Jubilee,” he says, “will thus be a Holy Year marked by the hope that does not fade, our hope in God.” The holy year will be, for us, a special holy year.</p>

<p>He says, “May it help us to rediscover the confident trust that we require, in the Church and in society, in our interpersonal relationships, in international relations, and in our task of promoting the dignity of all persons and respect for God's gift of creation.”</p>

<p>Notice how the whole social teaching of the Church is expressed in that word, ‘dignity.’ In the documents of the Church, it is repeated, again and again.</p>

<p>“May the witness of believers be for our world a leaven of authentic hope, a harbinger of “new heavens and a new earth” (<em>cf</em>. 2 Pet. 3:13), where men and women will dwell in justice and harmony, in joyful expectation of the fulfilment of the Lord's promises.”</p>

<p>“What are we waiting for,” says St. Peter, “relying on his promises, is the new heavens and the new earth, where uprightness will be at home” (<em>cf</em>. 2 Pet. 3:13).</p>

<p>“Let us even now be drawn to this hope. Through our witness, may hope spread to all those who anxiously seek it.”</p>

<p>Many souls around us come close to us. They are looking for hope. They are looking and seeking reasons for the hope that is in our life.</p>

<p>“Through our witness,” says Pope Francis, “may hope spread to all those who anxiously seek it. May the way we live our lives say to them in so many words: ‘Hope in the Lord! Hold firm, take heart, and hope in the Lord!’ say the Psalms (Ps. 27:14). May the power of hope fill our days, as we await with confidence the coming of the Lord Jesus Christ, to whom be praise and glory, now and forever.”</p>

<p>Pope Francis says, “It is not by chance that popular piety continues to invoke the Blessed Virgin Mary as <em>Stella Maris</em>–Star of the sea.”</p>

<p>Of that sea on which we are placed, where we drop anchor: <em>Stella Maris</em>–Star of the sea.</p>

<p>“It is a title that bespeaks the sure hope that, amid the tempest of this life, the Mother of God comes to our aid, sustains us and encourages us to persevere in hope and trust.”</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>CPG</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ash Wednesday</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ash Wednesday" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Book of Genesis, “The Lord God formed man from the dust of the earth, and he breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and man became a living being” (Gen. 2:7).</p>

<p>Genesis is very clear about the origin of man, where we have come from, where we're going.</p>

<p>Ash Wednesday is a day on which Our Mother the Church reminds us of where we have come from. How important in life it is to remember where we have come from, to remember our roots.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church reminds us that we are dust. “Remember, man, that you are dust, and to dust you shall return” (Gen. 3:19). I often think that whoever dreamed up the ceremony of the ashes was a bit of a genius, because it's so simple, yet it's so clear.</p>

<p>You take the palm branches of the previous Palm Sunday, you burn them, they become ash, which really is dirt. Somebody defined dirt once as “matter that is in the wrong place” (Mary Douglas, <em>Purity and Danger</em>). If clay is in the garden, it's clay; if it's in the house, it's dirt.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church comes along, and she blesses this dirt, as though reminding us that everything that God has created is good and can be made holy.</p>

<p>Then Our Mother the Church does a very curious thing: she takes this ash, and she smears it on our face. She dirties our face.</p>

<p>We spend most of our life trying to keep our faces clean. Our mothers and fathers probably have asked us ever since we were young: Did you wash your face? Did you wash behind your ears?</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church comes along one day each year and dirties our faces for us. As she does so, she says a very important message: “Remember, man...”, as though saying, remember, and don't ever forget it—who you are, where you come from. It's a message of humility.</p>

<p>Don't get any airs and graces because you're nothing—you're just dust. Every year the Church reminds us of that message, or gives us the opportunity to hear it, so that we never ever forget it—where we're going; where we've come from.</p>

<p>A man once remarked to me that our churches are full of small, sentimental, material things: holy water, Stations of the Cross, crucifixes, candles, incense.</p>

<p>Among those material things are the ashes. Often those material things can come to mean a lot to us.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul II liked to say that we go to the great spiritual messages through physical signs and symbols. Those physical signs and symbols come to be very important. Often little children—that's what they see, that's what they understand. They go to the spiritual through the material.</p>

<p>That's one of the reasons why we have to take very good care of these little, small, material things, because they can transmit wonderful spiritual messages, so that every child gets that message into his mind and heart and soul—that “you are dust”—knows where we're coming from, knows where we're going.</p>

<p>Often those material things speak volumes to millions of other people. Cardinal Dolan in New York has said how sometimes after the ceremony of the ashes, he stands on the steps of St. Patrick's Cathedral and offers ashes to any passersby.</p>

<p>He has said how it's interesting how many atheists, Hindus, Buddhists, Jews come to receive the ashes. Somehow it speaks to them about the origin of man and the meaning and purpose of our life.</p>

<p>Today, we're reminded on Ash Wednesday of the importance of dust.</p>

<p>A man in Singapore told me once how his father had died fifty years previous. He was buried in a center city cemetery which was going to be moved to the outskirts of the city because that had become very valuable land.</p>

<p>A family member was asked to come and be present at the exhumation of all the remains. He was there when his father's grave was dug.</p>

<p>He said after fifty years the only thing that was left was a little bit of the lid of the coffin. He remarked to me: ‘You know, this business of being dust, it's really true, you know.’</p>

<p>These are very deep lessons for us to learn. We might become the most important man in the world. We might become the most famous Super Bowl player in American history. We might become the Queen of England. We might be a Christian Dior.</p>

<p>But ultimately, we are just dust, and we will go back to being dust.</p>

<p>One time in the 1960s there was a very famous heavyweight boxing champion of the world: Muhammad Ali. He was very vocal. He liked to talk a lot about Allah.</p>

<p>One time he was in Sydney for a title fight. In a press conference, one of the journalists asked him: Look, now that you're the heavyweight champion of the world, why don't you give Allah a rest for a while? Why don't you talk about something else?</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali reached out and he got the journalist’s nostrils with one hand and his lips with the other, and held them tightly closed so that he couldn't breathe—rather an uncomfortable position to be in, to have your nostrils and your lips in the hands of the heavyweight champion of the world.</p>

<p>The guy was sort of gasping, turning blue in the face. Muhammad Ali said to him, ‘Would you like me to let go?’ And the guy nodded his head. Then he began to breathe.</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali said to him: ‘Can you feel the oxygen going down inside your lung?’ And the guy nodded his head. ‘Can you feel it being taken up by the whole of the globe?’ He said yes. ‘You feel it reaching the last cell of your little toe?’ Again, the guy nodded his head.</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali said: ‘God breathed into man the breath of life.’ In other words, every breath that we take, it's because God allows us to take that breath, and ‘I'll talk about Allah as much as I want.’</p>

<p>The simplicity of the ceremony of the ashes and its message is very profound. It speaks to the depth of man in all sorts of ways.</p>

<p>We have the forty days of Lent in front of us—a time that the Church uses to call us to conversion. We're told in Scripture, “Return to me with all your heart” (Joel 2:12).</p>

<p>The heart is very important in our faith. God reads the heart. The Church invites us in these days to look into our heart, to fashion our hearts after the heart of Christ.</p>

<p>When God looks into our hearts, is He happy with what He finds there? He tells us in Scripture that “out of the heart of man come all sorts of evil things” (Mark 7:21).</p>

<p>Our Mother invites us to change our heart during these days. Try and get out all the bad things that may be there, perhaps through a good Confession. Or through a greater acquisition of graces through the sacraments. Or a more frequent reception of Holy Communion. Or a more frequent confession, so that we can change our hearts.</p>

<p>“When you pray,” we're told in the Gospel of today, “go to your room, and shut the door, and pray to your Father who is in secret. And your Father who sees in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:6).</p>

<p>Prayer is a very personal thing. It's our own intimate relationship with Our Father God. It's a heart-to-heart relationship. That's what friendship is. Friendship with God and friendship with others involve the heart.</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us to take very good care of our hearts. Keep it in good shape; not to allow it to get sullied by anything. If it ever gets a bit messed up, we go back to the sacrament of Confession and we cleanse our hearts.</p>

<p>We say to Our Lord, “Create a clean heart in me” (Ps. 51:10). A new heart. “Take out my heart of stone and give me a heart of flesh” (<em>cf</em>. Ezek. 36:26).</p>

<p>Frequently, in the Responsorial Psalm during these days, we're going to read: “A humble and contrite heart, O Lord, you will not spurn” (Ps. 51:17). Part of the goal of our Christian life is to develop a humble and contrite heart.</p>

<p>Humble, because we're always aware of who we are and where we've come from—the reality of our own dust. We're nothing. We can do nothing. It's only in and through the grace of God that we can achieve anything.</p>

<p>Therefore, we look for that grace in the sacraments. We go closer to God with the hunger: Lord, let me know your face. We seek Him. Prophet Joel says, “Rend your heart and not your garments” (Joel 2:13).</p>

<p>Lent invites us to disconnect a little bit from the exterior things of our life and of this world, and look a little more into our interior. If I want the world to be a better place, then I have to be a better person—more virtuous, more humble, more charitable, more patient, more kind, more pure and chaste.</p>

<p>The Holy Spirit is always ready to transform our hearts, to lead us further in God's way of truth and holiness. This is the great force in our life: the Holy Spirit. We can ask Our Lord for the grace to use well this time of interior purification.</p>

<p>Sometimes, we think of Lent as a time of exterior purification, which is fine, which is also very true. We go very often to interior purification through exterior purification, through denying ourselves certain pleasures—trying to get up on time, eating a little bit less of what we like and a little more of what we don't like, not complaining, not criticizing, maybe not indulging in some pleasure or whim that we enjoy.</p>

<p>One time many years ago, I was having lunch with an 85-year-old Irish priest who was in a very faraway place. After lunch, we had coffee and I offered him the sugar for his coffee. He said, “No, thanks, I'm off it for Lent.”</p>

<p>I was rather edified. Here was this 85-year-old priest who was living Lent. I thought, before he was seven years of age his parents must have taught him very deeply about the meaning of Lent.</p>

<p>An awful lot of our spiritual preparation takes place before we're seven years of age. Try and introduce your children to these practices—very healthy spiritual practices—from an early age. Expose them to the ashes. You'll see they can come to love these things.</p>

<p>Or if you have an opportunity to get to Mass more frequently during Lent, that's a very good thing to offer to God—the effort to get up and make the time, and walk to where we have to go, and make the little efforts if it's raining, et cetera.</p>

<p>Or see if in your family you can make some visits to the poor or the sick, to bring some bit of joy into families that have a little less.</p>

<p>Or perhaps expose your children to the <em>Way of the Cross</em>, a wonderful devotion that we have in our Church, very appropriate for Lent, where we look at Christ on the Cross, follow Him along that journey, which has so many lessons for us.</p>

<p>Christ falls down, but He gets up again. In some ways, the story of our life is there.</p>

<p>He allows His heart to be pierced by a lance. He doesn't come down off the Cross. He stays there, so that we, when we get temptations to come down off the cross in our work, in our family, in our marriage, we also learn how to stay there.</p>

<p><em>The Way of the Cross</em> teaches us wonderful things, invites us to accept the blows that may come as a means to grow in virtue, in humility, in acceptance of the will of God; to develop our character in all sorts of ways; and to suspend all the bad interior things that may be there inside us—criticisms, judgments.</p>

<p>Sometimes we hear a lot about fasting and abstinence in Lent—the exterior fasting—on Ash Wednesday and Good Friday, but often, it's the interior things that we have to fast from a little more: from our criticisms, from our judgments, from our complaints, from our comparisons.</p>

<p>We're told in the Gospel about the Pharisee who said: “God, I thank you that I'm not like the rest of men, extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even like this tax collector” (Luke 18:11).</p>

<p>There's a bit of the Pharisee inside each one of us. It's easy for us to be a modern-day Pharisee, to say all sorts of things externally, but to be completely different on the inside.</p>

<p>That's why we have to purify the inside, to take care with our heart: “Rend your heart and not your garments” so that when God looks into our hearts and reads our hearts, He sees beautiful things there.</p>

<p>“In our life,” we're told by St. Josemaría in <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, “in the life of Christians, our first conversion—that unique moment which each of us remembers, when we clearly understood everything the Lord was asking of us—is certainly very significant.</p>

<p>“But the later conversions are even more important, and they are increasingly demanding. To facilitate the work of grace in these conversions, we need to keep our soul young; we have to call upon our Lord, know how to listen to him and, having found out what has gone wrong, know how to ask his pardon” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 57).</p>

<p>When Our Lord called Peter and Andrew, He said, “Come, follow me, and I will make you fishers of men” (Matt. 4:19). That was the beginning. But it wasn't the end. That was their first conversion.</p>

<p>Later, Our Lord was to say, “Feed my lambs...feed my sheep” (John 21:15-17). There were later and deeper conversions: conversions to a deeper responsibility; conversions from the spiritual to a deeper spirituality, from humility to a deeper humility; from faith to a greater faith.</p>

<p>All the time, Our Lord is leading us forward along the pathway of holiness, the pilgrimage of faith which our Christian vocation is. Lent can be a great stimulus. A lady told me once: I look forward to Lent and Advent. I hadn't heard that before; I was rather impressed.</p>

<p>But you see, Lent is a time of great spiritual bonanza. If you have a chance, try and follow the liturgy of Lent closely: the Responsorial Psalms, the Alleluia verse, the Entrance Antiphon.</p>

<p>Smaller parts of the liturgy, you'll find a great richness there, and a great beauty in the liturgy that will move your heart and whet your appetite for spiritual things, and help you to a much deeper approach to this whole period.</p>

<p>There are many aspirations that you may find in the words of the liturgy, and also in the words of Scripture that we read every day.</p>

<p>Incidentally, somebody told me that we Catholics have more exposure to Scripture than any other Christian denomination, because if we attend Mass regularly, especially on weekdays, we get the choicest parts of Scripture pre-selected for us in a regular way, so that our eyes fall on this great spiritual treasure which is Scripture.</p>

<p>We absorb these things in all these prayers of the liturgy. That's particularly true of Lent—to savor that richness and to thank God for it.</p>

<p>Possibly from those short prayers, you may get little aspirations that can help you in the rest of the day, like in the <em>Way of the Cross</em>, we say: “We adore you, O Christ, and we bless you, because by your holy cross you have redeemed the world.”</p>

<p>Many little phrases can come to us that can be very meaningful, can help us to supernaturalize our day, and sanctify it. Also, it can give us great peace and joy in leading us to prayer.</p>

<p>One thing we can try and focus on in this month is also the richness of Confession—of our own personal Confession—to get to Confession frequently, to be always in the state of grace, and to see how, if possible, we can reach out to others in the sacrament of Confession.</p>

<p>There was a student in Tokyo once who had heard about doing the apostolate of Confession. In Japan, this population is about 1 percent Christian or Catholic. This student was in the library of the university one time and was thinking, ‘If there are 100 people in this library, possibly one of them is Catholic.’</p>

<p>But then he thought, ‘The chances of bumping up against that Catholic are very rare, but I still have to try and do the apostolate of Confession.’ He leaned over to the student in front of him at the table and said: ‘Hey, how would you like to go to Confession?’</p>

<p>The person said: ‘What's that?’ And he said: ‘You go into this little box and it's all dark and there's a little grill there and you tell the priest all the bad things you have inside you. You get all of them out, you empty everything out, all the garbage, all the rubbish. And then you feel wonderful; you come out of there feeling as light as a feather.’</p>

<p>The guy said: ‘Oh, I think I'd like to try that.’ He began instruction, and three months later, he was baptized and went to Confession.</p>

<p>We never know where that apostolate of Confession is going to lead us in helping many other hearts and souls to grow, and to help the Blood of Christ to get in there and wash away the sins.</p>

<p>Sin is the ugliest reality on the planet. The only thing that we have to be afraid of is sin, because sin is the only thing that will keep us out of heaven.</p>

<p>All the things that the world may present to us as evils are not really evils—not having material things, losing our job, not having this or that, not having money, sickness or disease, or all the other things that can happen.</p>

<p>None of those things can keep us out of heaven—they may be the means to getting to heaven.</p>

<p>Our faith gives us an enormously positive outlook on the world, on creation, on our life. All the different moments of our life are opportunities for us to grow in the goals of our Christian formation—which are holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>We're told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “A spirit of mortification, rather than being just an outward show of Love, arises as one of its consequences. If you fail in one of these little proofs, acknowledge that your love for the Love is wavering” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 981).</p>

<p>The Church invites us to deny ourselves little things externally because of the effect that that has interiorly on our soul. We say “no” to the body in order to say “yes” to the soul.</p>

<p>Lent is all about our soul. Often if God permits some pain in our body, or some contradiction, or some reversal of fortune, it's because He wants our soul to fly. The spiritual realities can become enormously rich and enormously important. We can come to discover the greater reality of the spiritual.</p>

<p>I was passing through Dublin airport one morning at 8 o'clock and a man in a wheelchair beckoned to me to come over. He saw I was a priest and he wanted to talk to me, and initially, he asked me to get an attendant to help him to go to the washroom, which I did.</p>

<p>But then while we waited for the attendant, he said to me, ‘You know, today is a very difficult day for me; it's the fifth anniversary of the death of my eldest son in a motorbike accident.’</p>

<p>And my heart sank. Eight o'clock in the morning—I wasn't expecting this.</p>

<p>But he was a man going through a difficult moment, he sees a priest and wants a bit of a spiritual uplift. Then he explained how he was an accountant, he worked in London, but he had developed multiple sclerosis.</p>

<p>The last few years of his life he'd been confined to a wheelchair. His body had become limited at the very height of his career.</p>

<p>But, he said, ‘Suddenly all the spiritual things have come to mean an awful lot to me: I go to the sacraments more frequently, I get to receive the Anointing of the Sick.’ He says, ‘This gives me great joy and a great uplift.’</p>

<p>While we were waiting for the attendant to come, he was sort of giving me a whole catechesis on the sacraments; the effect of the sacraments in his life.</p>

<p>I was the one who benefited from that encounter. I learned so much, and forty years later I'm still talking about it.</p>

<p>There are souls all around us: souls who are looking for a spiritual uplift, souls that need to have their eyes open to the spiritual realities of the world, which are very rich, very beautiful.</p>

<p>Modern materialism, the culture in which we live, tends to tell us that man has no soul. Man is just a thing—that's why we can abort him or euthanize him. It doesn't matter; he's disposable.</p>

<p>But all the great religions of the world speak about the spiritual nature of man—Buddhism, Hinduism, Judaism, Islam, Christianity—it's one thing we all have in common: a belief in the spiritual nature of man.</p>

<p>“Have you noticed,” we're told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “that mortified souls, because of their simplicity, have a greater enjoyment of good things, even in this world?” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Pint 982).</p>

<p>When we deny our body certain pleasures, often it opens the eyes of our soul to deeper realities, to greater pleasures. Spiritual pleasures.</p>

<p>Sometimes as we move on in life, all the things that gave us pleasure earlier—playing sports, maybe, sweets, watching things on TV or movies or whatever—maybe, we find those pleasures pass. We get much greater joy from the spiritual things.</p>

<p>As the body begins to decay, the soul can grow and grow, discover a new youthfulness, a new joy.</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Furrow</em>, Point 983: “Without mortification there is no happiness on earth.”</p>

<p>“It's of great benefit,” says St. Paul, “that we all deny ourselves little pleasures. All things are pleasurable to me, but not all things are necessary or expedient” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:23).</p>

<p>Not all things are necessary. It's very good in every person's life that they deny themselves the fruit of a certain tree; certain pleasures that come from certain things.</p>

<p>We all need that salt of mortification. It strengthens our character, strengthens our soul, we grow in fortitude, we know how to say no to ourselves and sometimes to other people, so that we have a certain backbone.</p>

<p>“When you make up your mind to be more mortified,” we're told, “your interior life will improve and you will be much more fruitful” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 984).</p>

<p>The Church invites us to think of this period of Lent as training for the marathon. Any great Kenyan marathon runner has to run up and down mountains to strengthen their muscles and practice their breathing—all these sorts of things.</p>

<p>This is like a spiritual marathon. The Church gives us an opportunity every year to get into better shape spiritually and to help everybody around us to do the same thing.</p>

<p>“Let us not forget,” we're told by St. Josemaría, “that in all human activities there must be men and women who, in their lives and work, raise Christ's cross aloft for all to see, as an act of reparation.</p>

<p>“It is a symbol of peace and of joy, a symbol of the Redemption and of the unity of the human race. It is a symbol of the love that the Most Holy Trinity, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit had, and continues to have, for mankind” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 985).</p>

<p>The cross needs to be there in our life. When we go closer to the Mass, we go closer to the unbloody renewal of the sacrifice of Calvary, which can come to have great meaning for us.</p>

<p>Lent can be a time to be more focused on the Mass, make our attendance more frequent, and work at our Mass a little bit, so that it can truly become the summit and the source of our whole spiritual life, the center and the root.</p>

<p>From a deeper contemplation of Christ on the Cross, we come to understand better the workings of divine grace in our soul.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says that when the priest raises his hands to give the absolution and confession, the Blood of Christ is dripping from his hands. We're told in Scripture, “Without the shedding of blood, there is no remission of sin” (Heb. 9:22).</p>

<p>It's the Blood of Christ that washes away our sins. Blessed be His most Precious Blood. Lent is also a time when we can contemplate the Precious Blood of Christ. Thank God for shedding His Blood.</p>

<p>In that way, we prepare for the great feast of Easter, the most important feast in the whole of the liturgical year that is there for us to savor in a deeper way every year, in the beauty of its liturgy and the ceremonies, so that more and more, it comes to be a very important part of our life.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that we might never forget that we are dust, that we might savor days like today—Ash Wednesday—and help other people around us too, to come to appreciate the great spiritual richness of days like today.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>CPG</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>