<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-16T12:00:16+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Be You Perfect</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/be-you-perfect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be You Perfect" /><published>2026-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/be-you-perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/be-you-perfect/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Be you perfect, therefore, as also your heavenly Father is perfect” (Matt. 5:48).</p>

<p>By virtue of Baptism, the Christian carries supernatural, sanctifying grace in his soul. This is the seed, the root, of supernatural life. As every healthy seed carries within it the urge to grow and unfold, so also with the sanctifying grace within us.</p>

<p>Every baptized person comes under the law of impulse to growth and fulfillment. If a person was to try to escape this law and refuse to grow, he would necessarily wither and decline.</p>

<p>Every created life encounters disturbing forces that seek to hinder its development. And so too, there are many evil elements threatening the existence of supernatural life.</p>

<p>Anyone who is not earnestly concerned with fostering their supernatural life eventually succumbs to these disturbing forces. That’s why we must never hesitate but go on and on.</p>

<p>“The fundamental duty of every Christian is to press earnestly towards the goal of perfection, to become more perfect, moment by moment. Only in this way can we preserve our supernatural life and ensure its unfolding” (Benedict Baur, <em>In Silence With God</em>).</p>

<p>“Be perfect.” With inexpressible love the Lord has taken us up into His own life in the sacrament of Baptism, that we may “partake of his divine nature” (2 Pet. 1:4). Powerful phrase of St. Peter, that we would [be taken up into God’s own life].</p>

<p>In addition to the supernatural life principle of sanctifying grace, He has given us the three divine virtues—of faith, of hope, and of love—as well as feet to carry us to Him, arms with which to receive Him, and a plenitude of so-called moral virtues—like justice, prudence, strength, temperance—with which to circumvent the daily influence of earthly things, and in that way strengthen the gifts of the Holy Spirit, which in fact are supernatural prerequisites for a perfect, holy life.</p>

<p>Grafted to Christ, the vine (Rom. 11:17), in Baptism, we automatically become children of the Church (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 1213)—“ours, the holy, God-inspired writings of the Old and New Testament; ours, the sacraments; ours, the mystery of Christ in the blessed Eucharist as sacrifice and spiritual nourishment; ours, the rewards and virtues, the prayers and satisfactions of Christ in His holy, pure, God-loving soul in heaven and on earth” (<em>ibid</em>.)</p>

<p>In Baptism, God Himself—Father, Son, and Holy Spirit—lovingly takes residence in our soul, to be near to us, to draw us into His divine life, and secretly to copy and develop it in us.</p>

<p>It is not only possible, but imperative, for us to “become perfect, as our Father in heaven is perfect.”</p>

<p>Just as Baptism is the sacrament of rebirth, so Confirmation is the sacrament of fulfillment. As at Pentecost, the Holy Spirit descended upon the apostles, so He descends upon us Christians in confirmation, bringing us the strength to bear testimony for Christ.</p>

<p>How do we do that? Primarily by leading a life “dead unto the sins of the world” (Rom. 6:11), and then by allowing the intentions and virtues of Christ to light up in us, that we may become like another Christ, ready to make every sacrifice and put forth every effort to resist all things that might be contrary to our union with God.</p>

<p>In the sacrament of Confirmation, we receive the power and strength to attain maturity and perfection in Christian life. Confirmation urges us to take the first faltering steps toward Christian fulfillment: “Be you perfect.”</p>

<p>Ever anew, we are called to assist in the sacrifice of the Mass, that we may actively participate in the offering up of Christ, uniting ourselves with Him in the offering.</p>

<p>Whenever we receive Holy Communion worthily, or assist in the sacrifice with the priest, we renew the redemption Christ earned for us on the Cross. We join in His sacrifice, making His intentions and His objects our own.</p>

<p>When Our Lord, in Holy Communion, gives Himself for our soul’s nourishment, He fills us to the depths of our being with His spirit and His sacrificial power.</p>

<p>Then we become strong to cope with our daily tasks. All our efforts and strivings can be permeated with the Christ-like spirit of surrender to the glory of God.</p>

<p>In this way, the Christian can turn their entire day into one unbroken sacrifice of prayer, thanksgiving, praise, and expiation, by beginning it with Holy Communion, offering up everything that God’s will has imposed upon us to do, to endure, or to suffer.</p>

<p>Participation in Mass gives us the daily opportunity to enter more fully into Our Lord’s spirit of sacrifice, into His surrender to the Father, into His obedience unto death.</p>

<p>Every day it renews and intensifies our need to draw from Holy Communion the courage and strength to unite ourselves in an innermost spiritual wholeness with Christ, completely absorbed in His will, so that we may offer ourselves totally with Him and fulfill the command: “Be you perfect.”</p>

<p>In the first place, this means fulfilling God’s will. Who is it that submits to every demand for the honor of God; who surrenders themselves completely, without reserve, to the guidance and providence of God, than the person who is perfect?</p>

<p>One perfect soul glorifies God more than thousands of imperfect souls, because a single act of love on the part of a perfect soul is more pleasing to God than the sum total of all the incomplete acts of love offered by those who have not reached perfection.</p>

<p>But the perfect soul is constantly occupied in such acts of perfect love.</p>

<p>And so, if we wish truly and eagerly to worship Our Lord, our constant aim should be to rise above our shortcomings and reach perfection.</p>

<p>In the second place, “Be you perfect” means the well-being of our soul. The more we occupy ourselves with the attainment of perfection, the more surely we will guard ourselves against sin, against every sin, however unimportant it might seem.</p>

<p>The person who wrestles for perfection withstands the many opportunities and temptations that lead to evil. That person never loses sight of the ideal spurring him on, leaving him no peace. He has no time for half-measures.</p>

<p>“Be you perfect.” We need saints in these times. St. Josemaría and many people who came after him—Pope Benedict, Pope John Paul II—have talked about “these times are times for saints” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 301).</p>

<p>Sometimes we hear that conditions in the world today are hopeless, that we can’t go on. What can save the world today? Pope Francis has also emphasized that only the holiness of Christians can do so (<em>cf</em>. Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Gaudete et exsultate</em>, Point 6, March 19, 2018).</p>

<p>We need perfect Christians, perfect priests and nuns, perfect fathers and mothers, perfect students, officials, workers, and employers.</p>

<p>If anyone wishes to render a true service to the world, to the Church, to his country, to mankind, to himself, he must start with himself by subordinating everything to the pursuit and attainment of perfection.</p>

<p>There was a piece of news recently about a religious order in New York, I think called the Daughters of Charity (Sisters of Charity of New York), who have decided not to receive any more vocations and are sort of closing down. They feel they’ve reached the end of their mission after 150 years.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul II said this will happen to many religious orders. Many people who are there are elderly. But then in the next paragraph that announced this, they said that in the last 150 years, this religious order had started 160 schools, twenty-eight hospitals, a college of liberal arts, and quite a number of other things.</p>

<p>Sort of pause for a moment. Hundred and something schools, twenty-eight hospitals! One religious order did that over 150 years!</p>

<p>The history of some of these religious orders is truly incredible. What people have achieved with their lives!</p>

<p>And if you asked any one of those people involved in those organizations, I don’t think they’d tell you, ‘We were just here to build schools and to start hospitals.’</p>

<p>You’ll find this commitment to holiness and perfection was at the basis of all their endeavors. Over time, this yields this abundant fruit.</p>

<p>We have an awful lot to be proud of in our Church. It’s also important that we have a good knowledge of our history, and of the great things that people of the Catholic Church have achieved in society in the past hundreds of years, so that we see what <em>we</em> have to achieve in the 21st and 22nd centuries.</p>

<p>We might find ourselves surrounded today by a very unchristian world, a very worldly spirit in many places, in hearts, and in minds. We might think the world has never been in such a bad state.</p>

<p>But if you get to know a little bit more about history, you’ll find the opposite is the truth. The times we live in are no better or no worse than many other eras.</p>

<p>We might find the world is in a bit of a mess, in spite of all the effort on the part of ecclesiastical authorities or religious orders, or in spite of so many good books and writings, so many missions or congresses, or sermons, or Confessions, or Communions, or pilgrimages.</p>

<p>The build-up may be magnificent; the results might seem meager and impermanent. Over and over again, the Evil One arrives to sow his weeds, and “the weeds can choke the good seed” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 13:22).</p>

<p>But yet you look back after 150 years and you see a glowing treasure.</p>

<p>In truth there’s only one cure, one solution—the earnest striving for perfection, the full realization of living active Christian virtue—in a word, Christian holiness, and this has to have deep roots.</p>

<p>The soul of perfection is the inner life, turning from worldliness, breaking with every conscious sin and attachment to anything other than God, and to anything that can hinder our union with God.</p>

<p>We have to practice renunciation, and contrition, and atonement, taking care of our spiritual life, our prayer, our meditation, and working with the spirit of love so that we also put perfection into our work, because that’s the role of the ordinary layperson in the middle of the world: to sanctify the temporal realities, the world of work. That’s what our vocation in the middle of the world is all about.</p>

<p>That is why the present times demand of Christians a life of Christian perfection because this alone is what will change things.</p>

<p>When we love, we are perfect. “You shall love the Lord your God with your whole heart, and with your whole soul, and with your whole mind…and your neighbor as yourself” (Matt. 22:37,39).</p>

<p>Love is the highest expression, the ultimate term, of our capacity. In love, we gather up our whole being—our feelings, our will, our endeavor, our giving ourselves, with all that we possess and all that we are capable of—to the one that we love.</p>

<p>God is glorified by love more than by anything else. Love most completely fulfills His commandments.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew that on the commandments to love God and our neighbor “hang the whole law and the prophets” (Matt. 22:40).</p>

<p>All the commandments and duties refer to love. Love is the fulfillment of commandments and duties; without love, there is no fulfillment. It’s the soul of all the virtues; it is itself all virtues.</p>

<p>If love is lacking, all is lacking. “If I do not have love,” says St. Paul, “I have nothing, I am nothing” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 13:2). Where love is, there all things are, including all the other virtues.</p>

<p>These virtues grow as naturally out of love as out of their own roots: they serve love and smooth its path to such an extent that the loving soul easily and readily does everything that love demands.</p>

<p>We are just as perfect as the love that we bear. Bear to whom? To God and to our neighbor.</p>

<p>That is why God makes love the sign by which His disciples may be known. “By this will all men know that you are my disciples, if you have love for one another” (John 13:35).</p>

<p>In the same way, the Apostle measures our love for God by the love that we bear toward our neighbors. In the first Letter of St. John, he says, “For he that loves not his brother…how can he love God?” (1 John 4:20).</p>

<p>The love with which we love God and our brother in Christ is the same. Only the motive differs. We love God for His own sake; our brother, through the will of God and Christ.</p>

<p>The concept of perfection, which many people entertain, may be deceptive and destructive. Perfection does not consist of extraordinary penances or fasting or the greatest possible sacrifices.</p>

<p>Some might think that we’re perfect and they’re perfect when they are free from temptation and strife, when they can pray plentifully without any trouble, when they experience comfort and sweetness in prayer, when they are able to pray just as they wish to pray.</p>

<p>Or they might think that they’re perfect if they follow the rules and regulations to the letter. Mortifications, zeal in prayer, observance of rules are indispensable for spiritual perfection, but they’re not perfection in themselves.</p>

<p>There might be many among the mortified, among the ardent worshippers, many rule-abiding people, who might be unyielding in their judgment.</p>

<p>They might be proud and vain, obstinate and opinionated, fault-finding, lacking love in thought and speech, hypersensitive, jealous, easily put out, moody and uncontrolled. These can hardly be called perfect.</p>

<p>We are just as perfect as the love we bear, when love is within reach of all who are in a state of sanctifying grace, who keep God’s commandments, who commit no mortal sin.</p>

<p>And is such a one truly perfect? Not necessarily, because perfection demands more than this. It rules out not only all mortal sin but every conscious, venial sin.</p>

<p>It declares war on every fault of which it becomes aware. It tolerates no neglect, no half-measures, no easygoing indifference, no fault of character—even though it cannot prevent man here on earth from often falling victim to unconscious weaknesses and faults of human nature.</p>

<p>Perfection consists particularly of doing all that is good that is possible in given circumstances and situations—and not only what is commanded or cannot be omitted without sinning.</p>

<p>It extends beyond the sphere of duty. It does not ask, ‘Must I do this?’ ‘Is it a sin if I do it or don’t do it?’</p>

<p>And any good we have an opportunity to perform must be complete: outwardly perfect, performed in a proper and careful manner, leaving no room for the least reproach of negligence; inwardly perfect, springing from an intention of pure love, sincerely first for the sake of God’s will and Christ’s.</p>

<p>But we are really perfect only when it has become a habit, second nature, to regulate our thoughts and actions entirely with reference to God, His will, His honor and glory, yielding in all things to His good pleasure.</p>

<p>Perfection rests upon love, that is to say, on the complete fulfillment of the commandment: “You shall love the Lord your God…with your whole soul, and with your whole mind…and your neighbor as yourself” (Matt. 22:37,39).</p>

<p>Whoever loves anything more than God, whoever loves anything opposed to God, whoever loves in the same degree anything that is not God, fails to fulfill the commandment of love and consequently is not on the road to perfection.</p>

<p>If that person wishes to take the way of a perfect life, they must in some measure fulfill the law of love.</p>

<p>Christians have a wide field of endeavor in seeking perfection, because perfection, like love, has unlimited forms.</p>

<p>We can talk about two kinds of Christian perfection: essential perfection and perfection in a narrower and more particular sense.</p>

<p>Essential perfection may be described as perfection in a wider sense—that perfection without which no one can attain the goal of Christian life: eternal life in God.</p>

<p>This requires not only the fulfillment of the commandments but, over and above that, doing everything that is necessary to remain in a state of grace.</p>

<p>If a Christian were only to do or leave undone that which he is strictly commanded by the law to do or not to do, he would still not fulfill Christ’s command, “Be you perfect.”</p>

<p>If such a person were to practice brotherly love only when it was indicated by strict duty, where it could not be withheld without sin, they would have fulfilled the law of brotherly love in only the minimum of cases.</p>

<p>A person who never goes beyond the strict letter of the law is still a long way from essential perfection.</p>

<p>Perfection in the particular and narrower sense goes far beyond essential perfection. It not only fulfills the law but seeks to carry out every recommendation, every good act suggested by God and Christ.</p>

<p>Passing beyond what is strictly commanded or forbidden, this species of perfection consists of a positive eagerness to excel in the more difficult tasks, renunciations, and sacrifices.</p>

<p>Wherever the soul may most heroically prove its love, those striving for higher perfection are to be found, performing their tasks carefully, punctually, with complete devotion, self-surrender, and endurance.</p>

<p>We’re told that Our Lady went “with haste into the hill country” (Luke 1:39). She went quickly, with enthusiasm, with initiative, with daring, with the fortitude to face the challenges, to perform that corporal act of mercy with her cousin Elizabeth; and, with great fortitude, did not tell Joseph where she was going, placing her vocation first.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that we might follow in her example to lead a life of striving for that perfection that we see in her who is the model of all the virtues.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MVF</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Words Will Not Pass Away</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/my-words-will-not-pass-away/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Words Will Not Pass Away" /><published>2026-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-16T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/my-words-will-not-pass-away</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/my-words-will-not-pass-away/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will not pass away” (Luke 21:33), we’re told by Our Lord in St. Luke.</p>

<p>What Jesus has said in His preaching, in His conversations, will literally last forever. God has directed those words to every man, every woman, every child who will walk the face of the earth.</p>

<p>We’re told by St. Paul in his <em>Letter to the Hebrews</em>, “In many and various ways, God spoke of old to our fathers by the prophets, but in these last days he has spoken to us by a Son…” (Heb. 1:1-2).</p>

<p>Just as He spoke to our forefathers in the faith, Our Lord speaks to us in our day. Because His message is divine, it can’t be limited by human constraints of time and place.</p>

<p>Sacred Scripture acquires the fullness of its meaning in the figure and preaching of Christ. St. Augustine has commented, “The law was pregnant with Christ” (Augustine, <em>Sermon 196</em>).</p>

<p>On another occasion, he said: “To read the books of the prophets without seeing the coming of Christ is a most insipid practice. Seek therefore to find Christ in these words and they will prove not only delightful but stimulating” (Augustine, <em>Commentary on St. John’s Gospel</em>).</p>

<p>Christ will also enlighten our minds about the riches within Scripture. We’re told in St. Luke: “Then he opened their minds to understand the Scriptures” (Luke 24:45).</p>

<p>The Jews who refused to believe in the Gospel were left with a chest full of treasure, but without the key to unlock it. St. Paul explained [this situation] to the first Christians at Corinth. He said, “But their minds were hardened. For to this day, when they read the old covenant, that same veil remains unlifted, because only through Christ is it taken away” (2 Cor. 3:14).</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council says, “The economy of the Old Testament was deliberately so orientated that it should prepare for and declare in prophecy the coming of Christ, redeemer of all men, and of the messianic kingdom. … God, the inspirer and author of the books of [both] Testaments, in his wisdom has so brought it about that the New should be hidden in the Old and that the Old should be made manifest in the New” (Vatican II, <em>Dei verbum</em>, Points 15,16).</p>

<p>In this context, it can be inspiring to read the dialogue between Philip the Apostle and the Ethiopian official from the court of Queen Candace. The Ethiopian was sitting in his chariot reading the Prophet Isaiah. Philip ran up to the man and asked him, “Do you understand what you are reading?” The Ethiopian replied, “How can I, unless someone guides me?”</p>

<p>Philip took a seat in the chariot and “beginning with this Scripture he told him the good news of Jesus” (<em>cf</em>. Acts 8:27-35). He explained the writings of Isaiah by means of the message of Jesus. His catechesis was wonderfully straightforward. Jesus was the key concept.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom has commented on this passage from the <em>Acts of the Apostles</em>: “Let us meditate on the importance of our reading the Scriptures with devotion, even during our travels. … Some people excuse themselves from this practice because they’re busy with their family affairs, or because they have military drills, or because they have some worry or other. They think that such matters preclude any serious effort to read and meditate upon Sacred Scripture. …</p>

<p>“This Ethiopian official is an example for all of us: those who have a quiet life, those who belong to the army, those who are officials, those who have chosen a monastic life, those who care for their families at home.</p>

<p>“Let everyone learn,” he says, “that no circumstance should be an impediment for our divine reading. We can do this at home or in the town square or in the public park, or on a trip, or in the company of others, or right in the middle of our work. I beseech you, do not be careless with your reading of the Scriptures” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homilies on Genesis</em>).</p>

<p>From her earliest days, the Church has recommended that the faithful read and meditate on the texts of Sacred Scripture, particularly on the books of the New Testament. There we will find Christ coming out to meet us. Through a few moments each day, we can become best friends with Jesus. Truly, love depends on our prior knowledge.</p>

<p>The books of the Old Testament outlined in advance the path which Christ marked out on His earthly journey (<em>cf</em>. Luke 22:37). Scripture was, in a certain sense, a grand announcement of the Messiah.</p>

<p>The Prophets foretold the day of His coming and they ardently desired to see it (<em>cf</em>. Luke 10:24). The disciples recognized in Christ the fulfillment of all the prophecies (<em>cf</em>. John 1:41-45).</p>

<p>When St. Paul had to defend himself before King Agrippa, he simply stated, “So I stand here testifying both to small and great, saying nothing but what the prophets and Moses said would come to pass” (Acts 26:22).</p>

<p>Christ was not bound by the patriarchs and prophets. It was God who inspired them to describe the characteristics of the Son of God. As Jesus said to the leaders of Israel: “If you believed Moses, you would believe me, for he wrote of me” (John 5:46).</p>

<p>Later on He said to them, “Your father Abraham rejoiced that he was to see my day. He saw it and was glad” (John 8:56).</p>

<p>Our Lord took upon Himself the types and figures of the Old Testament: the temple (John 2:19), manna (<em>cf</em>. John 6:32), the rock (<em>cf</em>. Matt 16:18), the serpent raised up in the wilderness (<em>cf</em>. John 3:14). His biblical references are unmistakable.</p>

<p>This perhaps explains Our Lord’s frustration with the scribes and the Pharisees. He said to them in St. John, “You search the Scriptures because you think that in them you have eternal life; and it is they that bear witness to me” (John 5:39).</p>

<p>We read in the Gospel that the heavens and the earth will pass away, but that God’s word will last forever (Luke 21:33). God’s Revelation to man is fulfilled in the person of Christ.</p>

<p>“But now that the faith is founded on Christ, and in this era of grace, the law of the Gospel has been made manifest, there is no reason to inquire of him in that manner, nor for him to speak or to answer as he did then. For, in giving us, as he did, his Son,” says St. John of the Cross, “he has said everything to us together, once and for all, in this single Word, and he has no occasion to speak further” (John of the Cross, <em>Ascent of Mount Carmel, II</em>).</p>

<p>St. Paul in his <em>Letter to the Hebrews</em> says, “For the word of God is living and active, sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing to the division of soul and spirit, of joints and marrow, and discerning the thoughts and intentions of the heart” (Heb. 4:12). This word is directed to every person who receives it with faith.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council has said, “In the sacred books the Father who is in heaven comes lovingly to meet his children and talks with them. And such is the force and power of the Word of God that it can serve the Church as her support and vigor, and the children of the Church as strength for their faith, food for the soul, and a pure and lasting fount of spiritual life” (Vatican II, <em>Dei verbum</em>, Point 21).</p>

<p>The teachings of Jesus are always ‘up to date.’ We’re often amazed at the relevancy of the saga of the Prodigal Son (Luke 15:11-32), of the importance in every age of the leaven to transform the dough (Matt. 13:33), of the reactions of the people cured by Our Lord. Many times we have joined Bartimaeus in asking Jesus for His light: “<em>Domine, ut videam!</em>–Lord, that I may see!” (Luke 18:41). We’ve also used that plea of the publican: “My God, have mercy on me, a sinner!” (Luke 18:13).</p>

<p>Our daily reading of the Gospel can be a source of strength and comfort. The Psalms say, “How sweet are your words to my taste, sweeter than honey to my mouth!” (Ps. 119:103).</p>

<p>When we first heard the idea coming from St. Josemaría that we should try to read the Gospel for two or three minutes every day, we might have had the thought, ‘Can anything good come from doing something for just two or three minutes each day?’ But you may find that fifty years later, you’re still reading the Gospel for two or three minutes each day. That habit has led you to have a great knowledge of the person of Jesus and of the doctrine that He imparts.</p>

<p>Ronald Knox encouraged people to meditate on Our Lord’s passion. He gave an analogy from parish life. He said, “When you have a lot of people singing without any organ accompaniment, there’s a constant tendency for the note to drop all the time. It gets lower and lower as it goes on. Therefore, where the choir isn’t accustomed to singing without accompaniment, every now and then the choirmaster, who has a pitch pipe concealed in his person, gives a little toot in the background to remind them of the higher note which they ought to be taking, and are not.</p>

<p>“You see, we are rather like that. We go on living from day to day without thinking much about how we are living or what we are here for, or whether the things that chiefly interest us are really worth living for; and we can get accustomed to our sins, and feel vaguely that it is a pity we go on committing them, but after all, there doesn’t seem to be much chance of our stopping; and our prayers get very languid and washed out, and we think of very little except our food and our amusements.</p>

<p>“All the time, the note on which our lives are lived is dropping, dropping, till it is ready to die away into our boots, and we don’t notice, just as the choir doesn’t notice, when the note drops. We want that sudden little toot of the pitch pipe to pull us together and screw the note of our lives up again. The pitch pipe we use…is meditation on Our Lord’s Passion” (Ronald A. Knox, A Retreat for Lay People).</p>

<p>We should never turn the pages of the Gospel as if it were just another old book. With what love did our forefathers in the faith care for the Word of God! They went to great lengths to pass it on from generation to generation in all of its integrity.</p>

<p>St. Cyprian has written that the reading of Scripture is like the foundation for the building up of our hope. “It is the means,” he said, “to consolidate our faith, the food for our charity, and our unerring guide on the way of life” (<em>cf</em>. Cyprian, <em>Treatise on Prayer</em>).</p>

<p>St. Augustine compares the teachings of Scripture to “lights shining forth out of the darkness” (Augustine, <em>Commentary on the Psalms</em>). We can find no better beacon for our journey to the Father.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “When you open the Holy Gospel, think that what is written there—the words and deeds of Christ—is something that you should not only know, but live. Everything, every point that is told there, has been gathered, detail by detail, for you to make it come alive in the individual circumstances of your life.</p>

<p>“God has called us Catholics to follow him closely. In that holy Writing you will find the Life of Jesus, but you should also find your own life there.</p>

<p>“You too, like the Apostle, will learn to ask, full of love, ‘Lord, what would you have me do?...’ And in your soul you will hear the conclusive answer, ‘The Will of God!’</p>

<p>“Take up the Gospel every day, then, and read it and live it as a definite rule. This is what the saints have done” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 754).</p>

<p>This is how we can draw abundant fruit from Sacred Scripture. We will unite our prayer with the words of the Psalmist: “Your word, Lord, is a lamp to my feet and a light to my path” (Ps. 119:105).</p>

<p>There’s a story in the Old Testament that narrates the return of the Chosen People to Israel after many years in exile in Babylon. Once they reached Jewish soil, the priest Ezra explains to the people the content of the Law that they had forgotten during the years spent “in a foreign land.” He read from the sacred book, we’re told, “from early morning until midday.” His audience stood and followed the teaching attentively, and “all the people wept” (Neh. 8:2-6;8-10).</p>

<p>Their response is a lament compounded with joy as they hear God’s Law once more, and with grief also, because their previous neglect of the Law had brought about their exile.</p>

<p>When we gather to take part in the Mass, we stand, in an attitude of respect, to hear the Good News that the Gospel always brings us. We have to try to listen to it with a disposition which is attentive, humble, and grateful, because we know that God is speaking to each one of us.</p>

<p>“We should hear the Gospel,” says St. Augustine, “as if Our Lord were present and speaking to us. We must not say, ‘Happy were those who could see him,’ for many of those who saw him crucified him; and many of those who have not seen him have believed in him. The very words that came from Our Lord’s lips were written down and kept and preserved for us” (Augustine, <em>Commentary on St. John’s Gospel</em>).</p>

<p>We can only love someone we know. In order to know Christ, many Christians dedicate some minutes each day to reading and meditating on the Gospels. This practice leads us by the hand to the knowledge and contemplation of Jesus Christ. It teaches us to see Him as the Apostles saw Him, to observe His reactions, to watch the way He behaved, and to listen to His words, which were always filled with wisdom and authority.</p>

<p>The Gospels show Him to us on some occasions moved with compassion at the plight of people in misery. At other times, they show Him full of understanding for sinners, or firm with the Pharisees who were presenting a false image of their religion. He is full of patience with those disciples who often do not grasp the meaning of His words.</p>

<p>It would be very difficult to love Jesus, to get to know Him really well, if we did not frequently hear the Word of God, if we did not attentively read part of the Gospel each day. That reading, perhaps only lasting a few minutes, nourishes and increases our piety.</p>

<p>At the end of each Reading of Sacred Scripture, the priest says, “This is the Gospel of the Lord,” and the faithful reply, “Praise to you, Lord Jesus Christ” (<em>Roman Missal</em>).</p>

<p>How do we praise Him? Our Lord is not satisfied with bare words. ‘Show me,’ He says. He wants to be praised with deeds.</p>

<p>We can’t run the risk of forgetting God’s law, of allowing the teaching of the Church to remain in us as little more than truths which are diffuse and inoperative, or of which we have a merely superficial knowledge. For us, this would mean an exile far more devastating than that of Babylon.</p>

<p>God’s greatest enemy in the world is ignorance, “the cause, and as it were,” said Pope John XXIII, “the root of all the evils that poison entire nations and perturb many souls” (John XXIII, Encyclical, <em>Ad Petri cathedram</em>, Point 6, June 29, 1959).</p>

<p>We know well that one great evil that afflicts so many Christians is the lack of doctrinal formation. But what is graver still is that many people are turned astray by error, a sickness even more serious than ignorance.</p>

<p>What a pity if we, because we lack the necessary doctrine, can’t show Christ to them and give them the light they need in order to understand His teaching.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the Gospel of St. Luke, he tells us that he resolved to write down the life of Christ so that we may know the truth of the teachings we have received (Luke 1:1-14).</p>

<p>Each of us, according to the unique circumstances of our life, has the obligation to know Christ’s doctrine in depth. That obligation lasts for as long as our path here on earth shall continue.</p>

<p>“The growth of the faith and the Christian life,” said one writer, “even more in the adverse context with which we are living, needs from us a positive effort and the continuous exercise of our personal freedom. This effort begins when we have come to see our faith as the most important thing in our lives. From this consideration is born an interest in knowing and practicing all that is contained in our faith in God. This leads us to want to follow Christ throughout the complex and changing context of the reality of daily life” (Spanish Episcopal Conference, <em>Witnesses to the Living God</em>, June 28, 1985).</p>

<p>We should never allow ourselves to think that we have sufficient formation. We should never be satisfied with the amount of knowledge about Jesus Christ and His teaching that we have so far acquired.</p>

<p>Love always seeks to know the beloved better. In professional life, doctors or architects or lawyers or whoever, so that they may be good at their profession, never think that they finished studying once they have qualified; they go on learning—always.</p>

<p>And so it is with the Christian. We can apply St. Augustine’s maxim to doctrinal formation: “Did you say, ‘enough’? You have perished” (Augustine, <em>Sermon 169</em>).</p>

<p>The quality of the instrument—because that’s what we all are, instruments in God’s hands—can improve. It can develop new possibilities. Each day we can love a little more and give better example. But we will not achieve this if our understanding is not continually nourished by sound doctrine.</p>

<p>Frank Sheed in his writing said, “I cannot say how often I have been told all sorts of stories about all sorts of people, but I see that the knowledge of God is the most important thing” (<em>cf</em>. Frank J. Sheed, <em>Theology for Beginners</em>).</p>

<p>The so-called ‘plain man’s faith” (‘I believe it all even though I don’t know what it is’) is not sufficient for a Christian in the world who is confronted each day by confusion and a lack of light regarding Christ’s doctrine—the only doctrine that saves—and is daily encountering ethical problems, both new and old, at work, in his family life, and in the environment in which he lives.</p>

<p>A Christian needs to have the answers which enable him to counter the attacks of the enemies of the faith, and to know how to present them in an attractive way.</p>

<p>It takes time and persistence to acquire good formation. Continuity helps us to understand and to incorporate, to make our own, the doctrine that is presented to our understanding. If we are to achieve this, we have first of all to ensure that the right channels are open for sound doctrine to be transmitted and received.</p>

<p>We have to pay attention to our own formation, convinced of the transcendental importance of what we are about. We must make sure that our <em>spiritual reading</em> is in accordance with a well-directed plan. In this way, knowledge builds up gradually in our soul.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord that we might have a greater awareness of the fact that His words will not pass away, that they are like seeds in our mind and heart and soul that have to yield an abundant fruit.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that we might take very good care each day of acquainting ourselves with those words which can always have an ever-new fragrance and freshness for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ash Wednesday</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ash Wednesday" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/ash-wednesday/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Book of Genesis, “The Lord God formed man from the dust of the earth, and he breathed into his nostrils the breath of life, and man became a living being” (Gen. 2:7).</p>

<p>Genesis is very clear about the origin of man, where we have come from, where we’re going.</p>

<p>Ash Wednesday is a day on which Our Mother the Church reminds us of where we have come from. How important in life it is to remember where we have come from, to remember our roots.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church reminds us that we are dust. “Remember, man, that you are dust, and to dust you shall return” (Gen. 3:19). I often think that whoever dreamed up the ceremony of the ashes was a bit of a genius, because it’s so simple, yet it’s so clear.</p>

<p>You take the palm branches of the previous Palm Sunday, you burn them, they become ash, which really is dirt. Somebody defined dirt once as “matter that is in the wrong place” (Mary Douglas, <em>Purity and Danger</em>). If clay is in the garden, it’s clay; if it’s in the house, it’s dirt.</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church comes along, and she blesses this dirt, as though reminding us that everything that God has created is good and can be made holy.</p>

<p>Then Our Mother the Church does a very curious thing: she takes this ash, and she smears it on our face. She dirties our face.</p>

<p>We spend most of our life trying to keep our faces clean. Our mothers and fathers probably have asked us ever since we were young: Did you wash your face? Did you wash behind your ears?</p>

<p>Our Mother the Church comes along one day each year and dirties our faces for us. As she does so, she says a very important message: “Remember, man...”, as though saying, remember, and don’t ever forget it—who you are, where you come from. It’s a message of humility.</p>

<p>Don’t get any airs and graces because you’re nothing—you’re just dust. Every year the Church reminds us of that message, or gives us the opportunity to hear it, so that we never ever forget it—where we’re going; where we’ve come from.</p>

<p>A man once remarked to me that our churches are full of small, sentimental, material things: holy water, Stations of the Cross, crucifixes, candles, incense.</p>

<p>Among those material things are the ashes. Often those material things can come to mean a lot to us.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul II liked to say that we go to the great spiritual messages through physical signs and symbols. Those physical signs and symbols come to be very important. Often little children—that’s what they see, that’s what they understand. They go to the spiritual through the material.</p>

<p>That’s one of the reasons why we have to take very good care of these little, small, material things, because they can transmit wonderful spiritual messages, so that every child gets that message into his mind and heart and soul—that “you are dust”—knows where we’re coming from, knows where we’re going.</p>

<p>Often those material things speak volumes to millions of other people. Cardinal Dolan in New York has said how sometimes after the ceremony of the ashes, he stands on the steps of St. Patrick’s Cathedral and offers ashes to any passersby.</p>

<p>He has said how it’s interesting how many atheists, Hindus, Buddhists, Jews come to receive the ashes. Somehow it speaks to them about the origin of man and the meaning and purpose of our life.</p>

<p>Today, we’re reminded on Ash Wednesday of the importance of dust.</p>

<p>A man in Singapore told me once how his father had died fifty years previous. He was buried in a center city cemetery which was going to be moved to the outskirts of the city because that had become very valuable land.</p>

<p>A family member was asked to come and be present at the exhumation of all the remains. He was there when his father’s grave was dug.</p>

<p>He said after fifty years the only thing that was left was a little bit of the lid of the coffin. He remarked to me: ‘You know, this business of being dust, it’s really true, you know.’</p>

<p>These are very deep lessons for us to learn. We might become the most important man in the world. We might become the most famous Super Bowl player in American history. We might become the Queen of England. We might be a Christian Dior.</p>

<p>But ultimately, we are just dust, and we will go back to being dust.</p>

<p>One time in the 1960s there was a very famous heavyweight boxing champion of the world: Muhammad Ali. He was very vocal. He liked to talk a lot about Allah.</p>

<p>One time he was in Sydney for a title fight. In a press conference, one of the journalists asked him: Look, now that you’re the heavyweight champion of the world, why don’t you give Allah a rest for a while? Why don’t you talk about something else?</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali reached out and he got the journalist’s nostrils with one hand and his lips with the other, and held them tightly closed so that he couldn’t breathe—rather an uncomfortable position to be in, to have your nostrils and your lips in the hands of the heavyweight champion of the world.</p>

<p>The guy was sort of gasping, turning blue in the face. Muhammad Ali said to him, ‘Would you like me to let go?’ And the guy nodded his head. Then he began to breathe.</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali said to him: ‘Can you feel the oxygen going down inside your lung?’ And the guy nodded his head. ‘Can you feel it being taken up by the whole of the globe?’ He said yes. ‘You feel it reaching the last cell of your little toe?’ Again, the guy nodded his head.</p>

<p>Muhammad Ali said: ‘God breathed into man the breath of life.’ In other words, every breath that we take, it’s because God allows us to take that breath, and ‘I’ll talk about Allah as much as I want.’</p>

<p>The simplicity of the ceremony of the ashes and its message is very profound. It speaks to the depth of man in all sorts of ways.</p>

<p>We have the forty days of Lent in front of us—a time that the Church uses to call us to conversion. We’re told in Scripture, “Return to me with all your heart” (Joel 2:12).</p>

<p>The heart is very important in our faith. God reads the heart. The Church invites us in these days to look into our heart, to fashion our hearts after the heart of Christ.</p>

<p>When God looks into our hearts, is He happy with what He finds there? He tells us in Scripture that “out of the heart of man come all sorts of evil things” (Mark 7:21).</p>

<p>Our Mother invites us to change our heart during these days. Try and get out all the bad things that may be there, perhaps through a good Confession. Or through a greater acquisition of graces through the sacraments. Or a more frequent reception of Holy Communion. Or a more frequent Confession, so that we can change our hearts.</p>

<p>“When you pray,” we’re told in the Gospel of today, “go to your room, and shut the door, and pray to your Father who is in secret. And your Father who sees in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:6).</p>

<p>Prayer is a very personal thing. It’s our own intimate relationship with Our Father God. It’s a heart-to-heart relationship. That’s what friendship is. Friendship with God and friendship with others involve the heart.</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us to take very good care of our hearts. Keep it in good shape; not to allow it to get sullied by anything. If it ever gets a bit messed up, we go back to the sacrament of Confession and we cleanse our hearts.</p>

<p>We say to Our Lord, “Create a clean heart in me” (Ps. 51:10). A new heart. “Take out my heart of stone and give me a heart of flesh” (<em>cf</em>. Ezek. 36:26).</p>

<p>Frequently, in the Responsorial Psalm during these days, we’re going to read: “A humble and contrite heart, O Lord, you will not spurn” (Ps. 51:17). Part of the goal of our Christian life is to develop a humble and contrite heart.</p>

<p>Humble, because we’re always aware of who we are and where we’ve come from—the reality of our own dust. We’re nothing. We can do nothing. It’s only in and through the grace of God that we can achieve anything.</p>

<p>Therefore, we look for that grace in the sacraments. We go closer to God with the hunger: Lord, let me know your face. We seek Him. Prophet Joel says, “Rend your heart and not your garments” (Joel 2:13).</p>

<p>Lent invites us to disconnect a little bit from the exterior things of our life and of this world, and look a little more into our interior. If I want the world to be a better place, then I have to be a better person—more virtuous, more humble, more charitable, more patient, more kind, more pure and chaste.</p>

<p>The Holy Spirit is always ready to transform our hearts, to lead us further in God’s way of truth and holiness. This is the great force in our life: the Holy Spirit. We can ask Our Lord for the grace to use well this time of interior purification.</p>

<p>Sometimes, we think of Lent as a time of exterior purification, which is fine, which is also very true. We go very often to interior purification through exterior purification, through denying ourselves certain pleasures—trying to get up on time, eating a little bit less of what we like and a little more of what we don’t like, not complaining, not criticizing, maybe not indulging in some pleasure or whim that we enjoy.</p>

<p>One time many years ago, I was having lunch with an 85-year-old Irish priest who was in a very faraway place. After lunch, we had coffee and I offered him the sugar for his coffee. He said, “No, thanks, I’m off it for Lent.”</p>

<p>I was rather edified. Here was this 85-year-old priest who was living Lent. I thought, before he was seven years of age his parents must have taught him very deeply about the meaning of Lent.</p>

<p>An awful lot of our spiritual preparation takes place before we’re seven years of age. Try and introduce your children to these practices—very healthy spiritual practices—from an early age. Expose them to the ashes. You’ll see they can come to love these things.</p>

<p>Or if you have an opportunity to get to Mass more frequently during Lent, that’s a very good thing to offer to God—the effort to get up and make the time, and walk to where we have to go, and make the little efforts if it’s raining, et cetera.</p>

<p>Or see if in your family you can make some visits to the poor or the sick, to bring some bit of joy into families that have a little less.</p>

<p>Or perhaps expose your children to the <em>Way of the Cross</em>, a wonderful devotion that we have in our Church, very appropriate for Lent, where we look at Christ on the Cross, follow Him along that journey, which has so many lessons for us.</p>

<p>Christ falls down, but He gets up again. In some ways, the story of our life is there.</p>

<p>He allows His heart to be pierced by a lance. He doesn’t come down off the Cross. He stays there, so that we, when we get temptations to come down off the cross in our work, in our family, in our marriage, we also learn how to stay there.</p>

<p><em>The Way of the Cross</em> teaches us wonderful things, invites us to accept the blows that may come as a means to grow in virtue, in humility, in acceptance of the will of God; to develop our character in all sorts of ways; and to suspend all the bad interior things that may be there inside us—criticisms, judgments.</p>

<p>Sometimes we hear a lot about fasting and abstinence in Lent—the exterior fasting—on Ash Wednesday and Good Friday, but often, it’s the interior things that we have to fast from a little more: from our criticisms, from our judgments, from our complaints, from our comparisons.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Gospel about the Pharisee who said: “God, I thank you that I’m not like the rest of men, extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even like this tax collector” (Luke 18:11).</p>

<p>There’s a bit of the Pharisee inside each one of us. It’s easy for us to be a modern-day Pharisee, to say all sorts of things externally, but to be completely different on the inside.</p>

<p>That’s why we have to purify the inside, to take care with our heart: “Rend your heart and not your garments” so that when God looks into our hearts and reads our hearts, He sees beautiful things there.</p>

<p>“In our life,” we’re told by St. Josemaría in <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, “in the life of Christians, our first conversion—that unique moment which each of us remembers, when we clearly understood everything the Lord was asking of us—is certainly very significant.</p>

<p>“But the later conversions are even more important, and they are increasingly demanding. To facilitate the work of grace in these conversions, we need to keep our soul young; we have to call upon our Lord, know how to listen to him and, having found out what has gone wrong, know how to ask his pardon” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 57).</p>

<p>When Our Lord called Peter and Andrew, He said, “Come, follow me, and I will make you fishers of men” (Matt. 4:19). That was the beginning. But it wasn’t the end. That was their first conversion.</p>

<p>Later, Our Lord was to say, “Feed my lambs...feed my sheep” (John 21:15-17). There were later and deeper conversions: conversions to a deeper responsibility; conversions from the spiritual to a deeper spirituality, from humility to a deeper humility; from faith to a greater faith.</p>

<p>All the time, Our Lord is leading us forward along the pathway of holiness, the pilgrimage of faith which our Christian vocation is. Lent can be a great stimulus. A lady told me once: I really look forward to Lent and Advent. I hadn’t heard that before; I was rather impressed.</p>

<p>But you see, Lent is a time of great spiritual bonanza. If you have a chance, try and follow the liturgy of Lent closely: the Responsorial Psalms, the Alleluia verse, the Entrance Antiphon.</p>

<p>Smaller parts of the liturgy, you’ll find a great richness there, and a great beauty in the liturgy that will move your heart and whet your appetite for spiritual things, and help you to a much deeper approach to this whole period.</p>

<p>There are many aspirations that you may find in the words of the liturgy, and also in the words of Scripture that we read every day.</p>

<p>Incidentally, somebody told me that we Catholics have more exposure to Scripture than any other Christian denomination, because if we attend Mass regularly, especially on weekdays, we get the choicest parts of Scripture pre-selected for us in a regular way, so that our eyes fall on this great spiritual treasure which is Scripture.</p>

<p>We absorb these things in all these prayers of the liturgy. That’s particularly true of Lent—to savor that richness and to thank God for it.</p>

<p>Possibly from those short prayers, you may get little aspirations that can help you in the rest of the day, like in the <em>Way of the Cross</em>, we say: “We adore you, O Christ, and we bless you, because by your holy cross you have redeemed the world.”</p>

<p>Many little phrases can come to us that can be very meaningful, can help us to supernaturalize our day, and sanctify it. Also, it can give us great peace and joy in leading us to prayer.</p>

<p>One thing we can try and focus on in this month is also the richness of Confession—of our own personal Confession—to get to Confession frequently, to be always in the state of grace, and to see how, if possible, we can reach out to others in the sacrament of Confession.</p>

<p>There was a student in Tokyo once who had heard about doing the apostolate of Confession. In Japan, this population is about 1 percent Christian or Catholic. This student was in the library of the university one time and was thinking, ‘If there are 100 people in this library, possibly one of them is Catholic.’</p>

<p>But then he thought, ‘The chances of bumping up against that Catholic are very rare, but I still have to try and do the apostolate of Confession.’ He leaned over to the student in front of him at the table and said: ‘Hey, how would you like to go to Confession?’</p>

<p>The person said: ‘What’s that?’ And he said: ‘You go into this little box and it’s all dark and there’s a little grill there and you tell the priest all the bad things you have inside you. You get all of them out, you empty everything out, all the garbage, all the rubbish. And then you feel wonderful; you come out of there feeling as light as a feather.’</p>

<p>The guy said: ‘Oh, I think I’d like to try that.’ He began instruction, and three months later, he was baptized and went to Confession.</p>

<p>We never know where that apostolate of Confession is going to lead us in helping many other hearts and souls to grow, and to help the Blood of Christ to get in there and wash away the sins.</p>

<p>Sin is the ugliest reality on the planet. The only thing that we have to be afraid of is sin, because sin is the only thing that will keep us out of heaven.</p>

<p>All the things that the world may present to us as evils are not really evils—not having material things, losing our job, not having this or that, not having money, sickness or disease, or all the other things that can happen.</p>

<p>None of those things can keep us out of heaven—they may be the means to getting to heaven.</p>

<p>Our faith gives us an enormously positive outlook on the world, on creation, on our life. All the different moments of our life are opportunities for us to grow in the goals of our Christian formation—which are holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>We’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “A spirit of mortification, rather than being just an outward show of Love, arises as one of its consequences. If you fail in one of these little proofs, acknowledge that your love for the Love is wavering” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 981).</p>

<p>The Church invites us to deny ourselves little things externally because of the effect that that has interiorly on our soul. We say “no” to the body in order to say “yes” to the soul.</p>

<p>Lent is all about our soul. Often if God permits some pain in our body, or some contradiction, or some reversal of fortune, it’s because He wants our soul to fly. The spiritual realities can become enormously rich and enormously important. We can come to discover the greater reality of the spiritual.</p>

<p>I was passing through Dublin airport one morning at 8 o’clock and a man in a wheelchair beckoned to me to come over. He saw I was a priest and he wanted to talk to me, and initially, he asked me to get an attendant to help him to go to the washroom, which I did.</p>

<p>But then while we waited for the attendant, he said to me, ‘You know, today is a very difficult day for me; it’s the fifth anniversary of the death of my eldest son in a motorbike accident.’</p>

<p>And my heart sank. Eight o’clock in the morning—I wasn’t expecting this.</p>

<p>But he was a man going through a difficult moment, he sees a priest and wants a bit of a spiritual uplift. Then he explained how he was an accountant, he worked in London, but he had developed multiple sclerosis.</p>

<p>The last few years of his life he’d been confined to a wheelchair. His body had become limited at the very height of his career.</p>

<p>But, he said, ‘Suddenly all the spiritual things have come to mean an awful lot to me: I go to the sacraments more frequently, I get to receive the Anointing of the Sick.’ He says, ‘This gives me great joy and a great uplift.’</p>

<p>While we were waiting for the attendant to come, he was sort of giving me a whole catechesis on the sacraments; the effect of the sacraments in his life.</p>

<p>I was the one who benefited from that encounter. I learned so much, and forty years later I’m still talking about it.</p>

<p>There are souls all around us: souls who are looking for a spiritual uplift, souls that need to have their eyes open to the spiritual realities of the world, which are very rich, very beautiful.</p>

<p>Modern materialism, the culture in which we live, tends to tell us that man has no soul. Man is just a thing—that’s why we can abort him or euthanize him. It doesn’t matter; he’s disposable.</p>

<p>But all the great religions of the world speak about the spiritual nature of man—Buddhism, Hinduism, Judaism, Islam, Christianity—it’s one thing we all have in common: a belief in the spiritual nature of man.</p>

<p>“Have you noticed,” we’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “that mortified souls, because of their simplicity, have a greater enjoyment of good things, even in this world?” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 982).</p>

<p>When we deny our body certain pleasures, often it opens the eyes of our soul to deeper realities, to greater pleasures. Spiritual pleasures.</p>

<p>Sometimes as we move on in life, all the things that gave us pleasure earlier—playing sports, maybe, sweets, watching things on TV or movies or whatever—maybe, we find those pleasures pass. We get much greater joy from the spiritual things.</p>

<p>As the body begins to decay, the soul can grow and grow, discover a new youthfulness, a new joy.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>The Furrow</em>, Point 983: “Without mortification there is no happiness on earth.”</p>

<p>“It’s of great benefit,” says St. Paul, “that we all deny ourselves little pleasures. All things are pleasurable to me, but not all things are necessary or expedient” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:23).</p>

<p>Not all things are necessary. It’s very good in every person’s life that they deny themselves the fruit of a certain tree; certain pleasures that come from certain things.</p>

<p>We all need that salt of mortification. It strengthens our character, strengthens our soul, we grow in fortitude, we know how to say no to ourselves and sometimes to other people, so that we have a certain backbone.</p>

<p>“When you make up your mind to be more mortified,” we’re told, “your interior life will improve and you will be much more fruitful” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 984).</p>

<p>The Church invites us to think of this period of Lent as training for the marathon. Any great Kenyan marathon runner has to run up and down mountains to strengthen their muscles and practice their breathing—all these sorts of things.</p>

<p>This is like a spiritual marathon. The Church gives us an opportunity every year to get into better shape spiritually and to help everybody around us to do the same thing.</p>

<p>“Let us not forget,” we’re told by St. Josemaría, “that in all human activities there must be men and women who, in their lives and work, raise Christ’s cross aloft for all to see, as an act of reparation.</p>

<p>“It is a symbol of peace and of joy, a symbol of the Redemption and of the unity of the human race. It is a symbol of the love that the Most Holy Trinity, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit had, and continues to have, for mankind” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 985).</p>

<p>The cross needs to be there in our life. When we go closer to the Mass, we go closer to the unbloody renewal of the sacrifice of Calvary, which can come to have great meaning for us.</p>

<p>Lent can be a time to be more focused on the Mass, make our attendance more frequent, and work at our Mass a little bit, so that it can truly become the summit and the source of our whole spiritual life, the center and the root.</p>

<p>From a deeper contemplation of Christ on the Cross, we come to understand better the workings of divine grace in our soul.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says that when the priest raises his hands to give the absolution and Confession, the Blood of Christ is dripping from his hands (<em>cf</em>. Henry Dieterich, editor, <em>Through the Year with Fulton Sheen</em>).</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture, “Without the shedding of blood, there is no remission of sin” (Heb. 9:22).</p>

<p>It’s the Blood of Christ that washes away our sins. Blessed be His Most Precious Blood. Lent is also a time when we can contemplate the Precious Blood of Christ. Thank God for shedding His Blood.</p>

<p>In that way, we prepare for the great feast of Easter, the most important feast in the whole of the liturgical year that is there for us to savor in a deeper way every year, in the beauty of its liturgy and the ceremonies, so that more and more, it comes to be a very important part of our life.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that we might never forget that we are dust, that we might savor days like today—Ash Wednesday—and help other people around us too, to come to appreciate the great spiritual richness of days like today.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>CPG</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Knowing When To Speak</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knowing When To Speak" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/knowing-when-to-speak/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen. My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My immaculate mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in St. Mark that Jesus “was silent and made no answer” (Mark 14:61). For thirty years, Jesus had lived a life of silence. Mary and Joseph were the only ones who knew the mystery of the Son of God. During his public life, when he returned to his hometown, his relatives were disconcerted by his wisdom and his miracles. They had known him only from his exemplary life of work. During the three years of his public life, we see how he withdraws into the silence of prayer to be alone with his Father God. He withdraws from the superficial clamor of the multitude that wants to make him their king. He performs miracles without ostentation, asking people he cures to refrain from publicizing his powers.</p>

<p>We see that one of the characteristics of the life of Christ was silence. His silence before his enemies in the Passion is very moving. “He was silent and made no answer,” we’re told (Mark 14:61). In the face of so many false accusations, he makes no defense. St. Jerome comments, “Our God and Savior, who because of his mercy had redeemed the world, allows himself to be led to his death like a lamb, without a word of complaint or self-defense. The silence of Jesus obtains pardon for the protest and excuse of Adam.”</p>

<p>Jesus says nothing during the hearings before Herod and Pilate. We see him standing silent at their preference for Barabbas in front of his hate-filled enemies. “When he was accused by the chief priests and elders, he made no answer. Then Pilate said to him, ‘Do you not hear how many things they testify against you?’ But he gave him no answer, not even to a single charge,” so that the governor, we’re told, “wondered greatly” (Matt. 27:12’14).</p>

<p>The silence of Jesus in the face of human passions, before the sins which are committed every day by humanity, is not a silence of anger. It’s a silence that’s full of patience and love. The silence of Calvary is that of a God who comes to redeem all men by his indescribable agony of the Cross. The silence of Jesus in the tabernacle is that of a love which waits for a response. It’s the patient silence of one who treasures our attentions.</p>

<p>Christ’s silence during his earthly life represents interior strength and sense of purpose. One writer says, “Those who complain continually about their misfortunes or their bad luck should look at the example of Our Lord. Those who proclaim their problems to the four winds should consider the behavior of Christ. Those who feel compelled to explain and excuse their actions, who wait anxiously for praise or approval, should take note of Christ who says nothing.” We will imitate him when we learn to accept life’s duties and worries without sterile complaints; when we confront our personal problems without dumping them in someone else’s lap; when we face squarely the consequences of our actions; when we do our work for the glory of God without looking for earthly praise.</p>

<p>“Jesus says nothing,” we’re told in Scripture. We have to learn to say nothing on many occasions. At times vanity will have us say things which should have been kept locked in the soul. The silent figure of Christ is the ever-present model to reproach empty or useless words. His example will lead us to remain silent before calumny and rumor. The prophet Isaiah says, “In silence and in hope will be your fortitude and your courage” (Isa. 30:15). He encourages us that our fortitude is grounded in silence and in hope.</p>

<p>At the same time, Our Lord doesn’t always remain silent. He teaches us that sometimes we have to speak out when it’s necessary, with charity and with fortitude, avoiding the silence of consent. There is a silence that can collaborate with lying, a silence that can cooperate with cowardice, a silence which springs from the love of comfort and the fear of complicating one’s life. You can close your eyes to what is disagreeable. You can put off making a fraternal correction that ought to be made at home or at work.</p>

<p>The word of Jesus is full of authority as he faces injustice and abuse. In St. Matthew we’re told, “Woe to you scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, for you devour widows’ houses and for a pretense you make long prayers” (Matt. 23:14). St. John the Baptist was “the voice of one crying in the wilderness” (Matt. 3:3). He teaches us to say everything that must be said, even though it may seem as if we too are crying in the wilderness. Our Lord will not allow our words to be wasted. It’s important that we say what has to be said without worrying ourselves about the immediate consequences.</p>

<p>If each Christian were to speak in conformity with their faith, we would surely change the world. We can’t sit by silently in the face of such crimes of abortion and the degradation of marriage and the family. Nor can we surrender to those forces that would seek to remove God from the formation of the young. We can’t be silent at attacks upon the Pope and Our Lady, or upon institutions of the Church. To be silent when we should be speaking out can be a way of collaborating with evil because others might think that our silence means consent.</p>

<p>If Catholics were to speak out where there is need, if they were to boycott anti-Catholic publications or literature, it would be more difficult for those enterprises to prosper. In our prayer today, we can ask Our Lord for the grace to speak out when necessary. At times those occasions will be when we’re with a little group of our friends, coming or going to school or to work. In letters to the editor, we can write in praise of a good article or to criticize a bad one. We should always act with charity. It’s worthwhile to remember that true charity always goes hand in hand with fortitude. We need to exercise good manners, always working with the intention of bringing souls to Jesus Christ. Yet we should act at the same time with the fortitude of Our Lord.</p>

<p>If upon realizing that his life was in danger, St. John the Baptist had remained silent or retired to the sidelines of public affairs, he would not have been beheaded by Herod. But John was not that kind of man. He was not “a reed shaken by the wind” (Matt. 11:7). He was true to his vocation and also to his principles to the end. If he had remained silent, he could have lived a few more years, but his disciples would not have been the first to follow Our Lord. He would not have “prepared and made straight the way of the Lord” as we’re told by Isaiah (Isa. 40:3). He would not have lived up to his vocation. His life would have been bereft of meaning.</p>

<p>Probably Our Lord is not asking us to suffer a martyr’s death, but he is asking for courage and fortitude in facing up to the demands of ordinary life. Perhaps he is asking us to stop watching a bad TV show, or to cease putting off an apostolic conversation. We can’t allow ourselves to hide behind excuses when there is a lot of apostolic work to be done. We have to act with optimism, loving the world and the good that is in it, while seeking to increase that goodness. We can do this with the example of a joyful family and of the youthful love that is born of holy purity.</p>

<p>There are other kinds of cowardly silence which we have to struggle against: the silence we might maintain with the person next to us. But God has put that person there so that we might be a beacon of light for him or for her. It’s hard to imagine that we can be courageous at all in this life if we are not courageous first with ourselves, especially when we’re talking with our spiritual director, to say the things that need to be said. Many of our friends, on seeing that we truly practice what we preach, will be attracted to the faith.</p>

<p>Centuries ago, many people converted after witnessing the martyrdom of the first Christians. We can learn a lot from Our Lord’s silence. We’re told in the Psalms, “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2). God lives in our midst and often in a very silent way. Throughout the Old Testament, God makes known his intention of having an ongoing presence among men. The Tent of Meeting was the first temple to God in the desert. Upon the tent, there came to rest a cloud which symbolized the glory of God and his presence. “Then the cloud covered the Tent of Meeting and the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle” (Exod. 40:34). The cloud was a sign of the divine presence.</p>

<p>Much later, the temple in Jerusalem was the place where the Israelites worshiped God. It was the place they had been longing for while they were in the desert. They would recall with enthusiasm of old when they would go to the house of the Lord, singing songs of joy and praise. “How lovely is your dwelling place, O Lord of hosts! My soul longs, yes faints for the courts of the Lord; my heart and flesh sing for joy to the living God” (Ps. 84:1’2). To be far from the sanctuary was to be deprived of true happiness. “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:2).</p>

<p>In the fullness of time, the Word became flesh. In the moment of the Incarnation, the power of the Most High overshadowed Our Lady. This is an expression of the omnipotence of God. Following upon the Incarnation, Our Lady, the Virgin, became the tabernacle of God. “The Word of God dwelt among us,” we’re told in St. John (John 1:14). St. John uses a Greek verb for “dwelling” which originally meant “to pitch one’s tent,” hence to live in a place. The careful reader of Scripture will immediately think of the Tabernacle or the Tent in the period of the Exodus from Egypt where God showed his presence before all the people of Israel through certain signs of his glory, such as the cloud covering the tent.</p>

<p>In many passages of the Old Testament, it’s announced that God will dwell in the midst of his people. These signs of God’s presence, first in the pilgrim tent of the Ark in the desert, and then in the temple of Jerusalem, are followed by the most wonderful form of God’s presence among us: Jesus Christ, perfect God and perfect man, in whom the ancient promise is fulfilled in a way that far exceeded man’s greatest expectations. Also the promise made through Isaiah about the Emmanuel, our “God with us,” is completely fulfilled through this dwelling of the incarnate Son of God among us.</p>

<p>From that time onwards, we can say with exactitude that God lives among us. We can be next to him every day, closer to him than anyone might imagine possible—God truly dwelling among us. From the moment of the Incarnation, we can affirm that God is with us in the personal presence of Jesus Christ. As both true God and true man, Jesus is closer to us than any other being. Jesus is God with us. In earlier times, the Israelites would say that God was with them. Now we can say this in a very literal sense.</p>

<p>When Christ traveled about Palestine, he made an effort to preach in many towns. “When Jesus had finished these parables,” we’re told, “he went away from there” (Matt. 13:53). God left one town to go and meet other people. When the priest consecrates the host during the Mass, he brings Christ to the altar with his holy humanity. He is there in the Eucharist with a special presence for as long as the sacramental species last. This presence affects the body of Christ in a direct way, and the three persons of the Holy Trinity in an indirect way. The Word is tied to Christ’s humanity, while the Father and the Holy Spirit are related by the mutual immanence of their divine person.</p>

<p>Christ is really present in the tabernacle with his body, blood, soul, and divinity. It can be said quite literally that God is here, close to me.</p>

<p>We could make that act of faith: My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me.</p>

<p>Down through the centuries, the Church has developed a precise way of describing the Eucharistic presence, often requiring such exact definition to counter erroneous beliefs. The Eucharistic presence is a real presence, a silent presence. It’s not symbolic, nor does it signify or insinuate any image. It’s not fictitious, or merely the product of the imagination or the will. It is substantial because the words of the consecration, spoken by the priest, change the substance of bread and the wine into the substance of the body and blood of Christ.</p>

<p>In the encyclical “<em>Mysterium Fidei</em>,” Paul VI says, “Every theological explanation which seeks some understanding of this mystery must, in order to be in accord with Catholic faith, maintain that in the reality itself, independently of our mind, the bread and wine have ceased to exist after the consecration, so that it is the adorable body and blood of Our Lord Jesus that from then on are really before us under the sacramental species of bread and wine.”</p>

<p>As a result of transubstantiation, the species of bread and wine contain a new reality which we may justly term “ontological.” Not that there lies under those species what was already there before, but something quite different; and that not only because of the faith of the Church, but in objective reality. Jesus is silently present in our tabernacles, whether or not we take advantage of this amazing wonder. He is there silently with his body and his blood, his soul and his divinity. God made man. He could not be closer.</p>

<p>The Church possesses the Author of all Grace and the cause of our sanctification. We may venture to say that the Eucharistic presence of Christ is the sacramental prolongation of the Incarnation. From the tabernacle, Jesus invites us to bring to him our concerns and our petitions. In the visit to the Blessed Sacrament and other acts of worship offered to the Holy Eucharist, we give thanks for this great gift. There we can go to find new strength, to tell Jesus that we miss him, to tell him that we need him very much. “The Eucharist is reserved in the churches and oratories as in the spiritual center of a religious community or of a parish, and of the universal Church and of all humanity, since beneath the appearance of the species, Christ is contained: the invisible head of the Church, the redeemer of the world, the center of all hearts, ‘by whom,’” says St. Paul, “‘all things are and by whom we exist’” (1 Cor. 8:6).</p>

<p>It has been the constant practice of the Church to adore Christ’s silent presence in the tabernacle. If we recall how much reverence the Israelites had for their Tent of Meeting in the desert and for the Temple at Jerusalem, which were figures or images of reality, how much more reverence should we have for Christ truly present in the tabernacle.</p>

<p>In the first centuries of the Church, the main reason for reserving the sacred species was for the sake of those who were not able to get to Mass, especially the sick and the dying, and also for those in prison due to religious persecution. The sacrament of Our Lord was brought to them with piety and fervor so that these Christians might also receive communion. Later, faith in the real presence of Christ led to the cult of the Blessed Sacrament, and the Church authoritatively approved those practices. The Council of Trent declared, “There is therefore no room left for doubt that all the faithful of Christ, in accordance with the custom always received in the Catholic Church, offer in veneration the worship of latria which is due to the true God to this most holy sacrament.”</p>

<p>In the 13th century, St. Thomas Aquinas composed a Eucharistic hymn which embodies the faith of the Church in a faithful and pious manner. We should make this hymn our own so as to nourish our piety and give honor to the Blessed Sacrament. The hymn states: “O Godhead hid, devoutly I adore you, who truly are within the forms before me. To you my heart I bow with bended knee, as failing quite in contemplating thee.” Here we have all the truths of the faith. We have an understanding with humility and thanksgiving, amazement before the power of God, surprise at the extent of his mercy. With the confidence gained by having him so close by, we can ask Our Lord for his grace to unite ourselves to his most holy will.</p>

<p>Next to the silent tabernacle, we can learn how to love. There we will draw the strength necessary to remain faithful. We’ll find consolation in times of sorrow. He silently waits for us, and he rejoices when we are next to him, even if only for a short while. There Jesus waits for his people who suffer the contradictions of this life. He comforts them with the warmth of his understanding and his love. It is in the tabernacle that the words of Our Lord come to life, specifically those words where he says, “Come to me all you who labor and are heavy laden and I will give you rest” (Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>We should not fail to visit him. He is waiting for us. He has many gifts prepared for us. Mary, we turn to you, comfort of the afflicted, cause of our joy. We ask you for the grace to learn from the silence of Our Lord in his public life and also in the tabernacle.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mortification</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/mortification/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mortification" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/mortification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/mortification/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We read in today's Gospel: “But I say to you, my friends, do not be afraid of those who kill the body and after that have nothing more that they can do. But I will show you whom you shall be afraid of: be afraid of him who after he has killed has power to cast into hell” (Luke 12:4-5).</p>

<p>This passage is telling us about the passing nature of the human body, and that we don't need to be too worried about him who might kill the body. But we need to be much more concerned about him who could kill the soul, because the soul is immortal. The soul is going to live forever.</p>

<p>It's a passage that in a subtle sort of way tells us about the care of our soul. All through the Gospels, Our Lord reminds us of the care of our soul and one of the dangers is that our soul can be dominated a little bit by the body.</p>

<p>So we have to keep the body in check. That process is called mortification, <em>mortis facere</em>, to make death, to die to ourselves.</p>

<p>Jesus said to His disciples: “If anyone wants to be a follower of mine, let him renounce himself and take up his cross and follow me” (Matt. 16:24).</p>

<p>Our Lord speaks a lot about self-denial—the importance of self-denial—saying no to self, to our appetites, to our tendencies, to our likes and dislikes, to our whims. We have to try and keep our body in check, and in that way, we train our soul. We are more united to Christ. We look to the cross.</p>

<p>“It makes me happy,” says St. Paul, “to be suffering for you now, and in my own body, to make up for all the hardships that still have to be undergone by Christ for the sake of his body, the Church” (Col. 1:24).</p>

<p>Through dying to ourselves, we unite ourselves to Christ on the Cross. We become more holy, more effective. We allow our soul to breathe.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to recommend that we would have a little list of small mortifications, two or three things that we might try and do every day. Not big things, but small things. Things that fit in with our work, that if possible, help us to work a little better, or help us in other ways.</p>

<p>The whole pathway of mortification, according to our spirit, is meant to be in the ordinary things: getting up on time, being on time for different activities, punctuality, order in our cabinet, in our drawers, among our personal things, thinking of others, putting ourselves out in little things, eating a little bit less of what we like and a little bit more of what we don't like, finishing what's on our plate—in that way, thanking God for all the good things that He gives us.</p>

<p>“In all truth I tell you,” says Our Lord in St. John, “unless a grain of wheat falls into the ground and dies, it remains alone. But if it dies, it yields a rich harvest” (John 12:24).</p>

<p>We die to ourselves in order to yield a rich fruit.</p>

<p>We've come to the Work to die to ourselves, to forget about ourselves, to be that grain of wheat that falls into the ground, so that all the fruits that God wants may come from our life, from our day, from our work, from everything we do.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord in our prayer: What little mortifications should I be practicing? Or talk about it in our chat.</p>

<p>How do we practice this spirit of small mortifications? And the important thing is not just the dying to ourselves, not just the sacrifice.</p>

<p>It's the love with which we do it. It's all about love. It's saying “no” to our body in order to say “yes” to our soul. God wants us to live that spirit all throughout our life.</p>

<p>Many years ago, in Singapore, I was having lunch with an Irish diocesan priest who was based in New Zealand, but he had come to Singapore for the funeral of his brother. This man was 82.</p>

<p>We were having lunch, and after lunch we had coffee, and I asked him if he wanted some sugar for his coffee.</p>

<p>He said, “No, thanks, I'm off it for Lent.” Okay, that was a very nice thing to say, but I couldn't help thinking that at 82, he was still living a practice of Lent. I was very edified.</p>

<p>The spirit of mortification in small things was very much alive. We live this spirit not just for now, not when we're young, but always, so that that sort of mortification is in everything we do.</p>

<p>Sometimes the world gets a bit scandalized by sacrifice or by mortification, but it's a funny thing, because all the greatest athletes in the world undergo an enormous amount of self-denial.</p>

<p>If you look at Eliud Kipchoge, who broke the record for the marathon recently [in 2002], probably, we only see him in the last hundred meters of the race, breaking the record, and all the glory that's there.</p>

<p>We don't see him running over the hills of Eldoret at five o'clock in the morning when it's raining, or keeping on running and going uphill when he doesn't feel like it.</p>

<p>All the great athletes live lives like that—Messi and Usain Bolt. I saw a documentary of Usain Bolt recently, who I think holds the world record for the 100 meters. The amount of training that these people go through is really very heroic.</p>

<p>So, when we feel that we have to deny ourselves little things, it's nothing compared to what these great athletes do.</p>

<p>Self-denial is not an unusual thing. It's highly common. People deny themselves all sorts of things to pass this exam, to get this diploma, to get into this particular school, or all sorts of goals.</p>

<p>What scandalizes people is that if it's done for God, if it's done for others. Doing it for oneself is no problem.</p>

<p>The essence then of what Our Lord invites us to do is to offer these things to Him. It's all based on charity. We say no to ourselves in order to say yes to others, to say yes to love.</p>

<p>That mortification can be more necessary at certain times. There are exterior mortifications, corporal mortifications that we impose on our body, but there are also interior mortifications in our mind, in our imagination, in our heart.</p>

<p>There are passive mortifications that come: changes of plans, things that don't work out the way we wanted them to, something unpleasant. All these things are possibilities for mortification. Forget about ourselves and offer them to Our Lord on the Cross.</p>

<p>Lord, in this particular thing, I offer this thing to you now, in this moment. I say no to myself.</p>

<p>Sometimes God might send us a headache, or a sore toe, or we might not have slept so well last night, or all sorts of things. These are occasions to forget about ourselves and just offer them to Him, and in that we can find our peace and our joy.</p>

<p>There's a phrase in the Gospel that can be very helpful. It says, “We receive less blows than we deserve” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:48).</p>

<p>“We receive less blows than we deserve.” If on some occasion we feel Our Lord is sending us too many things, too many difficulties or hardships or bad news, or we fail this exam, or this thing doesn't work out, or the machine breaks down at a bad moment, or all these sorts of things, it's good to remember “we receive less blows than we deserve.”</p>

<p>There were many times in our life when maybe, we deserved all the most terrible things that could happen for our lack of honesty, for our lack of punctuality, our lack of order, all the sins we might have committed, all these things.</p>

<p>What Our Lord sends us, really, is very minimal. Mortification lightens the weight of our soul and makes it easier to be lifted up.</p>

<p>While this spirit is something that is meant to pervade our whole existence, there are certain periods in the year which the Church gives us where she encourages us to practice a little more penance: in Lent and Advent.</p>

<p>We start Lent with the ceremony of the ashes, reminding us that we are dust, we're nothing; reminding us of the importance of the soul, that the body is passing.</p>

<p>It's something positive, not something negative, and the essence of our sacrifice is not to destroy, but to offer.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way of the Cross</em>, we're told, “We must bring into our life, to make them our own, the life and death of Christ” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way of the Cross</em>, Fourteenth Station).</p>

<p>We're on a royal pathway. Christ never said it was going to be easy. We bring to our prayer sometimes the Way of the Cross, where we see Christ falling down three times.</p>

<p>But He gets up again. He endured all this suffering for you and me.</p>

<p>When we say no to ourselves, we try to accompany Him along that pathway of the Way of the Cross with generosity, with humility.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría also says, “We must die through mortification and penance, so that Christ can live in us through Love. And then follow in the footsteps of Christ, with a zeal to co-redeem all mankind” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>We mortify ourselves to be more apostolic, to think more of others, to go out of our way, to deny ourselves little pleasures here and there that we offer to Our Lord for this soul and for that soul.</p>

<p>This is the excitement of our life. We live for souls, everything for souls. Everything becomes a motive of joy. “We must give our life for others,” he says. “That is the only way to live the life of Jesus Christ and to become one and the same thing with him” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>In <em>The Way,</em> we’re told: “We must give ourselves in everything, we must deny ourselves in everything: the sacrifice must be a holocaust” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 186).</p>

<p>The self-giving of Jesus on the Cross is full of love. Christ is not bitter on the Cross. He's not full of hatred. He doesn't say. ‘all these people who put me here on the Cross…’—He doesn't curse us on the cross. “Thy will be done. Let not my will, rather, yours be done” (Luke 22:42).</p>

<p>Christ loved the Cross because it's the instrument of redemption, of salvation for the whole world. “Greater love than this no man has, that he lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13).</p>

<p>One time St. Josemaría was in a get-together in the early 1950s with a number of people. There was going to be a consistory, which is where some people are named cardinals.</p>

<p>One young fellow in the get-together piped up and said: “Father, maybe you'll be made a cardinal!”</p>

<p>St. Josemaría changed the topic very quickly. But after the get-together, he called that fellow to his room. The guy was a doctor.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría lifted up his cassock and then lifted up his shirt and lifted up his undershirt and showed a big red rash that was across his chest.</p>

<p>The young doctor immediately recognized the rash as the rash of Herpes Zoster or shingles. He knew that people with shingles are normally in a lot of pain. Often, they're in bed with a fever and they can be in hospital.</p>

<p>But St. Josemaría was there in the get-together and still nothing was the matter. And St. Josemaría pointed to the red of the rash and he said: “My son, this is the only red that God has in mind for me.”</p>

<p>Eventually that fellow was ordained and at the end of his life was made a cardinal by John Paul II, Cardinal Julián Herranz. He hesitated quite a bit before accepting the nomination as a cardinal, possibly remembering that experience with St. Josemaría.</p>

<p>On another occasion he said he had been sick and in his convalescence St. Josemaría brought him for a drive around Rome with Don Álvaro.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría was laughing and singing and joking in the little Fiat 600 that they had in the early 1950s.</p>

<p>When they went back home, St. Josemaría went upstairs and Don Álvaro hung back a little bit and asked him: “Well, how did you find St. Josemaría this afternoon?”</p>

<p>He said, “Well, he was in great form. He was laughing, he was singing, he was joking.”</p>

<p>He told him: “Just for you to know, St. Josemaría has a big boil on the back of his neck because of the diabetes. His Roman collar is biting down into his neck. So he had been in great pain all afternoon. But just for you to know that he did all of this for you.”</p>

<p>“The Father loves me,” said Our Lord, “because I lay down my life in order to take it up again” (John 10:17).</p>

<p>Our bodies can say at times what our heart cannot say. We say with our actions. We show Our Lord with our deeds that we're serious.</p>

<p>This deed of self-denial, this saying no to myself in this particular thing, training myself like a great athlete—because Our Lord wants me to be a great champion, a great leader in love, to show the world what charity is.</p>

<p>He wants to use me to be more effective spiritually in this world, which Pope Francis says has a great spiritual emptiness (Pope Francis, <em>Angelus</em>, June 19, 2016). We've come to fill that emptiness.</p>

<p>To live a life of mortification is not such a big thing. Atheists even do it. Atheists do corporal mortification. They go on hunger strikes.</p>

<p>So sometimes we might sleep on the floor, or they might do other things that we do—or just small things really, to try and show Our Lord how much we want to be united to Him.</p>

<p>If we try to practice that corporal mortification, we'll discover the cross in the ordinary things: family circumstances, social situations, work situations.</p>

<p>We might like to work in this particular way, or lay the table in this way, or sweep the floor in this way. But we might be told, “This is a better way to do it” or “This is more efficient.”</p>

<p>We might need to change our work habits, and it might take a little bit of saying “no” to ourselves in order to learn new things, in order to work better, to be more productive, to sanctify our work a little better, to create a better atmosphere around us.</p>

<p>We might have to mortify our way of doing things, our things we have learned before, because now there's a better way, because we've been lifted up onto a new level.</p>

<p>No matter what things may be there in our life, we are all addicted to something: the laziness, the gossip, the disorder. We all have to fight the battle in many of these areas. But all these things can be overcome.</p>

<p>I was impressed reading a book once by a priest who used to hear Confession in a downtown church in New York, Father Benedict Groeschel. He's written a number of books. He has a statement there that says, “All addictions can be cast out by prayer and sacrifice.”</p>

<p>That's a very powerful statement coming from a priest who hears Confessions in downtown New York where every possible addiction might make itself manifest.</p>

<p>“All addictions can be cast out by prayer and sacrifice.” No matter what we might be addicted to, we can overcome them: anger, envy, jealousy, lust, gluttony. We've come to conquer ourselves.</p>

<p>There's a point in <em>The Way</em> (Point 221) where St. Josemaría says: “If you are generous in voluntary mortification, God will give you the grace to love the trials that he sends you.”</p>

<p>What a great way to live, loving the trials. The key to loving the trials is to be generous in saying no to ourselves.</p>

<p>Often the greatest mortification will be in the ordinary things. Finishing our work well. Persevering in the work begun. Double checking. Very often, perfection is in the details. Double checking the work that we have to do.</p>

<p>One time I was accompanying somebody in a hospital and two ladies came to clean this room. It was a small room with a little bathroom attached.</p>

<p>So, I left the room, and I waited outside until they were finished. They were there for about twenty minutes.</p>

<p>Eventually they came out and I went back into the room. The first thing I saw was a wastepaper basket that was full on top of the table. I wondered what took them so long to clean this fairly small room and small bathroom.</p>

<p>When I walked into the room and saw that wastepaper basket on the table, I got the impression that I think they were spending the whole time talking, If they had just looked back, a small glance as they left the room, they would have seen that wastebasket on top of the table.</p>

<p>Often, perfection in our work is in that second glance. Double check to make sure everything is in its place. The last look.</p>

<p>This is finishing our work well, taking care of the details, not presuming that everything is okay. We type an email or write a little note or something. It's double-checking what we've done.</p>

<p>We offer to Our Lord the martyrdom of little things. Putting this thing right, turning off this switch, turning off a light, turning off a tap.</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>: “A little act, when done for love, is worth so much!” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 814).</p>

<p>Often, it's the difficult things that make us improve. We improve on the uphill climb. If we identify something that we're not so good at or we need to improve on, and we apply ourselves to that, that's a very good mortification.</p>

<p>Tackle this problem, this virtue, this vice, this habit, because I've come to be better. I've come to conquer myself. I've come to be more Christ-like.</p>

<p>If God permits certain crosses in our life, we can thank Him for the crosses. Thank you, Lord, for this contradiction, because it's good.</p>

<p>Or, Thank you Lord for this temptation that seems to cost so much—because through the temptations that God permits, He invites us to a greater fortitude, or a greater faith, or a greater spirit of struggle, or an optimism, or to rely more on His graces, or to look for the source of those graces more frequently.</p>

<p>Sometimes the mortification that Our Lord wants from us is interior mortification: in our mind, in our imagination. Getting rid of bad thoughts, not allowing them to linger. If we think long enough about bad things, those ideas come out as our actions.</p>

<p>If you think long enough about robbing a bank, you'll end up robbing a bank. If we spend our day thinking about how am I going to get into this bank, and how am I going to get the money, and how am I going to get that gun, and start to plan it little by little, one day we'll end up robbing a bank.</p>

<p>If we get thoughts about robbing a bank, we should try and get rid of those thoughts as quickly as possible. They're just a waste of time.</p>

<p>Our imagination can present all sorts of things to our mind. That's why we have to try and control the imagination. In the book<em>Jesus as Friend</em>, there's a whole chapter on imagination. It's often called the madwoman of the house, the imagination.</p>

<p>We can have all sorts of imaginary fears or pains, imagine all sorts of scenarios that have nothing to do with reality. Or we might have thoughts of discouragement, or sensuality, or infidelity, or all sorts of things, or comparisons.</p>

<p>Sometimes we have to calm our imagination. The apostles were in the boat and the storm was raging. Interestingly, Our Lord was asleep in the stern of the boat. They were terrified.</p>

<p>These experienced fishermen had seen many storms. They'd never seen anything like this. They go to Our Lord and say: “Master, does it not concern you that we are perishing?”</p>

<p>Jesus stands up in the boat, speaks to the elements, and says: “Peace, be still” (Mark 4:38-39).</p>

<p>Sometimes that's what we have to say to our thoughts, to our imaginations, maybe running around there inside our head, all full of nonsense.</p>

<p>One great way to put a stop to those sorts of thoughts is to go and talk about them to the person that we chat with. Don't wait for our day, or for our time, or for our chat.</p>

<p>Go today and say, “Look, I've got all these bad ideas in my mind. I just want to get them out.” When we're sincere, when we empty out all the garbage that we have inside us, that might take an effort.</p>

<p>It might be embarrassing or shameful, but that's when the devil leaves us alone, because now we've used the means.</p>

<p>Sometimes we have to fast and abstain, not just from chocolate or sweets or nice things, but from our anger, from our temper, from our discouragements, from our complaining—it might be exterior or interior—from our judgments, from our resentments, from any bitterness or grudges.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Romans: “Do not model your behavior on the contemporary world, but let the renewing of your minds transform you, so that you may discern for yourselves what is the will of God—what is good and acceptable and mature” (Rom. 12:2).</p>

<p>We haven't come to live like everybody else. It might be people among our friends or classmates or acquaintances that we know that will earn their salary and they go out and they spend it, or they buy this, or they buy that.</p>

<p>We know that's not the way that God has planned for us. We detach from the material things of the world. Complete detachment. We get a salary; we leave it on the desk of the director. We need to buy something, we consult it.</p>

<p>We pass our judgment through the judgment of somebody else, through the person that has the grace of state. ‘I want to make this phone call or make this trip. I think this thing is really necessary.’ We ask about it.</p>

<p>“Whatever you eat or drink or whatever else you do,” says St. Paul, “do it all for the glory of God” (1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>When Don Javier was about to have a bypass operation, somebody suggested to him that maybe he should call his sister and tell her he's about to have this bypass. He said: “That's a good idea. Maybe I should do that. I will consult.”</p>

<p>‘I will check if it's necessary.’ ‘I will live that little detail to obedience.’ ‘I will submit my will to the will of another.’ That's what obedience is.</p>

<p>So, we try to mortify our intellect, our curiosity. ‘I don't need to know all things. If I need to know, I will be told. Maybe I don't need to ask too many questions, because perhaps it's not my business.’</p>

<p>Silence can be a great mortification. On the way to the Cross, to a large extent, Christ was silent. Sometimes we need more silence in our life. Mortify our tongue, our curiosity.</p>

<p>We mortify our will through obedience. Things don't have to be done ‘because I want.’</p>

<p>It's a great thing to conquer our will, to tame our will; not just to follow every whim. ‘I've got to go here, I've got to go there, I have to have this, I have to have that.’ ‘I have to watch this TV program, I have to listen to this music, I have to do this, I have to do that.’</p>

<p>Keep our will in check. It can run all over the place. It can lead us to destruction.</p>

<p>We have to mortify our memory. Memory of grievances—what that person said to me ten years ago, wounds we may have acquired in the course of our life. We offer those to Our Lord, and we forget about them.</p>

<p>Mortify our triumphs. ‘When I passed that exam, that was great.’ ‘When I won that medal.’ ‘When I got that compliment.’ Sometimes we need to change the channel in our mind like you change the channel in a radio or a TV station.</p>

<p>We may need to mortify our daydreaming so we don't spend our daydreaming about all sorts of stupid things that may never happen. We live in the real world. It's much more interesting.</p>

<p>We need to mortify our appetites—an appetite for fear, or anger, or anxiety; or a desire for fun, or for excitement; or thoughts of loneliness, or all sorts of other thoughts that the devil might place in our heart or in our mind.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to be beside the Cross like Our Lady was. Help me to be more demanding on myself and less demanding on others.</p>

<p>Help me to bear with joy, for love of Christ, the discomfort, the scarcity of means, all the consequences of real poverty and detachment that I'm called to live.</p>

<p>The extra demands. A time when there might be a little more work someday. Or maybe, it's nine o'clock at night and ‘I'm going to bed and suddenly there's another job that has to be done or something is asked of me.’ The extra demands.</p>

<p>Always more—generosity—professionalism. Responsibility may make a little bit more demands on us: to check that that window is closed, or that door is locked, or all sorts of other things.</p>

<p>Help me to mortify my tongue so that all the words that I say may be words of charity. Kind words that bring joy to the lives of others.</p>

<p>Help me to accept with love, as wanted by God for my growth, all the sufferings, physical and moral, contradictions, misunderstandings, miscommunications, sicknesses, limitations, this headache, that sore throat, all the little things that God may send me.</p>

<p>We have a desire to co-redeem, then all these things will be freely taken up. “Not my will, rather, yours be done” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 22:42).</p>

<p>That desire to co-redeem will lead us not just to accept, but to seek with generosity. To go out of ourselves. Go over and above the call of nature, of justice. Love is active. It goes out and seeks; it doesn't just wait for things to come.</p>

<p>“Be clever,” said St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>, “spiritually clever. Don't wait for the Lord to send you setbacks; go out to meet them with a spirit of voluntary atonement. Then you'll receive them not so much with resignation (an old-sounding word) as with love—a word which is forever young” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 225).</p>

<p>We see a great dynamism in Our Lady’s life. She went into the hill country. She faced the dangers and the risks. She didn't live in the realm of her own comfort. She went out of her way, she stayed with Elizabeth three months—not three hours, not three days, but three months. It was a serious contribution (Luke 1:39,56).</p>

<p>All the time she was forgetting herself—in Bethlehem, in Nazareth, forgetting her own creature comforts. Going to Egypt, accepting the changes of plans, the availability, all of those things that were part of her vocation. She accepted them and lived them joyfully and generously.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady, that she might give us that same spirit of self-sacrifice, so that we might live that same spirit in everything, just as she did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Our Way To The House of Our Father</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Our Way To The House of Our Father" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/on-our-way-to-the-house-of-our-father/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in the Book of Revelation, “Then he showed me the river of the water of life, bright as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and of the Lamb through the middle of the street of the city; also, on either side of the river, the tree of life with its twelve kinds of fruit”’ There shall no more be anything accursed, but the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it, and his servants shall worship him; they shall see his face, and his name shall be on their foreheads” (Rev. 22:1–4).</p>

<p>Scripture draws to a close where it all began: in the Garden of Eden, in Paradise. The scriptures speak to us about our final destination, the house of the Father, our true homeland. Through the rich use of symbols, God teaches us in the Book of Revelation about the nature of eternal life. This is the fulfillment of man’s deepest yearnings. We are to see God face to face and glorify him forever.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to say that marriage in this world is a preparation for marriage in the next. The real marriage comes later. People who lead celibate lives in this world give witness to the fact that the real marriage comes later. If we have some cross or some challenge or some difficulty, or our marriage did not work out to be everything that we dreamt of, well never mind, that’s part of the preparation. We have great things to look forward to: the eternal wedding feast.</p>

<p>In the Book of Revelation, it says this water is a symbol of the Holy Spirit who proceeds from the Father and the Son. It runs as a river from the throne of God and of the Lamb. The name of God is to be found on the foreheads of the blessed; they belong to the Lord. In heaven, night shall be no more; they shall need no light of lamp or sun, for the Lord God will be their light, and they shall reign forever and ever.</p>

<p>Death is an indispensable step towards our reunion with God. Children of God should view death as a transition to eternity, a change of home, a change of place. Jumping over the pool that separates us from this and heaven. Once we’re in God’s company, night shall be no more. To the extent that we grow in our sense of divine filiation, we should become more desirous of meeting our loving Father.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Way</em> used to say, “Foster in your heart the glorious hope of heaven.” That means we can look at death without fear, but with a holy expectation. Life is a journey towards eternity. Pope John Paul II said, “Every moment becomes precious precisely through this perspective.” We live and work in time, beating within us the nostalgia for heaven.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, we’re well aware that many, many people don’t share this nostalgia for heaven. They may have grown accustomed to their prosperity and material comfort, as if these things were to last forever. They’ve forgotten that fundamental truth, that “here we have no lasting city, but we seek for the city which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). Our hearts were made to last for all eternity. The things of this world cannot satisfy our nature. They can therefore become an obstacle to our eternal happiness.</p>

<p>We Christians have a great love of life and of all noble earthly realities: friendship, work, joy, human love. As a consequence, we shouldn’t be surprised that the prospect of death frightens us. This is quite natural. But our body and soul were created by God to be united with him forever. In the Preface for Masses for the Dead, the Church prays: “Lord, for your faithful people, life is changed, not ended.” When the body of our earthly dwelling lies in death, we gain an everlasting dwelling place in heaven.</p>

<p>The true child of God expresses his joy in seeing at last the transcendent perfections of the Father in all his holiness. The child recognizes the condescension of infinite majesty in adopting him on earth, in guiding, training, sanctifying, and preparing him for heaven. He has invited that child to enter heaven, to be with his Father for all eternity. One writer says God had little regard for his littleness and gave him the power to glorify the Trinity forever. We have good reason to exclaim, “We shall never die.” We will only be changing our lodgings, nothing more.</p>

<p>In conjunction with faith and hope, we Christians also need to have this sure hope. At our death, we make only a temporary farewell. We should want to die, said St. Josemaría, “in the spirit of those words: until we meet again.”</p>

<p>The Book of Daniel says, “The saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom forever, forever and ever” (Dan. 7:18). We’ll find that everything appears new and young in heaven. The Book of Revelation says the old universe will seem to have vanished like a scroll that is rolled up. Yet heaven will not be a complete surprise for us. It is, after all, the focus of the deepest yearnings of every person, even of the most depraved sinner.</p>

<p>Heaven is the new community of the children of God, who have attained to the fullness of their adoption. We will have a new heart and a new will. At the time of Christ’s glory, our bodies will be transfigured. Interestingly enough, this happiness based on the vision of God will not override personal relations. There in heaven will be found all authentic human love: the love between spouses, the love between a father and his children, friendships, family relations, noble camaraderie. We are all traveling in this life. As the years go by, we find that more and more of our loved ones are now on the other side of that barrier.</p>

<p>We’re told by one writer, this knowledge might be a source of fear, but can also be a cause for joy. This is possible if we believe that death is the door to our true home. It leads to our definitive homeland, which is inhabited by all those who have gone before us marked with the sign of faith. Our common homeland is not a forbidding tomb, but the bosom of the Lord.</p>

<p>While here on earth, we find it quite difficult to imagine what heaven will be like. The Old Testament compares our condition in heaven to that of the Promised Land. The Book of Isaiah says, “They shall not hunger or thirst, neither scorching wind nor sun shall smite them, for he who has pity on them will lead them, and by springs of water will guide them” (Isa. 49:10). Our Lord frequently spoke of the incredible happiness that lies in store for us if we are faithful.</p>

<p>The soul and all its faculties, along with our glorified bodies, will be divinized, though there will still remain an infinite difference between creature and Creator. We will contemplate God as he truly is. In addition, the blessed will delight in the knowledge of other people in God—for example, parents, relatives, spouse, children, and friends. St. Thomas teaches that the blessed will know in Christ everything that pertains to the beauty and integrity of the world. Because of our membership in the human community, the blessed will know the objects of Christ’s love on earth.</p>

<p>The blessed, says St. Thomas, will have a clear understanding of the truths of the faith regarding our salvation: the Incarnation, the divine maternity of Mary, the Church, grace in the sacraments. In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría has written: “Think how pleasing to Our Lord is the incense burnt in his honor. Think also how little the things of the earth are worth; even as they begin, they are already ending. In heaven, instead, a great love awaits you, with no betrayals and no deceptions: the fullness of love, the fullness of beauty and greatness and knowledge. And it will never cloy: it will satiate, yet still you will still want more.”</p>

<p>In heaven, we will see God, and that will fill us with great joy. The extent of this joy will be related to our holiness here on this earth. Yet the mercy of God is so great that he has prepared additional motives for our joy in heaven. Theologians have termed these goods “accidental glory.” They include being in the company of Jesus Christ glorified, Mary our Mother, St. Joseph, the angels—particularly our guardian angel—and all the saints.</p>

<p>We will have the joy of being with our loved ones: parents, brothers and sisters, friends, those people who showed us our vocation. In heaven we will also be capable of acquiring new knowledge using our faculties. The <em>Catechism of the Council of Trent</em> says we shall have the joy of seeing new souls enter heaven. We shall be able to see the progress of our friends on earth. We shall see the fruits of our apostolic efforts and sacrifices. At the time of the Last Judgment, we shall possess our resurrected and glorified body. Accidental glory can increase up to the time of the Last Judgment.</p>

<p>We have to foster the virtue of hope. This will strengthen us in moments of difficulty. So much is at stake. We have to be vigilant in our struggle to be detached from the things of earth. Our Lord has given us ample warning. In St. Luke, he says, “But take heed to yourselves lest your hearts be weighed down with dissipation and drunkenness and the cares of this life… But watch at all times, praying that you may have strength to escape all these things that will take place, and to stand before the Son of Man” (Luke 21:34, 36).</p>

<p>We can also be consoled by the words of Our Lord when he says, “I go to prepare a place for you” (John 14:2). Heaven is our definitive homeland. There we will enjoy the company of Jesus and Mary. Here, we are but wayfarers. When the moment comes when we are to give an account to God, we will not be afraid. Death will only be a change of lodgings. It will come when God wants, being that liberation, that point of entry into the fullness of life. As the Preface for the Mass of the Dead says, “Life is changed, not taken away.” Life changes; it doesn’t come to an end.</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro said, “We have a firm hope that we will live in a new way, very united to the Blessed Virgin as we adore the Most Holy Trinity. This is the reward that awaits us.”</p>

<p>But Our Lord also warned us about the cities that would not be converted. He had spent a great deal of time in the cities along the shores of Lake Gennesaret. He granted countless miracles and favors to these people, and yet they would not be converted. They did not know how to receive the Messiah, about whom they’d heard so much in their synagogues. This was the reason for Our Lord to complain: “Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the mighty works done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago, sitting in sackcloth and ashes. And you, Capernaum, will you be exalted to heaven? You shall be brought down to Hades” (Luke 10:13, 15).</p>

<p>Jesus had sown abundant seed, and precious little of it had borne fruit in those places. Incredible signs had been multiplied, one on top of the other, but the people were not moved to penance. Without this conversion and a life of sacrifice, it was unlikely that they would recognize Christ in their midst. Tyre and Sidon were burdened with less responsibility since they had received fewer graces. The Holy Spirit says, “Today, when you hear his voice, do not harden your hearts” (Heb. 3:7–8).</p>

<p>God speaks to men and women throughout the ages, we’re told by St. Gregory. Christ continues to pass through our cities and towns, showering innumerable blessings upon us. To know how to listen to his will and fulfill it right away is of capital importance in our lives. Nothing is more important. We need to listen with great docility to the invitations that Christ gives in the heart of each individual.</p>

<p>God is not to blame when the faith fails to spring up among men. The reason is to be found in the unreadiness of those who have heard the divine words. Holy Scripture calls this resistance to grace “hardness of heart.” Men sometimes pose intellectual difficulties as inhibiting their growth in faith, when the real problem lies in their lack of desire. Perhaps they just don’t want to abandon some bad habit. They may not be willing to struggle seriously to overcome some defect that impedes their friendship with the Lord.</p>

<p>St. John Mary Vianney says, “Mortification prepares the soul to listen to the Lord and to follow his will.” If we want to reach God, we will have to mortify the soul and all its powers. Mortification can convert our souls into the good soil that will bring the divine seed to fruition. We have to weed out and burn those thorns that tend to flourish in the soul: laziness, egoism, envy, curiosity. This is why the Church recommends that we review our spirit of penance and mortification. This spirit will lead us to be more generous in our imitation of Christ on the Cross.</p>

<p>Closely related to mortification is that happiness which we all find so necessary. Anyone who intends to live their Christian faith seriously needs to put off the “old nature” with its practices. One writer says this “old nature” consists in the variety of bad inclinations we have inherited from Adam. It is the triple concupiscence, which we need to control through the exercise of mortification.</p>

<p>Mortification is not recommended as a negative action. On the contrary, it’s meant to rejuvenate the soul. Mortification makes the soul better disposed to receive supernatural gifts. It also helps us to make reparation for our past sins. This is why we frequently pray to Our Lord to grant us a time of true penance, a time of reformation of our life. By means of the Communion of Saints, we give help and strength to other members of the Mystical Body, which is the Church.</p>

<p>There are three main areas for daily mortification in our ordinary lives. Firstly, there’s the heartfelt and serene acceptance of the contradictions that each day brings. In most cases, this refers to the very small things that crop up unexpectedly and that force us to change our plans or adjust our expectations. An example might be a minor illness that interferes with our performance at work or that affects family life. Other examples could include having to put up with inclement weather, or heavy traffic, or the difficult personality of a colleague at work. These circumstances are beyond our personal control. We have to see them as providing opportunities to love God even more. None of these problems should take away our peace and joy.</p>

<p>If these small contradictions are not accepted for the sake of love, they will only succeed in making people become frustrated and irritable. The great majority of our frustrations come from small contradictions which we have not accepted, rather than from major disasters. One writer says, “The person who lies awake at night, who is gloomy, who is in a bad humor, has usually not suffered some great blow. They’ve simply been unable to turn small setbacks into encounters with God.” Such a one loses many chances to grow in virtue. In addition, when the soul gets into the habit of accepting small reverses as divine favors, it becomes better prepared to face more serious trials in union with Our Lord.</p>

<p>God came into the world to provide a healing remedy for the root of all our rebellion and misery. He destroyed many things as useless obstacles, but chose to leave pain intact. He didn’t take away pain, but he gave it new meaning. One writer says he could have chosen a thousand different ways to accomplish the redemption of the human race, but he chose the Cross. It was by this path that he has led his Mother Mary, Joseph, the apostles, and all the sons of God closer and closer to him. Our Lord allows evils to exist and draws good for our souls from them. We could make a resolution to convert setbacks of whatever type into occasions for our interior growth.</p>

<p>Another area of daily mortification lies in the conscientious carrying out of our duties: the basic material in our struggle for sanctity. It’s there that we find God’s will for us every day. We need to fulfill our duties with hard work, high standards, and much love. St. Josemaría wrote: “The mortification which is most pleasing to God is to be found in order, in punctuality, in care for the small details in whatever we do.” It has to do with the faithful performance of the most insignificant aspects of our vocation, even when it hurts. We need to struggle against the temptation to prefer comfort. We persevere in our work not because we feel like it, but because we know it has to be done. When we work in that frame of mind, we will work with enthusiasm and joy.</p>

<p>The mother of a family will find a thousand reasons to give her home a warm and cheerful atmosphere. The student will offer up his efforts to study well. In this way, tiredness will become one more offering to Our Lord. We can examine our conduct to see whether we complain about our work, grumbling perhaps about something that should be leading us to God.</p>

<p>The third area of our mortification consists in the sacrifices that we make voluntarily in order to please Our Lord: to make ourselves better souls of prayer, in order to overcome temptation, in order to help our friends come closer to God, and ultimately to help our friends prepare for heaven. We should be looking for ways to help others seek sanctity.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Bring out your spirit of mortification in those nice touches of charity, eager to make the way of sanctity in the midst of the world attractive for everyone. Sometimes a smile can be the best proof of a spirit of penance.” We could resolve to overcome our moods and our weariness with the help of our guardian angel.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Psalms: “My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. As a deer longs for flowing streams, so longs my soul for you, O God. When shall I come and behold your face?” (Ps. 42:1–2). These are words that are prayed in the liturgy of the Mass. The deer attempting to quench his thirst with water is the psalmist’s symbolic way of describing the desire for God resident in the heart of an upright person: a thirst and a vehement desire for God. Such is the aspiration of one who is not content to accept worldly success as the satisfaction for human ambitions.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew: “For what will it profit a man if he gains the whole world but forfeits his soul?” (Matt. 16:26). Our Lord’s question forces us to take a radical look at the broad horizon of our life, to which only God gives ultimate meaning. When Christ is passing by, St. Josemaría says the saints were men and women with a great desire to belong to God completely. In spite of their defects, we could each ask ourselves, “Have I a true desire to be a saint?” The answer would most assuredly be in the affirmative, yes. But our reply should not be as to a theoretical question—because for some, holiness is unattainable, something to do with ascetical theology, but not a real goal for them, a living reality.</p>

<p>We want to make it happen with the help of God’s grace. “So longs my soul for you, O God.” We must start by making the desire for holiness flourish in our soul, telling Our Lord that we really want to be with him, that we have that authentic yearning for heaven, that we truly want to be on our way all the time, each day, to the house of the Father. We can ask Our Lady, Queen of Heaven, to guide our steps in a regular way.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Barnabas (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-barnabas-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Barnabas (2026)" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-barnabas-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-barnabas-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>A native of Cyprus, Barnabas was one of the first believers in Jerusalem. It was he who presented St. Paul to the apostles after his conversion and accompanied him on his first apostolic journey. He took part in the Council of Jerusalem and was a figure of great importance in the church at Antioch, which was the first Christian nucleus of considerable size outside of Jerusalem. He was a relative of Mark, on whom he exercised a decisive influence. He returned to his native land, evangelized it, and died a martyr in or about the year 63. His name is mentioned in the first Eucharistic prayer.</p>

<p>From Barnabas, we can learn about the need for having a big heart in the apostolate. The word Barnabas means “son of consolation,” and was the name given by the apostles to Joseph, a Levite of a native of Cyprus, as we’re told in the Acts. St. John Chrysostom comments that this surname must have been inspired by his conciliatory spirit and his sympathetic manner. After the martyrdom of Stephen and the persecution that followed, some Christians went to Antioch, taking with them their faith in Jesus Christ. When word reached the apostles in Jerusalem about the wonders the Holy Spirit was working there, they sent Barnabas to Antioch. “When he came and saw the grace of God,” we’re told in the Acts, “he was glad; and he exhorted them all to remain faithful to the Lord with steadfast purpose; for he was a good man, full of the Holy Spirit and of faith” (Acts 11:23’24).</p>

<p>His zeal for extending the kingdom led him to look for instruments who would be capable of carrying out the enormous task that faced them. He went to Tarsus to look for Paul. And when he found him, he brought him to Antioch. The Acts says that for a whole year they met with the church and taught a large company of people. He had already detected in the new convert those qualities that, with the help of grace, would transform him into the apostle of the Gentiles.</p>

<p>It was Barnabas, we’re told in the Acts, who had presented Paul to the apostles in Jerusalem a short time before, when many Christians were still suspicious of their former persecutor. With the apostle, Barnabas set off on the first missionary journey, whose objective was the island of Cyprus, as we’re told in the Acts, chapter 13. They were accompanied by Mark, Barnabas’s cousin, who left them in Perga, halfway through the journey, and returned to Jerusalem.</p>

<p>When St. Paul was planning a second great missionary journey, Barnabas wanted to take Mark with them again. But Paul thought it better not to take him with them, one who had withdrawn from them in Pamphylia and had not gone with them to the work. This gave rise to a strong dissension between Paul and Barnabas, and that led to them separating one from another.</p>

<p>Barnabas did not afterwards want to leave out his cousin Mark, who was perhaps very young when his strength had failed him at the time of his initial desertion. Barnabas was able to encourage and strengthen Mark and make of him a great evangelist and a most effective collaborator of St. Peter and even of St. Paul, with whom Barnabas was to remain united. Later on, Paul was to express an opinion of the highest esteem for Mark, as though he saw in him a reflection of his sympathetic manner and recalled pleasant memories of Barnabas, the friend of his youth.</p>

<p>St. Barnabas invites us today to have a big heart in the apostolate, so that we will not become easily discouraged by the defects and the falling away of those friends or relatives of ours whom we want to take to Christ. We should not leave them out when they weaken, or perhaps do not respond to our efforts and prayers on their behalf. If sometimes they fail quite obviously, to correspond with our concern for them, this should only lead us to do all we can to treat our friends with still greater affection, with a more ready smile, and to make even greater use than we have done previously of the supernatural means.</p>

<p>We have to learn to understand people so as to be better able to help them. We’re told in the Gospel of St. Matthew, “Preach as you go, saying, ‘The kingdom of heaven is at hand.’ Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse lepers, cast out demons” (Matt. 10:7’8). This is a command of Christ’s that needs to resound in the hearts of all Christians. We read it in today’s Gospel. It’s an apostolate that each one of us has a positive duty to carry out personally in our own surroundings, whether it be in a town, or in a part of a great city, or a very rural place, or the place we work, or at a university or in an office.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>Friends of God</em> says we will come across people who are dead, whom we have to take to receive the sacrament of penance so that they recover their supernatural life. People who are sick, who cannot manage by themselves and need help in order to approach Christ. Lepers who will be cleansed by grace through our friendship with them. People possessed, whose cure will require of us an extraordinary prayer and penance.</p>

<p>As well as constancy, we cannot forget that souls improve with time. We must be aware of the different situations and circumstances of those who need our help. We’re told of St. Barnabas that he was a good man who deserved the surname “son of consolation,” and that he brought peace to many hearts. The Acts of the Apostles tell us, the first time they mention him, of his large-heartedness, a breadth of sympathy which can be seen in his generosity and in his spirit of detachment. We’re told Barnabas sold a field which belonged to him and brought the money and laid it at the feet of the apostles (cf. Acts 4:36’37).</p>

<p>In this way he was able to follow Our Lord with greater freedom. It’s interesting to see how the first Christians functioned, how they maneuvered to help support the apostles in their work of evangelization, with that background economic support that they needed for all their works. There are many similarities in today’s environment.</p>

<p>A generous and detached soul is in a position to give everybody a welcome and to understand the state that souls are in. When people feel they are understood, it’s more likely that they will allow themselves to be helped. In the apostolate, the best means a Christian has of winning people over is precisely this welcoming openness towards others. Accepting them, says St. Augustine, and really appreciating them as they are. For nobody can be known except in terms of the friendship that we bear towards him.</p>

<p>If we are to understand others, we need to look at everything that is positive about them, to see their faults only within the context of their good qualities, whether these good qualities are actual or simply potential. And we have to want to help them. St. Teresa gives us a certain amount of advice. She says, “Let us labor therefore always to consider the virtues and the good qualities that we discern in others, and with our own great sins cover our eyes so that we may see no more of their failings.”</p>

<p>St. Bernard encourages us. He says, “Even if you do see something bad, do not immediately pass judgment on your neighbor, but rather find excuses for him within yourself. Excuse his intentions if you cannot excuse his deeds.” St. Bernard says, “Think that he must have acted out of ignorance or have been overcome by surprise or misfortune.” If his conduct is so obviously bad that it cannot be overlooked, even then try to think in this way and say to yourself, “The temptation must have been very strong.”</p>

<p>We have to learn from Our Lord to live harmoniously with everyone, not to think too much about the way people around us fail to correspond with our efforts or seem deficient in good manners or generosity. Such shortcomings can often be the result of ignorance, of loneliness, or no more than just plain tiredness. The good we set out to do rises above all such mere trifles. If we consider them in God’s presence, they cease to have any real importance.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em> we’re told, “You spend your time with that companion of yours who is scarcely even civil to you, and it’s hard. Keep at it and don’t judge him. He’ll have his reasons, just as you have yours, which you strengthen so as to pray for him more each day.” Those reasons of ours originate in and are centered upon the tabernacle. We’re told in the Psalms: “Sing praises to the Lord with the lyre, with the lyre and the sound of melody! With trumpets and the sound of the horn make a joyful noise before the King, the Lord!” (Ps. 98:5’6).</p>

<p>It’s possible that some Christians allow themselves to be carried away by a bitter zeal, as they see everything around them so seemingly far from God, and see the lifestyle adopted by many people whom they feel should be giving better example. Such zealous Christians try to do good, but they are all the time lamenting the obvious evil they see around them and reproaching society, which according to them should take drastic measures to put an end to such evil.</p>

<p>God does not want us to be like that. He gave His life serenely and peacefully on the cross for all men. It would be a great failure if Christians were to adopt a negative attitude towards the world they have to save. We can see the first generations of those who followed Christ always full of joy, in spite of the frequent tribulations they had to undergo. In the Acts of the Apostles, when St. Luke tries to describe in a few words the little communities that had sprung up everywhere, he tells us that “the church was built up, and walking in the fear of the Lord and in the comfort of the Holy Spirit, it was multiplied” (Acts 9:31).</p>

<p>This is the peace of Christ, which we will never lack if we follow him closely. It’s the peace we have to give to everyone. We have to imitate Our Lord and resolutely reject any attitude tainted with harshness, bitterness, or a desire for condemnation. If as Christians we are to bring joy to the world, how can we think of presenting the good news as something unattractive or condemnatory? How can we judge others if we do not have the necessary facts on which to judge? And above all, if nobody has in any case given us such a mission?</p>

<p>Our attitude towards everyone should always be one of salvation, of peace, of understanding, and of joy. Even towards those who at some time or other may have behaved unjustly towards us. Understanding is real charity. St. Josemaría comments, “When you really achieve it, you will have a great heart which is open to all without discrimination, even with those who have treated you badly. We will put into living practice that advice of Jesus: ‘Come to me all you that are heavy laden and I will give you rest’” (cf. Matt. 11:28).</p>

<p>Each Christian is Christ, who passes by among his own, who lightens their burdens and shows them the way to salvation. We can ask Our Lord that we might have the same love that inspired St. Barnabas to carry the light of the Gospel to the Gentiles.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. John, “You are my friends if you do what I command you” (John 15:14). During their long journey through the desert, the chosen people would set up the tent of meeting outside of their camp. It was a holy site, away from the business of the world. To visit the Lord one had to leave the camp. It was there that Moses went to plead for his people before the Lord. We’re told in the book of Exodus, “Thus the Lord used to speak to Moses face to face, as a man speaks to his friend” (Exod. 33:11).</p>

<p>There are a number of occasions when Scripture reveals God to be a friend of men. Through the prophet Isaiah, God speaks of “Abraham my friend” (Isa. 41:8). The chosen people rely on this friendship to obtain pardon and divine protection. Even more, the whole of revelation tends towards the formation of a people who are friends with God, bound to him by an intimate covenant which is continually renewed. The Second Vatican Council says, “Through this revelation, therefore, the invisible God out of the abundance of his love speaks to men as friends and lives among them, so that he may invite and take them into fellowship with himself” (<em>Dei Verbum</em>, 2).</p>

<p>This divine plan came to fruition in the fullness of time, when the Son of God, the second person of the Blessed Trinity, became man. Friendship presupposes a certain equality and personal contact. But the distance between God and man is infinite. God took on a human nature so that man could take part in his divinity by means of sanctifying grace. Friendship requires mutual love. God reached out to us, and so we were able to correspond. “We love him,” said St. John, “because he first loved us” (1 John 4:19). And Jesus says to us, “As the Father has loved me, so have I loved you; abide in my love” (John 15:9). And Jesus prays to his Father “that the love with which you have loved me may be in them, and I in them” (John 17:26).</p>

<p>All of our apostolate is an apostolate of love, of reaching out in love to the souls that God has placed around us. The Christian’s joy is rooted in the sure knowledge that God loves him. Because God said, “You are my friends” (John 15:14). It can be a great joy for us to call ourselves the friends of God.</p>

<p>In the course of his earthly life, Our Lord was always open to friendship with those who approached him. On some occasions, it was he who took the initiative to bring people to himself, as in the case of Zacchaeus, or that of the Samaritan woman. He was a friend to his disciples, and they were quite aware of his concern. When they didn’t understand something, they would draw close to him with confidence, as is shown in many places in the Gospel. They ask Our Lord, “Explain to us the parable” (Matt. 15:15). Our Lord takes them aside and reveals to them the meaning of his teachings. The disciples joined in Christ’s happiness and in Christ’s worries. He encouraged them whenever necessary.</p>

<p>In a like manner, Our Lord now offers his friendship to us from the tabernacle. All this is very relevant for the personal apostolate with our friends that we have to carry out, similar to what St. Barnabas did in the times of the early Christians. There is a great difference between our temples—the house of God made man—and the tent of meeting. But the same Jesus, the same one who was born of the Blessed Virgin Mary, he who was to die for us on a cross, is present there. Christ was the perfect model of true friendship. He enjoyed speaking with everyone who came to see him, and with those he met along the road. He took advantage of those moments to enter into souls, to raise up hearts to a higher plane.</p>

<p>If the person concerned was well disposed, Jesus would give him or her the grace to be converted and make a commitment to his service. He also wants to speak to us or with us in the time of prayer. For this to happen, we have to be willing to talk and be open to real friendship. He himself has changed us from being servants to being friends. We’re told in St. John, “You are my friends if you do what I command you” (John 15:14). He has given us a model which we should imitate. As a result, we have to give our willingness as a friend, telling him what we have in our soul and paying close attention to what he carries in his heart. Once we open up our soul, he will reveal his own. “I have called you friends, for all that I have heard from my Father I have made known to you” (John 15:15).</p>

<p>St. Ambrose says that a true friend hides nothing from his friend; he reveals all of his spirit. Just as Jesus poured out into the hearts of the apostles the mysteries of the Father. Christians should be men and women with a great capacity for friendship. Because close contact with Jesus prepares us to put aside our egoism, our excessive preoccupation with personal problems. In that way we can be open to all those whom we meet along the way, even though they be of different ages, interests, cultures, or positions. We can thus be open to everybody.</p>

<p>Real friendship is not born of a mere occasional meeting or from simple mutual need of assistance, not even camaraderie. A shared task under the same roof will not necessarily lead to friendship. As we look at the history of one of the great apostles of the early times, we ask St. Barnabas to help us to have that same zeal, that yearning to spread the truths of the kingdom in ever more effective ways all throughout our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Catherine of Siena (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-catherine-of-siena-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Catherine of Siena (2026)" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-catherine-of-siena-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-catherine-of-siena-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Born in Siena in 1347, Catherine Benincasa, as a young girl, joined the Dominican Third Order, and was outstanding for her spirit of prayer and penance. Impelled by a great love for God, for the Church, and for the Roman Pontiff, she worked tirelessly for the peace and unity of the Church in the difficult years of the Avignon captivity. She spent much time at the papal court trying to persuade Pope Gregory XI to return to Rome because that was the place from which Christ’s Vicar on earth ought to rule the Church.</p>

<p>She said, “If I die, let it be known that I die of passion for the Church.” She said this a few days before her death, which took place on the 29th of April, 1380. She wrote very many letters, of which about 400 have survived, along with some prayers and elevations and just one book, <em>The Dialogue</em>, which contains her own account of her intimate conversations with Our Lord.</p>

<p>She was canonized by Pius II, and her veneration spread rapidly throughout the whole of Europe. St. Teresa of Avila said that after God, the person she felt most indebted to for her spiritual progress was St. Catherine of Siena. Pius IX declared her the second patron saint of Italy, together with St. Francis of Assisi. In 1970, Pope Paul VI proclaimed her a Doctor of the Church.</p>

<p>In a homily in 1980, Pope St. John Paul said, although she did not have the benefit of a very formal education—she learned to read and write as an adult and was only 33 years old when she died—St. Catherine of Siena led an extraordinarily full and fruitful life, as if she was in a great hurry to reach the eternal tabernacle of the Blessed Trinity. She is a wonderful example to us of love for the Church and for the Roman Pontiff, whom she described as the “sweet Christ on earth.”</p>

<p>She is also a wonderful example of forthrightness and courage in making herself heard by the people of her time. We can ask her today in our prayer to help us precisely in that endeavor, in doing what’s called the apostolate of public opinion, spreading good ideas, spreading doctrine. It should be a passion of every Christian.</p>

<p>At the time that she was living, it was a particularly troublesome time in the Church. The Popes lived in Avignon in the south of France. Rome, as the center of Christianity, had been allowed to fall into decay. Our Lord made St. Catherine see that it was necessary for the Popes to return to Rome in order to inaugurate the long-awaited and very urgent reform of Church life.</p>

<p>To this end, she prayed tirelessly, practiced penance, and wrote unceasingly to the Pope, to Cardinals, and to the various princes of Christendom. She always professed an unswerving obedience and love for the Roman Pontiff, of whom she wrote, “Anyone who refuses to obey the Christ on earth, who is in the place of the Christ in Heaven, does not participate in the fruit of the blood of the Son of God.”</p>

<p>St. Paul VI wrote, she continuously sent urgent appeals to cardinals, bishops, and priests for the reform of the Church and Christian living, and didn’t shrink from taking them to task seriously, although always with great humility and respect for their dignity because they are ministers of the blood of Christ.</p>

<p>It was principally to the Church’s pastors that she addressed herself again and again, realizing that the spiritual health of the flock depended to a great extent on their own conversion and exemplary behavior. Today, as we celebrate her feast, we could ask St. Catherine to enable us to rejoice with the joys of our mother the Church and to suffer with her sorrows.</p>

<p>We can ask ourselves how hard we pray each day for her pastors, and how generously we offer mortifications and hours of work and bear patiently life’s difficulties, all the sacrifices of which help the Holy Father to carry the tremendous responsibility that God has placed on his shoulders. We can pray for her intercession that the “sweet Christ on earth” may never be short of trustworthy helpers.</p>

<p>In <em>The Furrow</em>, we’re told: “I thought the comment on loyalty you had written to me was very appropriate to all those moments in history which the devil makes it his business to repeat: ‘I carry with me every day in my heart, in my mind, on my lips, an aspiration: Rome.’” That word “Rome” can help our daily presence of God and serve as an expression of our unity with the Roman Pontiff and our prayer with him. It can also help us to increase our love for the Church.</p>

<p>St. Catherine had an admirably feminine temperament, at the same time displaying an unusual drive and energy. A feature somehow distinguishing those women who are capable of undergoing great sacrifices and of taking their place beside the Cross of Christ. She refused to tolerate any faintheartedness in the service of God. She was utterly convinced that when the salvation of souls was at stake, being unduly tolerant or understanding with mediocrity was totally unacceptable, because it is, in effect, a concession to laziness or cowardice.</p>

<p>“Enough of this soft soap,” she cried out. “All it does is cause the members of Christ’s spouse to stink.”</p>

<p>She was always fundamentally optimistic. She would not allow herself to become downhearted if, in spite of having done all she could, things did not work out as she had hoped. Throughout her life, she had a profoundly serious and gentle manner. Her followers always remembered her radiant expression and her open gaze. Spotlessly neat and well-groomed in her person, she was fond of flowers and loved to sing as she moved about.</p>

<p>When an important person of the time went at a friend’s insistence to interview her, he expected to meet a woman with downcast eyes and a diffident manner, and was greatly surprised to find himself in the presence of a young lady who greeted him warmly with a welcoming smile as if he had been a brother returning from a long journey.</p>

<p>Eventually, the Pope did return to Rome in 1377, but died a year later. His successor’s election marked the beginning of what is known in history as the Great Western Schism, an upheaval that caused tremendous division and suffering in the Church. St. Catherine spoke and wrote to cardinals and kings, to princes and bishops, but all in vain. Utterly worn out and in great sorrow, she offered herself to God as a victim for the Church.</p>

<p>One day in January 1380, as she was praying at St. Peter’s tomb, she experienced something that other saints have also shared. She felt upon her shoulders the immense weight of the Church. Her agony lasted just a few months. On the 29th of April, around midday, God called her to his glory.</p>

<p>On her deathbed, she directed to God this moving prayer. She said, “O eternal God, receive the sacrifice of my life on behalf of the mystical body of the holy Church. I have nothing else to give except what you have given me.”</p>

<p>A few days earlier, she had told her confessor, “I assure you that if I die, the sole cause of my death is the zeal and love for the Church which burns me up and consumes me.”</p>

<p>We can pray to her today for this incandescent love for our mother the Church, which is an inseparable concomitant of being close to Christ. Our own times, too, are days of trial and sorrow for Christ’s mystical body. We have to ask Our Lord with an unceasing clamor, said St. Josemaría, to shorten them, to look mercifully on his Church, and to grant once again his supernatural light to the souls of her shepherds and of all the faithful.</p>

<p>We can offer the thousand little incidents of each day for the welfare of Christ’s mystical body. God will surely bless us for it, and Our Lady, Mother of the Church, will pour out his grace generously upon us.</p>

<p>St. Catherine’s example teaches us to speak forthrightly and courageously whenever matters affecting the Church, the Roman Pontiff, or the good of souls are at stake. We will often have the serious obligation to defend the truth. In this, we can learn a lot from St. Catherine. She never gave way in the fundamentals because she placed all her trust in God.</p>

<p>In the letter of St. John, we read that “this is the message we have heard from him and proclaim to you: that God is light and in him is no darkness at all” (1 John 1:5). This is where the first Christians and the saints of all times got their strength. What they proclaimed was not some doctrine of their own creation, but rather the message of Christ, handed on from each generation to the next.</p>

<p>The power of this truth transcends the changing fashions and attitudes of mankind’s history. We have to learn to speak about the things of God more and more naturally and straightforwardly, but at the same time with all the conviction that Christ has placed in our hearts.</p>

<p>The Roman Pontiffs have often denounced the systematic attempts by certain sectors of the media to misrepresent the truth by passing over in silence the sufferings of Catholics for the faith or their noble endeavors for good. Faced with this situation, each one of us in his or her place in society has to act as a mouthpiece for the truth.</p>

<p>Some popes have described the playing down of the contribution of Catholics to the literary, scientific, religious, or social life of nations as a conspiracy of silence. Often, the very fact that something is Catholic is enough to ensure that it never gets mentioned in the media.</p>

<p>We all have an important part to play in the apostolate of public opinion. At times, our personal sphere of influence may extend no further than the neighbors or friends we visit or who call on us, or we may be in a position to clarify some doctrinal issue by writing a letter to the editor of a newspaper, or by making a telephone call to a radio program where audience reaction on some controversial topic has been invited.</p>

<p>We may also have the opportunity to reply constructively to the questions of a survey or to recommend a good book to someone. We have to overcome any temptation to discouragement, thinking perhaps that we can do very little, because just as the current of a great river is fed by a network of tiny streams which in their turn have been formed drop by drop, our opportunity to contribute to the river of truth should never be omitted. That was how the first Christians started spreading the Gospel.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “To think of Christ’s death means to be invited to face up to our everyday tasks with complete sincerity and to take the faith that we profess seriously. It has to be an opportunity to go deeper into the depths of God’s love so as to be able to show that love to men with our words and with our deeds.”</p>

<p>In his encyclical <em>Evangelium Vitae</em>, the Gospel of Life, Pope John Paul has a strong phrase where he says we have to be unconditionally pro-life. We can ask Our Lord for the grace to see the consequences of that in our daily life: in our conversations with people, in the efforts we make to spread the truth about abortion, the truth about the sacredness of every human life, so that we turn society around. We have to bring about a great revolution in this area. A lot of this is tied up also to the truth about conjugal love.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen used to say that this world is tearing up the photographs of the family, of marriage, of purity, modesty, chastity, virginity, but he said the Church is keeping the negatives. In each successive generation she reveals those negatives to different generations of people: the truth about conjugal love, the truth about marriage, about the family, about purity, modesty, chastity, virginity, all of which have to do with human love. We have to spread this truth in all sorts of ways, in season and out of season.</p>

<p>Also in <em>The Forge</em>, we’re told: “Make sure that your lips are the lips of a Christian, for that is what you are and should be at all times. Speak those compelling, supernatural words which will move and encourage and will show your committed attitude to life.”</p>

<p>I know somebody here in Kenya who was very limited physically, suffering from multiple sclerosis, but used to listen to the radio, and one time heard a program that was very pro-family. The program gave a certain telephone number that you would call if you wanted to react to the things that were being said in the program.</p>

<p>He took up the phone and called the program and said, “Well, I just want to say I was very impressed with your TV program. It was wonderful to hear those ideas, so pro-family.” Very short, brief phone call.</p>

<p>The following day, the compere of the show called back to thank him for calling into the program. Sometimes we think the whole world is calling into those programs, but it may often be that nobody is ever calling. He said, “I had a bit of a battle with my producer to give this pro-family orientation to this program, and it was an uphill struggle. But your call has meant an awful lot to me in terms of support, and also in helping me to win over my producer.”</p>

<p>Sometimes we don’t know the impact of the little things we do: the email that we may send to a newspaper, or the phone call we may make to a radio or TV program. We can ask St. Catherine of Siena that she might open up new horizons to us, of influence. Every Christian is called to have an influence. Hopefully, that influence can increase with the passage of time.</p>

<p>Possibly like that man that I’m mentioning, in our later years, we may not be so active, we may not be able to do many physical things, but sometimes our capacity to influence can be much greater to spread around good ideas. We can ask St. Catherine today to open up avenues of influence for us, to have our antennae out to see where we can influence more. We can ask her for the gift of writing or of speaking, or ask her for that grace to spend a few minutes each day writing a few ideas or a few words in response to an article in the newspaper. We’re here to create a river of truth.</p>

<p>They say you learn to swim by swimming. We might never have ever written a letter to a newspaper; we might never have phoned a TV program or a radio program. But we can learn to do these things. We can develop talents with the passage of time.</p>

<p>It’s also good to see if we’re reading good newspapers. If we find that the newspaper that we’re reading is very alien to Christian virtues, well maybe we should read a different newspaper, or maybe forget about any newspaper, and just get our news on social media. The same thing with articles or novels. Read good material. Read material that increases your vocabulary. Very often, St. Josemaría would write down a phrase or a word that he’d come across in an article and share it with people in a get-together. He was always attentive to seek out those phrases or words because he said, “These are the vehicles that we use to communicate the truth.”</p>

<p>As followers of Christ, we have to become expert communicators. There’s a Roman writer of the fourth century who said that clarity of expression lights up the beauty of the world. We can ask St. Catherine that we might grow in our clarity of expression, to find those words, those phrases. Other people have said that we become what we read. We should be careful with what we read. We may have little time to read, and so we should make sure that what we read is good, and use all our reading for apostolic purposes. Have this in mind when choosing to read: Is what I’m reading going to help me in the living out of my Christian vocation today?</p>

<p>We may not be good writers at the present moment, but it’s a talent we can acquire so as to have a greater influence with time.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Faithful in little things. My son, your job is not just to save souls, but to bring them to holiness day after day, giving to each moment, even to apparently ordinary moments, the dynamic echo of eternity.”</p>

<p>This can also lead us to see as part of that apostolate of public opinion the importance of doing apostolate with journalists, or people who by their profession have a capacity to influence. We can develop friendships with these people, channel good ideas to them. We might be very hidden and silent individuals, but we could have friends or acquaintances around us who may be in a very strong position to influence. We may have their ear because they see that we speak sense, or what we say is true and good.</p>

<p>Another way of being involved in the apostolate of public opinion could be to involve ourselves in citizens’ watch groups, vigilating media, or other pro-family groups, pro-life groups. A good question to ask ourselves is: what national and international organizations do I belong to? Am I in a position to increase that sphere of influence? Society very much needs that apostolate.</p>

<p>Establishing personal contact with journalists, photographers, filmmakers—these can be very interesting areas of apostolate. This apostolate comes to be more important all the time because of the importance of the media in a world which is more globalized all the time.</p>

<p>Some people need to be more prepared than others in this area, but we all need to be aware and have some form of preparation. We need to be able to explain certain key ideas. Sometimes we need to have slogans ready. Instead of people talking about “safe sex,” maybe we should talk about “smart sex”: having no sexual partner before you get married, and after you get married having only one partner. That’s smart sex.</p>

<p>There are also concrete ways to transmit our love for the Church. In one of his early encyclicals, <em>The Mission of the Redeemer</em>, John Paul II said, “The first Areopagus of the modern age is the world of communications.” The Areopagus in Athens was the sort of central place of culture, of business, of finance, of exchange of ideas, of interaction. He says the first Areopagus of the modern age is the world of communication, which is unifying humanity and turning it into what is known as a global village.</p>

<p>The means of social communication have become so important as to be for many the chief means of information and education, of guidance and inspiration in their behavior as individuals, families, and within society at large.</p>

<p>One great idea to try and have, as we see from this quotation, is to read the encyclicals of the Popes in recent years. The Catholic Church has an awful lot to say about modern society, and is continually commenting in order to Christianize. There are some great words and phrases there, and great ideas, all of which help us to put Christ in the middle of society, to place values there.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says, the following comment, which caused me great sorrow, will also make you reflect: “I see very clearly why there is a lack of resistance, and why what resistance there is to iniquitous laws is so ineffective, for above, below, and in the middle, there are many people, so very many, who just follow the crowd.”</p>

<p>This is why, as Christians, we’re called to be leaders, to blaze a trail, to have an influence. Also, we shouldn’t have a sort of siege mentality in thinking that the media are against us. We should rather have the idea that we are the media. We are the ones who have to influence the course of culture and of society, of thinking and of ideas.</p>

<p>At a very early stage, St. Josemaría saw the growing importance of media, the importance of spreading doctrine, of having the light of Christ in public opinion, of having a dominant passion to spread that doctrine. There are immense apostolic opportunities.</p>

<p>He liked to say that in matters of education and marriage, we have to go all the way because those areas are so key for the health of society.</p>

<p>Again in <em>The Forge</em>, he says: “I insist: ask God to grant us, his children, the ‘gift of tongues,’ the gift of making ourselves understood by all. You can find the reason why I want this ‘gift of tongues’ in the pages of the Gospel, which abound in parables, in examples which materialize the doctrine and illustrate spiritual truths, without debasing or degrading the word of God. Everyone, both the learned and the less learned, finds it easier to reflect on and understand God’s message through these human images.”</p>

<p>I was at a conference in Singapore many years ago, of Catholic medical guilds of Asia, where the speaker—possibly at that time the top Catholic obstetrician in the world, Professor Robert Walley of MaterCare International—held up two documents. He said, “Here are two documents about two organizations in the world, talking about the same thing but saying completely different things. On the one hand,” he said, “we have the United Nations document on women, and on the other hand, we have the Catholic Church’s statement which is all about mothers, <em>Evangelium Vitae</em>.”</p>

<p>The United Nations, he says, talks about women, women, women. The Catholic Church talks about mothers, mothers, mothers. He asked all the doctors present there for the 21st century to try and do something for mothers because the maternal mortality rate in the developing world is way behind the maternal mortality rate in the developed world. It’s one of the scandals of modern medicine.</p>

<p>We have to try and promote that idea: more awareness of mothers. We have to try and answer the social discredit of chastity, to remind people there is no such thing as a safe abortion because somebody always dies in an abortion.</p>

<p>The apostolate of public opinion has many forms and expressions. When we hear a good idea, or somebody is doing something good, it can be good to think, “Well, how can I get that message out? How can I spread it around?” Because we’ve a message that has to reach every last person in society. Every opportunity is important. We’re involved in the evangelization of culture.</p>

<p>When the angel announced to the shepherds, they said, “We bring you good tidings of great joy which shall be to all the people” (Luke 2:10). Very beautiful words. We could ask St. Catherine of Siena that she might help us be more effective in bringing those good tidings of great joy to all the people.</p>

<p>Catherine, may you help us to share something of your love for the Church and for the Roman Pontiff, along with a holy desire to make the doctrine of Jesus Christ known everywhere, imaginatively and lovingly, always trying to see the positive side of things, and not missing a single opportunity.</p>

<p><em>Let me ask Our Lady, in St. Catherine’s own words: “To you I have recourse, O Mary, offering you my supplication for the sweet spouse of Christ and for his Vicar on earth, may he always have the light to rule the Holy Church prudently and with discernment.”</em></p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Justin</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-justin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Justin" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-justin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-justin/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Justin was born in the region of Samaria at the beginning of the second century. Like some other thinkers of his day, he opened a school of philosophy in Rome. After his conversion, he carried out an effective apostolate from the school. He defended the Christian faith with his knowledge in times that were difficult for Christianity. The <em>Apologia</em> addressed to Emperors Antoninus and Marcus Aurelius have been preserved. He died a martyr in Rome during the persecution of the latter emperor. Because of the effort he made to defend the faith with his learning, with his knowledge, and for the exemplary value that this has for everyone, Pope Leo XIII extended his liturgical feast to the universal Church.</p>

<p>To start with, the faith took root among simple working people. People who worked in wool, with wool, soldiers in the ranks, blacksmiths. The many inscriptions that have been found in the catacombs tell us of a great variety of occupations and trades: innkeepers, barbers, tailors, joiners, weavers. One of these inscriptions depicts a charioteer mounted on his chariot with a crown in his right hand and in his left the palm of martyrdom.</p>

<p>Very soon, Christianity reached all social classes. Already in the second century, there were Christians who were senators like Apollonius, chief magistrates like the consul Liberal, lawyers of the Roman forum like Tertullian, and philosophers like St. Justin, whose feast we celebrate today, who was converted to Christianity when he was already well on in years.</p>

<p>Christians do not separate themselves from their fellow citizens. They dress just like everyone else of their time and country. They claim their civic rights and they carry out their duties. They attend state schools like everyone else, and they are not ashamed to profess their faith, even though for a long time, the pagan environment in which they lived was very much against the good news. We see them defending the faith, their right, their right to live it, and be at the same time Roman citizens like everybody else. With admirable constancy, whether in the course of an ordinary conversation in the marketplace or in the forum, or in the more formal setting of a defense of the faith with the weapons of the intellect, which was what St. Justin and the others did in the apologies for Christianity.</p>

<p>All of them, each one in his own place, knew how to give a serene testimony of Jesus Christ, which was the best of all apologies for the faith. One of these living examples of the faith has come down to us through a piece of graffiti that is still preserved. On the Palatine, the hill on which stood the emperor’s palace and the villas of Roman noblemen, there was a school where pageboys of the imperial court were trained. Among the pupils there, there must have been a Christian called Alexamenos, because somebody had made a drawing on the wall representing a man with a donkey’s head nailed to a roughly hewn cross with a human figure alongside it. Beside the drawing can be read the inscription: “Alexamenos adores his God.” The young Christian, with valor and pride in his faith, had written underneath in reply: “Alexamenos is faithful.”</p>

<p>This graffiti was typical of the sort of slander that was frequently circulated about the Christians. The man in the street heard an abundance of rumors, gossip, nonsense, and incredible stories. Among the more cultured classes, expressions like those transmitted to us by Tertullian were disdainfully passed from mouth to mouth. For example, that Caius Seius is a good man; what a pity he’s a Christian. Another important personage said, “I am indeed surprised that Lucius Titius, a really intelligent man too, should have suddenly become a Christian.” And Tertullian comments, it doesn’t occur to them to wonder whether Caius is a good man and Lucius is intelligent precisely because they are Christians, or whether they have become Christians precisely because one man is good and the other intelligent.</p>

<p>St. Justin knows how to talk about the greatness of the Christian faith and how to compare it with all the different ways of thinking and ideologies fashionable in his day. He points out nobody believes Socrates to the point of giving his life for his teaching. However, not only philosophers and men of learning, but also lowly workers and totally uneducated men and women have believed in Christ. Such people have taken no notice of the opinion of the world at large. They have scorned fear and even death itself. Justin himself was later to die giving witness to his faith.</p>

<p>God asks us to be every bit as steadfast as he was, whatever our condition in life. Even if we sometimes find ourselves in an environment that is completely opposed to Christ’s teaching. The greater the adversity, often the more opportunity there is for apostolate. In times of persecution and major tribulation, Christians continued to attract others to the faith. One writer says the very difficulties they faced were the opportunity for carrying out an even more intense apostolate, which was given greater credence than ever by the good example and fortitude of the Christians. Their words took on a new strength, the strength of the Cross.</p>

<p>Martyrdom was a kind of testimony that was filled with supernatural vigor and had great apostolic effectiveness. Sometimes the martyr’s very executioner embraced the Christian faith. If we are really faithful to Christ, it is possible that we shall encounter difficulties of different kinds, from open slander and persecution to the realization that a door that should be open is closed to us. We may be relegated to a less prestigious job. Perhaps there will be sarcasm or superficial comments. But we are told in St. Matthew, and can be consoled by the words, that “the disciple is not greater than his master” (Matt. 10:24).</p>

<p>A Christian’s life and the meaning he gives to his existence, whether we like it or not, is bound to clash with a world that has fixed its heart on material things. Such difficulties afford us particularly appropriate opportunities for doing an effective apostolate. Teaching the true nature of the Church, spreading writings that can clarify even the most controversial issues, speaking out clearly about Christ and the Christian life.</p>

<p>The first Christians won through by their determination, and they taught us the way. Their unconditional fidelity to Christ overcame the pagan atmosphere that surrounded them. One writer says although they were immersed in the hostile mass of men, they did not look for isolation as a remedy against contagion and as a guarantee of their survival. They knew they were God’s leaven. In the end, their silent and effective action gave shape to that very mass.</p>

<p>In particular, they knew how to be serenely present in their world, how not to despise its values or to scorn any earthly realities. If at times of misunderstanding or calumny, we remain firm and constant in the personal apostolate that as Christians we are obliged to carry out, fruits will come to the Church in the most distant and remote corners of the world. In places where it seemed impossible that any results could be achieved. The more clearly the Cross can be seen, the more effective will be the apostolate.</p>

<p>We always have to live charity, particularly with those who may have no regard for us. Malicious gossip, calumny, and even martyrdom itself were unable to make the Christians retreat and resign themselves to being set apart from other citizens in some kind of ghetto, or feel themselves exiled from their own social milieu. Even during the most difficult times of persecution, the presence of Christians in the world was a driving, active force.</p>

<p>Christians defended their right to be consistent with their faith. Intellectuals like St. Justin defended it by their writings, which showed knowledge and common sense. St. Josemaría comments, mothers of families defended it by their friendly conversations and by the example of their lives. It was in the midst of this storm of contradiction that Christians lived the new commandment of Jesus with even more determination. It was love that enabled them to make their way through that corrupt pagan world.</p>

<p>This practice of charity is, more than anything else, what seals us with a special seal in the eyes of many. Tertullian quotes, “See how they love one another, they say, for they themselves mutually hate one another. And how those Christians are ready to die for one another, while they themselves are ready rather to put each other to death.”</p>

<p>The early Christians did not hold a grudge against those who ill-treated them in any way. Like our first brothers in the faith, we too have always striven to drown evil in an abundance of good. In the catechesis that he carried out during his short pontificate, John Paul I recalled the exemplary story of the 16 Carmelite nuns who were martyred during the French Revolution and beatified by Pius X. It seems that during their trial, it was suggested that they should be condemned to death for fanaticism. One of them asked the judge, “What does fanaticism mean?” He replied, “Your foolishness in belonging to religion.”</p>

<p>After the sentence had been pronounced and they were being led to the scaffold, they sang sacred hymns. When they reached the place of execution, one by one they knelt before the Prioress to renew their vow of obedience. Afterwards, they intoned the <em>Veni Creator</em>. Their singing became weaker as the successive heads of nuns fell under the guillotine. The Prioress was the last to go up. Her last words were, “Love will always be victorious. Love can overcome everything.”</p>

<p>The charity of the first Christians was aimed first and foremost at strengthening in the faith their weakest brethren, those who had only recently been converted, and all those who are most in need. On almost every page of the <em>Acts of the Martyrs</em>, specific details are related of this concern for the fidelity of those who were least strong. We must not fail to do the same in times of adversity, calumny, and persecution. We must support and wrap our cloaks around those who, owing to their age or other special circumstances, have greater need of being fortified. Our steadfastness and cheerfulness at such times will be of great help to others.</p>

<p>We can learn from the early Christians to have the courage to follow Christ in whatever environment we are in. When Jesus began his public life, many of his neighbors and relatives took him for a madman. On his first visit to Nazareth, his relatives deny seeing in him anything supernatural or extraordinary. In their comments, one can see that their envy is barely concealed. “Where did this man get this wisdom and these mighty works? Is not this the carpenter’s son?” (Matt. 13:54–55). And they took offense at him.</p>

<p>Right from the start, Jesus faced a steady stream of insults and abuse, born of cowardly egoism because he proclaimed the world without human respect. This ill treatment increased steadily with time until it broke out into calumny and open persecution, culminating in the death sentence. Christ’s fortitude was recognized even by his enemies, who said, “Teacher, we know that you are true and teach the way of God truthfully, and care for no man, for you do not regard the position of men” (Matt. 22:16).</p>

<p>Christ asked his disciples to imitate him in this practice. Christians should foster and defend their well-earned professional, moral, and social prestige because it belongs to the essence of human dignity. This prestige is also an important component of our personal apostolate. And yet we should not forget that our conduct will meet with opposition from those who openly oppose Christian morality and those who practice a watered-down version of the faith.</p>

<p>It is possible that Our Lord will ask us the sacrifice of our good name and even of life itself. With the help of his grace, we will struggle to do his will. Everything we have belongs to the Lord. Each Christian has to put aside any fears of rocking the boat should his upright conduct provoke criticism or rejection. Whoever, out of human respect, would hide their Christian identity in the midst of a pagan environment would merit the denunciation of Jesus when he says, “Whoever denies me before men, I also will deny before my Father who is in heaven” (Matt. 10:33).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that confessing our faith is a requirement for being his disciple, no matter what the consequences might be. This is the way many of Christ’s first disciples conducted themselves. In a way, we’re told Joseph of Arimathea and Nicodemus were hidden disciples of the Lord. But they stepped forward as Christians at the hour when all seemed lost, when to be a friend of the Galilean seemed most unlikely. They are courageous in the face of authority, declaring their love for Christ boldly in the hour of cowardice. This is how the apostles behaved before the Sanhedrin and the pagan persecutions.</p>

<p>“For the word of the cross is folly,” says St. Paul, “to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is the power of God” (1 Cor. 1:18). As the dauntless St. Paul wrote to his disciple Timothy, “For God did not give us a spirit of timidity but a spirit of power and love and self-control. Do not be ashamed of testifying to Our Lord” (2 Tim. 1:7–8). These are words that are directed at us today, as we seek to be faithful to the Master, even though the environment may seem to be against us.</p>

<p>The life of a Christian should develop in a fairly ordinary manner, in normal circumstances. Yet frequently this way of life will stand in stark contrast to other lifestyles more or less Christian, as well as to a kind of behavior which is beneath human dignity and is therefore anti-Christian. In these latter cases, it is not surprising that the contrast would be striking. We should not be surprised that non-believers or the indifferent may unjustly criticize a follower of Christ, perhaps even to the extent of resorting to ridicule.</p>

<p>The same thing happened to Our Lord. In the course of day-to-day living, we’re probably not talking about suffering physical harm for the sake of the Gospel. But what a Christian may well have to put up with are rumors and calumnies, mockery, discrimination at work, the loss of economic opportunities, or superficial relationships. At times, perhaps in our family or among friends, it may be necessary to exercise supernatural fortitude in order to be consistent with our beliefs.</p>

<p>In these uncomfortable circumstances, we may be tempted to take the easy way out and give in. By such means, we could avoid rejection, misunderstanding, and ridicule. We could become concerned at the thought of losing friends, of closing doors which we will later be unable to reopen. This is the temptation to be influenced by human respect, hiding one’s true identity and forsaking our commitment to live as a disciple of Christ. In such difficult circumstances, the Christian ought not to wonder which path is the most opportune to follow, but rather which path is the most faithful to Christ.</p>

<p>Our desire for popularity is the direct consequence of self-love. It may be that the Lord is waiting for us in just this kind of sacrifice, and this is the time we must choose between his way and our own. This choice may ultimately be expressed by our silence, by a few words, by a gesture or an attitude. Our behavior will be the proving ground of our deepest convictions. This firmness in the faith is often an excellent testimony to the beliefs of the Christian. In some cases, it can cause people to begin their return to the house of the Father.</p>

<p>For many who begin to follow Christ, the necessity for this sacrifice is one of the major obstacles in their path. According to the saintly Curé of Ars, there is no doubt about it. Do you know, he said, what the devil’s first temptation is to the person who wants to serve God with dedication? It is human respect. We all have an inner aversion from being put to shame before others. But this sacrifice, if we make it, will be the cause of our greatest joy: to take a stand for Jesus Christ whenever and wherever the circumstances require it. We can be assured that we will never regret being true to our Christian beliefs.</p>

<p>There are many people who are in need of our good example in this area. Many people around us are waiting for clear testimony to the Christian faith. We can accomplish an awful lot by our good example. How much is the world in need of Christian workers who are friendly, cordial, firm in the faith? Occasionally we hear of a daring article in which somebody attacks the teaching of the Pope or defends abortion or artificial contraception. Nevertheless, the real daring in our age is to defend the teaching authority of the Roman Pontiff in what pertains to faith and morals. To defend the right to life of every person. To have a large family if that is God’s will. To defend the indissolubility of marriage. Many wavering hearts have been fortified by one person’s loyalty to principle.</p>

<p>In order to have the courage necessary to overcome our fears, we need to rely on God’s help. We can’t allow that God be removed from society or put in parentheses, that misguided men relegate the universal moral law to the closet of individual conscience. It shouldn’t surprise us that we may be tempted to pass unnoticed in certain disagreeable situations. St. Peter himself, after having been confirmed as the head of the Church, after having received the Holy Spirit, gave in to the human respect of his Jewish brethren. It took no less a man than St. Paul to correct him in this matter.</p>

<p>This famous confrontation, far from disproving the holiness and unity of the Church, in fact demonstrates the perfect unity of the apostles, the respect that St. Paul had for the visible head of the Church, and the great humility of St. Peter in changing his position. We can help one another in similar circumstances by practicing fraternal correction with our fellow citizens, as was done in the early days of the Church.</p>

<p>Our Lord gives us good example on how we should conduct ourselves. From that sad day in Nazareth, he knew that many people were not in agreement with him. Yet he never based his actions upon the opinions of men. Only one thing matters to Our Lord: the will of his Father. He never gave up curing people on the Sabbath, even though spies were watching him. Jesus knew what he wanted to do, and he knew that from the start. We never see him have second thoughts or hesitate, much less reverse a decision.</p>

<p>Christ asks us to follow him with that same kind of fortitude. It is his own method, quite personal to himself, that he here enjoins on his disciples. Unconsidered, overhasty action, vacillation, any coming to terms or compromising, these are not for him. One writer says his whole life and being are a yes and a no, nothing else. Jesus is always the complete man, always prepared, for he never speaks or acts except out of his whole clear consciousness and his own firm will. We can ask Jesus for the strength to guide us at all times to do God’s will, unchanging will, rather than the fickle will of man.</p>

<p>As we finish our prayer, we go say to Our Lady a prayer that the first Christians often said: “We fly to your patronage, O holy Mother of God. Despise not our petitions in our necessities, but deliver us from all dangers, ever glorious and blessed Virgin.”</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this time of prayer. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thanksgiving Day (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/thanksgiving-day-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thanksgiving Day (2026)" /><published>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-15T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/thanksgiving-day-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/thanksgiving-day-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen. My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Today the Church invites the faithful to give thanks for the many blessings God our Father has bestowed on us. We also ask Our Lord to grant us generously the material and spiritual favors that we need. In the communion antiphon, we’re told: <em>You have crowned the year with your bounty, the hope of all the ends of the earth.</em></p>

<p>The Temporas are days the Church sets aside for thanksgiving and petition to God. They traditionally occur after the harvest is taken up. For many, it’s an annual occasion to rest and a favorable time to ask for Our Lord’s help to begin our normal work activities and the interior life afresh.</p>

<p>St. Teresa says we have a great deal to be thankful for and still stand in great need. Expressing gratitude and asking for specific graces are two ways we can daily pray to God our Father. In the first place, we need to recognize the gifts Our Lord has given us. We will not learn how to love if we are not grateful.</p>

<p>The first reading of the Mass further reminds us of the importance of gratitude to God for all His blessings. The Book of Deuteronomy says, “Be careful not to forget the Lord your God. Do not neglect his commandments and decrees and statutes I enjoin on you today. When you have eaten your fill, built and lived in fine houses, increased your herds and flocks, your silver and gold and your property, may you not become haughty of heart and unmindful of the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of slavery in Egypt, guided you through the vast and terrible desert with its serpents and scorpions and parched ground, and brought forth water for you from the flinty rock” (Deut. 8:11–14).</p>

<p>We find Christ in the Gospel constantly giving thanks to God. And He is our model. When raising Lazarus from the dead, Jesus exclaims, “Father, I give you thanks that you’ve heard me” (John 11:41). On the occasion of another miracle, Jesus took the loaves and after giving thanks, distributed them and the fishes to those who were reclining. At the institution of the Eucharist, Our Lord gave thanks before blessing the bread of the wine.</p>

<p>In the truest sense, said St. John Paul, we can say that the prayer of the Lord and His entire earthly existence became a revelation of the fundamental truth: “Every good and perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights” (James 1:17). Thanksgiving is the source of all blessings from on high. “Let us give thanks to the Lord our God” is the invitation the Church places at the center of the Eucharistic liturgy.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, St. Josemaría says nothing is more appropriate than to give thanks to the Lord each day of our lives. We cannot forget. The best way of showing our gratitude to God is by becoming passionately aware that we are His children. Today, we especially recall our divine filiation as we give thanks to God and praise Him.</p>

<p>Our entire life is a gift that we have received from God through no merit of our own. For this reason, our habitual disposition of thanksgiving to God should overflow in acts of thanksgiving throughout the day. We are reminded in the preface of the Mass: “Father, all-powerful and ever-living God, we do well always and everywhere to give you thanks through Jesus Christ our Lord.”</p>

<p>We can recall St. Paul’s principal reproach to the pagans as well: “Having known God, they did not honor him as God or give thanks to him” (Rom. 1:21). We need to be continually thankful to the Lord for the benefits we have received during the past year, some we are aware of, but perhaps even more valuable benefits have come to us without our recognition of them. These graces include rescue from dangers of body and soul, the making of new friends who play a part in our salvation, and even apparent setbacks like sickness or professional failure.</p>

<p>We should enjoy great peace, since we should know that God will draw abundant fruit from circumstances and events that present themselves as unwelcome and are seemingly counterproductive. We later understand these very occasions to be divine caresses. These veiled graces are like the wood that God showed Moses; when he threw it into the sea, the salt water was changed to fresh.</p>

<p>The founder of Opus Dei used to recommend giving thanks to Our Lord for all of his gifts, including those we are unaware of. Possibly one of our greatest embarrassments at the Last Judgment will come from knowing the enormous number of divine gifts that we did not appreciate as such. There may also be our unwarranted resentment of what seemed to be indifference to our prayers. At least then, though finally, but with shame, offer thanks, since we will know the Lord has the goodness not to answer our many foolish requests.</p>

<p>It’s possible, said one writer, that if He had granted our misguided petitions, we would have heard the same reprimand the rich man heard: “Remember, son, in your lifetime you received many good things” (Luke 16:25). How surprised many will be to learn that with more supernatural outlook, they could have understood the providence of God at work in the midst of both good and apparently ill fortune.</p>

<p>Furthermore, our present gratitude is a foretaste of Heaven and Purgatory. After death, we’ll thank God for the times of tribulation He permitted us to undergo during our life. We will perceive in every occasion of suffering the tender affection of a Father who wants His children to be purified and to arrive all the more quickly at His side in glory. In the end, we will thank Him above all because He will have granted us the opportunity for true and fruitful penance.</p>

<p>May we thank the Lord always and everywhere, but especially during Mass, which is the supreme act of thanksgiving. In today’s liturgy, we pray: “We offer you, Father, this sacrifice of praise and thanksgiving for the gifts you’ve granted us. Help us to recognize them as the benefits we have received from you through no merit of our own.”</p>

<p>Since we’re in need of a great deal of assistance in order to advance, we can join constant petition to our continual thanksgiving. Although Our Lord grants us many graces without our asking for them, He permits other graces to come to us in proportion to the fervor of our prayer. Since we don’t know the measure of petition His unfathomable providence expects from us, it’s necessary to keep praying with intensity. We’re told in St. Luke we must pray and not lose heart (cf. Luke 18:1).</p>

<p>In the Gospel of today’s Mass, Our Lord grants us the full assurance that everything we ask for that is in our best interests will be granted. God Himself gives His word: “Ask and it shall be given you. Seek and you will find. Knock and it shall be opened to you. For everyone who asks receives, and he who seeks finds, and to him who knocks it shall be opened” (Matt. 7:7–8).</p>

<p>There’s another reason to persevere in prayer: the more we petition Christ, the more our friendship with God matures. In human affairs, it’s necessary to ask a powerful person a favor; we seek a bond of union, an opportune moment, perhaps when the one approached is in a good mood, before making our request. With the Lord, however, we find Him ever ready to hear us.</p>

<p>“What man is there among you who, if his son asks him for a loaf, will hand him a stone? Or if he asks for a fish, will hand him a serpent? Therefore, if you, evil as you are, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father in Heaven give good things to those who ask him?” (Matt. 7:9–11).</p>

<p>We have every reason to approach our Father God with confidence, no matter what hour of the day it may be. Nothing should be able to diminish our faith in God’s almighty power.</p>

<p>What can we request? “Who has nothing to ask for? Lord, that sickness. Lord, this moodiness. Lord, that humiliation. I don’t know how to bear it for love of you.” We desire good things, including happiness and joy for people at home. Besides, there is the lot of those who hunger and thirst for bread and justice, which weighs down our hearts. Furthermore, we can remember individuals who experience the bitterness of loneliness. At the end of their days, they receive no affectionate glance or any helping gesture.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “The greatest misfortune is sin. Sin is the only evil we want to remedy through our petition, however, since it makes us suffer most is sin. Here there is a flight from God and the danger of souls being lost for eternity.”</p>

<p>The Church constantly points out that our prayers will reach God’s presence more quickly through the mediation of Our Lady, the Mother of God and our Mother. For this reason, she perennially recommends the Rosary, that efficacious prayer of petition. It does so in a special way during the month of October. Pope Pius XI says, “Don’t forget to give importance to spreading devotion to the Rosary. It’s very dear to Our Lady and is so highly recommended by the Roman Pontiffs. It’s a fine way for the faithful to fulfill the command of the Divine Master: Ask and you will receive, seek and you will find, knock and it shall be opened to you.”</p>

<p>May we not overlook this advice. Our acts of thanksgiving should try to be a norm of our lives. Chesterton says, “When it comes to life, the critical thing is whether you take things for granted or take them with gratitude.” I would maintain that thanks are the highest form of thought, and that gratitude is happiness doubled by wonder.</p>

<p>We should try to see the hand of God in everything. St. Paul says, “What have you that you have not received?” (1 Cor. 4:7). And the Psalm asks the question, “What shall I give back to God for all that He has given to me?” (Ps. 116:12).</p>

<p>In the preface of weekdays, we pray: “We do well always and everywhere to give you thanks. You have no need of our praise, yet our desire to thank you is itself your gift. Our prayer of thanksgiving adds nothing to your greatness but makes us grow in grace.”</p>

<p>In the first Eucharistic prayer, we say, “We come to you, Father, with praise and thanksgiving.” In the second Eucharistic prayer, it says, “We thank you for counting us worthy to stand in your presence and serve you.” In the third Eucharistic prayer, it says, “We offer you in thanksgiving this holy and living sacrifice. All creation rightly gives you praise.” And in the fourth Eucharistic prayer: “Father, we acknowledge your greatness. All your actions show your wisdom and love.”</p>

<p>Everything is a gift, including the crosses that God may send us. We should try to have a desire to lead a lifetime of thanksgiving. We could also try to thank God for the special gifts He’s given us that we may not think about very frequently: our hearing, our sight, our limbs. There may come a time when we have problems in those aspects of our human body and we realize maybe the decades that God has given us those things.</p>

<p>I heard an elderly priest in his 80s once who said that he had to have some cataract operations, and the doctor told him that he wouldn’t be able to see for two or three days. And he was wondering, “What would I do for two or three days?” And he said, “I suddenly realized, after almost 50 years of being a priest, how much we priests need our eyes to say Mass, to read our breviary, to give a class.” He said the following morning was about the man born blind. He felt the Holy Spirit was hitting him in the teeth with a baseball bat. “Here I have given you 80-plus years of sight. You’re not going to be able to see for three days and you’re all worried about it.”</p>

<p>Every day we can fill our day with wonderful hymns of thanksgiving to God for the food we eat, for the health we enjoy. Humble souls are grateful souls because they realize that everything is a gift; everything is on loan.</p>

<p>Our thanksgiving after Mass each day can be a special time to thank God for our Christian vocation. At times, we can thank God for the things we don’t have, which perhaps it’s not the will of God that we would have those things. It’s good sometimes we thank God without asking for anything. Thank Him for the crosses, the contradictions, the misunderstandings, the miscommunications, the providential injustices.</p>

<p>It can be easy to be thankful for the good things. The things we find more difficult may be more difficult to thank Him for. We can thank Him also for small things, for bed sheets. When I came to Kenya, there was a priest, parish priest in Singapore who had a parishioner who was the manager of a five-star hotel. They were changing the bed sheets. The manager asked this parish priest if he had any use for a thousand bed sheets. He didn’t, but he knew I had moved to Kenya. The parish priest contacted me, he sent me a thousand bed sheets. We distributed them to many people.</p>

<p>We kept certain bed sheets for a home for street kids that we had—maybe 20 or 30 of them—in a certain area of Nairobi. After a few days or weeks, I asked one of these kids, “So, how do you find the bed sheets?” Very aware that this kid probably never had bed sheets in his life. And the kid said, “Well, they’re okay,” he said, “But I was wondering if the next time, if they could be black.” And I was wondering why would you want black bed sheets? And he said, “So they don’t show the dirt.” Perfectly normal male psychology. I was thinking we could ask the manager of that five-star hotel in Singapore if he wouldn’t mind changing all his bed sheets to black; we could start a whole new culture of hospitality. So if you go to some hotel and you find there are black bed sheets, well, you know where the idea came from.</p>

<p>We can thank God for the small things that we experience every day that perhaps we take for granted: the bed we have to lie down on, the roof over our heads. We’re told in Scripture, “If you knew the gift of God” (John 4:10). A spirit of gratitude can turn a negative into a positive. It’s very difficult to be grateful and not to be happy.</p>

<p>We can be thankful for our mistakes because they teach us valuable lessons. We can be thankful when we’re tired and weary because maybe it means that we’ve made a difference. We can be thankful for our limitations because those limitations give us opportunities for improvement. We can be thankful for each new challenge because it will build up our strength and character. We can be thankful for the fact that we don’t already have everything we desire; if we did, we’d have nothing to look forward to. We can be thankful when we don’t know something because we realize it gives us the opportunity to learn.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>The Way</em>: “Give thanks often to Jesus, for through Him, with Him, and in Him, you’re able to call yourself a child of God.” As popular wisdom asserts, gratitude is proper to those who are well-bred. Giving thanks for favors, humbly and without affectation, is a sign of nobility, a true bond of union among men. The natural order itself, affirms St. Thomas, requires that whoever has received a favor should respond with gratitude to his beneficiary.</p>

<p>Our Lord was moved by thankfulness, and the selfish indifference with which some people received His favors hurt Him. Ten lepers came to meet Him, asking to be cured, and as they went they were cleansed. Then one of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, praising God with a loud voice, and he fell on his face at Our Lord’s feet giving Him thanks. Jesus said sorrowfully, “Were not ten cleansed? Where are the other nine?” (Luke 17:17).</p>

<p>Our Lord missed the gratitude of those nine. When He rewards that person’s gratitude with a much greater gift: “Rise and go your way; your faith has made you well” (Luke 17:19). To the person who humbly recognizes his debt and is grateful for his benefits, God grants new graces. St. Augustine teaches: “With good reason is he promised much more. For whoever is faithful in little, with perfect right will be put in charge of much. Just as the one who is ungrateful for what he has already received becomes unworthy of new favors.”</p>

<p>If we do a favor for a person and he thanks us, we’re much more inclined to continue helping him. In our prayer, we can thank Our Lord for our Baptism, a totally undeserved gift, and to rejoice in the countless good things that He has so lavishly bestowed upon us. Thanksgiving is the very first emotion that should be born in us in response to our Baptism. The second is joy. We should never think of our Baptism without deep feelings of interior gratitude. St. Leo the Great says, “Thanks to the Sacrament of Baptism, you have been turned into a temple of the Holy Spirit.”</p>

<p>One day, when we are in God’s presence eternally, we will comprehend with full clarity not only that we owe our existence to Him, but our lives were full of His care, His graces, and His benefits, more numerous than the sands of the sea. We will realize that we have only reason to be thankful to God and to others. Only when faith is dead can a person be unaware of those benefits and this present obligation.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Get used to lifting your heart to God in acts of thanksgiving many times a day. Because he gives you this and that. Because you have been despised. Because you haven’t what you need, or because you have. Because he made his Mother so beautiful, his Mother who is also your Mother. Because he created the sun and the moon and this animal and that plant. Because he made that man eloquent and you he left tongue-tied. Thank him for everything, because everything is good.”</p>

<p>In both the human and supernatural realms, our reasons for thanksgiving are great. We can’t count the movements of the Holy Spirit in our soul, the graces we’ve received in the Sacrament of Penance and in Holy Communion, the times when our guardian angel has protected us, the merit gained through the offering of our work and hardships for others, and the times when others have helped us.</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter if we only perceive a small part of this. We can give thanks to God for all the benefits we’ve received over the years. Our Lord taught us how to be thankful for even the least of favors: “Whoever gives to one of these little ones even a cup of cold water because he is a disciple, truly, I say to you, he shall not lose his reward” (Matt. 10:42). The Samaritan who returned to thank Our Lord went away with an even greater gift: faith and Our Lord’s friendship.</p>

<p>Our Lord expects us to go and say to Him many times each day, “Thank you, Lord.” Everyone loves to be thanked. When we’re grateful to others, we remember their favor affectionately, no matter how small it may be, and we wish to repay it in some form. Many times we can only say something like “thank you.” The joy shown in such a gesture contains our thanks. Our whole day can be filled with acts of service and favors for those around us. It costs little to show our gratitude, and it does so much good by creating a better atmosphere, improving relationships, and making charity easier to practice.</p>

<p>We must seek new strength with which to serve Him and endeavor not to be ungrateful, for that’s the condition on which the Lord bestows His jewels. Unless we make good use of His treasures and of the high estate to which He brings us, He will take these treasures back from us. We shall be poorer than before, and His Majesty will give the jewels to someone else who can display them to advantage and to his own profit and that of others. For how can a man unaware that he is rich make good use of his riches and spend them liberally? It is impossible.</p>

<p>Taking our nature into consideration, that anyone who fails to realize that he is favored by God should have the courage necessary for doing great things. For we are so miserable and so much attracted by earthly things that only one who realizes that he holds some earnest of the joys of the next world will succeed in thoroughly abhorring and completely detaching himself from the things of this earth.</p>

<p>We can be thanking God for the great mercy He has shown us and for the innumerable and often unseen benefits He confers on each one of us. Let us ask Our Lady to help us to grow in that spirit of appreciation and thanksgiving, so that spirit of thanksgiving may be present even in our breathing, as a manifestation of how much we appreciate all the great things that God has given to us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>