<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-26T14:11:13+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Zeal for Holiness Through Marriage</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zeal for Holiness Through Marriage" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/zeal-for-holiness-through-marriage/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>There was a meeting of priests in Singapore one time, and we were
talking about vocation. One religious missionary priest from Belgium
stood up and said he learned the meaning of vocation from a young
married couple in the United States, when he was on his first
assignment. They were 25 years of age, they were expecting their first
baby, and the baby turned out to be a Down's baby.</p>

<p>The obstetrician said to the mother, whose name was Nancy, “Are you
ready to accept this baby? I can't tell you it's going to be easy, but
I can tell you that for every ounce of love that you put into this baby,
you're going to get a pound of love in return.”</p>

<p>Nancy said, “Yes, we're ready to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>This elderly priest who was 28 years of age at the time said, “I was
very struck by that, because nobody gets married and says, ‘I want to
have a handicapped child.’ I realized that is the meaning of vocation:
to be ready to accept whatever comes.</p>

<p>This meditation is about zeal for holiness in marriage.</p>

<p>He said, “I began to ask myself, ‘Am I ready to accept whatever comes?
Here I am, a 28-year-old priest, my first missionary assignment setting
out in life. A couple of years later, I was asked to go and work in
Rome, work behind a desk, and handle all of the financial, legal, and
architectural aspects of our organization all over the world.</p>

<p>“One day, somebody came to me and said, ‘What are you doing here,
working behind a desk in Rome? You're supposed to be a missionary
priest. Why are you not off in Brazil or Alaska someplace?’”</p>

<p>He said, “I got my answer from Nancy. I didn't ask for this job. I
don't particularly like it. I'd much prefer to be somewhere else. But
I try to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>If somebody came to our organization and said, “I'm willing to join
your missionary organization as long as I can work behind a desk in Rome
and do all the jobs that I want and I like” they would be told, “I'm
sorry, you don't have a vocation to our organization. Part of the deal
is that you have to be ready to accept whatever comes.”</p>

<p>As we look to the topic of zeal for holiness in marriage, we could ask
ourselves, Why did I get married? What is the purpose of marriage?
What's it all about? What is the marriage contract?</p>

<p>Our baptismal vocation tells us that the goal of our Christian vocation
is holiness and apostolate.</p>

<p>If we're married, it's because we have a vocation to be married.
That's the pathway to holiness that God wants for us. Pope St. John
Paul II likes to say that we're all called to the eternal wedding
feast.</p>

<p>Marriage now is a preparation for marriage later. God wants to marry us.
People who live celibate lives skip the historical reality here on earth
in order to give witness to the fact that real marriage comes later.</p>

<p>So everything in our marriage is a preparation for marriage in the next.</p>

<p>There is a saying in different but similar words from St. Josemaría, who
spent his whole life saying that marriage is a pathway to holiness, and
holiness ultimately is love, charity. That's what we're called to.
That's the definition of holiness (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>,
Point 91).</p>

<p>Every moment of every day, every opportunity, is a calling to holiness.</p>

<p>In our prayer today, we could ask Our Lord that we might have a zeal for
that holiness. We might want the goal of our marriage ultimately to get
to heaven and to bring the people around us to heaven.</p>

<p>Our Lord says, “You did not choose me. No, I chose you and I
commissioned you to go out and bear fruit—fruit that will last” (John
15:16).</p>

<p>We have been chosen “before the foundation of the world” (Eph. 1:4).
Every aspect of our life has been chosen: your wife, your home, your
health, your work, your financial difficulties, your children. It's all
part of a great divine plan in which God wants us to participate.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul liked to say that “the Blessed Trinity is a communion
of persons” (quoting the <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point
2205). He liked to say that “the family is a communion of persons” (John
Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Familiaris Consortio</em>, Nov. 22, 1981).</p>

<p>So he lifted up the family onto this Trinitarian level. Our goal is
somehow to imitate the Trinity.</p>

<p>He said marriage is a life-giving communion of persons (Pope John Paul
II, <em>General Audience</em>, Nov. 14, 1979). The Blessed Trinity is a
life-giving communion of persons. The love of the Father for the Son
gives rise to the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>The Catechism of the Catholic Church says that children are the supreme
gift of marriage (<em>CCC</em>, Point 1652). It's an enormously positive
statement. And because God chose us, He gives us the grace for that
choice.</p>

<p>Like the apostles, we have not been chosen because of what we are, but
because of what we have to become. Peter was not chosen because of what
he was, but because of what he had to become, in spite of his miseries
and his failures.</p>

<p>He did the same thing as Judas. He betrayed Our Lord. “Woman, I do not
know him” (Luke 22:57). Then we're told in Scripture, “The Lord turned
and looked upon Peter” (Luke 22:61).</p>

<p>It's a very poignant moment. He seeks him out with His loving glance in
his lowest moment. “And Peter goes out and weeps bitterly” (Luke 22:62).
It's from this moment that he goes forward to become a great saint and
a great apostle.</p>

<p>That's God's will for each one of us: to be a great saint and a great
apostle in our marriage, with everything that comes with it, ready to
accept whatever comes.</p>

<p>We can thank God very much for this vocation that He's given to us, the
purpose of our existence. We can try and find meaning in that
calling—our growth in holiness, which is a growth in virtue.</p>

<p>Pope St. Paul VI said on one occasion that “the cultivation of Christian
perfection must still be regarded as the richest source of the Church's
spiritual strength” (Pope Paul VI, Encyclical, <em>Ecclesiam Suam</em>, August
6, 1964).</p>

<p>Rather interesting words: “the richest source of the Church's spiritual
strength” is the domestic Church.</p>

<p>We are called to live like great human persons, a man of virtue, that
sees every day as an opportunity to grow in charity, in patience, in
kindness, in order, in industriousness, in punctuality, in forgetfulness
of self.</p>

<p>It's in all these virtues and the cultivation of them that we find the
purpose and the meaning of our life. Now that may entail many occasions
of beginning again.</p>

<p>There was a lawyer in Sydney once who used to come to retreats every
year and attend Circles and recollections. One time an elderly couple
came to see him. He was 86 and she was 83. He said to them, “What can I
do for you?”</p>

<p>They said, “We want to get a divorce.”</p>

<p>“And why do you want to get a divorce?”</p>

<p>“Because we don't love each other anymore.”</p>

<p>“And how long have you been married?”</p>

<p>“Forty years.”</p>

<p>So the lawyer quickly tried to remember all the points about the talk or
the meditation on charity from his last retreat. He tried to give them
an impromptu talk on the meaning of charity.</p>

<p>Charity is patient. Charity is kind. It's letting the water flow under
the bridge. It's knowing how to forgive. It's not making a mountain
out of molehills. It's moving on. It's loving other people with their
defects.</p>

<p>He went through as many points as he could remember about the virtue of
charity and asked them to go away and think about it for a while.</p>

<p>They weren't very convinced, but the husband said, “Okay, we'll give
it a go.” So they went away.</p>

<p>Three years later, the wife came back and said, “I came back because I
want to thank you. My husband just passed away, but we've just had
three of the most wonderful years of our whole life.”</p>

<p>The moral of the story is that we're always beginning again in love.</p>

<p>Love is a mystery. God is love (1 John 4:8). As the Preface of the
Sacred Heart said to us last Friday, we go to the Sacred Heart of Christ
to “draw water in joy from the wells of salvation” (Isa. 12:3).</p>

<p>In the wounded heart of Christ, we learn the meaning of love:
forgetfulness of self, sacrifice, and a willingness to be on the cross,
to start over.</p>

<p>The devil can present sanctity to us as something unattainable.</p>

<p>Sanctity is continuously doing what God wants, not what we want.</p>

<p>There was a story of a Mexican man who, for 25 years, every Saturday
afternoon, used to bring his wife to the bullfights.</p>

<p>One Saturday afternoon, the wife said, “Let's not go to the bullfights.
I'm fed up going to the bullfights.” After thinking about it, the
husband said, “Okay, let's not go to the bullfights. I never really
wanted to go to the bullfights anyway.”</p>

<p>There was a man who learned how to keep his first love in first place.</p>

<p>We all know how the other loves of our life—Manchester United, golf,
tennis, the local bar—all these things can move themselves up,
maneuver themselves up sometimes, into first place.</p>

<p>Part of holiness is keeping our first love in first place—knowing the
importance of that. It's said that the greatest thing that a man can do
for his family is to love his wife very much. The greatest thing a woman
can do for her family is to love her husband very much.</p>

<p>That means we have to take care of love because if we're not careful,
the devil can rob us of it.</p>

<p>Love is expressed in details. St. Josemaria liked to say that married
couples, after many years of marriage, have to keep their love young and
fresh, like it was before they got married.</p>

<p>So we have to know how to sweep our spouse off their feet from time to
time with little details, with surprises, with small things. People need
affection. They need to be told that they're loved, that they're
beautiful, that they're appreciated.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas was asked, In the quest for holiness, what's the
most important thing? He answered, to desire it, to want it with all our
heart and soul.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord in our prayer today, Do I want that goal of my
marriage vocation more than anything else in the world? Do I take care
of it? Where am I now in that zeal for holiness? Am I looking after
things? Am I taking care of things? What's the theme of their marriage
vocation at the moment?</p>

<p>If you were to sing a song, what would that song be? There was a song in
the 1960s that said, “Where have all the flowers gone...long time
passing?”</p>

<p>Or in the 1990s, “Once upon a time, I was falling in love, and now I'm
only falling apart. There's been a total eclipse of the heart. Once
upon a time, there was light in my life.”</p>

<p>Wherever we may be, we have to try and go back and begin again, relying
sometimes a little more on the grace that God gives us.</p>

<p>There are two prayers to the Holy Spirit that you'll find in the
Christian devotions. One is for the sequence of Pentecost Sunday. It's
<em>Veni Sancti Spiritus</em>. And <em>Veni Creator Spiritus.</em></p>

<p>The Holy Spirit is the great sanctifier. It gives us fire, the fire of
love. So it makes a lot of sense to invoke the Holy Spirit frequently or
to pray those prayers, perhaps in your Thanksgiving after Mass, or other
moments of the day.</p>

<p>Just as we polish up our shoes every day or two, we need to do the same
with our vocation to holiness, to understand what is necessary to make
our vocation grow: sacraments, formation. We need regular input: yearly
retreat, monthly recollection. Maybe a weekly confession.</p>

<p>These are the systems that the saints have placed in a position to help
us to attain that goal of holiness. At the same time, we have to be
careful not to go to the wrong environment that can send us in the wrong
direction: discos, bars, etc.</p>

<p>The holier we become, the more transparent the face of Christ becomes in
us.</p>

<p>Holiness doesn't mean that we don't have miseries and mistakes.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was at Mass in another country and there was
a French missionary priest who was preaching the homily.</p>

<p>He talked about how when he was a kid in a small town in France, there
was a monastery of strict observance on the outskirts of the town and he
would go there as a 10-year-old kid to help the monks in their work.</p>

<p>They had a vocation of silence, so they didn't talk unless you talked
to them, and out of charity they would answer. Sometimes he would help
the monks in their work and they would have a bit of a chit-chat.</p>

<p>But he noticed over in the corner of the field near the garden there was
a very holy, elderly monk who was working away very silently on his own.
This man had a great aura of holiness about him.</p>

<p>One day, he went over to this elderly monk and said to him, “When I grow
up I want to be like you.”</p>

<p>This holy, saintly, elderly man said, “No, don't be like me because I
have hatred in my heart.”</p>

<p>This elderly missionary priest said, “As a 10-year-old I was shocked to
hear that this saintly, elderly man could have had hatred in his heart.”</p>

<p>Then he explained this because he said, “Yes, you see there's a monk
who sits beside me in the refectory and he makes a lot of noise when
he's eating. For the last thirty years, he's been driving me up the
wall.”</p>

<p>The lady who told me this story said, “You know, when I heard the priest
say that, I couldn't look at my husband because for the last thirty
years, I've been telling him, ‘Mind your manners.’”</p>

<p>We all have our miseries—things where we can improve on. Sometimes we
have to listen to what other people are saying to us because maybe they
see us as we really are, the realities.</p>

<p>We have to try and engrave in our hearts that we're called to is
holiness.</p>

<p>God wants me in particular to be a saint. He has created me and elevated
me to the order of grace. He has redeemed me, given me many graces, and
given me all the formation that I have because He loves me a lot.</p>

<p>Whether our life grows with depth in this way also depends on us. God
doesn't go against our freedom. He created us out of love. He wants us
to correspond with love.</p>

<p>Everyone wants to change the world. But few want to do it by changing
themselves.</p>

<p>The message of personal sanctification is not so much that we convert
China, but that we convert ourselves. We can't convert China if we
don't change ourselves. We want big things but we can forget about
ourselves.</p>

<p>Very often, conversion comes about in and through the cross. Try to
learn how to thank God for the crosses that He sends you. Our holiness
is there.</p>

<p>A zeal for holiness can often be a zeal for the cross, for the will of
God in my life—accepting that will. The cross may come to us in all
sorts of small ways on a daily basis, but from time to time in the
course of our life there may be larger crosses, greater things, possibly
crosses that we never expected.</p>

<p>That's where the wisdom of the words of that missionary priest may find
their true value: to be willing to accept whatever comes.</p>

<p>If something comes along that you never expected, never thought would
happen to you, a great contradiction, possibly it's not going to
change. This is your lot for the rest of your life.</p>

<p>You can be sure that is the will of God for you. That's the pathway of
your sanctification. That's why we have to learn to love it.</p>

<p>A lady told me once who had lost a 20-year-old daughter that she had
learned how to thank God for the crosses that He sends her “because,”
she said, “I realized it could be worse.”</p>

<p>Ask Our Lord for a passion for sanctity. Try to renew that eagerness for
sanctity with a human supernatural enthusiasm.</p>

<p>Lord, may I never lose my eagerness for holiness. May my whole life,
like the whole of Creation, give you glory.</p>

<p>Our vocation to holiness is a constant in our life. It's not a state of
mind. It's not a feeling. It doesn't depend on our state of
employment, on our finances, on our health. It has to do with our being.</p>

<p>No matter where I am or what situation I'm in, it's here. God wants me
to be holy in and through this situation.</p>

<p>“You saw it quite clearly:” said St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>, “while so
many people do not know God, he has looked to you. He wants you to form
a part of the foundations. a firm stone upon which the life of the
Church can rest. Meditate upon this reality and you will draw many
practical consequences for your ordinary behavior: the foundations, made
of blocks of stone, hidden and possibly rather dull, have to be solid,
not fragile. They have to serve as support for the building. If not,
they're useless” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 472).</p>

<p>Your zeal for holiness may depend on the zeal for the holiness of each
one of your children in their married life. Every hour is an opportunity
to give them an example, to lead by example.</p>

<p>Our vocation to holiness is a gift. It can't be earned. You have to be
chosen with a divine calling.</p>

<p>I was giving a retreat many years ago and there was an elderly teacher
who I knew had a lot of health problems in his life. Sp I asked him,
“How are things now?”</p>

<p>He said to me, “Well, Father, I've come to realize that happiness does
not consist in doing things that are easy.”</p>

<p>I nearly fell off the chair. Such wisdom. We learn an awful lot from
other people.</p>

<p>Sometimes we look for happiness in the easy things. Very often our
happiness is in the problems, in the challenges, in the changes of
plans, in the difficulties, in solving those things that crop up daily.</p>

<p>We find our happiness on the cross. St. Josemaría liked to say that joy
and happiness in this world have their roots in the form of a cross (J.
Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 43) and God is the one who makes
us holy.</p>

<p>“Committed!” says St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>. “How I love that word!
We children of God freely put ourselves under an obligation to live a
life of dedication to God, striving that he may have complete and
absolute sovereignty over our lives” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point
855).</p>

<p>There are certain areas that we always need to look out for in our
marriage. One of them is communication. Communication sometimes can be a
very difficult thing—to communicate charity, affection, love; to
listen carefully to what other people are saying to us, especially our
spouse.</p>

<p>There may be things that are difficult to say with words. To
communicate, we need to be able to read other people's body language
and to know the words and gestures that only those who love know are
important. When to be silent. When to listen. To be there at special
times.</p>

<p>A man asked his wife one time, “Why do you let our son talk to you like
that?”</p>

<p>The wife said, “Because that's the way that you talk to me.”</p>

<p>There may be great things we have to learn: great truths, personal
truths from knowing how to listen; good communication.</p>

<p>If the devil can place a barrier between us and our spouse, through
communication, it's not a great battle.</p>

<p>A couple told me many years ago how every month they take a time
out—half an hour, an hour—and they sit down.</p>

<p>They write down all the things that have annoyed them in the previous
few weeks, all the thoughts that have passed through their mind, the
feelings—feelings of injustice, feelings of neglect, feelings of lack
of kindness or attention to detail.</p>

<p>They write all those things down and then they swap papers. So they
communicate in writing the things that they might otherwise have found
difficult to communicate in words.</p>

<p>You need to work on communication in your marriage. When the devil
can't attack frontally, he attacks obliquely through misunderstandings,
miscommunications, neglect of details.</p>

<p>You have to learn how to be a good communicator, and in particular, to
communicate charity. “Charity is patient. Charity is kind” (1 Cor.
13:4). You have to try and work at being easy to live with.</p>

<p>We can all be difficult to live with. Sometimes we can think we are the
most lovable creature on this planet. If ever you have a thought like
that, ask your mother or your father, “Mum, was I ever unlovable?”</p>

<p>And they'll say, “Sit down for an hour and we'll tell you about it.”</p>

<p>We have all been the most unlovable creatures that you could possibly
imagine. But God has called us to try and work at being lovable
creatures, and that we have to try and show love to other people.</p>

<p>The mother is the queen of the home. We always have to try and treat our
spouse as that queen, so that other people see that. They see it in our
words, they see it in our actions.</p>

<p>Family values mean family priorities. Family comes first. Our marriage
comes first. There may be times when we have to be home: special dates,
birthdays, anniversaries, Sundays, Christmas.</p>

<p>The best moments of our life should be at home and with our family. This
is the apostolate of the family. This is where we find our holiness.</p>

<p>A spirit of service is a very important thing in the home. No job should
be beneath the husband to do: the washing up, to lay the table, sweep
the driveway, to wash the car, to wash our clothes sometimes.</p>

<p>In this way, we prepare our children to be good husbands and good wives.
Prepare them for their marriage by giving that example.</p>

<p>We can ask St. Joseph, spouse of Our Lady, that we might imitate his
example in a daily way, through our silence, through our service,
through our faithfulness; through our acceptance of the will of God like
he did, being in the background, forgetting ourselves, being a pillar;
trusting the humble faith; being manly, being available, being full of
fortitude.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that she might cultivate that desire for greater
holiness in our marriage so that we can truly prepare for that eternal
feast that God has wanted for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">|</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="|" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/"><![CDATA[<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“After this there was a Jewish festival, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.
Now in Jerusalem, next to the Sheep Gate, there is a pool called
Bethesda in Hebrew, which has five porticoes. Under these were crowds of
sick people—blind, lame, paralyzed. One man there had an illness which
lasted thirty-eight years.</p>

<p>“When Jesus saw him lying there and knew he had been in that condition
for a long time, he said: ‘Do you want to be well again?’ ‘Sir, replied
the sick man, ‘I have no one to put me into the pool when the water is
disturbed, and while I am still on the way, someone else gets down there
before me.’ Jesus said, ‘Get up, pick up your sleeping mat, and walk
around.’ The man was cured at once, and he picked up his mat and started
to walk around” (John 5:1-9).</p>

<p>Our Lord is always willing to listen to us and to give us whatever we
need in any situation. His goodness always exceeds in excess of our
calculations. But at the same time, it requires our correspondence, a
response on our part. We have to do what we can to give what we can.</p>

<p>We need to have a desire to get out of the situation we are in. St.
Josemaria in <em>The Forge</em> says: “Lazarus rose because he heard the voice
of God and immediately wanted to get out of the situation he was in. If
he hadn't wanted to move, he would just have died again. A sincere
resolution: to have faith in God always; to hope in God always; to love
God always; he never abandons us, even if we are rotting away as Lazarus
was” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 211).</p>

<p>When Our Lord called out to Lazarus and Lazarus heard His voice, he
might not have felt like moving. He might not have felt like beginning
again or starting his life over. He might have felt comfortable where he
was. He might have wanted just to turn over and go back to sleep.</p>

<p>But he wanted to get out of the situation he was in. So Lord, give me
that desire to want to be better.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas was asked, What is the most important factor in
achieving holiness? He said, “To want it with all your heart and soul.”</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>The Way</em> asked the question: “Do you want it like a
miser wants his gold...like a sensualist wants his pleasure?” (J.
Escriva, <em>The Way</em>, Point 316).</p>

<p>That's how we have to desire the goal of holiness in our life and be
ready to do whatever it is that God asks of us. It doesn't matter what
situation we may be in.</p>

<p>This man beside the pool of Bethsaida was thirty-eight years in his
infirmity. There might be some addiction or some vice or some habit that
we've been immersed in for most of our life, for decades. Our Lord is
telling us with this parable that there is hope for us.</p>

<p>This paralytic was full of hope. Each time, his hope and his desire to
be healed was greater than his disappointment, greater than his sadness
and his failure. There were many, many times he went down to the water,
but somebody always got there before him. He never quite managed it.</p>

<p>He failed and he failed and he failed, but he kept at it. He didn't
give up. The secret of his life was that one day, Christ was passing by.
Jesus saw him lying there and knew he'd been in that condition for a
long time. And He said: “Do you want to be well again?”</p>

<p>Our Lord comes to us through our spiritual reading, through our periods
of prayer, maybe through a retreat, perhaps through a friend who reaches
out to us in deeper spiritual matters of the soul, pushes us in the
right direction. It's the Holy Spirit speaking to us and saying, “Do
you want to be well again?” Come up onto a new level. Start over. Begin
the race again.</p>

<p>Any Olympic athlete who won a gold this year failed many times before
they won the gold. God has permitted our miseries, our shortcomings, our
difficulties and challenges, so that we have a specific area of fight, a
specific area where He wants us to do battle and to show with our deeds
that we want to be better. We want to be holy.</p>

<p>There can't be any pact with our defects and errors. You can't say:
‘Look, that's the way I'm made, that's the way I am. I can't help
it!’</p>

<p>We have to try and make an effort to overcome those shortcomings,
particularly shortcomings and weaknesses that separate us from God and
from others. We can't give the excuse that we've tried several times
to tackle them without any positive results.</p>

<p>‘Sorry,’ he said, ‘I have no one to put me into the pool when the water
is disturbed. While I'm still on the way, someone else gets down there
before me. I've tried and tried again. But I'm still here.’</p>

<p>It's the heart that moves us to improve our interior dispositions
through that conversion of the heart to God and to works of penance, and
in this way, preparing our souls to receive the graces that God wants to
give us.</p>

<p>Jesus asks us to persevere in the struggle, and to begin again as often
as necessary, realizing that it is in struggle that love grows.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom says, “The Lord doesn't ask the paralytic in order
to learn—this would be superfluous—but to make his patience known to
all, for that invalid for thiry-eight years had hoped, without ceasing,
to be freed from his illness.”</p>

<p>If we're looking forward, as Pope St. John Paul says, to the eternal
wedding feast, then everything is worthwhile—every struggle, every
beginning again, every bit of hope, every clinging to the teaching of
the Church in different areas about what is right and what is true,
because that's where love resides.</p>

<p>Sometimes Our Lord might ask us to struggle in a very difficult
situation, and maybe we don't feel like struggling.</p>

<p>There was a book I read many years ago called <em>The Battle of Monte
Cassino</em>. Monte Cassino was an abbey just south of Rome. St. Benedict is
buried there; I think his sister also. The abbey of Monte Cassino has a
commanding view over the approach road to Rome from the south.</p>

<p>The Nazis occupied this monastery. The Allies landed, I think, in the
winter of 1944. They landed in a place called Anzio, and they began to
make their way up the center of Italy. It was cold, it was winter, it
was very uncomfortable.</p>

<p>The Poles, the Americans, the British, the French, the Australians, New
Zealanders—they were all fighting to make a stand there in Italy. The
Nazis had a commanding view over this approach road, so they were picked
off like flies.</p>

<p>One journalist who wrote this book was in the front lines, and he
described the conditions in the front lines:</p>

<p>“The shells were landing all around them. The soldiers were cold,
battle-weary. Anyone in his right mind would want to be out of that
hellhole. And at night, during dark, the mules would come to bring
supplies. Then they would bring the dead and the injured back to the
home camp.”</p>

<p>He said the temptation to desert was very great, to get out of that
place. There was a sergeant checking all the wounded to make sure they
were really wounded. One day, two soldiers feigned being injured. But
the sergeant caught them and he ordered them back to the front lines.</p>

<p>Those tired, battle-weary soldiers went back and retook their positions
in the front lines. They began again. But that was the last thing they
felt like doing. They persevered in the battle.</p>

<p>Eventually, over time, the Nazis were pushed back off that promontory
and they withdrew to the north of Italy. Rome was spared. It was one of
the most decisive battles of the Second World War, won with tired
soldiers who fought on.</p>

<p>Our love for Christ is shown in our decisiveness, in the effort we make
to root out as soon as possible our dominant defect, or to obtain the
virtue that for us might seem so difficult to practice.</p>

<p>But our love for Christ is also shown in our patience—our patience in
the ascetical struggle, to let time pass.</p>

<p>Very often truth is the daughter of time. Victory is the daughter of
time. Patience can be a great social force. Over time we change
ourselves, we change our family, we change society, we change our
profession.</p>

<p>It's possible that Our Lord may ask us to struggle over a long period,
perhaps for thirty-eight years, maybe more, so that we grow in a
particular virtue, or to overcome some negative aspect of our interior
life.</p>

<p>A certain spiritual writer called Joseph Tissot has taught the
importance of being patient with our defects so as to develop “the art
of profiting from our faults.” He has a book entitled <em>How to Profit
from Your Faults</em>.</p>

<p>We shouldn't be surprised or scandalized or discouraged when we see or
discover the depth of our miseries, the depth of our weak humanity, or
when we've used all the means that are within our reach. We haven't
managed to reach the goal that we may have set ourselves.</p>

<p>We leave our spiritual progress in the hands of God. He's the one that
looks after everything. He brings the fruit.</p>

<p>We shouldn't just simply get used to our defects, but rather, use our
faults to grow in humility, in experience, in maturity of judgment.</p>

<p>We know that this man was constant over thirty-eight years, and maybe he
could have continued until the end of his days. But the reward for his
constancy was the meeting with Jesus.</p>

<p>Lord, give me patience in my interior life. Help me to return to you as
often as necessary.</p>

<p>St. James says: “Be patient, therefore, brethren, until the coming of
the Lord. Behold, the farmer waits for the precious fruit of the earth,
being patient over it until it receives the early and the late rain”
(James 5:7).</p>

<p>We sow the seeds. Then God wants us to give things time to ripen and to
mature. At the same time, He wants us to aim high.</p>

<p>There's a story of a farmer who had no food for his family. So he went
out to hunt and he had three bullets in his rifle. He saw a rabbit but
missed. Then he saw a fox and he missed. And then he saw a big fat
turkey up in a tree.</p>

<p>He lifted up his rifle to shoot the turkey. But then as he was about to
shoot the turkey. he heard a voice within him that said, ‘Aim high. Pray
first. Aim high. Carry on struggling.’</p>

<p>But then out of the left corner of his eye he saw a deer. That deer had
more meat than the turkey. So he lowered his rifle to shoot the deer.
And he heard the voice again deep down inside him. ‘Pray first. Aim
high. Stay focused.’</p>

<p>But then he noticed there was a rattlesnake between his feet. That posed
the greatest danger to life and limb. So he lowered the rifle to shoot
the snake. But again he heard that voice speaking a third time. ‘Pray
first. Aim high. Stay focused.’</p>

<p>He decided to obey this voice of conscience. So he lifted up the rifle
to shoot the turkey. He shot the turkey.</p>

<p>The bullet ricocheted off a bone in the turkey, hitting the deer and
killing the deer. The impact of shooting the rifle made him lose his
balance and so he stepped on the snake and killed it. And he fell
backwards into a pond that was full of fish</p>

<p>And so when he stepped up out of the pond, he had a dead turkey, a dead
deer, a dead snake, and plenty of fish with which to feed his family.</p>

<p>The moral of the story is ‘we pray first, we aim high, we stay focused’
irrespective of our failures and our mistakes. All sorts of things can
go wrong.</p>

<p>In the London Olympics a number of years ago, somebody said they noticed
a man with a tattoo on his arm. It was a tattoo that was specially made
for the Olympics, except that Olympics was not spelt O-L-Y, it was spelt
O-Y-L. Imagine if somebody puts a tattoo and then makes a misspelling.
Horror of horrors!</p>

<p>Or another thing that happened at that Olympics that got global news
was: somebody from South Korea won a gold medal, and when they stood up
on the podium to receive the gold, the national anthem that was played
was the national anthem of North Korea. Imagine the embarrassment in the
London Olympics. This went viral all over the world.</p>

<p>A lot of records broken and other athletes did not quite make global
news, but that little mistake did. When moments come when we make big
mistakes and we have to hang our head in shame, it's a moment to grow
in humility.</p>

<p>St. Francis de Sales used to say, “One has to suffer, in patience, the
setbacks to our perfection, doing whatever we can to make progress in
good spirit. We hope with patience, and instead of getting frustrated at
having done so little in the past, we try diligently to do more in the
future.”</p>

<p>The great way to look—to look to the future—to make up in the future
for the things of the past.</p>

<p>Jesus, help me to hope, to struggle with persevering patience, realizing
that that is something that gives you great joy.</p>

<p>Usually the virtues that we have to acquire are not acquired through
sporadic bursts of effort. Rather, they're acquired with continuity of
the effort, the constancy and trying again each day, each week, helped
by grace. Hence, the benefit of weekly sacramental Confession, so that
we get all the help from the graces that the sacraments have to give us.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em>, St. Josemaría says, “To win the battles of the
soul, the best strategy is often to bide one's time and to apply the
suitable remedy with patience and perseverance. ... Let me remind you
that in your interior life you will suffer defeats, and you will have
ups and downs—may God make them imperceptible—because no one is free
from these misfortunes. But our all-powerful and merciful Lord has
granted us the precise means with which to conquer. All we have to do is
to use them, resolving to begin again and again at every moment,
whenever necessary” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 219).</p>

<p>The heart of constancy lies in love. St. Thomas says, “Only with love
can one be patient” and struggle, without accepting failures and defeats
as inevitable, as baffling difficulties that don't have a solution.</p>

<p>We can't become like those Christians who, after many skirmishes and
battles, find, as St. Teresa of Avila says, “their strength has come to
an end; their courage has failed them” when “they're only a couple of
steps from the fountain of living water.”</p>

<p>To be patient with ourselves while uprooting unwholesome tendencies and
defects in character implies an unyielding approach and an acceptance of
the fact that we'll often have to present ourselves before God, “like
the servant who had no resources with which to pay” (cf. Matt.
18:23-25)—with humility, seeking new graces.</p>

<p>On our way towards the Lord, there will be many defeats that we suffer.
Many of those defeats will be of no consequence, but perhaps some will.
There might be big defeats, but the atonement and the contrition for
those defeats will bring us even closer to God.</p>

<p>“Peter went out, and he wept bitterly” (Luke 22:62), but this was the
moment of his gracious conversion. From that denial he went on to become
a great saint and a great apostle.</p>

<p>This type of sorrow and reparation for our sins and shortcomings are not
useless modes of gloom; rather, they are sorrow and tears born of love.
It's the heavy thought of not returning as much love as Our Lord
merits; it's the sorrow of returning evil for good to one who has loved
us so much.</p>

<p>Jesus, give me the heart with which you want me to love you. Help me to
see my shortcomings, defects, failures as things you have permitted so
that the pathway of my struggle is very clear. I know what I have to
fight on. I have to use all the means. I have to be heroic because
you've called me to a heroic sanctity.</p>

<p>After patience with ourselves, we have to also try and have patience
with others: patience and constancy in the apostolate; patience with
those whom we most frequently deal, our children perhaps, our
colleagues, and particularly with those to whom we may have a special
obligation to give formation, or to help in some illness.</p>

<p>We have to take into account the defects of those around us. Our
fortitude and our understanding will help us to remain calm, correcting
when necessary, and also at the right time and in the right way, waiting
a little, perhaps, before mentioning certain things, giving a positive
reply, smiling, encouraging, always encouraging. Children need
encouragement. Teenagers need encouragement.</p>

<p>If we do this in this way, then that approach allows our words to touch
the hearts of those to whom we're speaking—hearts that otherwise
might have remained closed. Then we can help them with much greater
effectiveness.</p>

<p>Impatience, on the other hand, makes mutual relationships difficult, and
can render any possible help and correction ineffective.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom says, “Continue making the same exhortation and
never lazily. Always act amiably and pleasantly. Do you not see how
often painters will erase their sketches and at other times retouch
them, when they are trying to portray a beautiful face?</p>

<p>“Don't let the painter be one up on you. For if they make so much of an
effort for a bodily image, how much greater reason do we have when we
try to form the image of a soul, leaving no stone unturned in trying to
perfect it.”</p>

<p>People need time. Souls, like good wine, improve with time, and God is
patient. At every moment He gives His grace. He pardons offenses,
encourages progress.</p>

<p>He has had—with each one of us—and he continues to have, limitless
patience. And we ought to have that same patience with those that we
want to bring closer to Him.</p>

<p>Though at times it might seem that they're not listening, or that the
things of God do not interest them, we can't abandon them just for this
reason.</p>

<p>It may be that Our Lord wants us to turn to prayer, a more silent
prayer, a more patient prayer. We may need to intensify our prayer and
our mortification, and also our charity and our sincere friendship, so
that none of our friends should ever be able to say to Our Lord the
words that the paralytic told him: “Sir, I have no one to help me. I
have no one to let me down into the water when the water is stirred”
(cf. John 5:7).</p>

<p>God has placed certain souls around us—children, relatives, friends,
colleagues, people we come in contact with—who have a right for us to
be that person who helps them into the water, to bring them closer to
the source of the eternal happiness that they're looking for.</p>

<p>In <em>Furrow</em>, St. Josemaría says: “‘I do not have anyone to help me.’
This, unfortunately!, could be said by many who are spiritually sick and
paralytic, who could be useful—and should be useful. Lord, may I never
remain indifferent to souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 212).</p>

<p>That's why we have to be attentive, attentive to the souls that God
brings into our path, we come in contact with. Everybody is important.</p>

<p>Jesus, help me to be sufficiently concerned about all those who
accompany me on my journey through life. Help me to be concerned about
their formation. Help me not just to get used to their defects, as
something they may regard as incorrigible. Help me to be really patient
with them.</p>

<p>That soul might be one of our children, one of our relatives, or
somebody very close to us.</p>

<p>In Christ lies the remedy for all the evils of which humanity complains.
In Him everyone can find life and help. He's the fountain of the waters
that give life to everything.</p>

<p>And so, when that paralytic was spoken to by Christ, that meant
everything. John Paul II liked to say, “In Christ we find the meaning
and the purpose of our life.”</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady, that she might help us to begin over and over, even
in our weakest moments with our greatest defects, drawing strength from
this parable.</p>

<p>The man, the patience of him who never gave up, as he was looking for
the waters of eternal life, the truth, the meaning, and the beauty that
he would only find in that healing, that he would only find in Christ.</p>

<p>Mary, may you lead me to keep on fighting always, so that I may merit
and find that wonderful reward.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(Proofread)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}Mary of Bethany’s Authentic Love</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchormary-of-bethanys-authentic-love/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}Mary of Bethany’s Authentic Love" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchormary-of-bethanys-authentic-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchormary-of-bethanys-authentic-love/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}Palm Sunday</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorpalm-sunday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}Palm Sunday" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorpalm-sunday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorpalm-sunday/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}The Raising of Lazarus</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorthe-raising-of-lazarus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[]{#_gjdgxs .anchor}The Raising of Lazarus" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorthe-raising-of-lazarus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_gjdgxs-anchorthe-raising-of-lazarus/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[]{#_heading=h.gjdgxs .anchor}Rejection</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_headinghgjdgxs-anchorrejection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[]{#_heading=h.gjdgxs .anchor}Rejection" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_headinghgjdgxs-anchorrejection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/_headinghgjdgxs-anchorrejection/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Christian Outlook on Death</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Christian Outlook on Death" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-christian-outlook-on-death/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit,
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Thessalonians, “For you yourself know well that the
day of the Lord will come like a thief in the night” (1 Thess. 5:2).</p>

<p>Our Lord Himself has said, “I am the resurrection and the life. He who
believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives and
believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26).</p>

<p>St. Paul to the Ephesians says, “Look carefully then how you walk, not
as unwise men, but as wise, making the most of the time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>A lot of these statements in Scripture can remind us not to be blind to
our final moment on earth.</p>

<p>The Church in some ways encourages us to prepare for death on a daily
basis. Our Lord has said that His coming in glory will take people
unawares.</p>

<p>“For as the lightning flashes and lights up the sky from one side to the
other, so will the Son of Man be in his day” (Luke 17:24). Our Lord
tells us that nothing can block His second coming at the end of time.</p>

<p>The disciples had a natural curiosity about when and where this would
happen. “Where, Lord?” they asked Him. “Where the body is,” He replied,
“there the eagles will be gathered” (Luke 17:37).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that everyone will be drawn to the Son of God at the
end of time just as eagles converge on their prey.</p>

<p>The same can be said about each person's moment of death.</p>

<p>St. Paul warns those Christians of Thessalonica that He will come “like
a thief in the night.” It is one more call to vigilance.</p>

<p>We cannot be blind to our final moment on earth, the day of the Lord,
when we will meet God face to face. St. Augustine has written that the
Lord keeps the circumstances of His coming hidden so that we might
always be on the alert (<em>cf</em>. St. Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 120</em>).</p>

<p>In modern culture, in certain environments, it's not easy to speak
about death and dying. In a materialistic culture, death is taboo
because it suggests the end of everything.</p>

<p>It's easy for people to forget the spiritual nature of man, that every
person has a soul and that soul is immortal. It has an eternal destiny.
It's one of the most important truths of our faith, with enormous
consequences.</p>

<p>But in a materialistic culture, the very mention of the subject of death
can be regarded by some as a sign of bad taste. But it's the certainty
of death that illuminates our life.</p>

<p>The Church invites us to meditate frequently on the inevitability of our
death so that we won't be taken by surprise when it comes.</p>

<p>Pagan culture would have us live as though death were a distant mirage,
something that only affects other people.</p>

<p>Regrettably, many who consider themselves good Christians can be unduly
influenced by such a seductive approach to life. They're led astray
because they fail to come to terms with the real meaning of death.</p>

<p>Rather than see death as a friend, or even as a sister, as St. Josemaría
says in <em>The Way,</em> Points 735 and 739, they view it as an enormous
catastrophe, as something that will undermine all their worldly hopes
and accomplishments.</p>

<p>I remember accompanying an elderly lady in another country once, at the
moment of her death.</p>

<p>I was rather impressed by some of her final words. She said, ‘If I had
known death was so beautiful, I would have tried to die a long time
ago.’ She was a very holy woman and very well prepared for her death.</p>

<p>This earthbound approach explains why death has to be put in the closet,
as it were. It's too uncomfortable a subject to deal with. Instead of
looking upon death as the key to the fullness of joy, the tendency is to
see it as the end of the road, the checkout counter on what is for them
a kind of terrestrial shopping spree.</p>

<p>These misguided people have lost sight of the fact that every person is
in possession of an eternal soul. In <em>The Way</em>, Point 744, St Josemaría
says, “Death is nothing more than a change of lodging.”</p>

<p>The liturgy often reminds us of that truth. In the Preface for the Dead,
it says, “Life is changed, not taken away.”</p>

<p>Life changes. It's not something we're deprived of.</p>

<p>Christians believe that death represents the end of an earthly
pilgrimage. Believers prepare for death on a daily basis.</p>

<p>It's through the sanctification of ordinary realities that we will win
heaven as an eternal reward and the Christian who behaves accordingly
will not be alarmed by death's arrival.</p>

<p>That person will have been patiently readying themselves for this
definitive encounter with the Lord. In the words of St Cyprian, “Death
is a stepping up into eternity after we have run in this earthly race”
(St. Cyprian, <em>Treatise on Mortality</em>).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow,</em> Point 891, St. Josemaría says: “If at any time you feel
uneasy at the thought of our sister death, because you see yourself to
be such a poor creature, take heart. Heaven awaits us and consider: what
will it be like when all the infinite beauty and greatness, and
happiness and love of God will be poured into the poor vessel of clay
that the human being is, to satisfy it eternally with the freshness of
an ever new joy?”</p>

<p>Death acquires a new meaning with the death and resurrection of Christ.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “God did not make death, and He does not
delight in the death of the living” (Wis. 1:13). There was no such thing
as death with all its pain and suffering, before our first parents
committed original sin. Death is a consequence of sin.</p>

<p>Man had been given the gift of immortality in the Garden of Paradise.
But when our first parents committed that sin, they lost that gift. They
lost that gift! St. Paul says, “By the sin of one man, death entered the
world” (Rom. 5:12).</p>

<p>The rebellion of our first parents led to the loss of that preternatural
gift. By his disobedience, Adam lost his friendship with God and that
gift of immortal life.</p>

<p>Since that time, our passage to the house of the Father, our final
resting place, takes us to this fateful gateway—the moment when we
“depart out of this world to the Father” as quoted in St. John (John
13:1).</p>

<p>St. Paul says Jesus Christ “abolished death and brought life” (2 Tim.
1:10). He removed the essential evil from death and gave it a new
meaning, making death into a stepping stone to Life.</p>

<p>His victory is shared by all who believe in Him and who participate in
His Life. Our Lord has told us, “I am the resurrection and the life. He
who believes in me, though he die, yet shall he live. And whoever lives
and believes in me shall never die” (John 11: 25-26). Our Lord's words
can fill us with hope, a hope that does not disappoint.</p>

<p>Death is the enemy of the natural life of man. Christ has converted it
into our friend and sister. Though the human person suffers defeat at
the hands of this foe, he or she can in the end be triumphant thanks to
Christ's immortal sacrifice.</p>

<p>For a materialistic society in which pleasure and comfort reign supreme,
death and even life itself are devoid of lasting value. Those who adopt
a pagan lifestyle behave as if suffering, failure, and death were curses
to be avoided at any cost.</p>

<p>Such people act as if Christ never achieved redemption.</p>

<p>The Psalmist says in his prayer to God: “Those who hate the righteous
will be condemned” (Ps. 34:21). But “precious in the sight of the Lord
is the death of his saints” (Ps. 116:15).</p>

<p>From her earliest days, the Church has celebrated the anniversaries of
the death by martyrdom of her saints. The Church likes to say that these
are the <em>dies natalis</em>, the birthdays to that new Life which entails joy
without end.</p>

<p>St. John tells us in the Book of Revelation, “I heard a voice from
heaven saying: ‘Write this: Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord
henceforth.’ ‘Blessed indeed,’ says the Spirit, ‘that they may rest from
their labors, for their deeds follow them.” (Rev. 14:13).</p>

<p>We know that we will be rewarded for even the smallest service that we
have done for the Lord. We're told in St Matthew that “whoever
gives...even a cup of cold water, because he is a disciple of the Lord,
shall not go without His reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>We have the joy of looking forward to every little thing being rewarded
that we have done for other people in this world.</p>

<p><em>Gaudium et Spes</em> of the Second Vatican Council has said: “For after we
have obeyed the Lord, and in His Spirit nurtured on earth the value of
human dignity, brotherhood, and freedom, and indeed all the good fruits
of our nature and enterprise, we will find them again, but freed of
stain,…transfigured, when Christ hands over to the Father: ‘a kingdom
eternal and universal...’” (Vatican II, <em>Gaudium et Spes,</em> Point 39).</p>

<p>All the things of the world will perish and be forgotten, but their good
“deeds will follow them.”</p>

<p>We can be reminded of that phrase of Scripture which says, “Do not store
up for yourselves treasures on earth, where dust and moth consume, and
thieves break in and steal. But store up for yourselves treasures in
heaven” (Matt. 6:19-20).</p>

<p>Every day, every hour, is an opportunity for us to store up for
ourselves treasures in heaven.</p>

<p>Death can teach us many things about life. It can inspire us to live
with only what we need, to be detached from the things we own and use,
to respect the lasting merit of our good works, and to get rid of
superfluous things—many good things.</p>

<p>Occasionally in your family, go through the cabinets of your children or
their rooms and help them to make a decision to pass on to others what
they don't need, so that in a subtle way, they get all these messages:
they are not here just to accumulate things.</p>

<p>It's not that the one who has accumulated the most toys wins. Rather,
the more we have gotten rid of things and passed them on to others will
we be ready for the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>Death also teaches us to make good use of every day, to have goals, to
have a plan for our spiritual life and, also for our professional and
material life. Things I need to do today, with priorities, to do number
one and then number two.</p>

<p>Ancient writers used to use the phrase <em>Carpe diem</em> <em>(</em>Horace<em>, Odes
1,11,17).</em> Horace, an early Latin writer, used this phrase ‘Seize the
day’ to encourage people to make the most of the present moment.</p>

<p>Look around you and see if people on your mode of transport or people
that you meet every day are making the most out of every moment. If they
have an article or a book they're reading in spare moments, in the
little pieces of time—one writer used to call them the butts of
time—the little pieces of time throughout the day when maybe nothing
is happening, to have something to be reading, something to be doing,
catching up on other little projects or little things to be done here
and there. Using our time well.</p>

<p>These words of Horace were a pagan maxim, but we can impart a Christian
meaning to it by living each day with joy as if it were our whole life.
We can ask ourselves: What is the will of God for me today?</p>

<p>From the things that happened from hour to hour—ups and downs,
reversals of fortune, pieces of good news, pieces of bad news—we can
decipher what exactly it is that God wants me to do today and try to
follow His will with a lot of peace and serenity.</p>

<p>It's a chance that will never be repeated. Time is like a flowing
divine treasure: it comes, it's here, and then it goes, never to
return.</p>

<p>During our examination of conscience, we can please Our Lord with the
quantity of acts of love, of our aspirations, of our moments of talking
to our guardian angel, of favors we've done on behalf of others, of the
quiet fulfillment of our duties, of our struggle to be patient.</p>

<p>Perhaps Our Lord will convert these deeds into splendid jewels of
eternal worth. “Death ends our time of meriting” (<em>cf</em>. Leo X, Bull,
<em>Exsurge Domine</em>, June 15, 1520). Interesting point.</p>

<p>I know a priest who went to see a man on his deathbed. This priest was
really renowned for making money, helping people to be detached. He
reminded this man on his deathbed: Look, after you die, really nothing
belongs to you. It all belongs to God.</p>

<p>There's not much merit in giving away things after you die. There's
much more merit in giving away things while you are still alive. That
way you gain merit—an act of generosity, charity, justice.</p>

<p>We can make a resolution not to waste the days that remain to us in our
lives. We do not know when we will die.</p>

<p>Every so often we hear of people dying young, or we hear of accidents,
or we hear of people having heart attacks, young people. Those are like
little gentle reminders to us from the Holy Spirit that we live in the
hands of God.</p>

<p>That very uncertainty helps us to be watchful, like the doorkeeper
awaiting the arrival of his master (<em>cf</em>. Luke 12:35-36). Hence the
importance of regular sacramental Confession to be always in a state of
grace. The Church has always recommended regular Confession.</p>

<p>Our examination of conscience at the end of the day can help us to
recognize and discover the failings we may have had this day—failings
of charity, of patience, of kindness, of justice, or failings in
sensuality, failings in pride and vanity.</p>

<p>Therefore, we can build up those little details that we want to bring to
Confession at the end of the week, to cleanse our soul from venial sin,
and from any omissions that would indicate a lack of love.</p>

<p>Sometimes our greatest faults or sins could be our sins of omission, or
our sins of neglect, things that we could have done and didn't do, or
things that we could have done much better than we did.</p>

<p>Our meditation on death can move us to work more earnestly on the great
project of our own sanctification. St. Paul says to the Ephesians,
<em>“</em>Look carefully then how you walk, not as unwise men but as wise,
making the most of time” (Eph. 5:15-16).</p>

<p>We need to make up for lost time<em>.</em> Let us take to heart that wise
observation written almost twenty centuries ago. Seneca, an ancient
Latin writer, said, “It's not that we have so little time,” he said,
“but that we have wasted so much of it” (Seneca<em>, De brevitate vitae,</em>
1,3). He was writing in the early centuries. Clocks and stopwatches had
not yet been invented.</p>

<p>We could make an act of contrition for all the time that we may have
wasted in our lives and make a resolution to make many wise decisions
about our use of time.</p>

<p>We should want to have a long life so that we can give God abundant
service. St. Josemaría used to say that if God has invested an awful lot
in our education, in our formation, it's very good that we give Him a
good return on that investment. It makes good economic sense.</p>

<p>It's a good thing to ask Our Lord for a long life so that we can serve
more, so that hopefully we go before Our Lord with our arms full. It's
so right for us to love life since this is a gift from God.</p>

<p>I heard of a person once who was involved in fundraising for a center
for young people where they would get a lot of formation, growth in
holiness, and learn many other skills, and develop their personality,
and develop many other virtues.</p>

<p>To try and get his friends to contribute to the growth of this youth
center, a center for young people, he said, ‘Look, if you buy a brick in
this place, that brick will always be there. Long after you die, that
brick will still be there. It would be like an investment for the
future. That brick helping that center to form young people will give
great glory to God over time and all that glory will be to your benefit
at the end of time, at the last judgment.’</p>

<p>There are ways that we can remind people that they have to make good use
of their time and also of everything that they have, for that abundant
service of God.</p>

<p>We have the grace to open horizons for them, to see those things that
perhaps they haven't seen, so that they also can go before Our Lord
with their arms full.</p>

<p>If we're faithful to our Christian vocation, when the time comes for
our encounter with Our Lord we will be prepared to make a tremendous act
of love for Our Father God.</p>

<p>What a beautiful thing to die with words of love on our lips. That holy
woman that I just mentioned did precisely that. She went out of this
world giving praise to God.</p>

<p>“As in one's whole life, so also in one's death. Each one should
struggle to give glory to the Lord Our God” (St. Ignatius of Loyola,
<em>Constitutions</em>).</p>

<p>It's good to be aware that most people die as they have lived. The
concept of last-minute deathbed conversions is very rare.</p>

<p>It's today we have to live better. This hour. Today we have to practice
the virtues. Today we have to live with a greater awareness that there
is an end to all this.</p>

<p>St Ignatius of Loyola says, “May He be honored and glorified. May other
people be edified by the example of our patience and fortitude, by the
testimony of our living faith, our hope, and our love for the eternal
goods” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Our last moment on earth should be spent for the glory of God.</p>

<p>I remember a 19-year-old person dying in a hospital once in Asia and the
doctor who was looking after him—this young fellow who had no
religion, no formation, no nothing—remarked, ‘He died like a soldier.’
It's rather a beautiful comment.</p>

<p>We're called to die like soldiers, but “soldiers of Christ” (2 Tim.
2:3).</p>

<p>It will be a great joy when we give Our Lord the present of our
professional work well done; of the apostolate that we've tried to do
with all the opportunities that He's given to us; of those many, many
details of service to our neighbors, in our family life, in our
environment, in our office, in our club, in our neighborhood; to present
to Him the joy that we contributed to our family life; and the effort
that we made to overcome our defects.</p>

<p>We will leave behind us works that will endure. We will take our
departure from this world in a way described by a poet: “I left my love
the shore and the singing current. I did not return to the bank for his
love, for his love was the water” (B. Llorens, <em>A secret spring).</em></p>

<p>We know that if we live close to Our Lady all through our life, every
hour and every day in the presence of Our Mother, she will also be with
us. We say so frequently and throughout our life, we have said now, “at
the hour of our death” (Prayer, <em>Hail Mary</em>).</p>

<p>There was a lady in Singapore whose husband passed away. But when he was
alive, they would go to the happy hour every day in the local pub, and
she would put on her earrings and her make-up and they'd go and have a
good time.</p>

<p>Then her husband passed away, and she ended her days in a home for the
elderly.</p>

<p>She had no religion, but the good nuns were converting her and teaching
her the basic prayers, and she learned all of them very well.</p>

<p>During this time, when the time came for the happy hour each day, she
liked to remember the good old times and to pretend that she was going
to the happy hour. She'd also put on her earrings, maybe some make-up,
to pretend she was accompanying her husband to the happy hour.</p>

<p>She learned all of the basic prayers, ready for her Baptism. But she
couldn't quite master the second part of the <em>Hail Mary</em> because she
kept saying: Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners, now and at
the happy hour of our death, Amen. But somehow, she had put her finger
on the nerve.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady to accompany us in that happy hour and to help any
people around us also to find Our Lady and to be with her in that very
special moment.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Cup of Cold Water</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cup of Cold Water" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-cup-of-cold-water/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“If anyone can give so much as a cup of cold water to one of these
little ones, because he is a disciple, then I tell you solemnly, he will
most certainly not lose his reward” (Matt. 10:42).</p>

<p>Giving a cup of cold water—and notice specifically how Scripture says
cold water, not warm water—to someone who needs it is not going to
make headlines. Most likely only the giver and the receiver will be
aware of it.</p>

<p>And yet Our Lord holds up this small act of kindness as having
tremendous value.</p>

<p>Even the simplest acts in which we lose ourselves for others have
eternal significance. The cloth of holiness is woven in small details.</p>

<p>With this and with other examples that Our Lord gives to us, He speaks
to us about the value of little things.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say, “A little act, done for love, is worth so
much!” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, 814).</p>

<p>Mother Teresa has said, “A few words of kindness may be very simple and
very brief, but their echoes are endless.”</p>

<p>On one occasion Our Lord sat up to the Temple treasury and He watched
people putting money into the receptacle for alms. The scene takes place
in one of the porticos, the so-called Treasure Chamber or Hall of
Offerings. The days of the Passion were almost upon Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord didn't comment at all on the many people who contributed large
amounts. But He saw a woman come up who was dressed in the typical garb
of widows, and who was obviously poor (Mark 12:41).</p>

<p>She had perhaps waited for the crowd to thin out before depositing two
small coins there. These coins had the least value of any in circulation
at the time.</p>

<p>St. Mark explains the real value of these particular units of currency
for the benefit of his non-Jewish readers, to whom his Gospel was
principally addressed. He wants everyone to know how very little they
were worth.</p>

<p>In men's eyes that anonymous offering had very little value. The two
coins were worth just a small amount. “That coin,” St. Mark says, “was
worth a quarter” (Mark 12:42). It's like a tenth of a denarius, which
was the basic monetary unit; a denarius was a day's wages for a farm
worker. And so, a quarter would scarcely buy anything.</p>

<p>If anyone was keeping a record of the offerings made that day in the
temple, he probably would have thought it was not worth recording that
widow's contribution. But we see that in fact this was the most
valuable contribution of all.</p>

<p>It would be so pleasing to God that Our Lord called together His
disciples, who were scattered around the place, so that they might be
taught the lesson to be learned from this widow.</p>

<p>Those tiny pieces of copper could scarcely be heard falling into the
treasury box. But Our Lord clearly perceived the love of this woman who
said nothing but who was giving all her savings to God.</p>

<p>“Jesus said, ‘Truly I say to you, this poor widow has put in more than
all those who are contributing to the treasury. For they all contributed
out of their abundance, but she out of her poverty has put in everything
she had, her whole living’” (Mark 12:43-44).</p>

<p>It often happens that what God considers important is very different
from what men consider important. His standard of measurement and ours
are not the same.</p>

<p>We are generally impressed by the big gesture, by unusual things of the
kind that attract everyone's attention. But God is moved by little
details filled with love—"a cup of cold water”—which are within the
radius of action of everyone, even small children.</p>

<p>Of course, He's also moved by happenings that we consider to be very
important, but only when they're carried out with the same spirit of
rectitude of intention, of humility, and of love.</p>

<p>The apostles, who later were to be the very foundation of the Church,
did not forget the lesson they were taught that day. That woman has
taught all of us to touch God's heart every day in the only way that
most of us can: through little things.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, Point 824, St. Josemaría says, “Have you noticed how human
love consists of little things? Well, divine Love also consists of
little things.”</p>

<p>In these passages of the Gospel, we learn the true value of these
things. We can turn everything that happens, no matter how
inconsequential it may seem, into something very pleasing to God. And
because it's pleasing to Him, it's turned into something of great
value. Only those things that we make pleasing to God have any true and
eternal value.</p>

<p>We could consider in our prayer the vast number of opportunities that
present themselves to us. We’re told by St. Francis de Sales, “Great
opportunities to serve God seldom arise, but little ones are frequent;
[and our Lord himself has told us that] ‘he who is faithful over a few
things will be placed over many’ (Luke 16:10). Do all things in the name
of God, and you will do all things well, provided you know how to
fulfill your duties properly.</p>

<p>“Then, whether you eat or drink, whether you sleep, or take recreation,
or turn the spit of an oven, you will profit greatly in God's sight by
doing all these things, because God wishes you to do them” (St. Francis
de Sales, <em>Introduction to the Devout Life</em>).</p>

<p>Often, it's the small things that make a job perfect, worthy of being
offered to God: the double-checking of an email or a WhatsApp message
that we write, the looking back to double-check on a room that we've
just cleaned, or a floor we've just polished, or a table we've just
laid, or some little professional job that we have done.</p>

<p>Perfection is in the details. It's not enough that what we're doing is
good, whether it's work or prayer or football or hockey or volleyball.
It also has to be well finished.</p>

<p>“For there to be virtue,” St. Thomas Aquinas teaches, “it is necessary
to attend to two things: to what is being done, and also to the way it
is being done” (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Quodlibet</em>, IV).</p>

<p>As far as the way it is being done is concerned, the final touches with
the chisel or brush can turn that work into a masterpiece, and Our Lord
wants us to work masterpieces every day.</p>

<p>On the other hand, shoddy workmanship, work which is done clumsily or
carelessly, is a sign of spiritual laziness or of lukewarmness in a
Christian who should be sanctifying himself through his daily work.</p>

<p>We're told in the Book of Revelation, “I know your works: you have the
name of being alive, and you are dead. ... For I have not found your
works perfect in the sight of my God” (Rev. 3:1-2).</p>

<p>The very nature of our Christian vocation demands that we take care of
little things. A teacher who picks up a piece of paper off the floor may
give a greater lesson to all his students, or to anybody who happens to
be in that particular corridor or place, than all the other classes he
may have given in his whole professional lifetime, because with that
little gesture we teach the value of order, of tidiness, but also the
value of the small things.</p>

<p>Our aim should be to imitate Our Lord during His years in Nazareth,
those long years of work, of family life, of friendly relationships with
His countrymen.</p>

<p>Doing little things with love for God's sake demands attention,
sacrifice, and generosity. A single isolated little detail may not in
itself be very important. St. Augustine says, “What is small is small,
but he who is faithful in small things is great” (St. Augustine, <em>On
Christian Doctrine</em>).</p>

<p>We're told in <em>The Way</em>, “Love is what gives little things their value”
(<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>The Way,</em> Point 814).</p>

<p>If this love were lacking, our endeavor to look after little things
would be pointless; it would become a mania or merely Pharisaical. We
would pay tithes in mint, dill and cumin—as the Pharisees do—and we
would run the risk of leaving out the most essential points of the law,
those of justice and of mercy.</p>

<p>Although what we have to offer may seem very little—just as the
contribution of that poor widow did—it acquires a great value if you
place it on the altar and unite it to the offering that Our Lord makes
of Himself to the Father.</p>

<p>St. John Paul said in one of his homilies: “Our humble
surrender—insignificant in itself like the oil of the widow of
Sarepta, or the poor widow's mite—becomes acceptable in God's eyes
through its union with the offering of Jesus” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>,
November 7, 1982).</p>

<p>At other times, details in our work, in our study, in our relationships
with other people are the crowning of something good which would remain
incomplete without those details.</p>

<p>One of the most obvious warning signs that we're starting on the path
to lukewarmness is that we give little value to the details of our life
of piety, to details in our work, and to little specific acts of virtue.
If we ignore these symptoms, we end up paying little attention to big
things as well.</p>

<p>“The misfortune is all the more grievous and incurable,” said one
writer, “when we barely notice that we are sliding downwards and only
slowly come to realize this … That if we are in this state, we give a
mortal blow to the life of the spirit, and that can be something obvious
to everyone” (Benedict Baur, <em>Frequent Confession</em>).</p>

<p>Love for God, on the other hand, is shown by our inventiveness, by our
unremitting zeal, and our effort to find in everything an occasion for
showing our love of God and for giving service to others.</p>

<p>Holiness is a cloth woven of little details. God is not indifferent to a
love that knows how to care for small details. He's not indifferent,
for example, as to whether we go to greet Him, first of all, when we go
into a church or when we happen to be passing by a church.</p>

<p>He's not indifferent to the effort we make to arrive on time (better, a
few minutes early) for Holy Mass, to the way we genuflect in front of
Him in the tabernacle, or the way we behave or try to be recollected in
His presence.</p>

<p>There was a man once who tried to do a lot of apostolate in his office,
befriending as many people as he could, being close to them, trying to
help them in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>He gave a lot of support to people in their marriage, in their family,
tried to invite them to recollections, to retreats, to grow spiritually.</p>

<p>But there was one man in the office who refused all of his overtures. He
had no time for these sorts of things.</p>

<p>But one day that man came to this other fellow and said, ‘Look, I have a
big problem in my marriage. My wife is about to divorce me. Can you give
me any advice?’</p>

<p>The original man was a bit surprised. He said, ‘You know, I've often
tried to give you advice or reach out to you in different ways, and you
never seemed very interested. Why do you come to me?’</p>

<p>The guy said, ‘Well, you're the only one that speaks about anything
serious around here.’</p>

<p>The original man said, ‘Okay, let me think about it and pray about
it’—which is always a good thing to say to people because they realize
you're taking them seriously.</p>

<p>That evening in his prayer, he brought this topic to talk to Our Lord
about it. He couldn't really see any great solutions. But for some
reason, a scene in a movie with St. Josemaría came to mind, where St.
Josemaría mentioned how husbands should try and bring their wives some
flowers from time to time.</p>

<p>He was thinking to himself, ‘It's a bit late for flowers. That's not a
very prudent sort of advice to give this fellow.’</p>

<p>But that was all he saw in his prayer. With a lot of supernatural
outlook, he thought, ‘If that's all I see in my prayer, that, maybe, is
what I have to transmit to this fellow.’</p>

<p>But he wasn't terribly convinced himself. It didn't seem very helpful.</p>

<p>The following day, he told his friend, ‘Look, I thought about this, and
I prayed about it. My suggestion to you is that you perhaps bring some
flowers to your wife.’</p>

<p>The second fellow was thinking, ‘I was really wasting my time talking to
you. What a stupid piece of advice. She's about to divorce me and
you're telling me to bring her flowers.’</p>

<p>He dismissed his suggestion and went off. But that evening, as he was
going home, he was thinking about this and he thought, ‘Even if I get
her flowers, I suppose it can't do any harm. The worst thing that could
happen is that she might hit me with them.’</p>

<p>So he bought some flowers. When he got home, his wife opened the door
and he handed her the flowers. She burst into tears and said, ‘This is
the first time in twenty years that you have brought me flowers.’ After
that, they lived happily ever after.</p>

<p>Sometimes the little things can make a huge difference.</p>

<p>Moreover, when we see somebody make a devout genuflection before the
tabernacle, it's easy for us to think: that person has faith and loves
God. That sign of adoration helps others to have greater faith and
greater love.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI says, “It may perhaps seem to you that the Liturgy is made
up of little things: the position of the body, genuflections,
inclinations of the head; the way the thurible, the missal, and the
cruets are to be moved. It is then that we have to recall Christ's
words in the Gospel: ‘He who is faithful in a very little is faithful
also in much’” (Luke 16:10).</p>

<p>“Moreover,” said St. Paul VI, “nothing is small in the Sacred Liturgy,
when we think of the greatness of him to whom it is directed” (Paul VI,
<em>Address</em>, May 30, 1967).</p>

<p>Our spirit of mortification usually consists in specific little
sacrifices throughout the day: keeping up a persevering struggle in our
particular examination of conscience, sobriety at meals, punctuality,
being pleasant to people, getting up on time, not leaving our work for
later even though we find it difficult or trying, having order in our
work and taking care of the tools or implements and materials that we
use, being grateful for whatever food is placed in front of us, not
allowing ourselves whims and fancies.</p>

<p>In order to live charity in a way that becomes ever more refined and
heroic, it would be necessary for us to apply this approach right down
to the smallest and least important details of daily life.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in the <em>Furrow</em> says, “Your duty to be a brother to all
souls will lead you to practice the ‘apostolate of little things’
without others noticing it. You will want to serve them so that for
them, their way becomes agreeable” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 737).</p>

<p>At times it will mean taking a real interest in what other people are
saying; at other times it will mean putting aside our own personal
concerns so as to give our attention to the people we live with.</p>

<p>A little girl was talking to her father who was reading the newspaper
and she said to him, ‘Daddy, you're not listening to me.’</p>

<p>Continuing to read the newspaper, he said, ‘Yes, I am. I'm hearing
every word.’</p>

<p>But then she said, ‘But you're not looking at me.’</p>

<p>The child was aware, and the child wanted his full attention. A small
thing, but it meant everything to the child.</p>

<p>Care of those little things will mean not getting annoyed about what are
really trivia, not being touchy, making people feel welcome.</p>

<p>If those little disturbances come during the day, little things, changes
of plans, or funny things go wrong, that can be a trigger to repeat our
<em>Morning Offering</em>.</p>

<p>We shall tell Our Lord: I'm really serious with the <em>Offering</em> that I
made to you. It's these things I wanted to offer to you.</p>

<p>We will try to help others in a way that they may not notice, or might
never find out, but which lightens their burden. We try to pray to God
for them when they're in need, to avoid having critical spirit towards
them, and always to be grateful to them.</p>

<p>All of these things are within the reach and the scope of each one of
us. And we should try and do the same where each one of the virtues is
concerned.</p>

<p>If we give attention to little things, we will live each day to the
full, and will know how to fill each moment with the sense of
preparation for eternity. To do this, we could frequently ask Our Lady
for help.</p>

<p>Our Lady, Mother of God, pray for us, now, and in every ordinary little
situation of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>PKN</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Merciful Messiah</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Merciful Messiah" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/a-merciful-messiah/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry for all these
people.’ Large crowds came to him, bringing the lame, the crippled, the
blind, the dumb, and many others; and they put these down at his feet
and he cured them. The crowds were astonished to hear the dumb speaking,
to see the cripples whole again, the lame walking, and the blind with
their sight restored” (Matt. 15:32, 29-31).</p>

<p>We’re told, “Jesus called his disciples to him and said, ‘I feel sorry
for all these people.’” This is why the heart of Our Lord is so often
moved. In His mercy, He was to follow up this episode with the wonderful
miracle of the multiplication of the loaves (Matt. 15:32-39).</p>

<p>We're reminded in these passages to turn always to the mercy of Our
Lord, and to meditate on His life, so as to learn to be merciful to
others.</p>

<p>The liturgy places this passage before us during Advent because of an
abundance of good things and the limitless mercy which will be the signs
of the coming of the Messiah.</p>

<p>“I feel sorry for all these people.” This is an overriding reason for
giving ourselves to others: to be compassionate and to have mercy.</p>

<p>In order to learn how to be merciful, we have to fix our eyes on Christ,
who comes “to save that which was lost” (Luke 19:10).</p>

<p>He doesn't come to crush the broken reed or to wholly extinguish the
wick that still smolders (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 12:20), but to take upon Himself
our wretchedness and save us from it, and to share in their misfortune
with those who suffer and are in need. Each page of the Gospel is an
example of divine mercy.</p>

<p>We should meditate on the life of Jesus because, as St. Josemaría says,
“[The life of] Jesus is a summary and compendium of the [story] of
the divine mercy. Many other scenes of the Gospel,” he continues, “also
make a deep impact on us, such as his forgiveness of the woman taken in
adultery, the parables—the prodigal son, the lost sheep, the pardoned
debtor—and the raising to life of the son of the widow at Naim.</p>

<p>“How many reasons based on justice could Christ have found to work as
great a wonder as this last one! The only son of that poor widow had
died—he who gave meaning to her life, he who would help her in her old
age. Jesus did not perform his miracle out of justice, but out of
compassion, because his heart was moved by the spectacle of human
suffering” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 7).</p>

<p>The mercy of God is the essence of the whole history of salvation, the
reason for all His saving actions.</p>

<p>God is mercy. And this divine attribute is like the engine supplying the
power that energizes the life story of every human being.</p>

<p>When the apostles wanted to sum up God's revelation, His mercy always
appeared to them to be the essence of an eternal and gratuitous plan
springing from God's generosity. With good reason, the Psalmist could
affirm: “The earth is full of the steadfast love of the Lord” (Ps.
33:5).</p>

<p>Mercy is constant in God's attitude to mankind. And recourse to it is
the universal remedy for all our ills, including those for which we
thought there was no answer.</p>

<p>Meditating on the mercy of God should fill us with great confidence “now
and at the hour of our death,” as we pray in the <em>Hail Mary</em>. What a joy
to be able to say to God, with St. Augustine: “All my hope lies solely
in your great mercy!” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>, Point 6,19).</p>

<p>Solely in that, Lord. On your mercy rests all my hope. Not on my merits,
but on your mercy.</p>

<p>In a special way, God shows His mercy towards sinners: He pardons them
their sins. The Pharisees often criticize Him for this. He rebuts their
criticisms saying: “It is not those who are well who have need of a
physician, but those who are sick” (Matt. 9:12).</p>

<p>We who are sinners are sick of soul and need to have recourse many times
to the divine mercy. In the Psalms, we say, “Show us, O Lord, your
mercy; and grant us your salvation” (Ps. 85:7). The Church repeats these
words continually in this liturgical season.</p>

<p>On so many occasions, every day even, we will have need to have recourse
to the merciful Heart of Jesus and say: “Lord, if you will, you can make
me clean” (Matt. 8:2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul in his encyclical <em>Dives in Misericordia</em> (Rich in
Mercy), says, especially in these circumstances, “The knowledge of God,
the God of mercy and benign love, is a constant and inexhaustible source
of conversion, not only as a momentary interior act, but also as a
stable disposition, like a state of mind. Those who come to know God in
this way, those who so regard Him, cannot live without being incessantly
transformed by Him.”</p>

<p>We can also say, as it is said in the Book of Sirach: “How great is the
mercy of the Lord, and his forgiveness for those who turn to him!” (Sir.
17:29). Great is the divine mercy toward each one of us.</p>

<p>This can lead us to turn frequently to God, in repentance for our faults
and sins, especially in that sacrament of divine mercy which we call
Confession.</p>

<p>God has placed a condition for our obtaining His compassion and mercy
for our offenses and weaknesses. The condition is that we too should
have a heart of compassion for those around us.</p>

<p>In the parable of the good Samaritan (Luke 10:30-37), Our Lord teaches
us the attitude that we should adopt towards a neighbor in distress.
We're not permitted to “pass by on the other side” in detached
indifference. Rather we must “go” to him.</p>

<p>One morning many years ago, I was going to say Mass in a conference
center outside Dublin. It was, maybe, a 45-minute drive. I was a little
bit late, so I had my foot on the accelerator. Then I happened to see a
car coming out of a side road and hitting a lorry. The front wing of the
car was torn off. It was a bit dramatic.</p>

<p>I slowed down. I could see that the only damage really was to the car.
Nobody was injured. There was a bit of drama, but nothing else. So, I
kept going and I put my foot on the accelerator to try and catch up on
the time that I had lost.</p>

<p>But after going about 100 meters, I remembered the story of the Gospel
about the priest who went by on the other side of the road.</p>

<p>Listening to my conscience, I had to turn around and go back and
double-check that everybody was okay, and give my phone number as a
witness, and a few more things. Then I proceeded with my journey a bit
more serenely than before.</p>

<p>We can all be that person who goes by on the other side of the road with
all sorts of hurried excuses. St. John Paul, in his Apostolic Lette<em>r
Salvifici doloris</em> (“The Salvation of Sorrow or Pain”) says: “A good
Samaritan is one who stops to relieve the suffering of the other, no
matter who he or she may be. This stopping is not just merely from
curiosity, but rather from the desire to make ourselves available.</p>

<p>“It's a specific interior disposition of the heart, which also has its
emotional side. Good Samaritans are those who are affected by the
suffering they see around them; they are genuinely moved by their
neighbor's misfortune.”</p>

<p>Each of us has to feel bad that people around us do not perhaps have the
dignity or the care that they should have as human beings. And it's not
enough for us to feel bad about it. We have to try and do something
about it, and infect other people with that sort of thinking,
particularly our children, with our words and with our examples.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “If Christ, who knows the interior of man,
emphasizes this compassion, this means that it's important for our
whole attitude towards the sufferings of others. Therefore one must
cultivate this sensitivity of heart, which bears witness to compassion
towards a suffering person. Sometimes this compassion remains the only
or the principal expression of our love for and of our solidarity with
the sufferer” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici doloris</em>,
Point 28, February 11, 1984).</p>

<p>The word compassion comes from two Latin words, <em>com passio</em>, to suffer
with.</p>

<p>Throughout Sacred Scripture there's an urgency on God's part to see
that men also have the stirrings of sympathy and deep-seated feelings of
mercy, that they too have this “compassion for another's misery, which
moves us to remedy it, if at all possible” (St. Augustine, <em>The City of
God)</em>.</p>

<p>We can look around us and see in our home, in our office, in our
workshop, in our neighborhood—is there not some person who's
handicapped, either physically or morally, or elderly, who perhaps needs
urgently our time, our affection, and our attention?</p>

<p>Our Lord promises us happiness if we have a merciful heart towards
others, and gives assurance that “we will obtain mercy” (Heb. 4:16) from
God in the same measure as we show it to our fellow men.</p>

<p>The scope for mercy is as great as the extent of the human suffering
that needs to be remedied. And, since mankind is subject to misery and
calamity in the physical, intellectual, and moral order, the possible
works of mercy are innumerable—as many as men have needs—though
traditionally, by way of example, fourteen ‘works of mercy’ have been
cited, since in them, this virtue is capable of being exercised in a
special way.</p>

<p>Our attitude of compassion and mercy must, in the first place, be shown
towards those who are near us—our family, our friends, our close
associates—to those whom God has placed at our side, and then to those
beyond who are most in need.</p>

<p>Mercy will frequently consist in our attention to the health, the
recreation, and the nourishment of those whom God has commended to our
care. The sick merit a special attention in terms of our company and our
real interest in their illness, as we show them how and help them to
offer their sufferings to God.</p>

<p>In a society dehumanized by frequent attacks on the family, more and
more old people and those who are ill are left without consolation and
affection. Visiting them in their loneliness is a work of mercy that has
never been more necessary.</p>

<p>The time spent in keeping them company is rewarded by God in a special
way: “As you did it to one of the least of these my brethren, you did it
to me,” said Our Lord (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Alongside the so-called material works of mercy, we should also carry
out those that are spiritual. In the first place it is our privilege and
duty <em>to correct those in</em> <em>error</em> with our advice when the opportunity
arises, and charitably, without ever causing offense.</p>

<p>Secondly, it is <em>to teach those who don't know,</em> especially with regard
to ignorance of religion, an ignorance which is the great enemy of God;
it increases daily in alarming proportions so that catechesis has become
a work of mercy of prime importance and urgency. St. Teresa of Calcutta
says ignorance is the greatest poverty.</p>

<p>Next comes giving <em>counsel to the doubting</em>, honestly and with the right
intention, so as to help them on their way to God. Then follows the
<em>consolation of the afflicted</em>, by sharing their sorrow and encouraging
them to recover their happiness in their supernatural understanding of
the pain they suffer.</p>

<p><em>Pardon for those who have offended us</em>, promptly and as often as
necessary, without giving excessive importance to the offense. We are
advised too, <em>to give help to the needy</em>, carrying out this service
generously and joyfully.</p>

<p>And finally, we have to <em>pray for the living and the dead</em>, feeling
ourselves linked in a special way through the Communion of Saints to
those we owe most because of family relationships, or friendship, or
whatever else.</p>

<p>Our attitude of merciful benevolence towards others must extend to many
different aspects of life because, says St. John Chrysostom, “nothing
can make you such an imitator of Christ as your concern for others.
Although you fast, although you sleep on the floor, even though, I dare
to say, you kill yourself, if you are not attentive to your neighbor,
you have done very little; you are very far from being an image of
Christ” (St. John Chrysostom, <em>Commentary on the First Epistle to the
Corinthians</em>).</p>

<p>We will ourselves obtain God's mercy and perhaps also merit it for
others in that immense depth of “mercy that extends from generation to
generation,” as Our Lady prophesied to her cousin Elizabeth (Luke 1:50).</p>

<p>We can also call down the divine mercy on ourselves, who are so much in
need of it. As Christians, we manifest our unity of life by encouraging
the works of justice and mercy. Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse
the lepers...</p>

<p>From the Church's earliest days, faithful Christians spread the faith
to all parts of the world. From those first years too, vast numbers of
Christians have “committed their powers and their lives to liberation
from every form of oppression and to the promotion of human dignity. The
experience of the saints and the example of so many works of service to
one's neighbor are an incentive and a beacon for the liberating
undertakings that are needed today,” said the Sacred Congregation for
the Doctrine of the Faith.</p>

<p>They are needed perhaps with an even greater urgency than in other
periods of history.</p>

<p>Our faith in Christ moves us to be aware of our common involvement with
the problems and shortages that other people experience, often with
their ignorance and their lack of economic resources.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says this solidarity with our fellow man is not a
“superficial sentiment about the evils that beset so many people,
whether close to us or far away,” but “a firm and persevering
determination to strive for the common good; that is to say, for the
good of all and of all individuals, so that we may all be truly
responsible for all persons” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Sollicitudo rei
socialis</em>–The Concern of the Church for the Social Order, Point 38,
December 3, 1987).</p>

<p>Faith leads us to feel a deep respect for others, for each person, and
never to remain indifferent to other people's needs.</p>

<p>Following Christ will manifest itself in deeds of justice and mercy; it
will show itself too in our determination to get to know the principles
of the social doctrine of the Church and to carry them out, first of all
in all our surroundings, right there where we live.</p>

<p>I remember my father coming back from bringing us to swimming lessons as
kids. We'd see sometimes a crocodile file of orphans who were going to
a local orphanage and were coming from, maybe, the beach as well.</p>

<p>We didn't know who these people were, what these kids were about, or
what was their problem. We didn't understand. I remember him buying ice
cream for those kids, and we were still left with question marks.</p>

<p>Only many years later do you realize what that little gesture was, from
a father of a family, in silence, doing that little gesture. It left its
mark.</p>

<p>This period coming up to Christmas is a very interesting period, a
potential period to engrave these messages in the lives of our children.</p>

<p>It should be possible to say of each one of us at the end of our lives,
as it was said about Our Lord: “He went about doing good” (<em>cf</em>. Acts
10:38).</p>

<p>We have to do good within our own families, among our colleagues at work
and among our friends, and even with those people whom we just chance to
come across.</p>

<p>Our Lord has opportunities outlined for us. There's a document of the
Spanish Episcopal Conference, <em>Catholics in Public Life,</em> which says:
“As disciples of Christ, we have to be stewards of fraternity, whatever
occasions and circumstances life brings with it. When a man or woman
lives the Christian spirit in all its intensity, all his or her
activities and relationships reflect and communicate God's love and the
surpassing goods of the Kingdom.</p>

<p>“As Christians we need to know how to make fast and strengthen our
relationships each day with our families, our friends, and our
neighbors, whether we are at work or at leisure, sealing them with the
seal of Christian love, which is simplicity, truthfulness, faithfulness,
meekness, generosity, solidarity, and joy.”</p>

<p>We can ask for the mercy of God to be extended to our generation through
Mary, Mother of Mercy, our life, our sweetness, and our hope.</p>

<p>Now that the Feast of the Immaculate Conception is so near, our
confident reliance on Our Lady will, if we have recourse to her, be more
continuous and loving.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MML</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abandonment</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abandonment" /><published>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/abandonment/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see
me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your
pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My
Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel,
intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in the Gospel, “Can you not buy two sparrows for a penny?
Yet not one falls to the ground without your Father knowing” (Matt.
10:29).</p>

<p>Our Lord uses this curious analogy of us with sparrows. It’s curious
that He would want to compare us to sparrows, but yet there is a very
important message there.</p>

<p>We look at a sparrow, and you blow at a sparrow, it could fall over;
very fragile, very timid, not very strong. And yet God tells us that
this sparrow can't do a single thing “without your Father knowing”
about it and we are “of much more value than any sparrow” (Matt. 10:31).</p>

<p>Our Lord is inviting us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of
trust and abandonment. This trust and abandonment, to a large extent,
flows from the fact that we are children of God.</p>

<p>We celebrated a few days ago, at the beginning of the month, the Baptism
of Our Lord, the institution of the Sacrament of Baptism. Through that
sacrament and through all the other sacraments we get divine grace into
our soul.</p>

<p>Divine grace is the presence of the Blessed Trinity within us.</p>

<p>Our Lord said we will “come and make our abode in him” (cf. John 14:23),
and so when we are in the state of grace, God is in our soul. Therefore,
all the fruits of God can be present in our life, in our words, in our
actions.</p>

<p>Hopefully, people can somehow detect that this person is trying to lead
a holy life, that they're in a state of grace, and therefore God is in
control.</p>

<p>If we are not in the state of grace, if God is not in our soul in grace,
then the devil may be there. Then all the fruits of the devil can be
present in our life, in our works, in our actions, in the atmosphere we
carry with us.</p>

<p>Because God is there within us in our soul in grace, we're told in
Scripture that we become “children of God” (1 John 3:1). We're told
that we're carried in the palm of the hand of a God who loves us.</p>

<p>Therefore, everything that happens to us in our life, we can try to see
from a supernatural perspective, and see that God is somehow in control,
or He has permitted this particular thing—this joy, or sometimes this
sorrow, or this contradiction, or this difficulty, or this challenge.</p>

<p>Or sometimes God can sweep the feet from under us and leave us hanging
there. And when that happens it’s because He wants us to learn how to
trust in Him, to have a great sense of abandonment like the sparrows.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, Our Lord says: “Look at the birds of the
air: they neither sow nor reap or gather into barns, and yet your
heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us in our spiritual life to have a great sense of
abandonment and trust and leave things in His hands. On the one hand, He
wants us to use all the human initiative that we have to solve problems.</p>

<p>When He sent the apostles out, He said: “Go ye therefore, teach all
nations” (Matt. 28:19). He didn't build chapels. He didn't build
schools or hospitals. He didn't give them technology or money or all
the other means to fulfill their mission.</p>

<p>He just sent them out with a few ideas. Those ideas were very important
ideas, and He wanted them to convert the world with those ideas. He
wanted them to be very clear that He would be acting in them and through
them.</p>

<p>What He wanted was their faith, their trust, and their abandonment, that
He would be at work through them.</p>

<p>Shortly after I was ordained, I was giving a retreat in the south of
Spain. (I was ordained there.) There was a number of men on the retreat.</p>

<p>On the first day of the retreat, an 80-year-old man came to chat with
me. Usually, people wait a few hours or a few days before they talk to
the priest about their resolutions or what they've got from the
retreat.</p>

<p>This man came first thing that morning and told me, “You know, I've
been attending recollections of Opus Dei for a number of years, and the
person in charge of the recollection asked me if I would come to this
retreat. I said no, and I had three very good reasons for saying no.</p>

<p>“One is that I train a certain type of horse. There are some people
coming these days to buy some of my horses from another country. I want
to be there when they come.</p>

<p>“Secondly, there are some people coming to put drains on my house and
I've been waiting for two years for them to come to put drains on my
house. I want to be there also when they come.</p>

<p>“Thirdly, it's the weekend of the local fiesta, which is a big thing in
Spain. Ever since I was seven, I have never missed this local feast. All
my friends will be there. It’s a time to catch up. We meet, we talk, we
set ourselves up for the next year. It's just unthinkable that I
wouldn't be at the local fiesta.</p>

<p>“So I had three very good reasons for telling this man who was in charge
of this recollection that I would not go on the retreat. And he asked me
again a few weeks later, and again, I said no; and he asked me a third
time, and again, I said no.”</p>

<p>But then he said, “I began to feel very uncomfortable, and the only way
that I could find any peace was to finally say yes, and so here I am on
this retreat very reluctantly. I came thinking about all the things I'm
missing, but you know, I've only been here a couple of hours, and
already I'm very glad I came.</p>

<p>“Because you see, I've been attending recollections of Opus Dei for the
last couple of years, and I keep hearing this idea of divine
filiation—that we are all children of God because God lives in our
soul in grace. They talk about the life of childhood and spiritual
childhood, and I've been trying to figure out what this means.</p>

<p>“Here I am, 80 years of age, and they're telling me I have to become
like a child. What does that mean? Does it mean I have to put on short
pants or what?</p>

<p>“Now I've come to realize what it means. I have to abandon myself into
the arms of my Father God. I've got to let Him call the shots.I've got
to let Him make the decisions.</p>

<p>“I've got to try and let myself be like a little child in the arms of
his Father, with one hand in the hand of his Father, let God lead me and
go where He leads me, irrespective of all the other human or material
considerations. I've got to try and do His Will and do His thing, in
fact, my Christian vocation.”</p>

<p>In those days, it was as though that man discovered “the pearl of great
price” (Matt. 13:45-46).</p>

<p>There are treasures in the Gospel, great spiritual treasures. At certain
stages of our life, God may reveal those treasures to us, and those
treasures can be worth far more than all sorts of material things,
because it's there that we can find our peace and our joy. A peace and
joy that this world cannot give.</p>

<p>Therefore, there is great importance in living in the state of grace, of
being close to the sacraments, of learning how to savor these great
treasures that God gives us.</p>

<p>I heard of a kid once who was walking along the beach and his foot hit
against a pouch of stones. He picked up the pouch of stones, and he
began to take a stone, and he flung it as far as he could into the sea.
He said at the same time, ‘When I grow rich, I'm going to get myself a
big house.’</p>

<p>He flung another stone and said, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to buy
myself a fine car’; and another stone, ‘When I get rich, I'm going to
buy fine clothes’; and another stone, ‘I'm going to have great food.’</p>

<p>One by one, he threw all the stones as far as he could into the sea.
When he got down to the last stone, suddenly a little sunbeam or
something hit the stone and it glistened. So, he looked again. It was a
diamond!</p>

<p>He'd been throwing diamonds far out into the sea, dreaming about
treasures that he might never have, but he'd been throwing away the
treasures that he had in his hand.</p>

<p>With this story, we have to come to try and realize that maybe we have
great treasures in our lives, in our spiritual life in particular,
things that we are perhaps not as aware of as we could be. We don't
realize the treasures.</p>

<p>One great way of trying to get to know the treasures that we have in our
life is through acts of thanksgiving.</p>

<p>If you thank God from the moment you get up in the morning until the
moment you get to bed at night, for the fact that you can see, the fact
that you can hear, the fact that you can walk around the place and have
two arms and two legs—these are all wonderful treasures that can lead
us to appreciate all the other treasures that are present every day of
our life: the air that we breathe, the things that we see, the health of
the people around us.</p>

<p>There are so many wonderful things to be grateful for. So we need to
learn how to abandon ourselves into the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>I got a haircut last week in Nairobi, and when I came out of the place
where I got it, I was driving up the street and saw a young girl
crawling on all fours with a little cup, begging. Not something you
often see: a young girl crawling on all fours, she had no wheelchair,
she had nothing.</p>

<p>The following day, with a friend of mine, we decided to go and look for
this girl and try and see if we could do something for her. We found her
in a completely different place, purely by accident, crawling across a
busy street with several crossings.</p>

<p>So my friend got out of the car and went to talk to her. She had no
English and I don't have Swahili. They talked and she explained that
she was from Migori. She was 22, she had come to Nairobi two years
previously, she lived with two other people with disabilities, and
somehow, she had managed to survive.</p>

<p>When she moved around Nairobi, she would hop onto a <em>matatu</em>. She got to
different places from which she could beg, and she managed to carry on
like this: a very cheerful lady and very happy to talk.</p>

<p>Then she came with us and we got her a wheelchair. Hopefully, she's now
using that wheelchair.</p>

<p>But thinking about how that girl has survived in an unknown city far
away from her home territory, and not having English, and not knowing
the place, and managing to move around like that—there must be a
tremendous abandonment in her, in her life, in her spirit. She went away
from her own home to a strange place.</p>

<p>So sometimes with people we meet we can learn an awful lot about the
spirit of abandonment, trust, of having faith in God, because we know
that God has a plan for us.</p>

<p>He wants us to live out that plan. He has a mission for us. There's
nothing in our life that He has not foreseen.</p>

<p>And so, as we start a new year we could try to ask Our Lord in the
Blessed Sacrament that we might have a greater spirit of faith and trust
and abandonment to live out those consequences of being a child of God,
so that we may leave the future in His hands.</p>

<p>And if we see, as we can probably do, that when we look back, God has
really taken care of so many things in our life: our primary education,
our secondary education, perhaps our tertiary education, our work, our
family, our children, our health—so many things that God has looked
after in all sorts of special ways. We have every reason to grow in
faith and trust in Him.</p>

<p>St. Thérèse of Lisieux says, “When…we feel no courage, no energy, for
the practice of virtue, this is grace” (Thérèse of Lisieux, <em>Letters of
Soeur Thérèse to Céline</em>, October 20, 1888). This is the moment to
depend solely on Jesus.</p>

<p>There might be moments in our life when Our Lord precisely sweeps the
feet from under us and leaves us hanging there. In those situations, He
wants us to look up.</p>

<p>He wants us to trust completely in Him, to leave things in His hands, to
learn what real hope is, what real abandonment is.</p>

<p>A farmer told me how one time he was going through his farm, and there’d
been a fire on the farm. He came across all sorts of things that had
been very burnt.</p>

<p>At one moment he came across a chicken that was very badly burnt,
totally dead, and he gave it a good kick—this chicken that was totally
dead, burnt black—but out from underneath the chicken ran four or five
little chicks.</p>

<p>He said, “I suddenly remembered that phrase from Scripture: ‘I will
gather you under my wing as a hen gathers her chicks’” (Matt. 23:27).</p>

<p>He said this hen saw the danger, the fire coming, she gathered her
chicks. So he was very aware of the fact that Our Father God looks after
us in all sorts of ways, takes care of us, preserves us from danger.</p>

<p>Sometimes we might wonder, Why? Why did this happen to my family, to my
parents, to my siblings, to my children, to my work? Why do all these
things specifically happen to me?</p>

<p>In certain moments, we may not appreciate that. But when time passes,
sometimes we can discover there's some great divine plan behind the
cross. God is at work. He has other plans that He's working out.</p>

<p>A man in another country told me once how he had a primary school
education. He began to be a salesman selling pots and pans.</p>

<p>He knocked one day on the door of the president of the Ford Corporation
who didn't want any pots and pans. He thought he would get his wife,
but he got the husband.</p>

<p>But the husband was impressed with his sales pitch. He said, “Young man,
how would you like to try selling cars? OK? So come along on Monday
morning, we'll start you out selling cars.”</p>

<p>So he sold a lot of cars. He graduated to Mercedes-Benzes. He ended up
importing Rolls Royces from London. He could tell you the mileage on the
clock of every Rolls Royce in Asia. He made a lot of money.</p>

<p>Then he gave a present of a watch to some man in government, which is
something you cannot do in that particular country. The government
turned around and bankrupted him.</p>

<p>So he lost everything. He lost all his money. He lost his house. He lost
his business. His wife left him. At the age of 49, he developed stage 4
cancer.</p>

<p>That's when I got to know him. He used to go to a support group in his
parish for people who were recovering from cancer. This was a fairly
well-to-do parish with a lot of wealthy people, and they would get
together and talk week by week.</p>

<p>Then they heard of a new drug that had been made in Houston, Texas, a
new cancer drug which was very expensive. One by one all these very
wealthy people flew off to Houston, Texas to try out this new drug.</p>

<p>He came to me and he said, “You know, it's not fair. There’s no justice
in this world. The wealthy can do all these things, and here I am, I’m
bankrupt, they’ve taken away my passport, I can't leave the country, I
couldn't have any money to fly, and so poor me, I can't try out this
new drug.”</p>

<p>And he said, “I was complaining to God for weeks and months about how
unfair this life is. Then, you know, the first one died; and then after
three months, the next one died; and after six months, another one died;
and now they're nearly all dead and I'm still here. So I'm saying
thank you, Lord, thank you, Lord.”</p>

<p>So sometimes all the injustices of this world are the things that we
find we can do. When time passes and you look back, sometimes you can
see, maybe the hand of God was working in funny ways here.</p>

<p>Maybe God has me in the palm of His hand, looking after me in special
ways or looking after my family.</p>

<p>There are times when there are things that maybe we'd like to have and
we can't have them. God doesn't permit us to have them: luxuries or
things that other people have. Maybe it's because God just wants us to
trust in Him, to abandon ourselves. He has some other plan. Maybe
that's not our mission.</p>

<p>When there are things in life that we find other people have, and we
can't afford them and we can't have them, it may be that God is
forming our soul at that moment more than at any other time.</p>

<p>Perhaps He's giving us spiritual treasures, teaching us what authentic
detachment means, or teaching us authentic hope or authentic trust,
which ultimately are the messages that Christ gives to us in Bethlehem.</p>

<p>Christ abandoned Himself in Bethlehem into the arms of Mary, into the
arms of Joseph.</p>

<p>Sometimes that's what God wants us to do. If we were to hear tomorrow
that we have some fatal disease, we can abandon ourselves into the arms
of Our Father God. It can be totally peaceful.</p>

<p>I knew some men a couple of years ago who used to come to recollections
like this. Both of them developed cancer, but they were leading very
good spiritual lives.</p>

<p>They happened to find themselves in the same hospital room, and one said
to the other: “Are you worried about anything? Do you feel bad about
anything?” “No, I'm very peaceful.” “Me too, there’s nothing to worry
about. I leave everything in the hands of God. It's a great way to live
and a great way to die.”</p>

<p>It’s a wonderful thing to be able to look forward to our death because
our souls are in the right state.</p>

<p>In the house where I lived, two people passed away in the last two or
three months. One was 87, the other was 94. They were both looking
forward to their death.</p>

<p>The 94-year-old priest in particular kept saying, “I want to die. I want
to die.”</p>

<p>We brought him into the hospital at one stage, The Mater Hospital in
Nairobi, and the nurse said to me, “You know, he keeps saying he wants
to die, he wants to die, but everyone in this hospital wants to live.
We’re wondering, is there something wrong? Is there something we should
be doing?”</p>

<p>At one moment he refused all his medication and all of his food. I said
to him, “Father, why don't you eat your food or take your medicine?”</p>

<p>“It's the only weapon I have to get out of this place.” So he had a
great sense of humor. He died laughing. A great way to live and a great
way to die. Abandonment in the moment of death, in the arms of God,
because he lived a holy life.</p>

<p>Likewise, the other one, 87, saying his rosary every day, getting to
Confession every week, receiving Holy Communion every day. I asked him
in the last couple of days before he died, “Is there anything that
you'd like?”</p>

<p>“Well, if you could find this dark chocolate, I'd be very happy.” I
went to the supermarket and I found the dark chocolate. He liked a
particular type of dark chocolate. So he went to heaven, enjoying
himself! Great way to live, great way to die.</p>

<p>I have no worries, I’ve lived a good life, I abandon myself into the
arms of my Father God, because we have tremendous things to look forward
to.</p>

<p>“Eye has not seen, nor ear heard, nor has it entered the heart of man,
the things that God has prepared for those who love him” (1 Cor. 2:9).
If we live our lives focused on heaven, it's a great way to live.</p>

<p>We try to make our life on earth as heavenly as possible, but we realize
that everything here is passing. It’s worth nothing, it’s fading away.</p>

<p>The things of the spirit, the things of the soul, the things that are
worth having—these are the things worth acquiring, the treasures that
God gives to us.</p>

<p>We look at little children, we see how they abandon themselves, and how
they can get great joy out of little things.</p>

<p>Over the last few weeks, I was involved in a number of Christmas parties
for poor kids. I have a friend who organizes these parties, and he gets
big numbers. He brings lollipops and chapatis and sodas.</p>

<p>One time we were going to a place, and I said, Where are you going to
get the children for the party? He said, You just watch.</p>

<p>So he gives two sodas to two kids. They go away. Fifty kids come within
five minutes. So he gives them a lollipop, one by one.</p>

<p>Well, you see the faces of those kids light up with the lollipops and
sometimes they have to struggle to get the tight wrapping off the
lollipop, because it seems to be there with concrete or something. They
fight to get it off. The joy on their faces, the happiness, the little
things.</p>

<p>Sometimes God wants us with our childlike spirit to get great joy and
happiness out of simple things. It's a great way to learn to be happy.</p>

<p>In the writings of St. Josemaría, you'll find in one place it says, “Be
content with what enables you to live a simple and sober life (J.
Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 631).</p>

<p>Great advice. Who do you know in this world who is content—content
with what they have, happy with what they have, thanking God for what
they have.</p>

<p>A great way to live every day: Thank you, God, for the food we have on
the table, for the air that I breathe, for the fact that my hands and
legs work, that I can see, that I can hear. So many things that we take
for granted too much.</p>

<p>We abandon every day, every hour, in our work, this project, the dreams
we have for this coming year, in our workplace, in our family, in the
problems we'd like to solve.</p>

<p>Maybe God has precisely given us those problems to work at solving them,
not because He wants us to worry about it or be perturbed about it. He
just wants us to work at them, but we know that things will work out.</p>

<p>“If you, evil as you are,” we’re told in Scripture, “know how to give
good things to your children, how much more will your heavenly Father
give good things to those who ask him?” (Matt. 7:11).</p>

<p>If you think back over the last few weeks, how many parents in the world
did their best at Christmastime to give good things from Father
Christmas to their children?</p>

<p>Maybe even if their children didn't deserve them, they still wanted to
give them good things, the best they could find. Our Lord tells us, “How
much more will your heavenly Father…” It's a great world for all of
them.</p>

<p>Our Father God is waiting to give us all the best presents in the world,
all the best treasures, but He wants us to trust in Him, to leave
everything in His hands.</p>

<p>Every day of our life we can ask Our Lord for an increase in faith, an
increase in hope, an increase in charity, an increase in that spirit of
divine filiation, that God is my Father.</p>

<p>There may be twists and turns along the pathway of our life, but we know
it will work out well in the end.</p>

<p>There was a little girl who asked Santa Claus for a thousand dolls for
Christmas. Her father was an atheist.</p>

<p>She got one doll. Her father said to her, “Well, your God didn't listen
to your prayer, did he?”</p>

<p>The little girl said, “Yes, He did. He said no. And that's okay. He's
my Father, so it's okay for Him to say no from time to time. You're my
father, you say ‘no’ pretty frequently also. That’s no big deal; that
doesn't mean you don't exist.”</p>

<p>Wow, profound wisdom from a small child.</p>

<p>Sometimes, God might seem not to answer our prayer. Sometimes He says
yes, sometimes He says no and sometimes He says, Wait, I’ll give that to
you later. Or, Wait, because I have something better to give you, I have
something greater off the line.</p>

<p>Or maybe, I don't want to give you that material thing, but I have some
great spiritual thing to give you, which is worth far more than you
realize, far more than a diamond. Abandonment!</p>

<p>There is a movie that came out about twenty or thirty years ago about a
nun talking to a prisoner on death row. This nun is trying to convert
this prisoner, helping him to repent and make his peace with God.</p>

<p>The movie is her conversation with this prisoner on death row, and at
one stage she says to him: “Did you ever hear that you are a son of
God?”</p>

<p>And he replied saying, “You know, in the course of my life I've been
called a son of many things, but I have never been called a son of God.”</p>

<p>Well, this great reality can be something that can open our eyes, that
we are truly sons of God, children of God.</p>

<p>God is my Father and therefore I can make this new beginning, this new
year, with an awful lot of confidence and hope and trust that God is
going to be there for me. He's going to work things out.</p>

<p>When we look back over the last year, possibly we can thank God for all
the graces that He's given to us in the past year, all the things that
are worked out.</p>

<p>A lady told me once how she was sitting in her garden, and she noticed
there was a rose in the garden. Suddenly her attention began to focus on
the rose, a beautiful rose.</p>

<p>She began to think how man has been able to put men on the moon, but no
man can make a rose like that. That was the beginning of a profound
spiritual conversion.</p>

<p>She began to focus on all the great spiritual things in her life. She’d
led a very busy career woman life up to then. She became a very
spiritual person.</p>

<p>In this coming year, God also wants some sort of spiritual conversion
inside us, so that we live out that spiritual childhood, that
abandonment, in so many ways.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to the apostles, “Do not be afraid.” On many occasions He
said those words.</p>

<p>In the face of the supernatural, very often there was fear. There was
the storm on the lake when He came walking to them: “Do not be afraid!
It is I. Have courage, do not be afraid” (John 6:20).</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lord and ask Him that we might also respond to those
words. Remember that we're worth more than many sparrows and not a
single sparrow falls to the ground without Our Father God knowing it.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord that we might have this greater spirit of trust and
abandonment, the trust and abandonment that we see that Our Lady had
throughout her life.</p>

<p>She didn't understand what was going to happen in Bethlehem. She
didn't know that they were going to go to Egypt. She didn't know how
long they were going to be there. She and St. Joseph were just totally,
completely abandoned to the arms of Our Father God.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help me to live that spirit of abandonment in the same way
that you did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and
inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I
ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint
Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.
Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>