<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-27T06:00:13+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Our Father God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Father God" /><published>2026-02-27T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-27T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-father-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“But when you fast,” we’re told in St. Matthew, “put scent on your head and wash your face, so that no one will know that you are fasting, except your Father, who sees all that is done in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:17).</p>

<p>Our Father God is always by our side.</p>

<p>As Moses tended the flock of his father-in-law, Jethro, near Mount Horeb, the holy mountain, God appeared to him in a burning bush. There Moses was given the extraordinary task—his life’s work—of leading the chosen people out of the slavery of Egypt into the Promised Land. God confirmed him in his mission with the words, “I will be with you” (Ex. 3:1-6, 9-12).</p>

<p>In our prayer today we could repeat those words, reminding ourselves that God has told us that He will always be with us.</p>

<p>In another place in Scripture, He says, “Do not let your hearts be troubled” (John 14:1), “for I am with you always” (Matt. 28:20). Very consoling words.</p>

<p>Moses little imagined how closely God would be accompanying him and the people in the midst of the trials and tribulations that awaited them. In our lives too, God’s presence at every moment is something we can scarcely fathom—how He is working.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story narrating how a ray of sunlight jumped from out of the azure sky and came down, down, down to a little droplet of muddy water in a puddle. It took hold of this little droplet of muddy water and lifted it up high, high, high above the clouds and deposited it as an immaculate snowflake on a mountain top, so that as it melts it makes the valleys fertile (Fulton Sheen, <em>Sermon</em>, September 22, 1940).</p>

<p>Unbeknownst to us, God is working all the time behind the scenes. That presence of God in our life takes on an even greater definition when God sees us on the road to holiness. He’s like a father minding a toddler.</p>

<p>Every time we see a young father walking with a young baby, it’s worth taking a second look because there’s something there to learn for us about how Our Father God is taking care of us.</p>

<p>Our Lord, true God and true Man, is always reminding us in the Gospel of God’s paternal concern, since “no one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). He alone can do this.</p>

<p>The Son knows the Father in the very knowledge by which the Father knows Him. There’s no greater intimacy than that.</p>

<p>This identity of knowing and knowledge bespeaks the unity of the divine nature. In claiming it, Jesus revealed that He was God.</p>

<p>As the Son, one in substance with the Father, He is also able to reveal the Father’s relationship with and attitude towards us, and in particular, His goodness in granting us the gift of the Holy Spirit. The mystery of the Blessed Trinity is at the heart of what He had to reveal to us, and with it and in it, we find the wonder of God’s fatherhood.</p>

<p>It’s an interesting word: “wonder.” Little children wonder. Often they can’t understand the great realities, but they wonder.</p>

<p>During that last evening in the Upper Room, when Our Lord seemed to be summing up the years of self-giving and trusting revelation, He said, “I have manifested your name to the men whom you gave me” (John 17:6).</p>

<p>To manifest someone’s name really meant to reveal their mode of being. Our Lord has revealed to us the depths of the Trinitarian Mystery: the fact that God is a Father, so close to us men. Jesus is always using the title ‘Father,’ both in private conversations and in His preaching.</p>

<p>He dwells on the goodness of the Father, who rewards the slightest action and recognizes our good deeds, even the ones that no one sees.</p>

<p>“But when you give alms, your left hand must not know what your right hand is doing. Your almsgiving must be in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:3-4).</p>

<p>“But when you fast, put scent on your head and wash your face, so that no one will know you’re fasting except your Father, who sees all that is done in secret. And your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:17-18).</p>

<p>He bestows bounty on the just and on the unjust. In St. Matthew we’re told, “But I say to you, love your enemies and pray for those who persecute you, so that you may be children of your Father in heaven. For he causes his sun to rise on the bad as well as the good, and sends down rain to fall on the upright and the wicked alike” (Matt. 5:44-45).</p>

<p>This loving Father is always aware of and concerned about what we need.</p>

<p>We’re told in other places in Scripture: “Ask, and it will be given to you; search, and you will find; knock, and the door will be opened to you. For everyone who asks receives, everyone who searches finds, everyone who knocks will have the door opened” (Matt. 7:7-8).</p>

<p>And elsewhere in Scripture, we’re told: “That is why I am telling you not to worry about your life and what you are to eat, nor about your body and what you are to wear. Surely life is more than food, and the body more than clothing.</p>

<p>“Look at the birds in the sky: they do not sow or reap or gather into barns. Yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not worth much more than they are? Can any of you, however much you worry, add one single cubit to your span of life?</p>

<p>“And why worry about clothing? Think of the flowers growing in the fields: they never have to work or spin. Yet I assure you that not even Solomon in all his royal robes was clothed like one of these.</p>

<p>“Now if that is how God clothes the wildflowers growing in the field, which are there today and thrown into the furnace tomorrow, will he not much more look after you, you who have so little faith? So do not worry. Do not say, ‘What are we to eat? What are we to drink? What are we to wear?’ It is the Gentiles who set their hearts on all these things.</p>

<p>“Your heavenly Father knows that you need them all. Set your hearts on his kingdom first and God’s saving justice, and all these things will be given to you as well” (Matt. 6:25-33).</p>

<p>These are very encouraging and consoling words.</p>

<p>Jesus encourages us to have the word ‘Father’ like a constant refrain on our lips, reminding ourselves that this Father is never far away, no more than a father who sees a little toddler alone and in danger. If we try to please Him, we will find Him by our side.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em> we’re told: “When you really come to love God’s Will, you will never, even in the worst state of agitation, lose sight of the fact that Our Father in heaven is always close to you, very close, right next to you, with his everlasting Love and with his unbounded affection” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 240).</p>

<p>When you’re at Mass, when you’re looking through the words of the <em>Eucharistic Prayer</em>, try and notice how frequently the word ‘Father’ appears in the liturgy. It’s like a daily reminder:</p>

<p>The way to be true children of God the Father is by imitating Christ. God didn’t just make us and then leave us, like a painter with his painting. He’s a Father to us, and He’s even brought us to be “partakers of the divine nature” (2 Pet. 1:4).</p>

<p>Beautiful phrase that we find in the letter of St. Peter worth contemplating: He’s lifted us up to be “partakers of the divine nature.” That’s why living in the state of grace is the most important goal that we should have for our life.</p>

<p>We’re told also in St. John’s Letter that the Father’s desire is “that we should be called children of God, and so we are” (1 John 3:1). Being children of God is not something we achieve on our own; it’s a gift from God. Pondering this will make us thank Him each day.</p>

<p>The sense of our divine filiation will be at the root of our joy and confidence in carrying out the mission that God has given to us. In it we find assurance in the face of difficulty and anguish.</p>

<p>“Father, my Father,” we can find ourselves saying, savoring that gentle but strong word ‘Father,’ be it at times of joy or of danger.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em>, we’re told, “Call him ‘Father’ many times a day and tell him—alone, in your heart—that you love him, that you adore him, that you feel proud and strong because you are his child” (<em>cf</em>. J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 150).</p>

<p>It is through Christ that we share in this divine sonship, as we try to resemble Him, the firstborn among many brethren and the only begotten Son of the Father.</p>

<p>The more like Jesus we become, the more God the Father will see us as His children, if we try to work as He did, if we too have pity on the people we meet each day, if we make reparation for sin and show our thanks, as Our Lord did.</p>

<p>But we achieve this above all by imitating Christ’s prayer to His Father. This can mean bursting into praise and thanksgiving for the many expressions of God’s love that we encounter.</p>

<p>Cardinal Văn Thuận, a Vietnamese Cardinal imprisoned for many decades in solitary confinement, tells a story of how some of the prison guards that were looking after him were curious when they knew that he knew some Latin.</p>

<p>They asked him to teach them some Latin. So he taught them Latin. Then he decided to teach them the hymn, the <em>Veni Creator</em>, which is one of the most beautiful hymns to the Holy Spirit that we have in the Catholic Church.</p>

<p>And so, when the guard learned this hymn, he would come every morning singing the <em>Veni Creator</em> to open the prison cell each morning. This was like a gift from God in his solitary confinement (<em>cf</em>. Francis Xavier Nguyen Văn Thuận, <em>Testimonies of Hope</em>).</p>

<p>We can find ourselves thanking God in a special way.</p>

<p>In St. Matthew we’re told, “I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth” (Matt. 11:25). It’s very appropriate that, as the <em>Preface</em> tells us each day, that we be “always and everywhere” giving thanks to God our Father.</p>

<p>We can say, ‘Thank you for bringing this friend of mine back to the sacraments, for helping me with my family, for giving me the opportunity to open my heart in spiritual direction.’</p>

<p>St. Josemaría recommended that we should each day also thank God for all the graces of which we are not aware. There must be millions and millions of graces that God has given to us in the course of our life, which we’re not aware of at all.</p>

<p>If our minds and hearts turn to God often, in good times and in bad, then we’re living as good children should.</p>

<p>In the Psalms we’re told, “My soul, give thanks to the Lord, all my being, bless his holy name. My soul, give thanks to the Lord, and never forget all his blessings. It is he who forgives all your guilt, who heals every one of your ills, who redeems your life from the grave, who crowns you with love and compassion” (Ps. 103:1-4).</p>

<p>We could ask for the grace to see other people as Christ saw them. The world looks very different through His eyes! It is the Holy Spirit who configures us to the Master.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us, “For all who are led by the Spirit of God are children of God” (Rom. 8:14).</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom explains that it is “through the spirit that we belong to Christ, we possess him, and we vie with the angels.</p>

<p>“Through the spirit,” he says, “we crucify the flesh, we taste the joy of eternal life, we possess the pledge of the resurrection, and make sure progress on the path of virtue” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homilies on Romans, 13</em>). Divine filiation is the easiest way to reach the Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>St. Irenaeus says, “How often we have reflected on God’s mercy and how he chose to become man so that man could, in a sense, become God” (<em>cf</em>. Irenaeus, <em>Against Heresies, Book 5, Preface; Catechism of the Catholic Church, Point 460</em>), sharing His very life.</p>

<p>And so, union with Christ is a consequence of our divine filiation.</p>

<p>The sanctifying grace that we receive in the sacraments and as a reward for our good works identifies us with Christ and makes us ‘sons in the Son,’ since God the Father has only one Son and it is only ‘in Christ’ that we can attain to this divine filiation.</p>

<p>We become united and identified with Him as members of His Mystical Body, as St. Paul wrote to the Galatians: “It is no longer I who live, but Christ who lives in me” (Gal. 2:20).</p>

<p>So when we turn to the Father it is really Christ who is praying in us. When we deny ourselves something for Him, it is He who has inspired this detachment of spirit. When we try to bring someone back to the sacraments, our apostolic spirit is a reflection of Christ’s zeal for souls.</p>

<p>Our work and our sufferings complete the works and sufferings which Our Lord took on for His Mystical Body the Church. We could think of the value which our daily work and sorrows assume then in this light.</p>

<p>The interior struggle which brings us, with the help of grace, to be conformed to Christ also moves us to “have this mind among yourselves, which was also in Christ Jesus,” says St. Paul (Phil. 2:5).</p>

<p>And this in turn makes us ‘more’ children of God, so to speak. In the ordinary way, one cannot be more or less the son of one’s father, though one could be a better or a worse one.</p>

<p>In the supernatural sphere, the holier one is, the more one is a son or daughter of God, not just a better one. This is the real goal of the Christian life: a constant growth in divine filiation.</p>

<p>Our Mother Mary is the perfect example of what divine grace can achieve when it’s fully availed of. No one, excepting the sacred Humanity of Our Lord, was ever closer to God, and no created being could ever become the Daughter of God the Father that she was.</p>

<p>We can ask her to make us seek the counsel of the Holy Spirit, who will lead us to imitate Jesus. Under His influence, we’ll feel this pressing need to turn to the Father at all times, but particularly at Mass, when we address Him as Most Merciful Father in the<em>Eucharistic Prayer I</em>, in union with the sacrifice of His Son.</p>

<p>We will think of Him as Father, calling Him <em>Abba</em>, anointed as we are by the spirit of His Son who cries out, “Abba, Father!”, says St. Paul (Gal. 4:6).</p>

<p>He will also make us feel the hunger and thirst for God and for His glory, which were so apparent in His Incarnate Son.</p>

<p>The Father also receives glory from our growing more like His only begotten Son, “who by the power at work within us,” says St. Paul to the Ephesians, “is able to do far more abundantly than all we ask or think. Glory be to him” whose power working in us can do infinitely more than we can ask or imagine (Eph. 3:20-21).</p>

<p>Our Father God is always our safeguard against the difficulties and temptations that we may have to undergo. We can win every battle with Him at our side.</p>

<p>The whole history of the Incarnation opens with the words, “Do not be afraid, Mary” (Luke 1:30). In the presence of the supernatural there is often fear, but God comes to calm our fears.</p>

<p>Likewise with St. Joseph: “Do not be afraid, Joseph, son of David” (Matt. 1:20). He’s told to calm down. God comes to bring him peace.</p>

<p>And also to the shepherds, the angel says, “Do not be afraid, for I bring you good tidings of great joy which will be to all the people” (Luke 2:10). This beginning of God’s coming into the world marks a style proper to Our Lord’s presence among men.</p>

<p>Later on, when Our Lord was crossing the Sea of Galilee, the boat was swamped by the waves. St. Mark puts this event in its proper context.</p>

<p>It was the evening of the day on which Our Lord had narrated the parables of the kingdom of heaven (Mark 4:35).</p>

<p>The Gospel explains that Our Lord, tired out after hours of preaching, was asleep in the boat. The storm must have been tremendous, because the disciples, accustomed as they were to the sea, nevertheless saw themselves in great danger. And they cried out for Our Lord to save them: “Lord, save us, for we perish!” (Matt. 8:25).</p>

<p>From the start, the apostles understood why Our Lord was asleep. He must have been very tired not to have been awakened by the waves. They did everything in their power to avert the danger, rowing hard, bailing out the water. But gradually the storm began to get the better of them, and they were in imminent danger of sinking. There’s a great sense of urgency in their words: “Save us, for we are perishing.”</p>

<p>The fears that we may experience often stem from the awareness that the security of our life is based on very weak foundations. In that case, we’re forgetting an essential truth: that God is our constant security. That doesn’t mean that we are insensitive to events, but that we should have more confidence in using the human means at our disposal.</p>

<p>We must never forget that to be close to God, even when He appears to be asleep, is to be safe. When we’re confused or going through unpleasant times, God does not forget us. St. Teresa of Ávila said, “He never fails his friends” (Teresa of Ávila, <em>Life, 2,4</em>).</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presence of God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presence of God" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/presence-of-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“The child whispered once, ‘God, speak to me.’<br />
And a meadowlark sang. The child did not hear.</p>

<p>The child yelled, ‘God, speak to me!<br />
And the thunder rolled across the sky. But the child did not listen.</p>

<p>The child looked around and said, ‘God, let me see you.’<br />
And a star shone brightly. But the child did not notice.</p>

<p>And the child shouted, ‘God, show me a miracle!’<br />
And a life was born, but the child did not know.</p>

<p>The child cried out in despair, ‘Touch me, God, let me know you are here!’<br />
Whereupon God reached down<br />
And touched the child.</p>

<p>But the child brushed the butterfly away<br />
And walked away unknowingly.”<br />
(Ravindra Kumar Karnani, <em>And the Meadowlark Sang</em>).</p>

<p>This meditation is about the <em>presence of God</em> in our life.</p>

<p>There was a priest and a professor in an ecclesiastical seminary in Rome. He’d been a popular professor of philosophy for almost thirty years. But he was also a very demanding professor.</p>

<p>He never missed a lecture, never relaxed the schedule, never gave his students free or half days, not even on special festivities or right before vacations.</p>

<p>One day he came to class, put his books on the table, smiled and announced, ‘Today we will not have class.’</p>

<p>The students were shocked. One tentatively raised his hand and asked, ‘Why not, Father?’</p>

<p>The priest answered, ‘Today I want to celebrate, because during my morning meditation, for the first time in thirty-five years, I felt the presence of God.’</p>

<p>For almost forty years, he was faithful to his daily prayer commitment without experiencing any consolation.</p>

<p>We know that God is close to us. “I am with you always, even until the end of the world” (Matt. 28:20).</p>

<p>The virtue of presence of God is the virtue whereby we remind ourselves that we are always in God’s presence—with or without any consolations, whether or not we feel Him.</p>

<p>We know with faith that Our Heavenly Father is close to us at all moments.</p>

<p>“Can a woman forget her sucking child...that she should have no compassion on the son of her womb? Even these may forget, yet I will not forget you” (Isa. 49:15).</p>

<p>“Oh, taste and see that the Lord is good!” (Ps. 34:8).</p>

<p>“The kingdom of God is within you” (Luke 17:21).</p>

<p>In all sorts of ways, Our Father God reminds us that He’s present to us all the time. He is present to us, but, as Ronald Knox says, the question is whether or not we are alive to Him, whether we notice Him, talk to Him, thank Him, appreciate His presence, and the things around us in nature.</p>

<p>“Look at the birds of the air; they neither sow or reap nor gather into barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them” (Matt. 6:26).</p>

<p>When we receive supernatural grace in the sacraments, the Blessed Trinity comes to live in us in grace. We will “come and make our abode in him” (John 14:23).</p>

<p>The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit are continually within us. All we need to do is turn our gaze there.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “In him we live and move and have our being” (Acts 17:28).</p>

<p>St. John Paul II liked to say that in Christ we find the meaning and the purpose of our life (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, World Youth Day, August 14, 1993). In turning to God frequently each day, we can find the meaning and the purpose of our life.</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “As the deer longs for flowing streams, so my soul longs for you, O God. My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When shall I come and behold the face of God?” (Ps. 42:1-2).</p>

<p>“O God, you are my God, I seek you; my soul thirsts for you; my flesh faints for you, as in a dry and weary land, where no water is” (Ps. 63:1).</p>

<p>The Old Testament and the New Testament are full of these petitions or reminders that God is all around us and that we need Him.</p>

<p>In one of his encyclicals, Pope St. John Paul II says that there is a hole in the human heart, a chasm in the human heart, that can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>“I stretch out my hands to you,” says the Old Testament, “my soul thirsts for you like a parched land. Make haste to answer me, O Lord; my spirit fails. Hide not your face from me” (Ps. 143:6-7).</p>

<p>We could try to make a resolution to be more aware of the presence of God in the ordinary things of each day, when we know He’s waiting for us in those ordinary things that He gives us to do.</p>

<p>Growth in friendship with God requires interior recollection. The presence of the three divine Persons in our souls in grace is a living presence, which is open to our friendship: they are inviting us to get to know them and to love them. It’s up to us to correspond.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Why climb the mountains or go down into the valleys of the world looking for him who dwells within us?” (Augustine, <em>De Trinitate</em>).</p>

<p>St. Gregory tells us, “As long as our mind is giddy with carnal images, it will never be able to contemplate...because there are as many obstacles blinding it as there are thoughts pulling it here and there. Hence, for the soul to contemplate the invisible nature of God, the first step must be: let it be recollected within itself” (Gregory the Great, <em>Homilies on Ezechiel</em>).</p>

<p>We turn to our soul, to our heart, we find God within, and having that spirit of finding God within, we can also find Him without, because “there is something…divine, hidden in the most ordinary human reality” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 114).</p>

<p>God may ask some people to withdraw from the world to achieve that recollection. But for the majority of Christians—housewives, students, employees—He wants us to find Him in the midst of our daily activities, and to achieve that recollection there.</p>

<p>A young married lady told me once how their young child was getting to the stage of three or four or so, and Christmas was coming. She decided that it was time to have a crib in their home. So she got a small little crib for their flat.</p>

<p>Then the little child came along and took the different pieces of the crib and began to deposit them all over the house. She found St. Joseph under the couch, she found Our Lady behind the curtains, she found the angels in the bedroom, the shepherds were somewhere else.</p>

<p>Little by little she was able to repossess all these little pieces of the crib. But she couldn’t find the baby Jesus. She looked high up and low down, but baby Jesus was nowhere to be found.</p>

<p>A day or two later, she said, “I opened the washing machine and there was the baby Jesus sitting on top of the washing.”</p>

<p>She said, “It struck me in that moment that the Holy Spirit was speaking to me. I’ve been to many recollections and retreats where I learned a lot of formation. One of the ideas that I often heard was that we have to find God in the ordinary things of each day.</p>

<p>“When I saw the baby Jesus sitting on top of the washing, I thought, this is the message that the Holy Spirit is saying to me. This is where I have to find God each day.”</p>

<p>Then she wondered: How on earth did the baby Jesus get into the washing machine? She realized that her son had put the baby Jesus into the pocket of his trousers. The trousers went to the wash and out came the baby Jesus in the wash.</p>

<p>We keep our senses for God by means of ongoing mortification throughout the day. It’s also the way to interior contentment. We find peace in the things of God.</p>

<p>We mortify our imagination by putting aside useless thoughts; our memory, by not entertaining memories that don’t bring us closer to God; our will, by fulfilling our schedule of work and our duties, however small they may be.</p>

<p>Concentrated work, if it’s offered to God, not only does not obstruct our conversation with God, but rather, facilitates it. The same applies to our external activities: social relations, family life, leisure time, journeys.</p>

<p>Everything in life—except when superficiality predominates—has a profound, intimate dimension. It takes on that dimension when we are recollected and brings it into our friendship with God.</p>

<p>Recollection means ‘bringing together what was scattered,’ reestablishing interior order, controlling our senses as they tend towards dispersion, even in things which are good or indifferent.</p>

<p>It means having God as the center of our intentions in what we’re doing and planning.</p>

<p>The opposite to interior recollection is dissipation and superficiality. In <em>The Way</em> we’re told, “Dissipation—You stake your senses and faculties in whatever pool you meet on the way. And you can feel the results: unsettled purpose, scattered attention, deadened will, and quickened concupiscence. Subject yourself once again to a serious plan that will make you lead a Christian life, or you will never do anything worthwhile” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 375).</p>

<p>Unless we’re recollected, we cannot pay attention to God in the ordinary things of each day. The more we purify our heart and our senses, the more recollected we are, the more our soul will long for contact with God, “like the deer that yearns for running streams” (<em>cf</em>. Ps. 42:1).</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>Friends of God</em>, “Our heart then needs to distinguish and adore each one of the divine Persons. The soul is, as it were, making a discovery in the supernatural life, like an infant opening his eyes to the world about him. The soul spends time lovingly with the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, and readily submits to the work of the life-giving Paraclete, who gives himself to us without any merit on our part” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 306).</p>

<p>Our refuge and our strength lie in the love of God, expressed in the ordinary things of each day.</p>

<p>I read an article once written by a housewife who talked about how to sanctify our home life. She talked about how she would get her children and her husband off to work in the morning. I think there were eight children.</p>

<p>When they were all gone off to school and to work, she would breathe a sigh of relief, clear away the breakfast table, clean up the kitchen a little bit, and then go upstairs to make some beds.</p>

<p>She said, “Every step of the stair is an opportunity for me to tell God how much I love Him.”</p>

<p>That’s living <em>presence of God</em> in the ordinary things of each day, and using human reminders or human situations to remind us of God’s presence. Because we are creatures of matter and spirit, we need material things to remind us often of the spiritual things.</p>

<p>On His way to the Holy City, we’re told, Jesus stops for a moment to express His disappointment at its rejection of His message: “O Jerusalem, Jerusalem...How often I would have gathered your children together as a hen gathers her brood, but you did not want” (Luke 13:34).</p>

<p>Our Lord emphasizes how we have to want. We have to go in that direction, make definite resolutions.</p>

<p>A farmer in Canada once said how there was a fire on his farm, and he was surveying the damage sometime later. He came across a chicken that had been cooked in the fire in the middle of the farmyard. Obviously, the chicken was cooked to a cinder.</p>

<p>He gave it a good kick, and out from underneath the chicken ran four or five little chicks. Suddenly, he remembered this phrase of Scripture. He understood it with greater depth. “How often I would have gathered you as a hen gathers her brood.”</p>

<p>The chicken saw the danger, gathered her chicks, and gave her life in the process so that her chicks would live.</p>

<p>Jesus watches over us from the tabernacle. He’s alert to the dangers that threaten us. He’s ever ready to cure our wounds. He continually shares His life with us. He’s our refuge and our strength.</p>

<p>The Psalmist says, “Keep me as the apple of your eye; hide me in the shadow of your wings” (Ps. 17:8).</p>

<p>“For you are my refuge, a strong tower against the enemy. Let me dwell in your tent forever! Oh, to be safe under the shelter of your wings!” (Ps. 61:3-4).</p>

<p>It’s a very good thing to try and have little aspirations, little phrases that suit us for different situations, or places, or feelings, or ups and downs, that can lead us to pray. They can be phrases from well-known prayers, like “our sweetness and our hope”—a phrase we find in the <em>Hail, Holy Queen.</em></p>

<p>It could be a phrase from some words of the Mass: “Do not look on my sins, O Lord, but on the faith of your children.” “Lord, have mercy. Christ, have mercy.”</p>

<p>They could be some aspiration to Our Lady: Queen of peace, Help of Christians, Refuge of sinners, Morning Star.</p>

<p>Other little phrases that may come to mind, or words that might jump up out of the page as we do our spiritual reading or follow the Mass—the Holy Spirit will be speaking to us.</p>

<p>He’ll help us to find those words or phrases that we can use as a means of prayer during the day, that come from the depth of our soul. In this way we can stay close to Our Lord in our earthly life.</p>

<p>At the close of that life, He will be Our Judge and Our Friend. He’ll remember helping us all the time from the tabernacle.</p>

<p>Our Lord has wanted to remain present throughout the world, so that we might seek Him more readily for friendship and assistance, and turn to Him in all sorts of moments.</p>

<p>“If we’re suffering pain and discomfort, he will lighten our burden and comfort us”—perhaps reminding us that whatever we might suffer in this world, He has been there before. “And a sword has pierced his Mother’s heart” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35).</p>

<p>“If we succumb to illness, he will either provide a remedy, or he will give us the strength to suffer it for the sake of eternal life”—to offer up in that moment that pain, or that difficulty, or that piece of bad news, or that contradiction, or that broken heart.</p>

<p>“If we find ourselves at war with the devil and our passions, he’ll supply us with arms for the battle, so that we can resist and ultimately be victorious.” Virgin most faithful, Comforter of the afflicted, Mother of mercy.</p>

<p>“If we are poor, he will enrich us with all kinds of good things in this life and in eternity” (John Vianney, <em>Sermon on Maundy Thursday</em>).</p>

<p>We need to make resolutions to seek His company every single day. From the moment we wake up, even before we get out of bed, our first thought can be a thought for God:</p>

<p>‘Thank you, Lord, for the sleep that you gave me. Thank you for the fact that I have a bed to lie down in, a pillow to put my head on, and a roof over my head. Thank you for this new day. I offer it to you.’</p>

<p>And the same thing as we lie down in bed at night. It can be a good moment to repeat the morning offering, offering to Our Lord those last minutes or seconds of this gift of a day that He has given to us.</p>

<p>Our determination to live as children of God should be expressed in ordinary life: at work, at home, among our friends. In every hour of the day, we should be striving to be men and women of faith. Full-time Christians.</p>

<p>We don’t just confine our relationship with God to the few moments that we may spend inside a church. We live out our friendship with God in our workplace, in our rest and recreation, in social gatherings. We reflect Christ’s love in everything we do.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “So whether you eat or drink or whatever you do, do all for the glory of God” (1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>A lady who was not a Catholic—but later became one—heard that phrase in a class one time. She felt the Holy Spirit speaking to her. “Doing everything for the glory of God.” She said, ‘Really. that’s what the spirit of Opus Dei is all about.’</p>

<p>Then she told me that after the class she went out to her car, and it was in a bit of a mess. She thought, ‘I better start with my car—clean up the inside a little bit so it reflects more the glory of God.’</p>

<p>Then she went to her office. She was a lawyer. And as often happens in lawyers’ offices, her files were all over the place. She put them back in their proper place.</p>

<p>Her secretary came in and wondered what earthquake in reverse has hit this place. She found everything in such order. She told her, ‘I’m trying to do everything for the glory of God.’</p>

<p>Then she went home that night, and she said, ‘Every night I would watch the news with my husband. Halfway through the news, he would ask me to get him a cup of tea. Very grudgingly, I would go downstairs to make a cup of tea. But this time I had it ready for him. He asked me: What’s happened? What’s come over you?’</p>

<p>She said, ‘I’m doing everything for the glory of God.’</p>

<p>St. Basil says, “When you sit down at table, pray. When you eat your bread, give thanks to God who is so generous. If you have some wine, remember that he has created it to bring us merriment and comfort in affliction.</p>

<p>“When you’re getting dressed, give thanks to the one who gave you these clothes. When you look up at the firmament and behold the beauty of the stars above, fall down at the feet of God and adore his infinite Wisdom that is manifest in all Creation.</p>

<p>“Do the same at sunrise and sunset, when you’re asleep and when you’re awake. Give thanks to God who created all this wonder for your benefit, so that you might know, love and praise his name” (Basil, <em>Homilia in Julittam maritem</em>).</p>

<p>All the noble realities should serve to bring us to the Lord.</p>

<p>And if some nights you can’t sleep well, have recourse to your presence of God. Pray a little more. One saint used to say, ‘Last night I slept a little less, but I prayed a little more.’</p>

<p>As you move around with your children, try and teach them to live in the presence of God: to give thanks for this and thanks to God for that; to say the <em>Grace Before Meals</em>, or the <em>Angelus</em>, or other little aspirations that they come across, so that they learn to pray and learn to realize where everything comes from.</p>

<p>Confucius, the Chinese philosopher, says, “When you drink water, remember the source.” As Christians in the middle of the world we have a lot of sources to remember.</p>

<p>Someone in love thinks of their beloved twenty-hour hours a day. That’s the kind of love we should try to have for Jesus Christ. It should constitute the essence of our being, the driving force behind all our actions.</p>

<p>He is Our One and Only Lord. He is the one we want to glorify through our work well done. Jesus is our inspiration when we try to practice the social doctrine of the Church, when we strive to protect the environment.</p>

<p>This all-embracing outlook leads a Christian to make an effort to be cordial and optimistic, to be punctual at work, to make good use of time, to overcome temptations to laziness.</p>

<p>If our love of God is authentic, it will shine out from and be appreciable in every aspect of our existence.</p>

<p>The Lord does not distance Himself from us. He wants us to live in His presence.</p>

<p>We’re told at the scene of the Transfiguration: “Immediately a cloud overshadowed them” (<em>cf</em>. Mark 9:7).</p>

<p>It’s a reminder of that other cloud that accompanied the presence of God in the Old Testament: “Then the cloud,” we’re told in the Book of Exodus, “covered the tent of meeting, and the glory…filled the tabernacle” (Ex. 40:34).</p>

<p>It was the sign of divine intervention. “And the Lord said to Moses, ‘Lo, I am coming to you in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with you, and may believe you forever’” (Ex. 19:9).</p>

<p>At Mount Tabor, that cloud overshadows Christ, and the powerful voice of God the Father is heard coming from it: “This is my Son, my Chosen, listen to him” (Luke 9:35).</p>

<p>God the Father speaks through Jesus Christ to men of all ages. His voice is heard in every age, in a particular way through the teaching of the Church, who, as John Paul says in his encyclical, <em>The Redeemer of Man,</em> his first encyclical, “continually seeks ways of bringing this mystery of her Master and Lord to humanity—to the peoples, the nations, the succeeding generations, and every individual human being” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Redemptor hominis</em>, Point 7, March 4, 1979).</p>

<p>We can detect when the Holy Spirit is speaking to us. When certain words or phrases of other people, or something we read, strikes us in a special way, or something we hear in some preaching, somehow, it’s engraved in our soul.</p>

<p>Things we remember a few days later—this is the Holy Spirit speaking to us, things He wants us to remember, like a divine call.</p>

<p>Every time our phone rings, I can think of it as a divine call, a human reminder to think of God at this particular moment. Or each time we walk into a room, or each time we see an image of Our Lady, or each time we go through a traffic light—this is the ordinary life that God wants us to sanctify.</p>

<p>He wants us to find Him in the street, in the hustle and bustle, in the people around us.</p>

<p>We have to find Him when He forgives us in the Sacrament of Penance and, above all, in Holy Communion, where He is really, truly, and substantially present.</p>

<p>Normally, Our Lord doesn’t show Himself to us with any special manifestations. He wants us to seek Him out—“Seek and you will find” (Matt. 7:7)—in the ordinary, everyday things.</p>

<p>Our God is a God of consolation. Occasionally, by our side, we realize that He gives us consolations that can only have come from Him.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “She hastens to make herself known to those who desire her” (Wisd. 6:13).</p>

<p>He grants us the grace sometimes of feeling His presence. He desires that we should speak to Him as your most beloved friend. Tell Him about your feelings. One saint used to say, “Lord, I’m fed up. I’m tired.” We share with Him the deep things that are going on in our heart.</p>

<p>“Without waiting for you to come close to him, he hastens towards you,” we’re told, “when you seek his love, and he presents himself to you, granting you the graces and remedies that you need. He only waits for one word from you in order to show you that he is beside you and wants to listen to you and console you” (Alphonsus Liguori, <em>How to Converse with God</em>).</p>

<p>We’re told in the Psalms, “His ears are towards their cry” (Ps. 34:15).</p>

<p>Our Lady and St. Joseph lived continuously in the presence of God. They were alive to God in everything they did. They listened to the angels. They responded. Living in the presence of God is hope.</p>

<p>We could ask the Holy Family that they may teach us also to be attentive to the voice of God as He speaks to us in the ordinary things of each day, and that we might respond in that same wholehearted way that Joseph and Mary did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MVF</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Dominic</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Dominic" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-dominic/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>St. Dominic was born in Caleruega about the year 1170. He fought the Albigensian heresy with his preaching and exemplary life. He founded the Dominicans, the Order of Preachers, and spread devotion to the Holy Rosary. He died in Bologna on August 6, 1221.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the 13th century, some sects were causing great harm in the Church, especially in the south of France. During a journey St. Dominic made throughout that region in the company of his bishop, he was able to verify the damaging effects that novel doctrines were causing in the people of God, on account of deficient formation, as has so often been the case. Ignorance has brought about an awful lot of evil.</p>

<p>During his tour, the saint perceived the need to teach the truths of the faith clearly and simply. With great zeal and love for souls, he gave himself fully to the task. Shortly thereafter, he decided to found a new religious order whose aim would be the spread of Christian doctrine and its defense against error throughout Christendom.</p>

<p>In this way, the Order of Preachers was founded. The study of truths was to be one of its fundamental tenets. Ever since then, Dominicans can be found in all kinds of apostolic activities in service to the Church, bringing truth to the minds of humanity.</p>

<p>Like their founder, they put their particular charism into practice so as to illuminate the consciences of persons with the light of the Word of God. The task of transmitting the deposit of faith to everyone is currently a pressing need, as it was in St. Dominic’s day. This is a mission of the entire Church, and it is becoming more urgent than ever before.</p>

<p>Pope John Paul II periodically warned of the widespread ignorance of the most elementary truths of the faith. In an address, he said there is a contagion of numerous doctrinal errors, with detrimental consequences to souls. The lack of love and esteem for the Holy Eucharist, the neglect of confession as a sacrament vitally necessary for obtaining God’s pardon and for the formation of a person’s conscience, the disregard for our supernatural last end, and a widespread relegation of the faith to private life, stripping it of all public expression.</p>

<p>Marriage is deprived of its natural meaning and dignity. Laws permissible of abortion declare the triumph of material ease and egoism over the most sacred value of human life. A decrease in the birth rate and an aging population have led one responsible European to speak of a demographic suicide in Europe. It appears to be a serious symptom of profound spiritual impoverishment.</p>

<p>Clearly, many are oblivious to our call to friendship with God, of sin, of eternal life, of the Christian meaning of suffering. It’s plain to see that the world becomes less human to the extent that it ceases to be Christian. A wave of materialism, the loss of supernatural perspective, also affects and perhaps very profoundly the people we see around us every day and whom the Lord perhaps puts under our care for one reason or another.</p>

<p>We can consider in the presence of God today whether we are taking to heart the call of the popes to re-Christianize the world around us, in our social milieu. May we consider whether we’re making an effort to know the teachings of Jesus Christ in depth and to spread them. Do we rectify our personal, family, professional, social, and political conduct accordingly? Are we trying to invigorate those external signs of religion and Christian life that so many are bent on disregarding? A scapular, blessings at meals, and of our new house, having recourse to images of Our Lord and of Our Lady in our home and at our place of work.</p>

<p>Like so many others before him, St. Dominic depended on a powerful weapon to conquer in what at first appeared to be a losing battle. Great in the integrity of his doctrine, in the example of his virtue, and in his apostolic labors, he dauntlessly declared war on the enemies of the Church. Not by force of arms, but through burning faith in the Holy Rosary.</p>

<p>He was the first to establish and personally spread this devotion, which was later continued by his sons to the four corners of the earth. The saint required his spiritual sons to frequently make use of their preaching of this form of prayer from which he drew so much profit. On the one hand, he knew of Mary’s enormous influence with her Son, who always dispenses His graces through her hands.</p>

<p>On the other, she is so naturally inclined to mercy and kindness and so used to spontaneously helping those in need that she cannot withhold her help from all those who ask it. The Church always finds her to be our Mother in the order of grace and Mother most merciful, and has long had the custom of greeting her as such, above all through the Rosary.</p>

<p>For this reason, said Pope Benedict XV, the Roman Pontiffs have extolled devotion to the Marian Rosary with the highest praise and have enriched it with indulgences. By filial instinct, and on the explicit recommendation of the Popes, Christians have recourse to the Holy Rosary in both ordinary and extraordinary circumstances. Including public catastrophes, wars, heresies, and important family problems.</p>

<p>This powerful and perennial devotion is an excellent means of thanksgiving too. The advice of the most recent popes is constant, particularly with respect to the family Rosary. The Second Vatican Council reminded the Christian faithful to esteem those acts of piety for the Blessed Virgin which the Magisterium has recommended throughout the centuries. And Paul VI explicitly interpreted these words as referring to the Rosary.</p>

<p>Today, when humanity is so much in need, we can examine the quality of our love for and our confidence in Our Lady as expressed through this grace-laden devotion. We can ask ourselves whether we turn to our Mother in heaven with faith while we spread good doctrine around us, especially if any of those closest to us are straying from the Lord.</p>

<p>If we try to pray the Holy Rosary with love every day, St. Dominic will win many graces for ourselves and also for those whom we want to lead to Our Lord. In it, we consider the principal mysteries of our salvation, from the Annunciation of Our Lady to the Resurrection and Ascension of Our Lord into heaven, by way of His Passion and death. The first five joyful mysteries cover the hidden life of Jesus and Mary. Contemplating them will teach us to sanctify the realities of ordinary life.</p>

<p>The five sorrowful mysteries lead us to reflect on and to relive the events of the Passion. They teach us to sanctify suffering, sickness, and the cross that are present in the life of every man and woman. In the last five glorious mysteries, we meditate on the triumphs of Our Lord and of His Mother. They fill us with joy and hope as we bring to mind the glory God has reserved for us if we are faithful.</p>

<p>By reflecting on these mysteries, we go to Jesus through Mary. We rejoice with Christ as we ponder His being made man like us. We suffer patiently with Him and anticipate His glory. To ponder these truths with piety, we need to direct our prayer to the heart of her who was closest to Christ on earth, says Paul VI. In this way, we can become privy to a favorable meditation on the mysteries of the life of Our Lord.</p>

<p>The never-ending wealth of truth contained in these mysteries opens before our mind’s eye. To pray the Rosary like this, says St. Josemaría, considering the mysteries, repeating the <em>Our Father</em> and <em>Hail Mary,</em> with the praises to the Blessed Trinity and the constant invocation to the Mother of God, is a continuous act of faith, hope, and love, of adoration and reparation.</p>

<p>During the time of St. Dominic, people greeted Our Lady with the invocation of a rose, a symbol of beauty and joy. Images of her were already adorned with crowns of roses in representation of the Rosary beads. Singing to Mary as the garden of roses was common throughout Christendom. The present term “Rosary” has its origin in this custom.</p>

<p>We shouldn’t forget that each <em>Hail Mary</em> is like a rose that we offer to our Mother in heaven. May we not allow them to pass lifelessly from our lips due to lack of interest or inattentiveness. In the face of the obstacles we encounter, let us not neglect this powerful weapon. In <em>The Furrow,</em> we’re told, let us draw close to Our Lady through this devotion, when we feel the weight of our weakness most.</p>

<p>“Immaculate Virgin, I know very well that I am only a miserable wretch, and all I do is increase each day the number of my sins.” You told me the other day that was how you spoke to our Mother. And I was confident in advising you with assurance to pray the Holy Rosary. “Blessed be that monotony of <em>Hail Marys</em> which purifies the monotony of your sins.”</p>

<p>We are reminded by St. Dominic that only God can fill our heart. St. Paul says, “If then you have been raised with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God. Set your mind on the things that are above, not on the things that are on earth” (Col. 3:1–2).</p>

<p>Things of the world last a relatively short period of time, and they can’t fill the longings of the human heart. We’re told in the Book of Wisdom that the life of man on earth is brief. The greater part of it is spent in pain and suffering. Every life passes like the wind, barely a trace is left behind.</p>

<p>In the best of cases, one might amass a fortune, only for it to be left to others. What does all this pain and effort add up to? Is it all for nothing? The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “Vanity of vanities, all is vanity” (Eccles. 1:2). In the face of this emptiness and inconsistency, all this pointlessness, God is the rock of our salvation.</p>

<p>The Psalm says, “Let us come into His presence with thanksgiving, let us make a joyful noise to Him with songs of praise” (Ps. 95:2). Nevertheless, the human heart has a tremendous capacity to seek the things that are of the world, without paying any attention to the transcendent meaning of life. The human heart tends to become attached to worldly goods as the one and only goal in life, forgetting what is really important.</p>

<p>Our Lord takes advantage of a question about inheritances to teach us about the true worth of things in the light of eternity. He brings up the subject of death, of our own death, to make this point. He said, “The land of a rich man brought forth plentifully. And he thought to himself, what shall I do, for I have nowhere to store my crops?” (Luke 12:16–17).</p>

<p>And he said, “This I will do. I will pull down my barns and build larger ones. And I will say to my soul, Soul, you have ample goods laid up for many years. Take your ease. Eat, drink, be merry” (Luke 12:18–19).</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that putting our hearts into the pursuit of wealth and worldly well-being is foolishness. Neither happiness, nor authentic human life itself, are founded on worldly goods. “A man’s life does not consist in the abundance of his possessions” (Luke 12:15).</p>

<p>The rich man discloses his value system in his mental dialogue. He sees himself in a very secure position because he has great resources. He bases his stability and his happiness on this wealth. For him, as for many people, living is a matter of enjoying as much pleasure as possible. That is, to do as little as need be, to eat, to drink, to have a good time. To lay up ample goods for many years. That is his ideal.</p>

<p>In his life, there’s no reference to God, much less to other people. He sees no need to share his goods with others less fortunate than himself. And how does he plan to maintain this thoroughly materialistic lifestyle? He says, “I will store up.”</p>

<p>Yet in the end, all of his calculations are for nothing. The things of this world give a fragile and insufficient security, since our lives will never be fulfilled without God. We can ask ourselves today in our prayer on this feast of St. Dominic, where is my heart? Because we know that our destination is heaven.</p>

<p>Because of that, we have to make positive and concrete acts of detachment with regard to what we own and what we use. We can ask ourselves, how much do we share our goods with the needy? How much time and wealth do we contribute to apostolic works? Taking advantage of the noble things of the earth so as to win heaven for ourselves.</p>

<p>It’s very good that we have a certain winning mentality in our life, a sporting spirit. Despite the fact that he has been overlooked, God interrupts the rich man in his ruminations to pass judgment on his chosen way of life. He says, “Fool.” Very strong word. Very strong written word, and even stronger in the words of scripture.</p>

<p>It’s not common that God calls people fools. But He says that to the rich man. “Fool, this night your soul is required of you, and the things you have prepared, whose will they be?” So is he who lays up treasure for himself and is not rich toward God (cf. Luke 12:20–21).</p>

<p>Our passage upon the earth is a time of testing. The Lord Himself has given it to us. St. Paul reminds us that “Here we have no lasting city, but we seek the city which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). On a certain day, Our Lord will come to settle accounts with us, to determine how well or ill we have administered His gifts.</p>

<p>Among His gifts that He has given to us are those of our intelligence, our health, our material goods, our capacity for friendship and leadership, our power to give joy to those around us. Our Lord will come only once. Perhaps when we least expect Him. Like, as He says Himself, a thief in the night. Like lightning flashing across the sky. He wants to find us well-prepared.</p>

<p>Tying ourselves down to the world, forgetting that our end is in heaven, can lead us to live a disoriented life of complete idiocy. “Fool” is precisely what God calls the man who lives only for the world. We certainly have to walk with our feet on the ground, taking care to safeguard our future and the future of those who depend upon us.</p>

<p>But we can’t forget that we are pilgrims. No more than actors in a show. No one is permanently made king or wealthy, since at the end of the performance, we will all find ourselves as paupers before God. All those things that we cannot carry away with us are not ours. They just belong to us, says St. John Chrysostom.</p>

<p>Worldly goods are but the means for us to attain the goal which Our Lord has pointed out to us. These goods can never become the be-all and the end-all of our existence. Our life on earth is short and limited. He says to the man, “This night your soul is required of you.”</p>

<p>We might think of death in terms of something remote, as if we’ll live forever. Yet Our Lord speaks of “this night.” Our days are numbered. We’re in the hands of God. Within a few years, maybe not that many, we’ll find ourselves face to face with Him. Meditating on our final end should motivate us to sanctify our work, redeeming the time as we strive to make up for lost time.</p>

<p>It should help us to take advantage of our circumstances in order to make reparation for sins and to become detached from earthly goods. One day, like any other day, will be our last day on earth. Today, thousands of people have died or will die in the most diverse circumstances. Those people were probably unaware that their time was up. They would have no more time to improve.</p>

<p>Some have died with their hearts immersed in things of little or no importance in terms of eternal life. Others have died who have been involved in exactly the same activities, but have kept their sights on God. It is these latter people who have come into possession of that marvelous treasure which neither dust nor moth consumes.</p>

<p>At the moment of death, the state of the soul is fixed forever. Afterwards, it is impossible to change. The destiny which awaits us is the consequence of our behavior on earth. The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “If a tree falls to the south or to the north, in the place where the tree falls, there it will lie” (Eccles. 11:3). This is the reason for Our Lord’s frequent warnings to be on watch.</p>

<p>We can learn from St. Dominic, from his life, from his quest for truth, from the great gifts and treasures that the religious order that he founded has given to the universal Church and to the world. We can pray for their ever greater fruitfulness and vocations. And ask that each of us might spread that truth in ever more fruitful ways along the course of our apostolate, and that we might take up our Rosary with greater devotion and piety every day.</p>

<p>St. Dominic, pray for us.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. James (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. James (2026)" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-james-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Saint James was from Bethsaida. He was the son of Zebedee and the brother of John. He is one of the three disciples to witness the Transfiguration and the agony in the garden, besides other important events of Our Lord’s public life. He and his brother’s impetuous zeal caused Our Lord to name them the sons of thunder. James developed his apostolate in Judea and Samaria, and according to tradition, he preached the Gospel in Spain. On his return to Palestine about the year 44, he became the first apostle to suffer martyrdom at the order of Herod Agrippa. His mortal remains were later brought to Santiago de Compostela in Spain, which became a popular medieval pilgrimage site and a sanctuary of the faith for all in Europe.</p>

<p>We’re told in Saint Matthew, walking by the Sea of Galilee, Jesus saw James and John, the sons of Zebedee, mending their nets, and called to them, giving the name Boanerges, which means sons of thunder (cf. Mark 3:17). It all began when a few fishermen on Lake Tiberias were called by Jesus of Nazareth to follow him. They responded to Our Lord’s call, followed him, and lived with him for nearly three years. They shared his daily life and were witnesses of his prayer, his mercy toward sinners, and those who suffer, and his power. They listened attentively to his words, the like of which they had never heard before. In the three years they spent together, the disciples experienced a reality that was to possess them forever. In a word, life with Jesus.</p>

<p>It was an experience that broke the threads of their prior existence. They had to leave everything, their family, their trade, and their possessions to follow him. In short, they were introduced to a new way of living. One day, Jesus invited James to follow him. He was the brother of John and the son of Salome, a woman who served Jesus with all she had and ultimately was present on Calvary. James knew Jesus before he was called. Together with Peter and his brother, the apostles enjoyed a special predilection from Our Lord. He was one of the three present at the Transfiguration on Mount Tabor. He was also present at the raising of the daughter of Jairus, and one of those who accompanied Our Lord in Gethsemane towards the beginning of the Passion.</p>

<p>Our Lord was so taken by the impetuous zeal of James and John that he nicknamed them Boanerges, the sons of thunder. We’re told that Jesus had finished speaking about his impending passion and death in the holy city. Saint Matthew says, “We’re going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be given over to the chief priests and the scribes, and they will condemn him to death and deliver him over to the Gentiles to be mocked and scourged and crucified, and he will be raised on the third day” (Matt. 20:18–19).</p>

<p>Our Lord feels the need to share with his disciples the innermost sentiments that fill his soul. Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee drew near to him with her sons, and bowed down at his feet to make a request. She asked him to reserve two eminent places for her sons in his seemingly imminent kingdom. Jesus turns to the brothers and asks them if they can share the same fate with him. He offers them his cup. To offer one another one’s chalice to drink from was considered a great sign of friendship in antiquity. They immediately respond, “We can.”</p>

<p>These words express generous docility. They reflect an attitude that belongs to all the young at heart and to all Christians, says John Paul II, especially those who are willing to be apostles of the good news. Our Lord accepts the generous response of the two disciples straight away, and tells them, yes, you will drink from my cup. You will participate in my sufferings, and you will complete my passion in your own bodies.</p>

<p>Sometime later, in the year 44, James was to die by decapitation. John was tried with innumerable sufferings and persecutions throughout his long life. Ever since Christ redeemed us on the cross, all Christian suffering consists in drinking from the cup of the Lord through participation in his passion, death, and resurrection. By means of our suffering, we complete in a certain way his passion that is thus prolonged in time with its saving fruits. Human suffering becomes redemptive when it’s closely associated with the ignominy that Our Lord endured. In his mercy, he lets us share in his cup.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>The Furrow</em>, in the face of difficulties, sickness, or pain, Jesus puts the same question to us: Can you drink from my cup? If we are united to him, we will respond positively and bear what is humanly disagreeable for his sake. In union with Christ, even our pain and failure are converted into joy and peace. The great Christian revolution has been to convert pain into fruitful suffering, to turn a bad thing into something good. We have deprived the devil of this weapon, and with it we can conquer eternity.</p>

<p>From the time Saint James made his not entirely ambitions known until the hour of his martyrdom, there’s a long interior development. That same zeal of his, earlier directed against the Samaritans who did not want to receive Jesus—the people would not receive him because, we’re told in Saint Luke, “His face was set towards Jerusalem” (Luke 9:53)—was later to be transformed into a zealous concern for souls. Little by little, without losing the vigor of his own personality, James learned that zeal for the divine interests cannot be violent or bitter. The glory of God alone is the only worthwhile ambition.</p>

<p>Clement of Alexandria relates how when the apostle of Spain was taken before the tribunal to be judged, his integrity was so apparent that his accuser approached him afterwards to ask his pardon. James thought about it and then embraced him, and said to him, “Peace be with you.” The two of them together then received the crown of martyrdom.</p>

<p>While meditating on the life of the Apostle James, it helps a great deal for us to see evidence of his defects and those of the other eleven that the Lord had chosen. They weren’t powerful or wise or simple. We see them at times being ambitious and argumentative. James was the first apostle to be martyred. Clearly, the help of God can work wonders in us. How thankful to God James will be in heaven for leading him along paths quite different from the ones he dreamt of earlier in his life.</p>

<p>Since Our Lord is good, infinitely wise, and loving beyond what we can realize, on many occasions he does not give us what we ask for, but what is most appropriate for us, and therefore the best. Like the other apostles, James has clear and undeniable defects and weaknesses that are clearly seen in the Gospel accounts. Nevertheless, together with these shortcomings, he had a great soul and a big heart. Jesus was always patient with him and with the others too. The master allowed them time for them to learn the lessons that he imparted with divine wisdom and affection.</p>

<p>Saint John Chrysostom says, let us examine how Our Lord’s way of questioning is equivalent to an exhortation and a stimulus. He does not say, can you bear defeat? Are you capable of shedding your blood? His words are, can you drink from the cup? To encourage them to the task, he adds, from which I am to drink. The prospect of drinking from the Lord’s very cup leads them to a more generous response. He gives the name baptism to his passion to emphasize that his sufferings would be the cause of a great purification for the whole world, says Saint John Chrysostom.</p>

<p>Our Lord has also called us. May we not give in to discouragement if our defects and weaknesses become manifest. If we approach Jesus for help, he will give us the courage to continue on our path with greater fidelity, since he is ever patient and allows us the time we need to improve.</p>

<p>In the second reading of the Mass, Saint Paul reminds us “We bear this treasure in vessels of clay so that it may be clearly seen that our power comes from God and not from ourselves” (2 Cor. 4:7). We are rather fragile creatures and not very constant. But nevertheless, we are capable of bearing in ourselves an incomparable treasure, since God works marvels in men despite their weaknesses. Just to show that it is he who acts and grants efficacy to our desires, Our Lord wants to “choose the weak to confound the strong, and the vile and scorned of the world as well as those who are not, to destroy the things that are, so that any human flesh should pride itself before the creator,” says Saint Paul (cf. 1 Cor. 1:27–29).</p>

<p>Amazingly enough, one who was formerly a persecutor of the Church of God wrote these words filled with humility. We Christians, by bearing God in our soul, can live at the same time both in heaven and on earth, divinized, but knowing that we are of the world and made of clay. An earthen pot which Our Lord has deigned to use in his service, with the frailty that is typical of such fragile material. When the vessel is cracked or broken, we will seek the seals that are put on pitchers in need of repair so that they may continue to be useful.</p>

<p>Like the prodigal son, we can say, “Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you” (Luke 15:21). God grants efficacy to those who have the humility to feel themselves as vessels of clay, the ones who bear in their own body the mortification of Jesus and who drink from the cup of the passion which Jesus drank.</p>

<p>Tradition recalls the preaching of Saint James throughout Spain. His great zeal for souls led him to the very limits of the known world. We also learn from accounts passed on to us of the difficulties he encountered in the beginnings of his evangelizing, and how Our Lady appeared to him to offer encouragement. It’s possible that we too may feel disheartened on occasion and baffled by the obstacles that obstruct our desires to bring other souls to Christ. We may also encounter misunderstanding, mockery, oppositions of all sorts, calumnies. However, we know that Our Lord will never abandon us. We will approach the Lord and be able to tell him with confidence like Saint Paul, “We are sore pressed but not destitute. We endure persecution but are not forsaken. We are cast down but never perish” (cf. 2 Cor. 4:8–9).</p>

<p>Our Lord says to his apostles, “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already kindled” (Luke 12:49). Just like any true friend, Our Lord reveals to his disciples his most intimate thoughts. He has a holy impatience to ignite the flame of charity in men’s hearts and offer his holocaust to the Father on Calvary for the sake of mankind. “I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am constrained until it is accomplished” (Luke 12:50). There on the cross, the fullness of God’s love for his creatures was made manifest. “Greater love than this no man has, than that he lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13).</p>

<p>We prove we are Christ’s friends if we struggle to follow him. Saint Augustine commented on this passage that people who believe in him are enkindled. They receive the flame of charity. That’s why the Holy Spirit appeared in this form at Pentecost. We’re told in the Acts, “There appeared to them tongues as of fire distributed and resting on each one of them” (Acts 2:3). Set aflame by this fire, the apostles set out across the entire world to inflame others, including their enemies. What enemies? says Saint Augustine. Well, those who had forsaken God their creator for the worship of man-made idols.</p>

<p>The faith of such as these has been smothered to ashes. It is good for them, says Saint Augustine, that they be set alight by this holy flame so that they may once again shine forth in Christ’s glory. This crucial task of setting the world on fire has been passed on to today’s Christians. This fire of love and peace will strengthen and purify souls. We need to go to the university, to the factories, into public life, to our homes. If one were to set fires at different locations throughout a city, even if they were modest fires, they would quickly consume the whole metropolis. Likewise, if in a city at the most separated points, one were to ignite the hearts of the inhabitants with the fire that Jesus brought to the world, then the good will of those people would quickly overrun the city, lighting it up with love for God.</p>

<p>The fire that Jesus has brought to the world is himself. It is the fire of love. This is the love which not only unites souls to God, but also unites souls to one another. In each city, these souls shall emerge from families, father and mother, son and father, mother and mother-in-law. This phenomenon can take place in parish life, in organizations, in schools, in offices, anywhere. One writer says each small flame for God necessarily kindles other flames. Divine providence takes care to distribute these souls on fire where they can best serve the process. Through their action, many places in the world will be restored to the warmth of the love of God and renewed hope.</p>

<p>Our apostolate in the middle of the world should spread like a flame of peace. Apostolate in the middle of the world should spread like wildfire. Each Christian who lives the faith seriously becomes a point of ignition at his or her place of work, among their friends and acquaintances. But this phenomenon will only occur if we make concrete the advice that Saint Paul gave to the Philippians: “Have this in mind among yourselves, which was also in Christ Jesus, who, though he was by nature God, did not consider being equal to God a thing to be clung to, but emptied himself, taking the nature of a slave and being made in the likeness of men. He became humble and obedient, even obedient to a cross” (Phil. 2:5–8).</p>

<p>Opus Dei’s author says the apostle challenges all Christians to live out in their lives as much as possible those sentiments which filled the divine Redeemer when he offered himself up as a sacrifice. Imitate his humility and present to God Almighty all the adoration, honor, praise, and thanksgiving. This offering is carried out primarily in the Mass, the unbloody renewal of the sacrifice of the cross.</p>

<p>The Second Vatican Council teaches us concerning the contribution of the laity. It says, for all their works, prayers, and apostolic endeavors, their ordinary married and family life, their daily occupations, their physical and mental relaxation, if carried out in the spirit, and even the hardships of life, if patiently borne—all these become spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. Together with the offering of the Lord’s body, they are most fittingly offered in the celebration of the Eucharist. Thus, as those everywhere who adore in holy activity, the laity consecrate the world itself to God (cf. <em>Lumen Gentium</em>, 34).</p>

<p>A Christian life ought to be an imitation of the life of Christ, a participation in his divine sonship. Through this way of life, we will learn from Jesus how to relate to other people. We are told in Saint Matthew that “When Jesus saw the multitude, he had compassion on them, for they were like sheep without a shepherd” (Matt. 9:36). Life held no meaning for them. Jesus had compassion on these people. His love was so great that he went to the extent of giving up his life for them and us on the cross. This is the divine love which should fill our hearts.</p>

<p>Then we too will have compassion on the people around us who perhaps have strayed from the Lord. With the help of God’s grace, our genuine friendship, hopefully, we will bring these souls back to the master. In the holy Mass, a surging current of divine love is transmitted from the Son to the Father through the Holy Spirit. The follower of Our Lord participates in this love, since he or she is incorporated into Christ. The Christian then extends this love to other people and to all earthly realities, which are thereby sanctified and made into a fitting offering to God.</p>

<p>We’re told in <em>Friends of God</em>, our apostolate should have its roots in the Mass, and should from there draw its efficacy. For the Mass is nothing less than the realization of the redemption in our time by means of apostolic Christians. Jesus came on earth to redeem everyone, because he wished all men to be saved. There is not a single soul in whom Christ is not interested. Each soul has cost him the price of his blood. If we truly imitate Our Lord’s example, we can never be indifferent towards any soul.</p>

<p>When a Christian participates in the Mass, the prayers should be concerned first of all with their brothers and sisters in the faith. One writer says the Christians should feel more and more closely united to them in the bread of life and in the cup of eternal salvation. This is the time to pray for everyone, and especially for those who are most in need. We should grow in the spirit of charity and fraternity, because the Eucharist makes us all one. As a consequence, we therefore treat one another as family. The Eucharist unites the children of God into one family closely related to Christ and to one another.</p>

<p>Following this unique encounter with the Lord, we will experience the same joy as was felt by the sick in Palestine once they had been cured by Jesus. They were so overjoyed at this manifestation of God’s mercy they went about the towns and villages of Palestine singing the Lord’s praises. When a Christian receives communion at Mass, he should be moved to share this wonderful grace with others as well as the need to communicate it to other people. This was how Christianity grew so quickly in its early years. From people like Saint James, it spread like a conflagration of peace and love which no one could extinguish.</p>

<p>We could resolve to center our life upon the Mass. Then we will find peace and serenity, as well as the need to communicate it to other people. Throughout the course of our day, we will want to let our friends know about the treasure of this sacrament. If we attend Mass, as Saint Josemaría says in <em>Christ is Passing By</em>, if we attend Mass well, surely we are likely to think about Our Lord during the rest of the day, wanting to be always in his presence, ready to work as he worked, and to love as he loved.</p>

<p>We will learn to thank Our Lord for his kindness in not limiting his presence to the time of the sacrifice of the altar. He has decided to stay with us in the host which is reserved in the tabernacle. The tabernacle should be a Bethany for us, a quiet and pleasant place where Christ resides, a place where we can tell him about our worries, our sufferings, our desires, our joys, with the same sort of simplicity and naturalness as Martha, Mary, and Lazarus. We will find in the tabernacle the strength we need to do Our Lord’s work in union with many other Christians.</p>

<p>With Saint James, we could repeat the Lord’s cry, “I came to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already kindled” (Luke 12:49). This is the fire of divine love which will bring peace and joy to souls, to families, and to society as a whole. We can also seek the intercession of Our Lady, Queen of Apostles. In her we will find the courage and the joy to proceed on our way, just like the Apostle Saint James did.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Mary Magdalen (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Mary Magdalen (2026)" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/st-mary-magdalen-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, and that you hear me.</em></p>

<p><em>I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful.</em></p>

<p><em>My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Mary was originally from Magdala, a small city of Galilee on the northwest shore of Lake Tiberias. She was one of a group of women who followed Jesus and cared for him out of their own possessions.</p>

<p>Mary was present with Jesus on Calvary, and she was the second one, after Our Lady, to behold the Risen Savior on Easter morning.</p>

<p>She recognized him when Our Lord called her by name.</p>

<p>Devotion to this most constant follower of Christ spread throughout the Western world during the Middle Ages.</p>

<p>Most probably, she is not the same Mary who out of sincere contrition pours out precious ointment on Our Lord’s feet at the home of Simon the Pharisee.</p>

<p>She exemplifies our search for God at every moment.</p>

<p>In the Psalms, we read, “O God, you are my God, for you I long, for you my soul is thirsting. My soul pines for you like the dry parched earth” (Ps. 63:1).</p>

<p>We read these words in the responsorial psalm of today’s Mass.</p>

<p>They remind us of the steadfast love of Mary Magdalene. Steadfast faith.</p>

<p>After nearly twenty centuries, the refinement, fidelity, and love of this stalwart follower of Jesus are deeply moving.</p>

<p>St. John narrates for us in the gospel of the Mass, “Now this woman set out for the tomb as soon as the Sabbath rest permitted, when it was still dark, to go to find the dead body of Our Lord.”</p>

<p>Sometime previously, he had freed her of an evil spirit, and grace quickly bore fruit in her soul.</p>

<p>She followed the Master faithfully on some of his apostolic journeys and served him generously with all her possessions.</p>

<p>During the terrible moments of the crucifixion, she remained on Calvary, near the one who cured her of all that was wrong in her life.</p>

<p>Furthermore, when they laid Jesus in the tomb, she stayed close and kept him company, as we may have done at some point on the occasion of a loved one’s death.</p>

<p>St. Matthew talks about her courage. He says, “Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were seated there in front of the tomb” (Matt. 27:61).</p>

<p>When the Sabbath was over, as the first day of the week began to dawn, she sets out with the other holy women for the place where the dead body of Jesus was lying, in order to anoint it.</p>

<p>But Our Lord was no longer there. He had risen.</p>

<p>She saw the heavy stone rolled away and the tomb empty.</p>

<p>Then she began to run to Simon and the other disciple whom Jesus loved and said to them, “They have taken the Lord out of the tomb and we do not know where they have laid him” (John 20:2).</p>

<p>Peter and John went running towards the empty sepulchre.</p>

<p>St. John tells us that this moment was crucial in his life: “He saw and believed” (John 20:8).</p>

<p>Both apostles went back to their home again, but Mary stayed there, weeping, in the absence of the Master’s body.</p>

<p>With unspeakable sadness, still not believing in the resurrection, she perseveres in her vigil, not wanting to tear herself away from the place where she last saw our Savior.</p>

<p>Today, we consider the intensity of the love burning in the heart of the woman who did not leave the tomb, although the disciples had already gone away.</p>

<p>She continued to seek the one she had failed to find.</p>

<p>She sought for him in tears, and inflamed with the fire of love, was burning with longing to see the one she thought they had taken away.</p>

<p>Because Mary Magdalene remained there with the expectation of finding him, she was the only one to then encounter him.</p>

<p>Perseverance strengthens good deeds.</p>

<p>As the voice of Truth informs us, quoting St. Gregory, “Whoever perseveres to the end will be saved” (Matt. 10:22).</p>

<p>In <em>The Furrow</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Let us not stop seeking Jesus in every circumstance of our lives, even during those moments in which, if Our Lord so permits, discouragement or darkness penetrate our soul.”</p>

<p>Let us never forget that he is always very much in touch with the events of our life, though we may not be aware of him.</p>

<p>He is always close at hand.</p>

<p>“For,” as the Apostle assures us, “the Lord is near” (Phil. 4:5). <em>Dominus prope est.</em></p>

<p>“I shall walk with him, therefore, quite confidently, for the Lord is my father, and with his help I shall fulfill his most lovable will, even if I find it hard.”</p>

<p>When Jesus calls her by her name, she recognizes him, and has great joy before the Risen Christ.</p>

<p>Through her perseverance and great love in seeking him, Mary Magdalene received the grace of being the first person to whom Christ appeared.</p>

<p>At first she didn’t recognize him, despite his being right beside her.</p>

<p>St. John tells us she turned around and saw Jesus standing there, but she did not know that it was Jesus.</p>

<p>Even though he spoke to her, she didn’t immediately realize it was Christ, alive, there at her side.</p>

<p>Jesus said to her, “Woman, why are you weeping? Who is it you are seeking?” (John 20:15).</p>

<p>Her tears prevented her from seeing the Master, whom we can guess was smiling, being happy, very happy over the encounter.</p>

<p>Jesus looks at us too, as we continue to seek him out, in the midst of all the circumstances and events of our lives.</p>

<p>For Christ is the same now as then.</p>

<p>Supposing him to be the gardener, she said to him, “Sir, if you have removed him, tell me where you have laid him, and I will go and take him away” (John 20:15).</p>

<p>An unusual thing to say. Jesus was 6 feet tall, probably weighed 75 kilos, and Mary thinks she’s strong enough to carry Jesus away.</p>

<p>But then Jesus called her by her name, the way he used to. He said to her, “Mary” (John 20:16).</p>

<p>The dark clouds oppressing her heart for those past three days were all of a sudden dispersed.</p>

<p>One writer says, “How many interior sufferings, how many torments of the spirit, caused by great love and apparently without consolation, are frequently dissolved, and how often like the surf of a wave, at one word from Jesus.”</p>

<p>Like a river bursting its banks, as if it had all been a nightmare, Mary looks at him and says, “Rabboni” (John 20:16).</p>

<p>As though the connotation of this familiar term were a moving reality incapable of translation, St. John wanted to leave us the precise Hebrew word that Magdalene offered, that Magdalene often used to address Christ.</p>

<p>She sought him among the dead, comments St. Augustine, and he presented himself alive. How is it he is alive? He calls her by her name, “Mary.”</p>

<p>She responds the same instant that she hears her name spoken, “Rabboni.”</p>

<p>The gardener could have said, “Who is it you seek? Why are you crying?”</p>

<p>Mary, on the other hand, only Christ could have said it in that way. He called her by her name, the same one who called her to the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>He spoke the name “Mary.” He had written in the book of life, and she, “Rabboni,” which means “teacher.”</p>

<p>She already recognized the one who had illuminated her so that she could possibly recognize him.</p>

<p>She already saw Christ in the one whom before she perceived a gardener.</p>

<p>He said to her, “Do not touch me, for I have not yet ascended to my Father” (John 20:17).</p>

<p>Our burdens can disappear when we make an effort to discover Jesus, alive and glorious at our side, calling us by our name.</p>

<p>It’s a great joy for us to be on familiar terms with Christ, and to be able to call on him in the particular way that he knows so well.</p>

<p>Prayer, dialogue with the Lord, is our most profound blessing and the foundation of our entire life.</p>

<p>We will never stop seeking his company, even if at times we don’t perceive his presence.</p>

<p>If we persevere in prayer, he will always come out to meet us, calling us by our name.</p>

<p>Closely united to Jesus, we will recover our peace and joy.</p>

<p>One word from him will restore our hope and renew our desire to begin again.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, we’re told, “Let us never forget, in any situation, that the Lord’s triumph on the day of the Resurrection is final. Where are the soldiers the rulers put on guard? Where are the seals they affixed to the stone of the tomb? Where are those who condemned the Master? And those who crucified Jesus? He is victorious, and these poor wretches have fled away. Be filled with hope: Jesus Christ is always victorious.”</p>

<p>He conquers even in the battles of our own life. He triumphs over those defects and weaknesses of ours, which at times seem insurmountable.</p>

<p>After consoling Mary, Jesus gave her a message for the Apostles, whom he affectionately called “brothers.”</p>

<p>“Then Mary went and said to the disciples, ‘I have seen the Lord,’ and she told them all that had happened” (John 20:18).</p>

<p>Pope Francis likes to use an interesting term for Mary Magdalene at this juncture. He said, “She became the apostle of the apostles.”</p>

<p>She announces to the apostles that Christ is risen.</p>

<p>We can imagine Mary’s joy upon saying those words, “I have seen the Lord.”</p>

<p>We can imagine her joy at bringing that news to the Apostles, inflaming their own apostolic zeal, and hopefully ours also, and everyone who is to come after us.</p>

<p>This is the joy and happiness of all apostolate, worthy of the name, in which we proclaim to others in countless ways the fact that Jesus is alive today.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas comments, “This woman, who was eminently steadfast in finding out about the burial place of Christ, is prefigured every person who yearns to know divine truth, and is therefore well-disposed to pass on the knowledge of such a grace to others.”</p>

<p>Just as Mary announced it to the disciples so that she could not be reprimanded for hiding her talent.</p>

<p>The Angelic Doctor concludes, “God has not granted us this joy in order for you to hide it in the recesses of your hearts, but to share it with those who are capable of love.”</p>

<p>Whoever finds Christ finds him for everyone.</p>

<p>The news of the resurrection spread like wildfire during the first centuries. Christians were conscious of being bearers of the good news.</p>

<p>The disciples rejoiced over the one who died for us, and rose again on the third day, as he said.</p>

<p>They were happy people in the midst of a sad world. Their joy, like ours, stems from always being near the living Christ.</p>

<p>Apostolate is always the communication of this joyful message, the most cheerful message of all.</p>

<p>Today we can ask St. Mary Magdalene to gain for us a share in her loving perseverance in seeking the Lord.</p>

<p>Father, we’re told in the opening prayer of the Mass, “your Son first entrusted to Mary Magdalene the joyful news of the resurrection. By her prayers and example, may we proclaim Christ as our living Lord, and one day see him in glory.”</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Keep me as the apple of your eye, hide me in the shadow of your wings” (Ps. 17:8).</p>

<p>Our refuge and our strength lie in the love of God. We need to go to the tabernacle frequently to seek the presence of Jesus, like Mary Magdalene did.</p>

<p>On his way to the holy city, Jesus stops for a moment to express his disappointment at its rejection of his message. “Jerusalem, Jerusalem. How often I would have gathered your children together, as a hen gathers her brood under her wings, but you did not want” (Matt. 23:37).</p>

<p>Our Lord describes how he protects his own as a hen gathers her brood.</p>

<p>Jesus watches over us from the tabernacle. He is alert to the dangers that threaten us. He is ever ready to cure our wounds.</p>

<p>He continually shares his life with us. This has continually been our prayer on many occasions: “<em>Pie pellicane, Iesu Domine, me immundum munda tuo sanguine.</em>” “O loving Pelican, O Jesus Lord, unclean I am, but cleanse me in your blood.”</p>

<p>Of which a single drop, for sinners spilt, can purge the entire world from all its guilt.</p>

<p>Our Lord is our refuge and our strength. The image of this just one seeking protection from the Lord as a hen gathers her brood, is to be found repeatedly in sacred scripture.</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Keep me as the apple of your eye, hide me in the shadow of your wings, for you are my refuge, a strong tower against the enemy. Let me dwell in your tent forever. Oh, to be safe under the shelter of your wings” (Ps. 17:8; 61:3–4).</p>

<p>The prophet Isaiah employs this image to reassure the chosen people of God’s protection against the Egyptians.</p>

<p>“Like birds hovering, so the Lord of hosts will protect Jerusalem” (Isa. 31:5).</p>

<p>At the close of our earthly life, Jesus will be our judge and friend.</p>

<p>While we live on earth, his mission is to save us, to give us all the help we need.</p>

<p>From the tabernacle, Jesus protects us in a thousand ways. How can we imagine that he is indifferent towards our problems and worries?</p>

<p>Jesus has wanted to remain present throughout the world so that we might seek him more readily for friendship and assistance, and rely on him, like St. Mary Magdalene did.</p>

<p>Getting up early in the morning, while it was still dark, because she had a hole in her heart.</p>

<p>St. John Vianney says, “If we are suffering pain and discomfort, he will lighten our burden and comfort us. If we succumb to illness, either he will provide a remedy, or he will give us the strength to suffer it for the sake of eternal life. If we find ourselves at war with the devil and our passions, he will supply us with arms for the battle, so that we can resist and ultimately be victorious. If we are poor, he will enrich us with all kinds of good things in this life and in eternity.”</p>

<p>Like Mary Magdalene, we could resolve to seek his company every single day without fail.</p>

<p>St. Alphonsus says, “Those few minutes we spend in our visit will be among the most productive moments of the day.”</p>

<p>What are we to do in the presence of the Blessed Sacrament? Love him, praise him, thank him, ask of him.</p>

<p>What does a poor man do in the presence of a wealthy man? What does a sick person do in the presence of a doctor? What does a thirsty person do at the sight of a fountain of sparkling water?</p>

<p>Our confidence that we will be victorious in trial and tribulation is not founded on our own limited resources, but on the protection of Our Lord.</p>

<p>He has loved us from all eternity, to the point of sacrificing his son for our salvation.</p>

<p>Jesus remains present among us in the tabernacle. As a consequence, he may be very close to the place where we live and work. He’s ready to help us, to heal us, to give us energy for our earthly sojourn.</p>

<p>All we have to do is draw close to him. He is waiting for us.</p>

<p>Nothing should separate us from God.</p>

<p>Because, as St. Paul teaches us in scripture, “If God is for us, who is against us? He who did not spare his own Son, but gave him up for us all, will he not also give us all things with him? Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? Shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?” (Rom. 8:31–35).</p>

<p>“Nothing can separate us from God if we are determined to abide with him.”</p>

<p>The Psalms say, “Clothed in grace we can cross mountains and climb the hill of our Christian duty without panting on the way.”</p>

<p>If friends of God, St. Josemaría says, “If we use these resources with a firm purpose, and beg Our Lord to grant us an everlasting hope, we will possess the infectious joy of those who know they are children of God.”</p>

<p>If God is for us, who can be against us?</p>

<p>Even though Our Lord permits us to experience strong temptations, family difficulties, sickness or reverses of any kind.</p>

<p>No trial, no matter how fierce, can separate us from Jesus.</p>

<p>By making a devout visit to the tabernacle nearest to us, we will reach out to the most powerful hand of God. We will then be able to say, “<em>Omnia possum in eo qui me confortat,</em>” “I can do all things in him who strengthens me” (Phil. 4:13).</p>

<p>“For I am sure that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, nor height, nor depth, nor anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God in Christ Jesus our Lord” (Rom. 8:38–39).</p>

<p>This is the psalm of trust and optimism, which we should make our own.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom reminds us that Paul himself had to fight against numerous adversaries. He was attacked by barbarians, his guards laid traps for him.</p>

<p>There were times, says St. John Chrysostom, when he was opposed by his own faithful in great numbers. Yet Paul was triumphant.</p>

<p>Let us not forget that the Christian who is faithful to the laws of God will win out over those who oppose him, and even over Satan himself.</p>

<p>If we stay close to Jesus in the Eucharist, we will be victorious in every engagement, though sometimes we may appear to have been overcome.</p>

<p>The tabernacle will be our strength.</p>

<p>That’s why Jesus wanted to remain with us, in a tangible way, so that we could seek his help.</p>

<p>“Come to me, all you who labor and are heavy burdened, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you, for my yoke is easy and my burden is light” (Matt. 11:28–30).</p>

<p>Jesus invites us and beckons to us every day. Our Lord, may we go to you, like Mary Magdalene did, with insistence, with perseverance, with courage, with a spirit to overcome all obstacles.</p>

<p>In that way our serenity will be rooted in Our Lord. We don’t close our eyes to reality, we look at the present and to the future with optimism, because Our Lord is by our side.</p>

<p>Life’s difficulties can, in the end, yield for us a great good. We’re never alone, in even the most overwhelming circumstances.</p>

<p>Just as we appreciate the company of a friend when things are going badly, so should we be grateful for the company of our Friend in the nearest tabernacle. We should go to him for consolation, peace, and strength.</p>

<p>What more can we want, wrote St. Teresa, than so good a friend at our side? Who will not forsake us when we are in trouble and distress, as they do who belong to the world.</p>

<p>St. Thomas More realized that his doom was sealed when he was called to testify before the Lambeth Tribunal.</p>

<p>He bade farewell at home to the people of his household, because he didn’t want them to follow him to the wharf, as was their custom. Only his son-in-law William Roper, and his favorite daughter Margaret, accompanied him on this final, short journey, together with a few servants.</p>

<p>Everyone aboard the upstream ferry was silent. After a while, More whispered into the ear of Roper, “Son Roper, I thank Our Lord the field is won.”</p>

<p>Roper later wrote that he did not comprehend the meaning of these words.</p>

<p>With the passing of time, however, he came to understand that More’s faith had given him the confidence of victory over any obstacle.</p>

<p>He knew without a shadow of a doubt that Our Lord would be with him in his ultimate battle.</p>

<p>If we seek to be close to Jesus, to be eucharistic souls, Our Lord will watch over us as a hen gathers her brood.</p>

<p>We too can be strengthened in the knowledge that the field is won.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>The Forge</em>, “Be a eucharistic soul. If the center around which your thoughts and hopes turn is the tabernacle, then my child, how abundant the fruits of your sanctity and apostolate will be.”</p>

<p>We ask Mary Magdalene to give us those desires that she had in her heart, as she set out so early to seek Jesus, not worrying about what people would think or what people would say, overcoming all the difficulties.</p>

<p>The Mother of God contemplates her Son in heaven. She’ll put the right words and desires, right words on our lips and the right desires in our hearts. If we don’t know what to say or to do, she’ll provide a prompt response to make up for all our tongue-tied clumsiness.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice.</em></p>

<p><em>My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trinity Sunday (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trinity Sunday (2026)" /><published>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-26T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/trinity-sunday-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen. My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Today the Church celebrates the feast of the Blessed Trinity. It’s the ineffable mystery of God’s intimate life. It’s the central truth of our faith and the source of all gifts and graces. The <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> places it at the top of the hierarchy of truths in which we are invited to believe. The liturgy of the Mass invites us to a loving union with each of the three divine persons: Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. This feast was established for the Latin Church by Pope John XXII to be celebrated on the Sunday after the coming of the Holy Spirit, which is the last of the mysteries of our salvation.</p>

<p>Today is a good day to say many times, savoring it, <em>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.</em> There’s an ancient prayer to the Blessed Trinity called the <em>Trisagium Angelicum,</em> which has <em>Tibi laus, tibi gloria, tibi gratiarum actio.</em> To you be praise, to you be glory, to you be thanksgiving, world without end, O Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>Having completed the commemoration of the mysteries of salvation, from Christ’s birth in Bethlehem to the descent of the Holy Spirit at Pentecost, the liturgy now invites us to contemplate the central mystery of our faith, the Blessed Trinity. The mystery of God’s own inner life and the fountain of all gifts and graces.</p>

<p>In his infinitely wise providence, God gradually revealed to mankind his inmost being. That is, as he is in himself, and not just as the cause of created things. In the Old Testament he makes known above all his oneness, and his complete transcendence from the world as its creator and Lord. We learn that God, unlike the world, is uncreated. That he is not limited in space, he is immense. He is not limited in time, he is eternal. His power knows no limits, he is omnipotent.</p>

<p>The book of Deuteronomy says, “Know therefore this day, and lay it to your heart, that the Lord is God in heaven above and on the earth beneath; there is no other” (Deut. 4:39). The Old Testament proclaims above all the greatness of Yahweh, the one God, creator and Lord of the universe. But he is also revealed as the shepherd who seeks his flock, who looks after his own indulgently and tenderly, who forgives and forgets the frequent infidelities of the chosen people.</p>

<p>At the same time, we get glimpses of the paternity of God the Father, of the incarnation of God the Son, whose advent is foretold by the prophets, and of the action of the Holy Spirit, who vivifies all things. But it is Christ who reveals to us in all its fullness the inner workings of the Trinitarian mystery and calls us to participate in it.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Matthew, “No one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). In St. John it is he who speaks to us of the coexistence of the Holy Spirit with the Father, and who sends him to the Church to sanctify it until the end of time. He it is who reveals to us the perfect oneness of the life of the three divine persons.</p>

<p>The mystery of the Trinity is the starting point of all revealed truth. The fountain from which proceeds supernatural life and the goal to which we are headed. We are children of the Father, brothers and co-heirs with the Son, and continually sanctified by the Holy Spirit. To make us ever more and more resemble Christ. Accordingly, we deepen in the understanding of our divine filiation and become living temples of the Blessed Trinity.</p>

<p>Since it is the central mystery of the Church’s faith, the Blessed Trinity is continually invoked in the liturgy. We were baptized in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. In their name also are our sins forgiven. We begin and end many prayers by invoking the Father, through Jesus Christ, in the unity of the Holy Spirit. Often during the day, we say the prayer, <em>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.</em></p>

<p>“God is my Father,” we’re told in <em>The Forge.</em> “If you meditate on it, you will never let go of this consoling thought. Jesus is my dear friend, another thrilling discovery, who loves me with all the divine madness of his heart. The Holy Spirit is my consoler, who guides my every step along the road. Consider this often. You are God’s, and God is yours” (<em>The Forge,</em> 2).</p>

<p>The divine life in which we are called to participate is extraordinarily bounteous. The Father eternally engenders the Son, and the Father and the Son together breathe forth the Holy Spirit. This generation of the Son, and the spiration of the Holy Spirit is not something that took place at a particular moment in time and gave rise once and for all to the three divine persons. These processions, rather, as theologians call them, are eternal.</p>

<p>In the case of human generation, a father begets a son, but thereafter both father and son continue to exist independently of the act of begetting. Even if one of them later dies. The man who is father is not just father. Both before and after begetting he is man. In God, by contrast, the essence of the Father consists in giving life to the Son. This is what determines him as a divine person, really distinct from the others.</p>

<p>One author says, among human beings the son who is begotten has a separate existence from his father, but the essence of the only begotten Son of God consists precisely in being Son. It is through him, making ourselves like him by the constant impulse of the Holy Spirit, that we obtain and grow in the awareness of our divine filiation.</p>

<p>“For all who are led by the Spirit of God are children of God. For you did not receive the spirit of slavery to fall back into fear, but you have received the spirit of sonship. When we cry, ‘Abba, Father!’ it is the Spirit himself bearing witness with our spirit that we are children of God. And if children, then heirs, heirs of God and fellow heirs with Christ” (Rom. 8:14–17).</p>

<p>Among men, paternity and filiation are circumstances that fall short of defining the subject completely. But in God, paternity, filiation, and spiration constitute the entire being of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. From the moment man is first called to participate in the divine life through the grace of baptism, he is destined to participate in it ever more and more. Along this path he must journey continually.</p>

<p>From the Holy Spirit we constantly receive impulses, motions, and inspirations to encourage us to travel faster along the way that leads to God, and to revolve in an ever tighter orbit around Our Lord. Our heart now needs to distinguish and adore each one of the divine persons. The soul is, as it were, making a discovery in the supernatural life. Like a little child opening his eyes to the world about him.</p>

<p>The soul spends time lovingly with the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, and readily submits to the work of the life-giving Paraclete, who gives himself to us without the slightest merit on our part, bestowing on us his gifts and the supernatural virtues. “We have run like the deer, longing for flowing streams, thirsting, our lips parched and dry” (cf. Ps. 42:1–2). We want to drink at the source of living water. All day long, without doing anything strange, we move in this abundant, clear spring of fresh waters that leap up to eternal life.</p>

<p>“Words are not needed,” we’re told in <em>Friends of God,</em> “because the tongue cannot express this wonder. The intellect grows calm, one does not reason, one looks. And the soul breaks out once more into song. A new song, because it feels and knows it is under the loving gaze of God all day long” (<em>Friends of God,</em> 307).</p>

<p>The Blessed Trinity dwells in the Christian soul as in a temple. St. Paul explains that “God’s love has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who has been given to us” (Rom. 5:5). There, in the inner recesses of the soul, says St. Catherine of Siena, we learn to be intimate with God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit. “You, O Eternal Trinity, are a deep ocean, into which the more I penetrate, the more I discover. And the more I discover, the more I seek you.”</p>

<p><em>My God, Blessed Trinity. Draw from my poor being what most contributes to your glory, and do with me what you wish, both now and in eternity. May I no longer place between us any voluntary hindrance to your transforming action. Second by second, with a forever actual intention, I desire to offer you all that I am and all that I have. Make my poor life an intimate union with the Word incarnate, an unceasing sacrifice of glory to the Blessed Trinity.</em></p>

<p><em>My God, how I wish to glorify you. If only in exchange for my complete immolation or for any other condition, it were in my power to enkindle the hearts of all your creatures and the whole of creation in the flames of your love, how I would desire to do so. May at least my poor heart belong to you completely. May I keep nothing for myself nor for creatures. Not even a single heartbeat. May I have a burning love for all mankind. But only with you, through you, and for you.</em></p>

<p><em>I desire above all to love you with the heart of St. Joseph, with the immaculate heart of Mary, with the adorable heart of Jesus, and finally to submerge myself in that infinite ocean, that abyss of fire that consumes the Father and the Son in the unity of the Holy Spirit, and love you with your own infinite love.</em></p>

<p><em>O eternal Father, beginning and end of all things. Through the immaculate heart of Mary, I offer you Jesus your Word incarnate. And through him, with him, and in him, I want to repeat ceaselessly this cry that rises from the bottom of my soul: Father, glorify continually your Son, so that your Son may glorify you, in the unity of the Holy Spirit, forever and ever.</em></p>

<p><em>O Jesus, who said, “No one knows the Son except the Father, and no one knows the Father except the Son and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him” (Matt. 11:27). Show us the Father, and we shall be satisfied.</em></p>

<p>Sister Elizabeth of the Trinity ends this prayer saying, “And you, O Spirit of love, teach us all things. And form Jesus with Mary in us until we become perfectly one in the bosom of the Father.”</p>

<p>Because of this great truth—we are children of God—we can spend our life giving thanks for this immense gift. We’re told in St. John, “But to all who received him, who believed in his name, he gave power to become children of God; who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God” (John 1:12–13).</p>

<p>God the Father “destined us in love to be his sons through Jesus Christ, according to the purpose of his will” (Eph. 1:5). God has made us his children. We will never completely understand nor value enough this incredible gift. Child of God! “See what love the Father has given us, that we should be called children of God. Beloved, we are God’s children now; it does not yet appear what we shall be” (1 John 3:1–2).</p>

<p>When we say, “I am a child of God,” we’re not using a metaphor or a pious phrase. We are children in the same way as human generation gives rise to fatherhood and sonship. Those who have been begotten by God are really his children. The Second Vatican Council states that this incomparable truth is carried out in baptism, in which, thanks to the passion and resurrection of Christ, there takes place a new birth into a new life, which did not previously exist. A new creature has emerged, by which the newly baptized person is called and really is a child of God.</p>

<p>The Council of Nicaea said divine sonship reaches its ultimate perfection in God the Son. Jesus Christ, the only begotten Son of God, born of the Father before the beginning of time. Begotten, not made, consubstantial with the Father. To highlight the essential difference between our sonship and the eternal sonship of the Son, ours is called adoptive.</p>

<p>Here below, the word adoption has a specific meaning. The new father has not given life to his son, although he sets out to educate him, supports him with his work, looks after his affairs, gives him his name, his rights of inheritance, and other privileges his natural children would have enjoyed. This might lead some people to have a somewhat confused idea about the true reality of our divine sonship. It must be understood that we are children of God, because God’s life is present in our souls in the state of grace.</p>

<p>It will help us in today’s prayer to consider that God is more our father than he whom in this life we call father, because he has given us our natural life. To refer to a Christian as a child of God is not a mere figure of speech, which brings to mind the fatherly protection or watchfulness that God exercises over him. Rather, it must be understood in the strictest sense, with the same meaning in which it is said that so-and-so is a son of such-and-such.</p>

<p>Through the act of conception, a new person comes into existence. Just as an animal gives birth to an animal of the same species, a human being gives birth to another human being, similar to the parents. Often enough there’s quite a similarity, and people are pleased to see that this or that child takes after his father, in his features, his behavior, his looks, his speech, and so on. Well, the Christian born of God is his son in the most real sense, so that he must be like his Father in heaven.</p>

<p>His condition as a son actually consists in his participation in the same nature as God. Here the words of St. Peter find their true meaning, “participants in the divine nature” (2 Pet. 1:4). Which is more than just an analogy, more than a likeness or a relationship. It implies, rather, an elevation and a transformation of human nature into a nature that is proper to a divine being.</p>

<p>There was a kid in a kindergarten school one time who was being prepared for First Holy Communion. The teacher was explaining the sacraments and explained how in baptism and in all the other sacraments we get grace and are lifted up onto a new supernatural level. That’s what grace does. Therefore we can lead a supernatural life. We’re called to lead a life on a whole new plane, with a supernatural goal.</p>

<p>The kid was amazed; he had never heard such wonderful things before. He had seen movies of Batman and Batwoman, and Spider-Man and Spider-Woman, and Superman and Superwoman. Now he hears that he is called to lead a supernatural life, that this business of baptism raises us up onto this new level. He decided that he should go home and baptize his pet dog, Rufus. He went home and got Rufus and brought him to the washroom, filled a cup with water, poured it over the head of Rufus, and said, “Now Rufus, I baptize you in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Now Rufus, you should be able to perform a supernatural action, an action above your nature. Talk to me, Rufus. Talk to me.” The story ended with Rufus beginning to talk rather clumsily, saying, “You’ll have to be patient with me while I learn to talk, because this is a whole new ball game for me.”</p>

<p>The Christian enters into a higher supernatural world, which is above his original nature, the world of God. This sense of our divine filiation and being participants in the divine nature is something incredible, something huge. It guides our relationship with God, and also with others. The Second Vatican Council said, “The Son came, sent by the Father, who chose us in him before the foundation of the world and destined us to be adopted sons, for it pleased him to restore all things in himself.”</p>

<p>Let us turn to Our Lady, daughter of God the Father, mother of God the Son, spouse of God the Holy Spirit. Mary, may you take us by the hand and lead us to be better children of God each day of our life.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me. In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blessed Are The Merciful</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/blessed-are-the-merciful/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blessed Are The Merciful" /><published>2026-02-25T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-25T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/blessed-are-the-merciful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/blessed-are-the-merciful/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Be merciful, therefore, even as your Father is merciful” (Luke 6:36).</p>

<p>Our Lord in the Gospel talks a lot about mercy. Our God is the God of mercy.</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul II liked to refer a lot to this also. He had an Encyclical that he called <em>Dives in misericordia–</em>“Rich in Mercy.” It is a beautiful description of God.</p>

<p>We could ask ourselves occasionally, What am I rich in? It is a beautiful thing to be rich in mercy. We are told, “Be merciful…as your heavenly Father is merciful” (Luke 6:36). “Blessed are the merciful, for they shall obtain mercy” (Matt. 5:7).</p>

<p>Our Lady says that “mercy is from generation to generation on those who fear him” (Luke 1:50). It is a quality that we are asked to have in all situations of our Christian vocation and to put into practice.</p>

<p>Like the good Samaritan—when he saw the person injured along the road, he was moved with compassion, moved with mercy that put everything else, all other considerations, aside. It was a characteristic reaction of his at that particular moment (Luke 10:30–37).</p>

<p>God’s mercy is infinite. It is greater than His justice. He showed His mercy on the Cross. “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing” (Luke 23:34).</p>

<p>He has given us the sacrament of mercy: Confession. God is “the Father of mercies,” we are told in Scripture (2 Cor. 1:3).</p>

<p>He sees in secret, and He rewards in secret (Matt. 6:4), and He forgives in secret. He wanted to reveal this mystery of His love.</p>

<p>John Paul II says that mercy is another word for love (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 7, November 30, 1980). A rather nice idea.</p>

<p>He liked to say that modern man needs mercy (<em>ibid</em>.). Every human person needs a certain amount of mercy, so it is one of the principal themes of Our Lord’s preaching, in fresh aspects all the time: the good shepherd that goes in search of the lost sheep (Luke 15:3-7); the lost coin—the woman stops what she is doing and goes to look for that particular coin, until she has found it (Luke 15:8-10). St. Luke’s Gospel is the Gospel of Mercy.</p>

<p>In many ways, Christ reveals the content of the mercy of God, which He wants us to express in concrete situations.</p>

<p>There was a visiting priest in a coastal town in England saying Mass one day. A parishioner approached him, an elderly lady, and asked him to say ten Masses for the dead.</p>

<p>As he was a new priest, she explained that she lost her son in the Battle of Britain in the Second World War. Every year she got Masses said for the repose of his soul.</p>

<p>But also, she got ten Masses said for whoever was most responsible for his death, “because,” she said, “after the war, that person would have to live with his conscience. He would come to know the evils of Nazi ideology.”</p>

<p>She said, “He stood in need of my forgiveness, and of my son’s forgiveness.”</p>

<p>So she got Masses said for the well-being of that fellow and of his family. She managed to move beyond righteous indignation, bitterness, or hatred.</p>

<p>It could have been there. She knew how to set aside feelings of vengeance—or exacting vengeance under the guise of justice.</p>

<p>She explained her concern for this stranger’s salvation and for the well-being of his family. This is having a heart full of mercy.</p>

<p>A document of the Second Vatican Council, <em>Ad gentes,</em> says, “For it is only by putting to death what is old that we are able to come to the newness of life.”</p>

<p>Put to death the old reactions that are there inside us in the old person. “The Gospel,” it says, “has truly been a leaven of liberty and progress…a leaven…of unity and of peace” (Vatican II, Decree, <em>Ad gentes</em>, Point 8, December 7, 1965).</p>

<p>It helps us to move on, to put this virtue into practice in concrete ways. Our lives are meant to be guided by mercy and by love because “God is love” (1 John 4:8,16).</p>

<p>We also say that God is mercy. Christ then becomes a “model of mercy” towards others. He reaches out in all sorts of ways.</p>

<p>He doesn’t just have a vague feeling of compassion for people, but He does things, does something about it. He puts it into practice.</p>

<p>When He saw the widow of Nain, He was approaching the town with a lot of people. He didn’t just think, ‘look at this poor widow’ and go along His way.</p>

<p>He stopped what He was doing, disrupted the movement of where He was going, and He went over to this lady and to the funeral stretcher, and touched the stretcher.</p>

<p>He performed a great miracle, possibly seeing in this woman an image of His own Mother after His own death. He was moved with a particular mercy (Luke 7:11-15).</p>

<p>He is the “model of mercy” towards others. As we become more Christ-like, we need to become more merciful, let things pass, have a forgiving spirit, not to focus on our past hurts, or get too rigid about when people have stepped on our toes in various moments.</p>

<p>“The merciful,” we’re told, “shall obtain mercy” (Matt. 5:7). We are all in need of mercy.</p>

<p>“As you give to others, so you shall receive yourself” (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 7:2), the Lord says.</p>

<p>That mercy of God signifies a special power of love that prevails over sin. God is absolute mercy. There is no sin that cannot be forgiven (<em>cf</em>. Mark 3:28).</p>

<p>The subtleties of God’s love become manifest in His mercy. Another beautiful aspect.</p>

<p>It’s a notion that pertains to God, but also to men. Mercy is a sign of man’s closeness to God. He is able to have mercy and look upon other people with compassion.</p>

<p>There was this nun, a Consolata nun (Consolata Sister Leonella Sgorbati) who died in Mogadishu, ten or twelve years ago. She was shot by somebody. As she lay dying on the street, she said the words, “I forgive, I forgive.”</p>

<p>Now she is beatified. Great words with which to end our life: words of mercy. A great example. Pope Benedict spoke about her the following Sunday in Rome.</p>

<p>“Contrasted with God’s justice, His mercy is shown to be more powerful, more profound” (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 4). It reaches further than justice.</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us to put that virtue into practice in concrete ways. Justice ends up meaning salvation won by God, and also His mercy. It excludes hatred towards others.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says, “Virtuous innocence never claims immunity from the guilt of others” (Fulton J. Sheen, <em>Neighborliness</em>). We realize that somehow we are also guilty. Somehow it’s my fault.</p>

<p>Humility leads us to have mercy on other people. He says, “This is why an innocent woman was found at the foot of the Cross. The truest sympathy is found in those who, with the strength of love, come out of the sunshine into the gloom and dimness of others, to touch wounds tenderly, as though their own nerves throbbed with pain” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Mercy leads us to get into the shoes of other people, a kind of sensitivity of where they’re coming from, of what cross they may be carrying.</p>

<p>God’s mercy is infinite. He has called us all to the eternal wedding feast. It’s as though He has thrown a great party where we can receive infinite mercy and we are all invited.</p>

<p>“No human sin can erase the mercy of God, or prevent him from unleashing all his triumphant power” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Veritatis Splendor</em>, Point 118, August 6, 1993). We just have to “call upon him” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>“Ask of me, and I will give you the nations for your inheritance, the very ends of the earth for your domain” (Ps. 2:8).</p>

<p>“Sin itself makes the love of the Father even more radiant” (John Paul II, <em>ibid</em>.) Because of man’s sin, God sent His only begotten Son. He came to save us from sin.</p>

<p>St. Augustine, in talking about original sin, says<em>,</em> “O happy fault!”</p>

<p>In a theology class one time, somebody asked me a question, saying, “St. Augustine says these words, ‘O happy fault.’” This person used to sing the <em>Exultet</em> in a parish church on Holy Saturday night and knew Latin and studied Latin and came across the phrase, <em>O felix culpa</em>.</p>

<p>He couldn’t quite figure it out. How come original sin is a happy fault with all the consequences that came from original sin?</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “It’s a happy fault because if man had not sinned, God would not have sent a Savior who died on the Cross shedding every ounce of his blood. Man would not have known how much God loves him” (<em>cf</em>. Augustine, <em>Enchiridion</em>).</p>

<p>God gave proof of His love on the Cross, proof of the extent of His mercy.</p>

<p>“It is proper to God,” says St. [Thomas Aquinas], “to exercise mercy. He manifests His omnipotence, particularly in this way” (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, II. II. Question 30).</p>

<p>Pope Francis said, “Thomas Aquinas’s words show that God’s mercy, rather than a sign of weakness, is the mark of his omnipotence” (Pope Francis, Bull of Indiction of the Extraordinary Jubilee of Mercy, <em>Misericordiae vultus,</em> Point 6, April 11, 2015).</p>

<p>The Father constantly extends that mercy to each one of us. How often have we benefited from the sacrament of mercy, the grace of God flowing into our soul, the blood of Christ washing away our sins?</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen likes to say that every time the priest raises his hands in the [Consecration], “the blood of Christ is dripping from his hands” (<em>cf</em>. Henry Dieterich, editor, <em>Through the Year with Fulton Sheen</em>).</p>

<p>“Without the shedding of blood,” we’re told in Scripture, “there is no remission of sin” (Heb. 9:22).</p>

<p>Christ then is the “Incarnation of that mercy. … In Christ and through Christ,” says John Paul in that Encyclical, “God becomes especially visible in His mercy…there is emphasized in him that attribute of his divinity using various concepts and terms.</p>

<p>“Christ confers on the whole of the Old Testament tradition about God’s mercy a definitive meaning.” He is Divine Mercy Incarnate.</p>

<p>“He doesn’t just speak of it; He explains it by use of comparisons and parables, but above all, he personifies it. He himself, in a certain sense, is mercy. … God becomes ‘visible’ in a particular way as the Father who is ‘rich in mercy’” (Eph. 2:4; John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 2).</p>

<p>Our Lord invites us continually to contemplate His mercy—the source of joy, serenity, peace. We know we can be forgiven.</p>

<p>We can always come back like the prodigal child. His father saw him a long way off. The father in that parable of the prodigal son is like a symbol of God the Father (Luke 15:11-32).</p>

<p>Every day he was looking out for his son, hoping that he might come back. One day he spots him on the horizon, yet a long way off.</p>

<p>It’s an insight into the heart of that father, never giving up, hoping that that son was going to come, and he doesn’t ask for a gun or a whip or something to teach him a lesson. He runs to him and embraces him.</p>

<p>“In the parables devoted to mercy, Our Lord reveals the nature of God as the nature of a father who never gives up. … he’s overcome all the evil with compassion and mercy” (<em>cf</em>. John Paul II, <em>Misericordiae vultus</em>, Point 9).</p>

<p>The role of the Church then is to manifest that mercy. “Mercy is the very foundation of the Church’s life” (John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 10).</p>

<p>He says, “The Church ‘has an endless desire to show mercy’” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Evangelii gaudium</em>, Point 24, November 24, 2013).</p>

<p>“All of her pastoral activity should be caught up in the tenderness she makes present to believers” (John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 10)—tenderness through health care, education, concern, and the promotion of the dignity of the human person.</p>

<p>“The Church is,” as it were, “commissioned in a special way “to announce the mercy of God, to announce the beating heart of the Gospel, which…must penetrate the mind and heart of every person” (Pope Francis, <em>Misericordiae vultus</em>, Point 12). Something very attractive.</p>

<p>Somebody was remembering last night a famous actor, Alec Guinness, I can’t remember the name, who was playing the part of a priest in a movie and acting in that movie. It was being shot in northern France.</p>

<p>On the way home from one of the shootings he decided not to change out of his costume, so he just walked home dressed as a priest to a hotel wherever he was staying.</p>

<p>He was a bit shocked when a young kid ran up to him, took him by the hand, grasped his hand firmly, and did not let it go until he reached his destination. Just the fact of being dressed as a priest, this kid was supremely attracted.</p>

<p>He said, “That was what moved me to convert to the Catholic faith.” Something very special there. Little children detect that sign of God’s love and of His mercy, the goodness that is there.</p>

<p>“Mercy is not opposed to justice but…expresses God’s way of reaching out to the sinner, offering him a new chance to...begin again, convert, and believe” (<em>cf</em>. Pope Francis, <em>Misericordiae vultus</em>, Point 21).</p>

<p>“Come back to me with all your heart. … Rend your hearts and not your garments” (Joel 2:12-13).</p>

<p>“A humble and contrite heart, O Lord, you will not spurn” (Ps. 51:17).</p>

<p>In this period of Lent, we find words of mercy frequently in the readings of Scripture. It’s very good as we move through Lent to pay a lot of attention to all the different things that are placed before us by the Church.</p>

<p>They all have their purpose: the First Reading, the Second Reading, the Responsorial Psalm, the Entrance Antiphon. There are a lot of little gems there, Scriptural gems that all go to make up the whole picture of Lent and the whole message of Lent.</p>

<p>We are called to be witnesses of mercy, “called to gaze…more attentively on this virtue so that we ourselves might become a more effective sign of God’s action in our lives” (<em>cf</em>. Pope Francis, <em>Misericordiae vultus</em>, Point 3).</p>

<p>People might see that mercy in us, in the things we do, the things we say, the words, the actions, that somehow, maybe, change an environment or change a conversation, help people to be that little bit more loving. It’s something we have to grow in throughout our life.</p>

<p>Forgiveness is the loving refusal to demand compensation for past injuries or hurts, to wipe the slate clean. “You don’t owe me anything.”</p>

<p>Any little grudges or pains that may be there deep inside us—we place those before the tabernacle. We don’t keep a blacklist in some fold of our brain. Sometimes we can have an amazing memory, some little black dots.</p>

<p>We should try and remember that the people who may have hurt us in the course of our life don’t even know that they’ve hurt us. Maybe God has used them as an instrument to shape us in various ways.</p>

<p>Our Lord said to St. Paul, “Why do you persecute me?” (Acts 9:4). He identified Himself with all the Christians that Paul was persecuting.</p>

<p>When we criticize or judge or compare, we’re persecuting. And when we consider God’s mercy, it leads us to remember all the times when God has forgiven us our sins.</p>

<p>All the greatest crimes that other people may commit against us are nothing compared to what God has forgiven us. We are the beneficiaries of His mercy.</p>

<p>Our Lord has also told us the parable where the steward who owed so much to his master begged for mercy and received mercy. The master forgave him of his debt.</p>

<p>But then he was owed something by somebody else and he went out and throttled that other person. He did not show any mercy to the other person, when he had been shown mercy. He’s worthy of condemnation (Matt. 18:23-33).</p>

<p>Hurts, abuses, injustices can burrow actively into our memory. But poking at sores only prevents healing. You have to hand life’s hurts over to the Holy Spirit. Let Him take care of those things.</p>

<p>The <em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em> says, “The heart that offers itself to the Holy Spirit turns injury into compassion and purifies the memory in transforming the hurt into intercession” (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 2843).</p>

<p>That hurt can become a prayer. It can be a way of being sure, “Lord, I really want this favor that I’m asking for, or this grace for myself or for others.”</p>

<p>We learn to excuse rather than to accuse.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to be a more forgiving person, to learn the art of forgiving.</p>

<p>“It’s a journey. The deeper the wound, the longer the journey. It’s only when we forgive that we’re ready to be healed. Forgiving is the only way to be fair to ourselves” (Lewis Smedes, <em>Forgiveness: Healing the Hurt We Don’t Deserve</em>).</p>

<p>There’s no limitation to forgiveness. There’s no injury so gross that cannot be forgiven.</p>

<p>Something that somebody said or did to us—if we ever say, ‘I could never forgive that person, I’ll always remember that thing or some little sentiment that may be there’—God invites us to leave all these things at His feet.</p>

<p>The sea absorbs impurities, remaining undefiled. Something similar has to happen in our life. We absorb all the little negligences of others, perhaps misdemeanors that they don’t realize they’re committing. Absorb them and let them pass, and carry on.</p>

<p>Love keeps no record of wrongs, because “God is love” (1 John 4:8,16). Love is in the will, “like” is in the emotions or in the senses.</p>

<p>“Without memory there is no healing. Without forgiveness, there is no future” (Desmond Tutu, <em>No Future Without Forgiveness</em>).</p>

<p>Love doesn’t let the wrongs of others pollute its flow of positive energy.</p>

<p>We look at the mercy of God and we see that God is full of breathtaking mercy. A beautiful adjective.</p>

<p>It shows us that understanding and forgiving are the most radical manifestations of love. We have to try and understand those who don’t understand us, even those who don’t want to understand.</p>

<p>“Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing” (Luke 23:34). They don’t realize this terrible crime.</p>

<p>We try to understand, but with no duplicate in the files. If we’re to practice this type of forgiving, we need a certain amount of mortification to be understanding, to be willing at times to give in, because in practice, nothing really matters in this world.</p>

<p>Blame hurts, forgiveness cures. Our first reaction in different situations could be an emotional one. But we need to be careful with those first reactions.</p>

<p>Our Lord reminds us that we have to try and “forgive seventy times seven times” (Matt. 18:21). That means to have a forgiving approach to life, without limit. Unlimited pardon, always.</p>

<p>The various things that may give rise to little frictions—arguments, or trifling matters, or sharp replies, or disconcerting gestures—often may be the fruit of nothing else but just tiredness. This person is tired, or this person is this way or that way.</p>

<p>The least sign of friction—our charity can’t begin to grow cold. We can’t distance ourselves from others. This is where we invoke that virtue of mercy.</p>

<p>Following Our Lord means finding even in areas of tiny contradictions the pathway to holiness.</p>

<p>There’s a reminder of all of this, the pathway to the Cross, which is the greatest manifestation of love.</p>

<p>“Mercy…has the interior form of love. … It’s able to reach down to every prodigal child, to every human misery, every form of moral misery. … When that happens, the person doesn’t feel humiliated, but feels found again, ‘restored to value’” (John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 6).</p>

<p>The Church talks a lot about the spiritual and corporal works of mercy (<em>Catechism</em>, Point 2447). We’re invited to give high profile to these things, to foster them in society, to practice them ourselves, to reach out to other people in all sorts of ways, so that they may see this quality of God’s love manifested in each one of us.</p>

<p>Mercy leads to service. The first thing that Our Lady did after the Annunciation: she went to the hill country (Luke 1:39), got over the problems, left Joseph behind, immediately thought of her cousin.</p>

<p>St. John Chrysostom says, “He who assists the needy makes God his debtor” (St. John Chrysostom, <em>Homily 15 on Matthew</em>). Mercy is that other word for love.</p>

<p>“How very insistent,” said St. Josemaría in <em>The Forge</em>, “the apostle St. John was in preaching the <em>mandatum novum</em>, the new commandment that we should love one another! —I would fall on my knees, without putting on any act—but this is what my heart dictates—and ask you, for the love of God, to love one another, to help one another, to lend one another a hand, to know how to forgive one another. —And so, reject all pride, be compassionate, show charity; help each other with prayer and sincere friendship” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 454).</p>

<p>We can always grow in this virtue, going deeper.</p>

<p>He says in <em>The Way</em>, “Charity does not consist so much in ‘giving’ as in ‘understanding.’ Therefore, seek an excuse for your neighbor—there is always one to be found—if it is your duty to judge” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 463).</p>

<p>“Practice a cheerful charity,” he says in <em>The Forge</em>, “which is at once kindly and firm, human and at the same time supernatural. It should be an affectionate charity, knowing how to welcome everyone with a sincere and habitual smile, and how to understand the ideas and feelings of others. —In this way, with gentleness and strength, and without concessions in matters of personal morals or in doctrine, the charity of Christ—when it is being well lived—will give you a spirit of conquest. Each day you will have a greater desire to work for souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 282).</p>

<p>As we move through Lent, we could ask Our Lady, the Mother of Mercy, to help us to grow in this particular virtue, to contemplate a bit more the mercy of Christ on the Cross. Very frequently we say, “Hail, Holy Queen, Mother of Mercy, hail, our life, our sweetness, and our hope.”</p>

<p>Mary has the deepest knowledge of the mystery of God’s mercy. “No one…penetrated the profound mystery of the Incarnation like Our Lady” (Pope Francis, <em>Misericordiae vultus</em>, Point 24).</p>

<p>She merits that mercy in her own life. “He has looked upon the lowliness of his handmaid. … His mercy is from generation to generation” (Luke 1:48,50).</p>

<p>Through her sacrifice, she shares in the revelation of God’s mercy. “The motherhood of Mary in the order of grace lasts from the Annunciation until the end of time” (<em>cf</em>. Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 62, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>John Paul says, “No one has received into his heart, as much as Mary did, that mystery, that truly divine dimension of the redemption effected on Calvary by means of the death of her Son, together with the sacrifice of her maternal heart, together with her definitive <em>fiat</em>.</p>

<p>“Mary, then, is the one who has the deepest knowledge of the mystery of God’s mercy. She knows its price, she knows how great it is.</p>

<p>“In this sense, we call her the Mother of Mercy, Our Lady of Mercy, or Mother of Divine Mercy; in each one of these titles there is a deep theological meaning, for they express the special preparation of her soul, of her whole personality, so that she was able to perceive, through the complex events, first of Israel, then of every individual and of the whole of humanity, that mercy of which ‘from generation-to-generation’ (Luke 1:50) people become sharers according to the eternal design of the Most Holy Trinity” (John Paul II, <em>Dives in misericordia</em>, Point 9).</p>

<p>“Mary experiences…the universality of God’s love, which opens her heart and enables her to embrace the entire human race. So, Mary becomes the Mother of each and every one of us…, the radiant sign and inviting model of the moral life” (John Paul II, <em>Veritatis Splendor</em>, Point 120).</p>

<p>Mother of Mercy, may you help us to contemplate during these days and hours a little more of that radiance of God’s mercy that comes to us through you, so that we may grow in this great divine attribute.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All the Glory to God</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All the Glory to God" /><published>2026-02-24T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-24T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/all-the-glory-to-god/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>In the Gospel of St. Matthew, we’re told, “Be careful not to parade your uprightness in public to attract attention; otherwise you will lose all reward from your Father in heaven. So when you give alms, do not have it trumpeted before you; this is what the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets to win admiration. In truth I tell you, they have had their reward.</p>

<p>“But when you give alms, your left hand must not know what your right hand is doing; your almsgiving must be in secret, and your Father who sees all that is done in secret will reward you” (Matt. 6:1-4).</p>

<p>In this passage of the Gospel, Our Lord talks to us about the supernatural goal of everything we do, seeing that that supernatural intention is the only really worthwhile intention to have.</p>

<p>We have to try and declare war on our love of self, when perhaps the desire to be well-regarded comes into play. We have to remember that phrase, <em>Deo omnis gloria</em>, all the glory to God.</p>

<p>“The weather pays no attention to criticism.” Meaning will never be found in the praise and adulation of others.</p>

<p>Malcolm Muggeridge liked to say that it often happens that the real reason for doing something only emerges after it has been done (Malcolm Muggeridge, <em>The Third Testament</em>). Altruism can hide a lot of pride. Conscience and conscious intent can be but the tip of the iceberg of unconscious intent.</p>

<p>After we’ve done something which we think has been done for very altruistic reasons, when the truth has to be told, we may realize a few hours or days later that yes, it was done thinking of others, but perhaps only 30 percent thinking of others; 70 percent may have been because there was ‘something in it for me.’</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord for lights to see when we don’t have the supernatural goal as clearly as we might. Often, it’s in small, subtle things which are difficult to detect.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>The Forge</em>, “You are like the little pauper who suddenly finds out that you’re the child of the King. That is why now the only thing that concerns you on this earth is the glory of your Father God, his glory in everything” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 334).</p>

<p>God’s love is manifested in the gifts that are given to us. St. Paul says, “I do not cease to give thanks for you…that the God of Our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give you the Spirit of wisdom and of revelation in the knowledge of him” (Eph. 1:16-17).</p>

<p>The intention with which we do things is one of the most important aspects of the moral act. We have to try and take care of that intention. It can affect very much the actions that we do.</p>

<p>Rational creatures give glory to God with reason and will. Irrational creatures, like a cow, a dog, a goat, give glory to God just by being. And when we practice virtues, that reflects an aspect of the divine glory, perfection.</p>

<p>[Our Lord] said, “Let your light shine before others, that they may see your good works and give glory to your Father in heaven” (Matt. 5:16).</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord that our deeds may shine, especially in charity. To want to do things well all the time can also be an expression of love of me. We have to try and get into the habit of giving the glory to God.</p>

<p>The radicality of the Christian life requires that we go beyond what is convenient or easy or comfortable. We have to try and be ready to go the extra mile.</p>

<p>And it’s good to ask ourselves occasionally: Is the glory of God the motive of all my actions? Do we repeat the <em>Morning Offering</em> frequently as we go through the day?</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to point out to people on the roof of the Cathedral of Burgos certain stone sculptures that were there on that roof, which the sculptors had made fully aware that they could not be seen from below. They were done for the glory of God (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 65).</p>

<p>He liked to talk about a chalice he once found where there was a gem hidden up underneath the base of the chalice—there for God to see, not for human eyes.</p>

<p>With the wounds of original sin, that has made it difficult to give God all the glory, because we can get distracted. The devil can keep our vision on other things. We can have a tendency to turn our work, our family life, our material things that we use, into instruments of our own glory, to seek ourselves. We might find that we become disheartened at our own failure.</p>

<p>Thus, it’s very good that we examine our intentions. What happens when we’re asked to change our plans for the day or for the week? Or when we experience something like Our Lady and St. Joseph did on their journey to Bethlehem, and then to Egypt, and then back to Nazareth?</p>

<p>We have to put this right intention into practice when we don’t look for recognition or gratitude, and be careful that our vanity doesn’t take over. We’ve got to try and work intensely even when no one may see the results, when those results may remain hidden or pass unnoticed. Maybe they will be discovered or seen or appreciated by future generations. St. Josemaría liked to say we have to plant trees in whose shade others will bask.</p>

<p>One clear manifestation of the fact that we are trying to give glory to God in all that we do is to struggle to get the norms of our <em>plan of life</em> fulfilled every day, even when it’s difficult, when there are deadlines, when there are exams, when there’s pressure.</p>

<p>Try and give priority to the things of God.</p>

<p>Or when we have to put in the extra effort to get our work done on time, or the effort to be punctual for family gatherings. When we’re giving glory to God all throughout our day, we give off the good odor of Christ.</p>

<p>I was giving a class once in another country and I happened to quote in the class a phrase from St. Paul, who says, “In all that you’re doing, in eating and in drinking, give glory to God” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>There was a lady who had been a convert to Catholicism in the class, and suddenly she was struck very much by the Holy Spirit with this phrase. She said she got a lot out of it. For her, it seemed to sum up the whole spirit of Opus Dei.</p>

<p>She told me that after the class, she went out to her car and there was a bit of a mess on the front seat, on the floor of the car, and she tidied that up a little bit because she realized she had to try and give glory to God in everything.</p>

<p>She was a lawyer, and sometimes lawyers’ offices have a lot of files all over the place. When she got to her office, she put the files back in their place, and the secretary came into the office and wondered what earthquake in reverse had hit this place. The lady said, “I’m trying to give glory to God in everything that I do.”</p>

<p>She told me that every evening she would watch the news with her husband, and halfway through the news he would ask her for a cup of tea, and she would go downstairs to get a cup of tea but sometimes, grinding her teeth. But this time she had the tea ready. He asked her, “What’s come over you?” She said, “I’m trying to give glory to God.”</p>

<p>We can find ways and means of giving glory to God in the ordinary little challenges of each day, putting virtues into practice, and having a loving service orientation with everything that we do. Not wanting to be anybody in life, in our family, in our profession; being willing to just be a nobody—because someday we will be a nobody.</p>

<p>One way of giving the glory to God as we go through the day is to repeat the <em>Morning Offering</em>: “I offer you all my thoughts, words, actions, sufferings, feelings of this day.”</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro del Portillo had a nice phrase where he used to say that with one act of love, we can make up for many lacks of love. That’s a rather encouraging thought through our day, that one act of Jesus in the Blessed Sacrament or of Our Lady can make up for all the other moments of negligence when we’ve been distracted or thinking about other things.</p>

<p>The interruptions of our day, the changes of plans, the pieces of not such good news—all these things are meant to sanctify us so that we live a certain peace in all these things.</p>

<p>Each time the phone rings or we get a WhatsApp message, it can be seen as a divine call to give glory to God in this particular moment.</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, we’re told, “You are ambitious: for knowledge, for leadership, for great ventures. Good, very good. But let it be for Christ, for love” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 24).</p>

<p>In one passage of the Gospel, we’re told, “They came to Capernaum, and when he was in the house he asked them, ‘What were you discussing on the way?’ But they were silent, because on the way they had [discussed] with one another about who was the greatest.</p>

<p>“Jesus sat down and called the Twelve. And he said to them, ‘If any one of you would be first, he must be last of all and the servant of all.’ And he took a child and put him in the midst of them, and taking him in his arms, he said to them, ‘Whoever receives one such child in my name receives me, and whoever receives me, receives not me but him who sent me’” (Mark 9:33-37).</p>

<p>The disciples must have been rather ashamed when Our Lord overheard them arguing about which one of them was the greatest. That appetite for glory and greatness can be inbred in us. We can cherish the ambition to be somebody whom others admire, rather than a nobody.</p>

<p>If it’s the will of God that we are that somebody, wonderful. Give glory to God in that situation. It’s a really good human ambition to have. But at the same time, to be ready someday to be that nobody.</p>

<p>And in the face of those dramatic gestures on the part of the apostles, Our Lord made another very dramatic gesture. He embraces a child to show His disciples who really is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>“What can a little child possibly teach us about greatness? Children in the ancient world had no rights, no position, no privileges of their own. Socially, they were at the bottom of the rung, at the service of their parents, much like the household staff or domestic servants” (Don Schwager<em>, The Gospel of Luke</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lord’s lesson that He’s teaching the apostles is a pretty strong lesson.</p>

<p>There can be no share in God’s glory without the cross. All the challenges that we can have in the 21st century, things that can happen to us that we never imagined might happen to us—unemployment, financial difficulties, health problems, weight of work on our shoulders, abandoned by loved ones—these all may be characteristics of the saints of the 21st century.</p>

<p>In all those difficult situations that Our Lord may permit in our life, He wants us to learn to give Him glory in those moments; to say, “Here I am, because you have called me” (1 Sam. 3:5).</p>

<p>“That gesture of Our Lord’s elevating a little child in the presence of His disciples is very significant. … The one who is humble and lowly of heart, who, instead of asserting their rights, willingly empty themselves of pride and self-seeking glory by taking the lowly position of a servant or of a child” (Schwager, <em>ibid</em>.)—that’s the person that Christ admires.</p>

<p>Jesus Himself is our model. “Though he was by nature God, he did not consider being equal to God a thing to be clung to, but emptied himself, taking the nature of a slave and being made like unto men and appearing in the form of man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient unto death, even unto death on the cross” (Phil. 2:6-8).</p>

<p>Our Lord emptied Himself in order to give God all the glory. Often, He passed unnoticed. He shunned praise, disappeared from the people who wanted to make Him King, lowered Himself to take on our lowly nature, that He might raise us up and clothe us with His divine nature. “God opposes the proud but gives his grace to the humble” (James 4:6).</p>

<p>“If we want to be filled with God’s life and power, we need to empty ourselves of everything that stands in the way, of pride, of self-seeking glory, of vanity” (<em>cf</em>. Schwager, <em>idem</em>.).</p>

<p>God wants empty vessels so that He can fill them with His own glory, with His power, and with His love (<em>cf</em>. 2 Cor. 4:7).</p>

<p>In <em>The Way</em>, St. Josemaría says, “<em>Deo omni gloria</em>. All the glory to God. It is an emphatic confession of our nothingness. He, Jesus, is everything. We, without him, are worth nothing: nothing. Our vainglory would be just that, vain glory; it would be a sacrilegious robbery. There should be no room for that ‘I’ anywhere” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Way</em>, Point 780).</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture that we “cannot serve two masters” (Matt. 6:24). We have to try to be giving glory to God in all that we do. Even in our prayer, we could be doing it for the wrong reasons, as we see in the parable of the Pharisee and the publican (Luke 18:9-14).</p>

<p>The Pharisee was giving glory to himself. We can be praying for the wrong reasons: to get it done, so that we can feel good, so that we can tell other people that we’ve done it. We can forget that God is waiting for us in each moment.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría had a short prayer that he used to use, which said, “Separate from me anything that separates me from you.”</p>

<p>In the living out of our Christian vocation, in our daily work, in our apostolate, in our family life, in the ordinary things of each day, we have to try and seek moments to give God all the glory, including when we might be annoyed about something, or we’re not feeling well, or we’re tired, or we made a mistake and we’re wrong, or we’ve been passed over, or not told, or not consulted, or not informed.</p>

<p>We have to try and do things for God’s glory, not just because this happens to be the most efficient way of doing things.</p>

<p>This can apply also to the small ordinary tasks in the house that need to be taken care of: making our bed, closing a door, opening a window. With St. Peter, we can try to say, “Lord, you know all things; you know that I love you” (John 21:17).</p>

<p>We give God glory when we make the effort to get the norms of our <em>plan of life</em> done. A lady stood up at a get-together with Blessed Álvaro in Dublin many years ago and she said that she had eight children, and she had to do the ironing and the washing and the marketing and the cleaning and everything in the family, a big, long list of things.</p>

<p>Then she asked, “How can I find time in my busy day to fulfill the norms of a <em>plan of life</em>?” And Blessed Álvaro said, “The litany of things that you have to do are very many. It’s true, you’re a very busy person. But,” he said, “you’ve left something out of your list. You’ve left God out of your list. If you put God into your list and you put Him first, you’ll find you’ll have time for all the other things.”</p>

<p>Giving God all the glory often means putting Him first; taking care of little things; offering our work before we do it, when we’ve finished it, in the meantime when we lift our eyes from what we’re doing, pause for a few moments, we offer it to Him again; when we make little acts of contrition during the day; when we have the joy of giving God the glory that perhaps we have denied Him in previous hours.</p>

<p>In that way, we realize that nothing gets lost. Everything works out for the good when we ask Our Lord that all our actions might be inspired by Him and might be truly brought to completion.</p>

<p>We can say: Lord, may everything I do be pleasing in your eyes. Help me to turn to you occasionally during the day, and, as it were, say a <em>Gloria</em>: “Glory to God in the highest” (Luke 2:14).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, St. Josemaría says, “Reject any ambition for honors. Think instead about your duties, how to do them well, and the instruments you need to accomplish them.</p>

<p>”—In this way, you will not hanker for position, and if one comes you will see it just as it is: a burden to bear in the service of souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 976).</p>

<p>We can try to also be attentive to what the Holy Father is saying, what are his intentions, so that we’re grazing where he is grazing, asking for what he’s asking.</p>

<p>That desire to give God all the glory, in the final analysis, is a fruit of charity. And charity does not seek its own interests.</p>

<p>A lack of giving God glory can decrease the effectiveness of our apostolate. Pride and vanity that may rear their ugly heads can make a mess of things.</p>

<p>We can ask the Holy Spirit for lights to see where I might not be giving God the glory that is His due.</p>

<p>We’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>, “The understanding that so many people demand of others is that everyone should join their party” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 576).</p>

<p>In another point in <em>The Way</em>, it says, “It only takes a second. Before setting about anything, ask yourself: What does God want of me in this? Then with divine grace, do it!” (<em>ibid</em>., <em>The Way</em>, Point 778).</p>

<p>And in <em>The Forge</em>, “‘I can do all things in him who strengthens me’ (Phil. 4:13). With him, there is no possibility of failure, and this conviction gives rise to the holy ‘superiority complex’ whereby we take on things with the spirit of victory, because God grants us his strength” (<em>ibid</em>., <em>The Forge</em>, Point 337).</p>

<p>Our determination to live as children of God should be realized in ordinary life: at work, in the home, among our friends. At every hour of the day we should be striving to be men and women of faith, full-time Christians.</p>

<p>We can’t confine our relationship with God to those few moments we spend inside a church. We have to live out our friendship with God in the middle of the world, in our workplace, in our recreation, in social gatherings.</p>

<p>We should reflect Christ’s love in everything we do. St. Paul said to the Corinthians, “So, whether you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do it all to the glory of God” (1 Cor. 10:31).</p>

<p>St. Basil, commenting on that passage, said, “When you sit down at table, pray. When you eat your bread, give thanks to God who is so generous. If you have some wine, remember that he has created it to bring us merriment and comfort in affliction. When you are getting dressed, give thanks to the one who gave you those clothes. When you look up at the firmament and behold the beauty of the stars above, fall down at the feet of God and adore his infinite Wisdom that is manifest in all Creation. Do the same at sunrise and sunset when you’re asleep and when you are awake. Give thanks to God who created all this wonder for your benefit so that you might know, love, and praise his name” (Basil of Caesarea, <em>Homily on the Martyr Julitta</em>).</p>

<p>All noble realities should serve to bring us to God, to give Him glory. When someone is in love, they think of their beloved twenty-four hours a day. That’s the sort of love we should have for Jesus Christ.</p>

<p>It should constitute the essence of our being, the driving force of all our actions. He is Our One and Only Lord. He is the one we want to glorify through our work well done.</p>

<p>Jesus is our inspiration when we try to practice the social doctrine of the Church, when we strive to protect the environment.</p>

<p>This all-embracing outlook leads a Christian to make an effort to be cordial and optimistic, to be punctual at work, to make good use of time, to overcome temptations to laziness.</p>

<p>If our love of God is authentic, it will shine out from and be appreciable in every aspect of our existence. “In all that you do,” said St. Paul, “give him glory” (<em>cf</em>. Col. 3:23).</p>

<p>A wrong intention destroys the best of actions. The deed can be well done, it can even be beneficial, but if it’s corrupted at source, it loses all its value in the eyes of God. Vanity or self-seeking can destroy what could have been a deed meriting holiness. Without a right intention, we go astray.</p>

<p>Many times, during the day, we need to remind ourselves that I am here to give God glory. On some occasions, receiving some praise is a sign of friendship and can help us along the path of goodness. But we should direct that praise towards God in all simplicity.</p>

<p>It’s one thing to receive a word of praise, a sign of being well received; it’s another thing altogether to look for praise. We must always be careful and attentive when we are praised or commended, since, as St. Gregory the Great said, “…many times our poor soul goes off the right path, as soon as it is applauded…thus it finds its delight more in being called happy than in actually being so. And that thing which should have been a reason for praising God becomes instead a cause of our separation from him” (Gregory the Great, <em>Moralia in Job).</em></p>

<p>In the Gospel, Our Lord points out the result of good deeds done without a right intention: “They have received their reward” (Matt. 6:2,5,16), He says, referring to the Pharisees, who wanted to be praised and well thought of.</p>

<p>They got what they wanted: a glance of approval, a gesture of admiration, some words of praise. Shortly, there would be nothing left but dust, and nothing at all for eternal life. A terrible failure to lose so much for so little.</p>

<p>God accepts our actions, even very small ones, if we offer them to Him with that pure intention of giving Him glory. The two small coins that the poor widow threw into the offering box of the Temple became a great treasure in heaven (Mark 12:42).</p>

<p>Our Lord contemplates our lives and has His hand outstretched each day for what we can offer Him. He accepts whatever we really do for Him. We get our own sad recompense for the rest here below.</p>

<p>“The suggestions of vanity and pride and the impulses of the flesh are not difficult to recognize,” St. Josemaría says in <em>The Way</em> (Point 788), “…and you fight and, with grace, you conquer. But the motives that inspire you, even in the holiest actions, do not seem clear; and deep down inside you hear a voice which makes you see human reasons in such a subtle way that your soul is invaded by the disturbing thought that you don’t act as you should—for pure Love, solely and exclusively to give God all his glory. React at once each time and say, ‘Lord, for myself I want nothing. All for your glory and for Love.’”</p>

<p>This was the attitude of Our Lady when she learned the plans that God had for her. “Behold, the handmaid of the Lord…”—I’m just here to serve, to do whatever it is that you want. —“Be it done unto me according to your word” (Luke 1:38).</p>

<p>The life of Our Lady was a life of continual praise and glory to God. Mary, may you help us to live in that same way.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patience in Adversity</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patience in Adversity" /><published>2026-02-23T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-23T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/patience-in-adversity/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“But before all this happens, you will be seized and persecuted; you will be handed over to the synagogues and to imprisonment, and brought before kings and governors for the sake of my name. That will be your opportunity to bear witness.</p>

<p>“Make up your minds not to prepare your defense, because I myself shall give you an eloquence and a wisdom that none of your opponents will be able to resist or contradict.</p>

<p>“You will be betrayed even by parents and brothers, relations, and friends, and some of you will be put to death. You will be hated universally on account of my name, but not a hair of your head will be lost. By your patience, you will win your souls” (Luke 21:12-19).</p>

<p>When Our Lord talks about the end times, He talks to us about patience.</p>

<p>He predicts the destruction of Jerusalem, which is going to come to pass some forty years later. His Second Coming will be in power and great glory.</p>

<p>In this particular passage, Our Lord warns His disciples of impending persecution. He exhorts His followers to persevere with patience, no matter what should happen: “By your endurance you will gain your lives and your souls” (Luke 21:19).</p>

<p>In the years that followed, the apostles meditated on Our Lord's warning. He told them: “A servant is not greater than his master. If they persecuted me, they will persecute you” (John 15:20).</p>

<p>Even the worst tribulation has a role to play in God's Providence. God permits contradictions because they can be the cause of greater goods. The early Roman persecutions strengthened the primitive Church and deepened her supernatural spirit.</p>

<p>All this was to fulfill what Our Lord predicted. He said, “In the world you will have tribulation; but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world” (John 16:33).</p>

<p>Life presents us with all manner of problems and trials. Some are great, but some are also of little consequence. With the help of God's grace the soul can be strengthened by every trial.</p>

<p>Certain contradictions can come from other people. There can be direct attacks, or veiled threats from people who don’t understand our calling, or there can be public opposition from a pagan culture, or from people who are declared enemies of the Church.</p>

<p>Other contradictions can have their origin in the limitations of our human nature. We might experience financial difficulties, or health problems, or grave family problems. At times we might become sick or exhausted or completely discouraged.</p>

<p>If we are to persevere in times of adversity, we need patience. We should be cheerful, no matter what happens, because we have our eyes fixed on Christ.</p>

<p>He has encouraged us to move forward, to live in His peace. Our confidence should be anchored in the fact that Christ has been triumphant.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says that patience “is the virtue that allows us to bear adversity with a serene spirit. … We should prize this serenity of soul, because it allows us to obtain greater goods” (Augustine, <em>On Patience, 2</em>).</p>

<p>The Christian should learn how to endure physical and moral hardship without complaining.</p>

<p>Usually, we are presented with many different opportunities to practice this virtue in the ordinary circumstances of everyday life.</p>

<p>There was a kid who was being driven home from school by his mother, a Standard Two or Grade Two child. There was a traffic jam and the mother was getting a bit exasperated.</p>

<p>The Standard Two child pipes up and says, ‘Today, Mommy, we got a talk about patience. The teacher told us that we're in Standard Two; we can't expect to be in Standard Eight. We have to take one day at a time and we have to accept the contradictions of everyday life.’</p>

<p>And this and that, and the child rambled on for quite a few minutes, giving his mother a talk about patience— about this virtue that he had learned in class today.</p>

<p>The mother listened patiently. When he finished, she said, ‘I felt like turning the car around and going back to the school and paying more fees.’</p>

<p>Patience is a powerful virtue. The struggle to live this virtue can relate to very mundane things: a character defect that keeps resurfacing in ourselves or in others, undertakings that don't go as we had planned, unexpected changes in schedule, bad manners of a colleague at work or on the road, people who mean well but don't understand, traffic jams, delays in public transportation, too many phone calls, forgetfulness, queues.</p>

<p>All of these are occasions for us to grow in humility and to become more refined in our charity.</p>

<p>This virtue should not be understood just to mean passivity in the face of suffering. It is a dynamic virtue. We're called to bear well the contradictions of ordinary life.</p>

<p>It is not a matter of stoically accepting the blows of outrageous fortune and accepting our fate. Patience belongs to the virtue of fortitude. It's a character strength. Fortitude is the virtue whereby we face difficulties, put up with problems.</p>

<p>When we practice patience, we strive to accept pain and trial as something coming from the hand of God. Therefore, it is good.</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas says, “We therefore seek to identify our will with the Will of God. The virtue of patience enables us to endure persecution of every kind. Patience should be the foundation of our hope and joy” (<em>cf</em>. St. Thomas, <em>Commentary on the Epistle to the Hebrews 10, 35</em>).</p>

<p>There are many ways in which a Christian can practice this virtue. The first battleground can be in the area of our own behavior. It is so easy to become disheartened by our defects.</p>

<p>Patience with ourselves. Good wine improves with time. Sometimes we have to give ourselves time to grow in this virtue or get better at something else.</p>

<p>We need to exercise patience in our interior struggle based on our unshakable confidence in the love that God has for us.</p>

<p>We know He is beside us in our ups and in our downs, in our failures and in our successes, like little children. If we are trying to overcome a character defect, it won't happen overnight.</p>

<p>Our victory will ultimately be won by the cultivation of humility, of a trusting confidence in God, of greater docility.</p>

<p>St. Francis de Sales liked to remind people that we need to have patience with everyone, but first and foremost with ourselves (<em>cf</em>. St. Francis de Sales, <em>Letters</em>).</p>

<p>Whenever we have contact with other people we will encounter opportunities to exercise this virtue. This is certainly the case when we try to help people to receive spiritual formation or when we look after people who are sick.</p>

<p>We also have to exercise patience with regard to unexpected events that can happen to us or interfere with our plans: sickness, poverty, extreme heat or cold, the minor misfortunes of everyday existence, crossed telephone lines, traffic jams, or having forgotten something and left it at home, an unexpected visitor. All these little contradictions can cause us to lose our peace.</p>

<p>Yet this is where Our Lord is waiting for us, right there in the ups and downs of ordinary life. This is the raw material of our sanctity. It is where we have to try and struggle to sanctify ourselves and to sanctify others.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us that “charity is patient” (1 Cor. 13:4). Our apostolate is a clear manifestation of charity.</p>

<p>We need to be patient with other souls—patience when we don’t see the fruits from the seeds that we may have sown in our children, in our friends, in our environment.</p>

<p>Fr. Joseph de Torre in the Philippines used to say that patience is a great social force. Often, we need to give the good seed time to grow. Sometimes that is a lot of time.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants us to sow His seed with a great peace of mind. We are sowing for the future, we are forming souls, we are building up great human beings.</p>

<p>We can remember that Our Lord has prepared the field beforehand. He has cultivated the earth. He has prepared the soil.</p>

<p>We can be mindful of the rhythm of the seasons. Sometimes, to plant a seed, we have got to wait for the right time and place, and that takes patience.</p>

<p>We should not give in to discouragement. Things do not change overnight. “Our hope should rest in the Lord” (Ps. 33:20). He is the one who gives the growth. He will make a tiny shoot grow into a fine ear of wheat.</p>

<p>Our Lord gives us many examples of how to practice this virtue. He was very well aware that the crowds did not grasp the full meaning of His teaching: “Seeing they do not see and hearing they do not hear, nor do they understand” (Matt. 13:13). “Too slow a wit, too dull of heart” (Luke 24:25).</p>

<p>But yet Our Lord manifests a tireless devotion to those same people. He travels the length and breadth of Palestine. He knows that someday, somehow, ‘all my words, all my efforts’ are going to yield abundant fruit.</p>

<p>This is a great example for every father and mother of a family who may think that all their effort and example is falling on deaf ears. The silent apostolate of good example in the home is never lost.</p>

<p>We see from the Gospel how the twelve apostles had their great limitations. Our Lord tells them on the eve of His Passion, “I have yet many things to say to you. But you cannot bear them now” (John 16:12).</p>

<p>Our Lord was very understanding towards His disciples. He makes allowances for their limitations. He goes the extra mile with them. He had patience with their defects and their less than perfect ways. He did not give up on them. In the years to come, those same men would be the pillars of the Church.</p>

<p>In our home, in our family, we are hopefully building pillars of the Church. Our home can be a seedbed of vocations, a domestic Church.</p>

<p>Patience and constancy are necessary for any work of spiritual formation, either aimed at ourselves or others. James Stenson, the educationalist in the States, says how parents have to repeat things 500 times for their children who only get the message on the 501st. That takes an awful lot of patience and constancy.</p>

<p>A patient person accepts the workings of God's providence and operates within that general framework. They see that maybe, this thing was not meant to work out now; maybe, this was not the fruit that God was expecting.</p>

<p>One time in the early development of Opus Dei, St. Josemaría with two or three other people made a journey overnight to a Spanish city called Villadolid to get in contact with some young people there.</p>

<p>They made a lot of phone calls. They contacted a lot of people. But nobody came to the spiritual activity that they were trying to organize, after all their efforts.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría said, ‘Look, we used all the human means. We came here. We’ve prayed. We’ve sown the seed. We haven’t lost out.’</p>

<p>They went back to Madrid happy and peaceful in spite of the fact that there seemed to be no fruits. Today there is a bustling apostolic activity in that city. We are building for the future.</p>

<p>Patience is closely allied with the virtue of humility, to accept our own defects and also, the defects of others, which may be very glaring.</p>

<p>One writer says, “A Christian who practices the manly virtue of patience won’t become disconcerted by the fact that most people are indifferent to the things of God, and the fact that most people do not think about eternity. But the truth remains that there are many good people have deep longings to encounter God. Their inner desire could be compared to a wine cellar, in which locked away is a very good wine.” Many souls are like that.</p>

<p>“The farmer must accommodate himself to the seasons and the soil. Hasn’t the Master likened the Kingdom of God to a householder who went out to hire workers for his vineyard?’ (Matt. 20:1-7)” (Jose Luis R. Sánchez de Alva, <em>The Gospel of St. John</em>).</p>

<p>If truth were told, we would have to see that Our Lord has been incredibly patient with each one of us. We have to be sure to exercise that same virtue towards others in the apostolate.</p>

<p>St. Paul tells us, “Love bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things” (1 Cor. 13:7). If we live this virtue, we will be faithful. We will become holy and help others to be holy—all the people that may become entrusted to our care.</p>

<p>This virtue has a great power enclosed within it. If we are impatient with our own interior life, to return to Our Lord is often necessary.</p>

<p>“Be patient, therefore, brethren,” says St. James, “until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the farmer waits for the precious fruit of the earth, being patient over us until it receives the early and the late rain” (James 5:7).</p>

<p>It is necessary for one to know, to hope, and to struggle with persevering patience. realizing that this is what pleases God very much. He precisely places us in those sorts of situations so that we practice that virtue.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría in <em>Friends of God</em> says, “Make more acts of hope. Let me remind you that in your interior life, you will suffer defeats, and you will have ups and downs—may God make them imperceptible—because no one is free from these misfortunes. But our all-powerful and merciful Lord has granted us the precise means with which to conquer…all we have to do is to use them, resolving to begin again and again in every moment whenever necessary” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 219).</p>

<p>St. Thomas Aquinas says, “The heart of constancy lies in love: only with love can one be patient” (<em>cf</em>. St. Thomas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part II-II, Question 136).</p>

<p>“The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a king who decided to settle his accounts with his servants. When the reckoning came, they brought him a man who owed ten thousand talents. He had no means of paying, so his master gave orders that he should be sold, together with his wife and children and all his possessions, to meet the debt. At this, the servant threw himself at the master's feet with the words, ‘Be patient with me, and I will pay the whole sum’” (Matt. 18:23-26).</p>

<p>On our way towards Our Lord, many may be the defeats that we suffer; many of these will be of no consequence, but some will. But the atonement and contrition for those will bring us even closer to God.</p>

<p>The sorrow and reparation for our sins and shortcomings are not useless moods of gloom, because they are sorrow and tears born of love.</p>

<p>It is the heavy thought of not returning as much love as Our Lord merits; it is the sorrow of returning evil for good for one who loves us so much.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord for grace to see the opportunities that He gives us to be more patient, particularly in difficult moments.</p>

<p>None of our friends should ever be able to speak to Our Lord in the words of the paralytic. We’re told in the <em>Furrow:</em> “‘I do not have anyone to help me’ (John 5:7). This—unfortunately!—could be said by many who are spiritually sick and paralytic, who could be useful—and should be useful. Lord, may I never remain indifferent to souls” (J. Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 212).</p>

<p>Christ has converted everything that was previously death and turned shortcomings and errors into virtue. He is the fountain of those waters that give life to everything.</p>

<p>We can examine ourselves in our prayer and see if we're sufficiently concerned about those who accompany us on our journey through life; if we are concerned about their formation; or if, on the other hand, we have gotten used to their defects as something we've come to regard as incorrigible. Are we really patient towards them?</p>

<p>It can be good to recall that with mortification we can also atone for the sins of others, and merit for them the grace of faith, of conversion, and of a greater dedication to God.</p>

<p>In Christ lies the remedy for all the evils of which humanity complains. In the Book of Ezekiel, we are told: “This water flows east down to the Arabah and to the sea; and flowing into the sea, it makes its waters wholesome. Wherever the river flows, all living creatures teeming in it will live. Fish will be very plentiful. Wherever the water goes, it brings health, and life teems wherever the river flows” (Ezek. 47:8-9).</p>

<p>Christ converts everything into life. We can ask Our Lord for that grace to be patient in all the situations He places before us, patience with every aspect of our being.</p>

<p>“The Lord said to him, ‘Go your way, for this man is to me a vessel of election, to carry my name before the Gentiles, and kings, and the children of Israel, for I will show him how great things he must suffer for my name's sake’” (Acts 9:15-16).</p>

<p>Ananias, faced with Paul, had to be patient with the plans of God for how he was being used in a certain way.</p>

<p>This virtue is the virtue that helps us to accept, for love of God, generously and peacefully, everything that is displeasing to our nature, without allowing ourselves to be depressed by the sadness which easily comes over us when we meet with disagreeable things. We can be meeting with disagreeable things on a regular basis.</p>

<p>Our Lord was patient with the Pharisees. He was patient with the people of His village who did not recognize Him. He was patient with His accusers. He was patient with the man who slapped Him in the face.</p>

<p>We should never think that God's delays are God's denials. Sometimes He says “yes,” sometimes He says “no,” and sometimes He says, “wait.” Maybe He has a better solution, or He has greater things planned for us up the way.</p>

<p>We can be patient with close and distant relatives, with the idiosyncrasies of the people that we live with who have ailments and pains and physical suffering; being subject day after day to the same work: small fastidious things, struggling in the little points.</p>

<p>It is not that we should do nothing about them. But we should not be discouraged or upset by them. We see continual examples of this virtue given by Our Lord. Patience is a sign of faith and of hope.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady, who was so patient with the plans of God, patient with St. Joseph, with the Magi, with the angels, with the shepherds, as little by little, she came to know those plans. Patience in Bethlehem and patience in Egypt: “Remain there until I tell you” (Matt. 2:13).</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to learn how to practice this virtue in ever greater ways all the time.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>UI</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning to Ask</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning to Ask" /><published>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-21T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/learning-to-ask/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“He has filled the hungry with good things, and the rich he has sent away empty” (Luke 1:53).</p>

<p>We should pray frequently about our divine filiation.</p>

<p>Our Lord had the habit of praying early in the morning and in out-of-the-way places. We’re told in St. Matthew that after sending the crowds away, “He went up into the hills by himself to pray. When evening came, he was there alone” (Matt. 14:23).</p>

<p>And in St. Mark, we’re told, “In the morning, long before daybreak, he got up and left the house and went off to a lonely place, and there he prayed” (Mark 1:35).</p>

<p>Likewise in St. Luke: “He would go off to some deserted place and pray” (Luke 5:16).</p>

<p>“Now it happened that he was praying alone and his disciples came to him. And he put the question to them: ‘Who do the crowds say that I am?’” (Luke 9:18).</p>

<p>The disciples often found Our Lord thoroughly absorbed in conversation with His Heavenly Father. We’re told also in St. Luke, “He was praying in a certain place, and when he ceased, one of his disciples said to him, ‘Lord, teach us to pray’” (Luke 11:1).</p>

<p>We are very much in need of making the same request to Our Lord: Jesus, teach me how to deal with you. Tell me what I should ask you for.</p>

<p>We should do this because we can often find ourselves in front of God without knowing what to say to Him or how we should speak to Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord answered His disciple’s request with the perfect prayer, the <em>Our Father</em>. He must have pronounced every word with care. He taught them how to put all their trust in prayer to their Father God.</p>

<p>He said, “Which of you has a friend who will go to him at midnight and say to him, ‘Friend, lend me three loaves, for a friend of mine has arrived on a journey and I have nothing to set before him.’ … I tell you, though he will not get up and give him anything because he is his friend, yet because of his insisting, he will rise and give him whatever he needs” (Luke 11:5-6,8).</p>

<p>Whenever we’re talking to God, most probably we’re asking Him for something. That’s because we’re children of God, children in need. For His part, God only wants to spend Himself on us.</p>

<p>When my mother heard us saying, “I want this, I want that,” she had a frequent phrase which she would say: “Well, you never stop wanting.” Children are like that. We never stop wanting. Our Father God knows it.</p>

<p>He says, “What father among you, if his son asks for a fish, would instead of a fish give him a serpent? Or if he asks for an egg, will give him a scorpion?” (Luke 11:11-12).</p>

<p>We should go to the tabernacle, exactly as the sick and suffering used to go to Jesus.</p>

<p>John Paul, in explaining prayer, said, “Prayer means feeling one’s own insufficiency through the various necessities which man has to face, necessities that are part of his life. Such as, for example, the need for bread to which Christ refers in the example of that man who wakes up his friend at midnight to ask him for bread. Similar necessities are numerous.</p>

<p>“The need for bread is, in a way, a symbol of all the material necessities, the necessities of the human body, the necessities of this existence which springs from the fact that man has a body. But the range of these necessities is wider” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>Humility is a prerequisite [to] confident conversation with God. We need to realize who He is and who we are. We need to realize our limitations before we can appreciate how much we depend on Our Father God.</p>

<p>John Paul says, “To learn to pray means ‘to learn the Father.’ If we learn the ‘Father’ reality in the full sense of the word, in its full dimension, we have learned everything. … To learn who the Father is means learning what absolute trust is. To learn the Father means acquiring the certainty that he absolutely cannot refuse anything.</p>

<p>“This is all said in the Gospel (Luke 11:1-13). He does not refuse you even when everything, materially and psychologically, seems to indicate refusal. He never refuses you” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>A little girl once asked Santa Claus, Father Christmas, for a thousand dolls for Christmas. Her father was an atheist. She got one doll.</p>

<p>He said to her, “Well, your God didn’t listen to your prayer, did he?” The little girl said, “Yes, he did. He said ‘No.’”</p>

<p>It was as though she was saying to her father, “God is my Father, you’re also my father. Sometimes you say ‘No.’ You don’t always say ‘Yes.’ But I know that even if He says ‘No,’ He always listens.”</p>

<p>He will never abandon us. In our conversation with God, we have to keep in mind our divine filiation and our human limitations.</p>

<p>We should ask God for spiritual and material goods insofar as they will bring us closer to Him. “For everyone who asks receives, and he who seeks finds, and to him who knocks it shall be opened” (Matt. 7:8).</p>

<p>In our prayer to God, the first things we should seek from Him are spiritual goods—the grace to love Him more each day, the grace to have an authentic desire for sanctity, the goal of our Christian vocation, the grace to do a more fruitful apostolate.</p>

<p>We should also ask God for material goods insofar as they serve to bring us closer to Him. These goods can also include good health, economic well-being, getting a job.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Pray for temporal goods in private, and rest in the knowledge that they come to us from him who knows what is best for us. Did you ask and not get what you wanted? Trust in your Father. If it would have been good for you, you would have received it.</p>

<p>“Before God, you are much as a little child is before you. All day long, the child cries his eyes out so that you will give him a knife to play with. You wisely refuse his plea and pay no attention to his wailing.</p>

<p>“When the child demands to ride your horse, you won’t let him. The child doesn’t know how to ride, and may get injured or even killed as a result.</p>

<p>“You deny him in little things, so as to preserve more important things. You want the child to grow up safely and possess all his own goods without danger” (Augustine, <em>Sermon 80</em>).</p>

<p>And so, that little girl who didn’t get a thousand dolls for Christmas—she knew that her Father God was listening. In only getting one doll, He gave her what she needed or what was important. She can be at peace, trusting her Father God.</p>

<p>And that’s how Our Lord is with us. Many times we’re like the child who doesn’t realize what he’s asking for.</p>

<p>I had a niece many years ago, and a big tree fell down close to their garden. It was all fallen down and the tree had been put in half.</p>

<p>She brought me out to the garden and pointed to the tree and said, “Can you fix that?” Little children don’t know what they’re asking for at times.</p>

<p>Our Father God always wants what’s best for us. Our happiness will always be found in our full identification with the Divine Will. ‘Lord, if you don’t want to give me this thing, then it’s okay. I realize this isn’t the time, it’s not the moment. It’s not the right thing for me.’</p>

<p>Even though what God wills may sometimes not seem so appealing from a human point of view, it necessarily leads to what is in our best interests.</p>

<p>John Paul II once recalled how impressed he was by the cheerfulness of a man he met in a hospital during the Warsaw Uprising in the Second World War.</p>

<p>He said, “This man achieved happiness by some other way because visibly, judging by his physical state from the medical point of view, there was no reason for him to be so happy, to feel so well, and to consider himself heard by God. Yet he was heard in another aspect of his humanity” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>This aspect was the identification of His human will with the Divine Will. We have to want the will of God: “Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven” (Matt. 6:10; the prayer, <em>Our Father</em>). This is the best path to follow. It’s the one prepared for us by Our Lord.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “Tell him: Lord, I want nothing other than what you want. Even those things I am asking you for at present, if they take me an inch away from your Will, don’t give them to me” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 512).</p>

<p>‘If you don’t want these things, why should I? You know best. Your Will be done.’</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture about the prayer of Abraham, his prayer for those cities who had offended God. He asked, “Will you indeed destroy the righteous with the wicked? Suppose there are fifty righteous within the city, will you then destroy the place and not spare it for the fifty righteous who are in it?” (Gen. 18:23-24).</p>

<p>Abraham tries to save the cities from destruction by giving his beloved God a hard time. He makes his case to God that even a small number of holy people are an immense treasure.</p>

<p>Our Lord takes such great pleasure in those who love Him that He is ready to forgive thousands of sinners for the sake of a handful of just people. God is willing to forget the sins and iniquities of entire cities for the sake of the love and the adoration of ten people (Gen. 18:32).</p>

<p>This is an unmistakable teaching for all of us who seek to follow Our Lord closely. We may at times be tempted to question the merit of our struggle when there are so many people around us who live without a care for God and His rights.</p>

<p>One day, Our Lord will show us the enormous effectiveness of our humble prayers, of the sacrifices made by a mother for her family’s welfare, of the sufferings offered up by a sick person for the Church, of the merit of an hour of study or work converted into prayer.</p>

<p>Yahweh was willing to save Sodom and Gomorrah for the sake of only ten just men. According to divine logic, the good works of a few people can outweigh in value the sins of thousands.</p>

<p>When we struggle to be faithful to Our Lord, we are bound to experience the joy of knowing that we are pleasing Him, for God listens attentively to our prayer.</p>

<p>We ought to pray every day for our society, a society which seems to be moving farther and farther away from its Creator. John Paul II pointed out in this regard, “I think that Abraham’s prayer and its content is very relevant for the times in which we live. Such a prayer is so necessary, to negotiate with God for every just man, to redeem the world from injustice” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, July 27, 1980).</p>

<p>“See what love the Father has given us,” we’re told in St. John, “that we should be called children of God, and such we are” (1 John 3:1).</p>

<p>Awareness of our divine filiation gives meaning to our day. We’re told in the Psalms, “I have been set by him as a king on Zion, his holy mountain, to tell of his decrees. The Lord said to me: ‘You are my son, today I have begotten you’” (Ps. 2:6-7).</p>

<p>In <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, St. Josemaría says, “The kindness of God Our Father has given us his Son to be our king. ‘You are my son.’ The words are addressed to Christ—and to you and me if we decide to become other Christs” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 185).</p>

<p>That’s what our whole Christian life is all about: to imitate Christ, to identify ourselves with Him. We want to be good children of God in the midst of our work and our normal activities, in spite of our weaknesses.</p>

<p>Jesus came to John, just like one more person, to be baptized in the Jordan. The Holy Spirit descended upon Him, and the voice of the Father could be heard saying, “You are my beloved son” (Mark 1:9-11).</p>

<p>From all eternity, Jesus Christ is the only Son of God. “Eternally begotten of the Father…begotten, not made, of one being with the Father. Through him all things were made” (<em>Nicene Creed</em>). We say these words in the <em>Creed</em> during Mass.</p>

<p>In Him and through Him—true God and true Man—we have been made children of God and heirs to heaven.</p>

<p>Throughout the New Testament, divine filiation occupies a central position in the preaching of the Good News of Christianity. It’s presented as a reality that gives expression to God’s love for men.</p>

<p>“See what love the Father has given us,” says St. John, “that we should be called children of God; and so we are” (1 John 3:1).</p>

<p>Jesus Christ constantly revealed this truth to His disciples. He showed it to them in a direct way, by teaching them to talk to God as their Father (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 6:9).</p>

<p>“When you pray, say: ‘Father, hallowed be thy name…’” (Luke 11:2). He explains sanctity to them in terms of a son imitating his father. “Do not even the Gentiles do as much? You must therefore be perfect, just as your heavenly Father is perfect” (Matt. 5:47-48).</p>

<p>He also developed this truth of divine filiation for them through numerous parables in which God is represented as the father. One particularly moving picture is the picture of Our Father God in the parable of the prodigal son (Luke 15:11-32).</p>

<p>The Prelate of Opus Dei says, “In his infinite goodness, God created man and elevated him to the supernatural order. Through the gift of sanctifying grace, we could enter into the intimacy of the Blessed Trinity, without destroying or distorting that nature proper to us as creatures. He did this through the ineffable gift of divine filiation” (<em>cf</em>. Fernando Ocáriz, <em>God as Father</em>).</p>

<p>He makes us His children. Our divine filiation is not merely a title; it is a real elevation, an effective transformation of our inmost being. That is why “God sent his Son, born of woman…so that we might receive adoption as children. And because you are sons, God has sent the spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying ‘Abba! Father!’ So through God you are no longer a slave but a son, and if a son, then an heir” (Gal. 4:6-7).</p>

<p>Our Lord gained for us the most precious Gift, the Holy Spirit, who makes us cry out, ‘Abba! Father!’, who identifies us with Christ and makes us children of God.</p>

<p>“‘You are my Son’ (Ps. 2:7). Not a stranger,” says St. Josemaría, “not a well-treated servant, not a friend—that would be a lot already. A son!</p>

<p>“He gives us free access to treat him as sons do, with a son’s piety—and I would even say with the boldness and daring of a son whose Father cannot deny him anything” (J. Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 185).</p>

<p>“The Lord said to me, ‘You are my son, today I have begotten you’” (Ps. 2:7). These words of the Psalm 2, which refer principally to Christ, are spoken also to each one of us. They can truly make our day and give meaning to our whole life, if we once resolve—in spite of our weakness and frailty—to follow Jesus, to try to imitate Him, to identify ourselves with Him in our own particular circumstances.</p>

<p>In our ascetical struggle we will at times have to consider more deeply the consequences of our divine filiation. At times, this can become the object of our <em>particular struggle</em>.</p>

<p>One writer says, “When we are living as good children of God, we see everything that happens, including the minor occurrences of any ordinary day, in the light of faith, and we become accustomed to thinking and acting constantly in accordance with Christ’s will” (<em>cf .</em> M. Equibar, <em>Why Do the Gentiles Rage</em>?).</p>

<p>In the first place, we try to see ourselves as brothers or sisters of all the people we meet, because we are all children of the same Father. Our appreciation and respect for others will generate within us the same desire that resides in the heart of Christ—the desire for their sanctification.</p>

<p>Another writer says, “Above all, fraternal love will move us to wish that those people should come ever closer to Christ and should be more fully children of Our Father God. We will make our own the concern of Christ for the apostolate, his zeal for the Father’s glory, and the salvation of all mankind” (Bonaventure Perquin, <em>Abba Father</em>).</p>

<p>The manifestations of fraternity, rooted in spiritual childhood, will be countless throughout any one of our days. Prayers for others will remind us. Little opportunities of helping in material things will have their obvious motivation. And understanding for the defects of others will be more readily achieved if we see in them the faults of our brothers and sisters.</p>

<p>Spiritual childhood is just one more aspect of our lives. [Fr. Ocáriz] says it determines our whole supernatural character and shows us how to deal with every situation. “It is not a particular virtue that has its own acts, but the permanent condition of our being, suffusing and permeating all the other virtues” (Fernando Ocáriz, <em>op</em>. <em>cit</em>.).</p>

<p>Whatever the circumstances or the situations that affect us, we are children of God, and this firm conviction fills the whole of our life and our entire way of behaving.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says, “We are children of God all day long, even though we set aside special moments for considering it, so that we can fill ourselves with awareness of our divine filiation, which is the essence of true piety” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 102).</p>

<p>If we frequently consider this truth—I am a child of God—if we go deeper into its meaning, our day will be filled with peace, serenity, joy.</p>

<p>We will make a resolution to rely on God Our Father, on whom everything depends, especially when difficulties and disappointments arise, when sometimes we seem to be fighting an uphill battle (<em>cf</em>. J. Lucas, <em>We Are Children of God</em>).</p>

<p>It will be easier for us to return to Our Father’s house, like the prodigal son, if we should ever leave it through our faults and sins. We will not lose sight of this truth, that Our Father is waiting to embrace us and to give us back our dignity as His children, if ever we lose it.</p>

<p>He’s waiting to fill us with good things, with a splendid banquet, even though we may have behaved badly a thousand times and more.</p>

<p>Our prayer, just like these moments we are dedicating exclusively to God, will really be the conversation of a child with his father. The son knows that his father understands him, that he listens to him, that he gives him the whole of his attention in a way that nobody else has ever done.</p>

<p>It’s a conversation with God that’s full of trust. It moves us frequently to a prayer of petition because we’re small and needy children. It’s a conversation with God that has our life as its theme.</p>

<p>In <em>Friends of God</em> we’re told, “Everything that is on our mind and in our heart: our joys, sorrows, hopes, disappointments, successes, failures, even the most trivial happenings in our day. We will discover that Our Heavenly Father is interested in everything about us” (J. Escrivá, <em>Friends of God</em>, Point 245).</p>

<p>We can finish our prayer today with that resolution, that we must pray more as children of the Father. With the conviction that we have to turn to Our Lord frequently every day. Like those many sick people in the Gospels, we need to be brought to Jesus to be cured.</p>

<p>Our Lady will teach us how to have the daring of little children in our petitions. We ask her to help us to do an effective apostolate where we live and work.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JSD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>