<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-13T18:00:30+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fr. Conor Donnelly Meditations</title><subtitle>A collection of meditations by Fr. Conor Donnelly</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Corpus Christi (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/corpus-christi-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corpus Christi (2026)" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/corpus-christi-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/corpus-christi-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen. My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Today’s solemnity goes back to the 13th century. It was first established in the Diocese of Liège in Belgium by Pope Urban IV. He had been the bishop of that diocese, and a nun had received some communication from God that there should be a feast dedicated to the Blessed Sacrament. She talked to the local bishop about it, it happened there, and then that bishop was elected Pope, and he instituted it in 1264 for the whole church. The meaning of this feast is the consideration of and devotion to the real presence of Christ in the Eucharist.</p>

<p>The center of the feast was to be a solemn procession with the Blessed Sacrament, and popular devotion reflected in hymns and in joy. That same year, at the Pope’s request, St. Thomas Aquinas composed two offices for the day which have nourished the piety of many Christians throughout the centuries. In many different places, the procession with the monstrance through especially bedecked streets gives testimony of the Christian people’s faith and love for Christ who once passed through our cities and towns. The procession began in the same way as the feast itself. In places where the solemnity of the Most Holy Body and Blood is not observed as a holiday of obligation, it is kept on the Sunday after the Trinity Sunday as its proper day.</p>

<p>There is a sequence of this mass that say the praises of your Shepherd King in hymns and canticles divine. Sing forth, O Zion, sweetly sing. Today we celebrate this great solemnity in honor of the mystery of the Holy Eucharist. On this day the liturgy itself and popular piety, which have spared no efforts in their search for inventiveness and beauty, come together to sing to the love of loves. For this day, St. Thomas Aquinas composed those very beautiful texts of the mass and for the breviary. Today we must give thanks to God for having remained among us. We have to make atonement to him, and express to him our joy at having him so close to us.</p>

<p>The hymn which St. Thomas Aquinas composed can be a good prayer to pray today, <em>Adoro te devote, latens Deitas</em>. O Godhead hid, devoutly I adore you. We could repeat that phrase many times from the depths of our heart. When we visit the Blessed Sacrament, we’ll be able to say slowly to Our Lord with love, <em>Plagas, sicut Thomas, non intueor</em>. I do not see your wounds as Thomas saw them, but I confess that you are my God. Make me believe you ever more and more, in thee my hope, in thee my love to store.</p>

<p>It was faith in the real presence of Christ in the Holy Eucharist that led to devotion to Jesus in the Blessed Sacrament outside of mass as well. In the first centuries of the church, the sacred species were reserved so that communion could be taken to the sick and to those who were in prison awaiting martyrdom because they had confessed their faith. As time went by, the faith and love of the believers caused them to make both public and private devotion to the Holy Eucharist far richer. Their faith led them to treat the body of Christ with the greatest possible reverence, and this also led to greater public devotion. We can find many testimonies in those ancient documents of the church to the veneration by the early church which later was to make way for the feast that we celebrate today.</p>

<p>Our Lord and our God is in the tabernacle. Christ is in the tabernacle. It’s there that we must show him our adoration and our love. This veneration for Jesus in the Blessed Sacrament is expressed in many ways: Benediction of the Blessed Sacrament, processions, prayer before Jesus in the Blessed Sacrament, genuflections that are real acts of faith and of adoration. Amongst these devotions and various forms of worship, particularly worthy of mention is the solemnity of Corpus Christi as a public act by which the church seeks to pay homage to Christ present in the Eucharist.</p>

<p>John Paul II wrote, “The church and the world have great need of Eucharistic devotions. Jesus is waiting for us in the sacrament of love. Let us not be sparing in the time we spend going to meet him in adoration, in contemplation filled with faith, and let us be prepared to make reparation for the many grave faults and offenses committed against him in the world. May our adoration never cease.”</p>

<p>Today especially can be filled with acts of faith and love for that real presence of Our Lord in the Blessed Sacrament. If we take part in some procession accompanying Jesus, we will be like those simple people who joyfully followed the Master during the days of his life on earth, and who with great naturalness told him of all their needs and about the sufferings they endured. As Christ is passing by, St. Josemaría says, “We too will experience the happiness and the joy of being with him. If we see him pass through our streets exposed in the monstrance, we will tell him from the depths of our hearts how much he means to us.”</p>

<p>“Adore him reverently and devoutly. Renew in his presence the sincere offerings of your love. Don’t be afraid to tell him that you love him. Thank him for giving you this daily proof of his tender mercy, and encourage yourself to go to communion in a spirit of trust. I am awed by this mystery of love. Here is the Lord seeking to use my heart as a throne, committed never to leave me provided I don’t run away. Jesus is happier on this throne of my heart than in the most magnificent monstrance.”</p>

<p>The words of the entrance antiphon remind us that “He has fed them from the finest wheat and given them their fill of honey from the rock” (Ps. 81:16). For many years, God fed manna to the people of Israel as they wandered in the wilderness. This was an image and symbol of the pilgrim church, and of each individual who journeys towards his or her definitive homeland, heaven. That food given in the desert, said John Paul II, in the desert of Sinai is a figure of the true food, the Holy Eucharist. This is the sacrament of the human pilgrimage. Precisely because of this, the annual feast of the Eucharist that the church celebrates today contains within its liturgy so many references to the pilgrimage of the people of the covenant in their wanderings through the wilderness.</p>

<p>Moses often reminded the Israelites of this wonderful deed that God had performed for his people. In the first reading, we’re told, “Do not forget the Lord your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage” (Deut. 8:14). Today is a day of thanksgiving and of joy because God has wanted to remain with us in order to feed us and to strengthen us so that we may never feel alone. The Blessed Eucharist is our nourishment, the food for the long journey of our days on earth towards the goal of true life. Jesus accompanies us and strengthens us here in this world, for our life is like a shadow compared to the reality that awaits us.</p>

<p>Earthly food is a pale image of the food that we receive in Holy Communion. The Blessed Eucharist opens our hearts to a completely new reality. Although we celebrate this feast only once a year, the church really proclaims this most happy truth every day. Jesus gives us himself daily as our food, and he remains in our tabernacles to be for us the strength and the hope of a new life, a life without end and without limit. It is a mystery which is ever alive and ever new. Thank you, Lord, for remaining with us. What would have become of us without you? Where would we have gone to restore our strength and to ask for consolation? From the tabernacle you preside over the world, but especially over the life of men and women. From there, how easy you make the way for us.</p>

<p>One day as Jesus was leaving the city of Jericho to continue his journey towards Jerusalem, he passed by a blind man who was begging for alms at the side of the road. When he heard the sound of the little crowd that was following the Master, he asked what it meant. The people around him answered, “Jesus of Nazareth is passing by” (Luke 18:37). If today in the many cities and towns where this ancient custom of carrying the Blessed Sacrament in procession is still observed, someone was to ask when he hears the noise of the crowd, “What is it? What’s happening?” We could answer him with the same words with which they answered Bartimaeus: “Jesus of Nazareth is passing by.”</p>

<p>It is Christ himself who walks through our streets, receiving the homage of our faith and of our love. It is Christ himself. Like the heart of Bartimaeus, our hearts too should burst into shouts, “Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me” (Luke 18:38). Our Lord, who went about blessing and doing good as we’re told in the Acts of the Apostles (cf. Acts 10:38), will have compassion on our blindness and on all the ills that sometimes lie heavy on our soul.</p>

<p>St. Paul VI said the church, by means of the feast we are celebrating today with an exuberance of faith and love, desires only to dispel the mysterious silence that surrounds the Eucharist and to emit a triumphant cry that bursts out through the walls of sanctuaries and overwhelms the streets of cities so as to infuse the whole human community with joy at the presence of Christ, of him who is the silent and strong companion of pilgrim man along the paths of time and over the earth. This is what fills our hearts with joy.</p>

<p>It’s logical, particularly today, that the hymns that accompany the Blessed Sacrament should be hymns of adoration, of love, and of profound joy. One song says, “Let us sing the love of loves, let us sing to the Lord. Behold, our God is here. O come, let us adore Christ our Redeemer.” <em>Pange lingua gloriosi.</em> Sing, my tongue, the Savior’s glory, of his flesh the mystery sing.</p>

<p>One writer says the solemn procession that takes place in so many towns and cities of Christian tradition is of very ancient origin and is the expression with which Christian people give public testimony of their piety towards the Blessed Sacrament. On this day Our Lord takes possession of our streets and town squares. It is piety that leads the faithful to cover the streets with carpets of flowers and other ornaments. Magnificent monstrances have been designed for this feast. The closer their decorations are to the consecrated host, the richer and more intricate they are. Today many Christians will accompany Our Lord in procession as he comes to meet those who want to see him and to make himself available to those who are not looking for him. Once more he comes among his people.</p>

<p>How should we respond to this call of his? The Corpus Christi procession makes Christ present in towns and cities throughout the world, but his presence cannot be limited to only one day, like a sound you hear and then forget. It should remind us that we have to discover Our Lord in our ordinary everyday activities. Side by side with this solemn procession, there is the simple, silent procession of the ordinary life of each Christian. He is a man among men who by a great blessing has received the faith and the divine commission to act so that he renews the message of Our Lord on earth.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría says in <em>Christ is Passing By</em>, “Let us ask Our Lord then to make us souls devoted to the Blessed Eucharist, so that our relationship with him brings forth joy and serenity and a desire for justice. In this way, we will make it easier for others to recognize Christ. We will put Christ at the center of all human activities. And Jesus’ promise will be fulfilled: ‘I, when I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all men to myself’” (John 12:32).</p>

<p>“I have come to bring fire to the earth, and how I wish it were blazing already. I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am constrained until it is accomplished” (Luke 12:49–50). There is a divine zeal in Christ for all souls. Just like any true friend, Our Lord reveals to his disciples his inmost thoughts. He tells them of his zeal for the salvation of souls. “I have come to cast fire upon the earth, and would that it were already enkindled” (Luke 12:49). Our Lord has a holy impatience to ignite and offer his holocaust to the Father on Calvary for the sake of mankind. “I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how I am constrained until it is accomplished” (Luke 12:50). There on the cross the fullness of God’s love for his creatures was made manifest. “Greater love has no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13). We prove that we are Christ’s friends if we struggle to follow him.</p>

<p>St. Augustine comments, “People who believe in him are enkindled. They receive the flame of charity.” That’s why the Holy Spirit appeared in this form at Pentecost. “There appeared to them tongues as of fire, distributed and resting on each one of them” (Acts 2:3). Set aflame by this fire, the apostles set out across the entire world to inflame others, including their enemies. What enemies? Those who had forsaken God their creator for the worship of man-made idols. The faith of such as these has been smothered to ashes. It’s good for them, says St. Augustine, that they be set alight by this holy flame so that they may once again shine forth in Christ’s glory.</p>

<p>This crucial task of setting the world on fire has been passed on to today’s Christians. This fire of love and peace will strengthen and purify souls. Lord, help us to go to the university, to the factories, into public life, to our own homes. If one were to set fires at different locations throughout a city, even if they were modest fires, they would quickly consume the whole metropolis. Likewise, if in a city at certain points one were to ignite the hearts of the inhabitants with the fire that Jesus brought to the world, then the good will of those people would quickly overrun the city, lighting it up with the love of God.</p>

<p>The fire that Jesus has brought to the world is himself. It is the fire of love. This is the love which not only unites souls to God but unites souls to one another. In each city, these souls should emerge from families—father and mother, son and father, mother and mother-in-law. One writer says this phenomenon can take place in parish life, in organizations, in schools, in offices, anywhere. Each small flame for God necessarily enkindles other flames. Divine providence takes care to distribute these souls on fire where they can best serve the process. Through their action, many places in the world will be restored to the warmth of the love of God and renewed hope.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord today in the Blessed Sacrament that this apostolate in the middle of the world might spread like wildfire. Pius XII says each Christian who lives the faith seriously becomes a point of ignition at his or her place of work, among friends and acquaintances. But this phenomenon will occur only when we make concrete the advice of St. Paul to the Philippians: “Have this mind among yourselves, which was in Christ Jesus” (Phil. 2:5). The apostle challenges all Christians to live out in their lives, as much as possible, those sentiments which filled the divine redeemer when he offered himself up as a sacrifice. Imitate his humility, he says, and present to God Almighty all the adoration, honor, praise, and thanksgiving.</p>

<p>This offering is realized primarily in the Mass, the unbloody renewal of the sacrifice of the cross. The Second Vatican Council says, “For all their works, prayers, and apostolic endeavors, their ordinary marriage and family life, their daily occupations, their physical and mental relaxation, if carried out in the Spirit, and even the hardships of life if patiently borne—all these become spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. Together with the offering of the Lord’s body, they are most fittingly offered in the celebration of the Mass” (<em>Lumen Gentium</em>, 34). As those everywhere who adore in holy activity, the laity consecrate the world itself to God.</p>

<p>Christian life ought to be an imitation of the life of Christ, a participation in his divine sonship. Through this way of life, we will learn from Jesus how to relate to other people. “When Jesus saw the multitude,” we’re told in St. Matthew, “he had compassion on them, for they were like sheep without a shepherd” (Matt. 9:36). Life held no meaning for them. But Jesus had compassion on these people. His love was so great that he went to the extent of giving up his life for them and us on the cross. This is the divine love which should fill our hearts. Then we too will have compassion on the people around us who perhaps have strayed from Our Lord. With the help of God’s grace and our genuine friendship, hopefully we will bring these souls back to the Master.</p>

<p>In each Mass, a surging current of divine love is transmitted from the Son to the Father through the Holy Spirit. The follower of the Lord participates in this love, since he or she is incorporated into Christ. Friends of God, St. Josemaría says, “The Christian then extends this love to other people and to all earthly realities which are thereby sanctified and made into a fitting offering to God.” “Our apostolate,” he says, “should have its roots in the Mass and should from there draw its efficacy. For the Mass is nothing less than the realization of the redemption in our time by means of apostolic Christians.”</p>

<p>Jesus came on earth to redeem everyone because he wished all men to be saved. There is not a single soul in whom Christ is not interested. Each soul has cost him the price of his blood. If we truly imitate Our Lord’s example, we can never be indifferent towards any soul.</p>

<p>When a Christian participates in the Holy Mass, his prayers should be concerned first of all with his brothers and sisters in the faith. One writer says the Christian should feel more and more closely united to them in the bread of life and in the cup of eternal salvation. This is the time to pray for everyone, but especially for those who are most in need. We should grow in the spirit of charity and fraternity because the Eucharist makes us all one. As a consequence, we therefore treat one another as family. The Eucharist unites the children of God into one family, closely united to Christ and to one another.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady, whom John Paul II liked to call “Woman of the Eucharist,” that she may help us to spread this fire of love for the Blessed Sacrament through our daily Eucharistic piety.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My immaculate mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Good Anger and Bad Anger</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/good-anger-and-bad-anger/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Good Anger and Bad Anger" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/good-anger-and-bad-anger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/good-anger-and-bad-anger/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Now the older son was out in the fields, and, on his way back, as he drew near the house, he could hear music and dancing. Calling one of the servants, he asked what it was all about. The servant told him, ‘Your brother has come, and your father has killed the calf we had been fattening, because he has gotten him back safe and sound.’ He was angry then, and refused to go in. His father came out and began to urge him to come in” (Luke 15:25-28).</p>

<p>There are two types of anger. There is a good anger and a bad anger.</p>

<p>A good anger is an anger to correct, an anger about things that are wrong. It’s the anger of a mother with a two-year-old child. She sees something wrong, she gets angry, she corrects, and then it’s over.</p>

<p>The other type of anger is an anger that smolders on, that’s bitter, full of pride or selfishness. It’s the sort of anger that we see in this older son that’s very much in need of conversion.</p>

<p>In today’s Gospel, we read about the other type of anger: “Now the Passover of the Jews was at hand, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. He found in the temple men selling oxen, sheep, and doves, and money-changers at their tables. And making a kind of whip of cords, he drove them all out of the temple, also the sheep and the oxen. And he poured out the money of the changers and overturned the tables. And to them who were selling the doves, he said, ‘Take these things away, and do not make the house of my father a house of business’” (John 2:13-16).</p>

<p>He went to the temple and He found all these people—money changers, sheep and oxen, the whole marketplace there. He was very calm about the whole thing. He said, ‘OK, it doesn’t matter, I can turn a blind eye to this.’</p>

<p>He was very cool and calm. In this situation, He could have expressed a certain carelessness, a lack of love, a lack of interest, a lack of fortitude—could be a great lack of virtue.</p>

<p>Sometimes it’s a great virtue to react, to see things are wrong and to want to put them right, and to make every effort that’s necessary to put them right—the good anger that’s against wrongdoing that has to be changed in our own lives or in the situations around us.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord for that grace to have that good type of anger, to react when things are wrong—not to be careless or lacking in love, or not to go the extra mile, not to be lacking in fortitude.</p>

<p>“We are born children of anger” (Eph. 2:3). There’s a great anger that dominates the world. It can live in the hearts of men. It can cause a lot of trouble, a lot of chaos.</p>

<p>That bad anger can be everywhere. It’s a condition where the tongue works faster than the mind. That bad anger can cause people to hurt each other, to say things they don’t really mean, or that later on they regret.</p>

<p>We can be unable to forgive or to ask for forgiveness. Hearts overcome by anger are difficult to penetrate. And we’re all susceptible to it.</p>

<p>The fact that we try to live lives close to God does not make us immune from these things. We have to try and watch out for that bad anger. Bitterness and resentment can become full-blown.</p>

<p>It’s difficult for the spirit of God to live in a heart that’s full of anger. In such a heart, the spirit of hatred and violence lives. That’s a little bit what we see in the case of the older son.</p>

<p>This older son wasn’t just a particular person. What Our Lord is describing here is a character trait that’s in each one of us. As we get older, we’re all like the older son in the parable—very much in need of conversion of that inner pride.</p>

<p>Anger can be a powerful tool of the devil. It can cause a lot of disunity. The devil enters through anger. We get the impression that this older son was dominated by anger, because he’s not open to be changed or to be converted, even by the gentle words of his father. “His father came out and began to urge him to come in.”</p>

<p>He finds he doesn’t love his brother; he doesn’t love his father. The only one he loves is himself. He’s difficult to say things to, difficult to penetrate.</p>

<p>The Book of Proverbs says, “The fool blurts out every angry feeling, but the wise subdues and restrains them” (Prov. 12:16). It says, “A fool gives full vent to his anger, but a wise person keeps themselves under control” (Prov. 29:11).</p>

<p>That anger can be like a galloping blind horse. Dangerous—it can go all over the place. This older son is full of self-righteousness: ‘I am right.’ ‘I have done the right thing.’ ‘I have not wasted my father’s money.’ ‘I have not misspent it and misused it in all sorts of bad ways. What a good little boy I am.’</p>

<p>He’s patting himself on the back, full of vanity. He’s hard-working, yes. He’s faithful, yes. But he’s also mean, jealous, selfish. He has a bit of a temper. Fast temper, fast pride.</p>

<p>The whole situation of this older brother is ugly. He has a bad type of anger. He puts a distance between himself and people—his brother and his father—people whom he should love.</p>

<p>He should be very happy at the return of his younger brother. But he’s not able to be happy. His heart is not there in his human relationships. His heart is in his own personal things. In this situation, it all comes out. There may be situations in our life that sort of reveal an awful lot.</p>

<p>For many months and years, perhaps he was working away quietly there in his father’s house, and everybody thought, ‘What a good person he is. What a good son he is. Look at that other rascal who’s off, wasting all his father’s money.’</p>

<p>But deep down, this guy was also a bit of a rascal in a worse sort of way, in a way that’s not easy to change or to convert. The conversion needed, which is so deep, was all the more necessary. Then this occasion occurs that his brother comes back and suddenly all is revealed—what he’s really like on the inside.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lord in our prayer to give us the grace to see what we are really like on the inside, so that we don’t fool ourselves and we don’t fool other people.</p>

<p>All it took was this little piece of news that “your brother has come and your father has killed a fatted calf” and all the ugly, bad things come out of that human heart: jealousy, anger, envy.</p>

<p>He retorted to his father: “All these years I’ve slaved for you and I’ve never once disobeyed any order of yours” (Luke 15:29a). ‘I tick all the boxes for a perfect son, externally.’</p>

<p>All these years he’s been counting the cost, and of course, all these years, the reality is that he hasn’t really been loving his father. He hasn’t really been loving his brother. He hasn’t been growing in charity. He’s been loving himself.</p>

<p>Then this particular event happens, and that reality becomes public. “Yet you never offered me so much as a kid for me to celebrate with my friends” (Luke 15:29b). He’s a complainer. Deep down he’s been complaining.</p>

<p>Jesus, keep me from complaining. Help me to turn to prayer.</p>

<p>There are things to complain about, to leave them before you in the tabernacle, before you on the Cross, so that I don’t become a habitual complainer, which is easy to become—making comparisons, making judgments, criticizing. ‘Why aren’t things better? Why isn’t everyone else better?’ All the time I am the one that’s in need of conversion.</p>

<p>He doesn’t behave like a son of the family. He behaves like a paid servant, like a mercenary. His heart is not there. The mercy of his father irritates him. ‘Why is my father so forgiving and so loving with this terrible brother of mine? To me he gives me nothing.’</p>

<p>He’s blind to the reality which his father tries to make him aware of. “‘My son, you’re always with me. All I have is yours’” (Luke 15:31).</p>

<p>He doesn’t realize how close he is to the heart of his father because he’s so wrapped up in himself. The joy of his brother, and the joy of his family, and the joy of his father leaves a bitter taste. He’s alien to the central ideas of the father. He’s not “united to the vine” (<em>cf</em>. John 15:4).</p>

<p>He’s very much in need of reconciliation; a deep Confession of his miseries. He doesn’t even see. He’s fulfilling his duty, but there’s no love.</p>

<p>Lord, help us to be careful with the fulfillment of our duties. We all have duties to fulfill, and we could get into the ordinary humdrum, day-to-day reality of fulfilling the duties. But all the time, St. Josemaría talks to us about doing it with more love.</p>

<p>Otherwise, we could fall into the situation of this older brother. with a heart that’s difficult to penetrate. ‘I’m doing so much work. Others are not working.’</p>

<p>He’s mean-spirited. The reality is that perhaps others are doing what they can. At the same time, he wants to be the center of attention. The salt of every dish. ‘Why wasn’t I told? How come this is happening? It’s not fair.’</p>

<p>Many things in life are not fair. You can’t look for perfect justice in this world. This world is a world of imperfect justice.</p>

<p>A man in Malaysia told me once, when I asked him how his ten-year-old son was, he told me, ‘He’s going through the age of justice.’</p>

<p>I was wondering, ‘What’s that?’</p>

<p>‘Everything is not fair.’ ‘My sister can stay up to watch the movie and I have to go to bed early. It’s not fair.’ ‘My sister has a free day tomorrow and I’ve got to go to school. It’s not fair.’ ‘My sister has less homework and I have more homework. It’s not fair.’ Everything was not fair.</p>

<p>We could spend our whole life in the “age of justice” and never grow out of it. We need a more mature approach to life. Thank God for the talents and abilities that He’s given to us.</p>

<p>If I have a greater capacity to get things done or to fulfill this job, the talent in this area will be wonderful. It will help me to push as far as I can in that area and to realize that I have bigger faults in other areas, and that other people have great talents in other areas.</p>

<p>This older son is complaining, ‘I’m not appreciated. Nobody cares about me.’ He’s talking like a spoiled child full of vanity and envy and jealousy. ‘All my efforts are not recognized.’ He hasn’t learned to forget about himself.</p>

<p>All through the writings of St. Josemaría, there’s a phrase that keeps cropping up, which is, “Forget yourself” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Points 640, 793; 947; <em>The Forge</em>, Point 97).</p>

<p>Learn how to focus on others. We solve all our own problems by thinking about the others. If we’re so involved in our own little problems, then we’ll be so easily aroused to anger. The devil can get in there very easily with all sorts of bad things.</p>

<p>He’s full of justice and responsibility, but he has no mercy. No mercy for his brother, no mercy for his father. He crucifies his brother with his pride. His heart is cold.</p>

<p>Lord, help me not to have a cold heart. Warm up my heart. Don’t even let it be lukewarm. I want to be on fire with love of you and love of others, to have burning zeal. “Come Holy Spirit, and kindle in our hearts the fire of your love.”</p>

<p>When we look at the ugliness of this particular fellow, Lord, help us to run a mile from being this type of person, because the potential is there in each one of us.</p>

<p>He’s not happy, because now he has to share what he has with his brother. The brother has come back. ‘All this was going to be mine, and now I have to share.’</p>

<p>Sharing can be a very challenging business. We see when parents die and family members have to share the land or share the products—all sorts of ugly things can come out, because we’re selfish a bit by nature. We have to learn how to share.</p>

<p>He has a bone to pick with his father. He’s very independent-minded. To be independent-minded can be a good thing, but it can also be a bad thing. He wants things his own way. He doesn’t want what the father wants.</p>

<p>In the course of our life, each one of us has to work under other people. We all have a supervisor. We all have a boss. Our job in that particular situation is to make our boss happy, to make our supervisor happy.</p>

<p>Probably if your supervisor or your teacher is happy with you and with your work, then God is happy with you. Our first duty is to make the person above us happy, not to want things our own way or to do things the way we want to do them, but to do them the way our boss wants them done—to bend to their will.</p>

<p>That’s how we serve and improve our service. And all through our life we will always have somebody asking us to do things or paying us to do things, and they want them done a certain way.</p>

<p>Even if we don’t like that way or think there’s a better way, for this particular moment, for this particular boss, I have to try and serve them the way that they want to be served. Refinement in service.</p>

<p>This guy had no refinement. He wants things his own way all the time. He was older, so he should have known better. We could have expected a greater maturity from him.</p>

<p>But instead, we find the opposite. He’s immature. We could be mature in age or physically, but we might be very immature on the inside.</p>

<p>He doesn’t realize that everything that he has is a gift of God. If he realized that everything he had was a gift of God, he would be so happy—so happy that he’s able to work, so happy that he has such a good father, so happy that his brother has come back, which was the most important thing.</p>

<p>Because he’s all wrapped up in himself, he misses the most important thing. He takes it all for granted. He forgets others, and he forgets that others need forgiveness. They need tenderness. They need mercy.</p>

<p>This son who had come back after a very rough patch in his life—he was in need of being handled with kid gloves, been through a lot, learned the great lessons of life. But this fellow was so cold-hearted. He had no tenderness in him.</p>

<p>We could examine our conscience and see: Lord, do I have those tender words or actions for people who live around me or work with me? Should I lift them up, make them feel better if they make a mistake?</p>

<p>In the last few days, there’s been this, in some ways, very terrible story, a thing that happened in a school in Madrid, a girl’s school, I think it was a kindergarten school.</p>

<p>A mother was collecting her children. She had the children in the car, and then she goes to move the car, and instead of going into reverse, she goes forward. She hits three six-year-old kids, kills one of them, and badly injures two others. All in the school car park.</p>

<p>Heart-rending story. The secretary of the school, the mother of the child that dies, comes out to see her dead child. Of course, it’s a heartbreaking moment. Then she sees the other mother, who has been the one who has made this mistake in the car, and goes to embrace her and console her.</p>

<p>It’s come out in all the newspapers in Spain (Aleteia, <em>Faith shines through tragedy at Madrid Catholic School</em>, November 5 and 10, 2021). A heart-rending moment, but a wonderful virtue in this difficult time: knowing how to give tenderness, to give forgiveness; to reach out to others, even though your own heart is breaking.</p>

<p>A beautiful example of virtue on a national scale and level. Here we are talking about it. It’s what the school of sanctity is all about: a tender heart.</p>

<p>Lord, give us that heart that helps us to reach out to others, to give them what they need in certain moments.</p>

<p>The problems and the sufferings of his father and of his brother are foreign to this particular fellow, whereas this woman, completely the opposite. In that terrible moment, when God has taken her child, she sees somebody else in need of consolation, of forgiveness, of help, and she reaches out.</p>

<p>If we view things from the outside like a stranger, we won’t know how to react with charity and love and forgiveness and tenderness in those moments. We won’t know what to say or what to do.</p>

<p>God is using this tragic event to give great lessons of charity to people all over the world—great catechesis.</p>

<p>This son, he doesn’t hope to see his brother again. He doesn’t receive him with joy. Perhaps he was wishing that his brother would stay away, just feeding the pigs, and die in the gutter someplace, so he can forget all about him.</p>

<p>He’s very much in need of conversion. The happiness that his brother is found, the meaning of life, the change that has come about—it leaves a bitter taste in his heart.</p>

<p>The father comes out and speaks gently to him, man to man, calls him to conversion. “My son, all that I have is yours” (Luke 15:31). He calls him his son, imploring from him that fraternal understanding, that respect for the person, that joyful apostolate of example.</p>

<p>Forget yourself. Reach out to others. Conquer your anger. Don’t let the devil dominate this moment that can be a tremendous moment in our family, a great moment of great significance.</p>

<p>But the son is so wrapped up in himself that he has no time for these great moments. He wants all the glory ‘to me.’ He doesn’t accept the will of God. He’s insensitive to correction. He seems to say to his father, ‘Don’t come with your stories to me. I have no time for you, this brother of mine. No time for you either, with your nice, sweet words.’ Tremendous insensitivity.</p>

<p>Lord, help us to be very sensitive to correction. May I be a person that’s easily able to be talked to, to be told things.</p>

<p>You see, sometimes if we’re working in some department, or we’re doing some job and our supervisor comes along and says, ‘You missed a little piece here on the floor,’ or ‘That could be a little bit done better there,’ or ‘You forgot to put a fork on this table,’ or ‘You pressed the wrong button on the washing machine’—we might explode!</p>

<p>‘Somebody has told us these things. How dare they tell us these things!’ We can be full of pride and vanity. We can be like a stick of dynamite.</p>

<p>We have to learn how to control those sorts of reactions, because we have to learn how to work with other people, how to live with other people. Everybody should be able to tell us anything at any moment, because ultimately, they’re not out to try and make us suffer. They’re trying to make us into a better professional person.</p>

<p>It’s a great service that they tell us things. It’s a sign of confidence that they feel that they can tell us something without us exploding like a stick of dynamite. We’ll take it, we’ll be sensitive, we’ll be grateful, because it’s a great act of charity. It helps us to be better, which is ultimately what we want.</p>

<p>This older brother, he knows it all already. He has it all figured out. He’s full of self-exaltation. I can imagine he’s impossible to work with, impossible to live with.</p>

<p>That picture that Our Lord paints of this person on the inside is very relevant for each one of us. ‘I need to change. I need to be better. I need to ask people also, maybe in spiritual direction, what are my great faults? Where do you think I can improve, to prevent me from making big mistakes in my life?’—like this fellow did.</p>

<p>Or also, all those money changers in the temple, or all the people that brought the oxen and the cattle into the temple—what were they thinking? What did they think this place was? They converted it into a marketplace. You get the impression they must all have been very, very stupid.</p>

<p>And yet, we can all be very stupid. We can use things for the completely opposite purpose for which they have been created. We can mistake the meaning and the purpose of certain great instruments that God has given to us. We could be the ones that lead our goats or our cattle or something into some sacred place. Our Lord has come along and corrects them in a very clear way.</p>

<p>This older son—he sees only the sins of others. He refuses to see his own imperfections.</p>

<p>“Lord, that I may see” (Luke 18:41). Help me to see myself as others see me. Help me to have that humility of spirit, so that I realize that I have defects and that I need to change.</p>

<p>If we love others with a heart that’s full of pride, then our love becomes conditional. We will show love only if other people behave according to our will, if they conform to be what we want them to be.</p>

<p>This fellow was living in a house full of love and mercy, with such a good father. But he doesn’t get it.</p>

<p>Lord, prevent me from being in such a good atmosphere, such a good family—such tenderness around me, such charity—and yet I don’t get the message. What a tragedy!</p>

<p>This parable helps us to look into the depths of the heart of man, the depths of the hearts of God’s children. See what we’re all like on the inside.</p>

<p>This older son becomes the example to avoid. The younger son is the one to imitate. The older son is detestable, but yet God still loves him. He still goes out to him: “All that I have is yours.”</p>

<p>Even when we are detestable on the inside, full of misery and wretchedness, failure, God still loves us, reaches out to us, invites us to a new conversion.</p>

<p>We could ask Our Lady to help us to understand these types of anger, so that we might have a lot of the good anger, whereby we want things to be right, we want to put things right, and that we might have none of the bad anger.</p>

<p>If it’s there, that we might conquer it with a deeper humility, which comes as a result of getting to know ourself a little better on the inside, just like Our Lord has given us this older son for us to examine in concrete ways, so that we can know ourselves a little better.</p>

<p>Mary, may you lead me along the pathway of a deeper humility.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>MVF</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Great Mothers</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/great-mothers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Great Mothers" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/great-mothers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/great-mothers/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>There was a lady from a small village in the Mogilev region of the Russian Empire, in what is now Belarus. Her name was Bryna.</p>

<p>In her youth, she was engaged to a man called Herschel, who left for America with promises and dreams. A year later, he sent money for her passage. In those days before visa requirements, she boarded a ship to join him, carrying nothing but hope for a better life.</p>

<p>They married and settled in Amsterdam, New York—not the glamorous city, but a small mill town. Bryna gave Herschel seven children: six daughters and finally, a son. They named him Issur, though everyone else called him Izzy.</p>

<p>But the American dream turned into an American nightmare.</p>

<p>Herschel, who had been a horse trader in Russia, became a ragman in America, collecting junk and scraps to sell. What little money he made, he spent on alcohol and on gambling with his friends. He was known throughout the neighborhood as a troublemaker and a bully. Worse still, he was cruel at home—so cold that he never once called his wife by her name. He addressed her only as, “Hey, you!”</p>

<p>The family lived in crushing poverty. Bryna, who couldn’t read or write, worked her fingers raw, taking in laundry and doing whatever job she could find, but it was never enough. The children often went hungry.</p>

<p>She would send Izzy to the Jewish butcher with a simple request: “Please give me the bones you don’t need anymore.” She would take those discarded bones and boil them for hours, making a thin soup that kept her family alive for days.</p>

<p>Years later, her son—by then known as Kirk Douglas—remembered those days: “When it was a good day,” he said, “we would eat omelets made with water. When it was a bad day, we wouldn’t eat at all.”</p>

<p>But Bryna never gave up. She held her family together through sheer force of will, and she believed in her son with a fierceness that defied their circumstances. When Izzy talked about becoming an actor—a ridiculous dream for a poor kid from a ragman’s family—she encouraged him.</p>

<p>Issur Demsky left that small town and became Kirk Douglas. He became a Hollywood legend, starring in classics like <em>Spartacus</em>, <em>Paths of Glory</em>, and <em>Lust for Life</em>. But he never forgot where he came from, and he never forgot who made it possible.</p>

<p>In 1949, when Kirk formed his own film production company, he gave it a name: Bryna Productions. Not after himself; after his mother.</p>

<p>In 1958, Bryna Productions released <em>The Vikings</em>, an epic film starring Kirk Douglas and Tony Curtis. It was one of the year’s biggest movies.</p>

<p>Kirk decided his mother needed to see something. He took her by the arm and led her to Times Square in New York City. Among the flashing lights and enormous advertisements, he showed her a massive poster that said: “Bryna Presents <em>The Vikings</em>.” Her name. The woman who couldn’t read. The woman who boiled bones for soup. The woman who was called “Hey, you!” by her husband. Her name was on a billboard in Times Square.</p>

<p>Bryna Demsky burst into tears, perhaps the first tears of pure joy she’d ever cried in her difficult life.</p>

<p>That December, just months after seeing her name in lights, Bryna passed away at the age of 74. Kirk was with her until the very end. Her last words to him were simple and loving: “Izzy, my son, don’t be afraid. This happens to everyone.” Even in death, she was still trying to comfort him.</p>

<p>Kirk Douglas lived to be 103 years old. He became one of Hollywood’s greatest stars, a producer, a philanthropist, and father of actor Michael Douglas. But until his death in 2020, he always said the same thing: everything he achieved was because of his mother.</p>

<p>The woman who couldn’t write her own name gave the world a legend. The woman who had nothing gave her son everything. The son who became a star made sure the world remembered her name.</p>

<p>Every film that bore the title “A Bryna Production” was a love letter from a grateful son to the mother who believed in him when he had nothing but dreams. She deserved to see her name in lights. And her son made sure she did.</p>

<p>From this story, we can be mindful in our prayer of how our earthly life is short and fleeting. We have to take advantage of the noble things of the earth so as to win heaven.</p>

<p>We might not be rich in this world, but we can be rich before God, and that’s the sort of richness that we have to try to acquire.</p>

<p>“Do not lay up for yourselves treasures on earth, where dust and moth consume and thieves break in and steal, but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven” (Matt. 6:19–20). Our passage upon this earth is a time of testing. Our Lord Himself has given this particular time to us, and we have to try and make use of everything: the difficulties, the challenges, the crosses, the failures.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Hebrews, “For here we have no lasting city, but we seek for the city which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). That’s what it’s all about.</p>

<p>On a certain day, Our Lord will come to settle accounts with us, to determine how well or ill we have administered His gifts. His gifts include intelligence, health, material goods, a capacity for friendship, the power to give joy to those around us.</p>

<p>Our Lord will come only once, perhaps when we least expect Him, like a thief in the night (Matt. 24:43), like lightning flashing across the sky (Matt. 24:27). He wants to find us well prepared.</p>

<p>If we tie ourselves down to this world, forgetting that our end is in heaven, that can lead us to live a disoriented life of complete idiocy. How important it is that we get to a retreat once a year, that we’re reminded of those eternal truths and never lose sight of them, which can easily happen.</p>

<p>We have to walk with our feet on the ground, taking care to safeguard our future and the future of those who depend on us. But we can’t forget that we are pilgrims, no more than “actors in a show,” as St. John Chrysostom says. “No one is permanently made king or wealthy, since at the end of the performance, we will all find ourselves as paupers” (John Chrysostom, <em>Homily on Lazarus</em>).</p>

<p>Worldly goods are but the means for us to attain the goal which Our Lord has pointed out for us. Those worldly goods can never become the be-all and the end-all of our existence.</p>

<p>Our life on earth is short and limited. Perhaps we think of death in terms of something remote, as if we will live forever. But Our Lord tells us that our days are numbered. We’re in the hands of God. Within a few years—maybe a few months or a few days, perhaps not that many—we will find ourselves face to face with Him.</p>

<p>Meditating on our final end can motivate us to sanctify our work, redeeming the time, as we strive to make up for lost time (Eph. 5:16). It should help us to take advantage of our circumstances in order to make reparation for sins and to become detached from earthly goods.</p>

<p>One day, like any other day, will be our last day on earth. Today, thousands of people have died, or will die, in the most diverse circumstances.</p>

<p>All those people were probably unaware that their time was up, that they would have no more time to improve. Some have died with their hearts immersed in things of little or no importance in terms of eternal life.</p>

<p>Others have died who have been involved in exactly the same activities, but have kept their sights on God. It’s these latter people who have come into possession of that marvelous treasure “which neither dust nor moth consumes” (Matt. 6:20).</p>

<p>St. Paul tells the Colossians, “If then you have been raised with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is, seated at the right hand of God. Set your minds on the things that are above, not on things that are on the earth” (Col. 3:1–2). Things of the world last only a relatively short period of time. They can’t fulfill the longings of the human heart.</p>

<p>The Book of Wisdom says, “The life of man on earth is brief” (Wis. 2:1). The greater part of it can be spent in pain and suffering. Every life passes like the wind. Barely a trace is left behind (<em>cf</em>. Ps. 90:10).</p>

<p>In the best of cases, one might amass a great fortune, only for it to be left to others. What does all this pain and suffering add up to? Is it all for nothing? The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “Vanity of vanities! All is vanity” (Eccles. 1:2).</p>

<p>In the face of this emptiness and inconsistency, all this pointlessness, God is “the rock of our salvation.” The Psalm says, “Let us come into his presence with thanksgiving. Let us make a joyful noise to him with songs of praise” (Ps. 95:1-2).</p>

<p>At the same time, the human heart has a tremendous capacity to seek the things of the world without paying any attention to the transcendent meaning of life. The human heart tends to become attached to worldly goods as the one and only goal in life, forgetting what is really important.</p>

<p>Our Lord takes advantage of a question about inheritance to teach us about the true worth of things in the light of eternity. He says there was once a rich man, who “having had a good harvest from his land, thought to himself, ‘What am I to do? I have not enough room to store my crops.’ And he said, ‘This is what I will do: I will pull down my barns and build bigger ones, and store all my grain and my goods in them. And I will say to my soul: My soul, you have plenty of good things laid by for many years to come; take things easy. Eat, drink, have a good time.’ But God said to him, ‘Fool! This very night the demand will be made for your soul, and this hoard of yours, whose shall it be then?’” (Luke 12:16-20).</p>

<p>So it is when someone stores up treasures for himself instead of becoming rich in the sight of God. Our Lord brings up the subject of death, of our own death, to make His point.</p>

<p>He says the land of this man brought forth plentifully, and he planned about how he was going to increase all of those things. Then he has to hear the strong words from Our Lord: “Fool.” It’s about the only time in Scripture that that word is used.</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that putting our hearts into the pursuit of wealth and worldly well-being is foolishness. What we have to strive for is to be rich before God, like Bryna was, in spite of all the difficulties.</p>

<p>Neither happiness nor authentic human life itself are founded on worldly goods. We’re told in St. Luke, “A man’s life does not consist in the abundance of his possessions” (Luke 12:15).</p>

<p>The rich man discloses his ‘value system’ in his mental dialogue. He sees himself in the story in a very secure position because he has great resources. He bases his stability and his happiness on his wealth.</p>

<p>For him, as for many people, living is a matter of enjoying as much pleasure as possible. It is to do as little as need be, to eat, to drink, to have a good time, to lay up ample goods for many years. That’s his ideal. In his life, there’s no reference to God, much less to other people. He sees no need to share his goods with others less fortunate than himself.</p>

<p>And how does he plan to maintain his thoroughly materialistic lifestyle? “I will store up for myself.” Yet in the end, all his calculations are for nothing. The things of this world give a fragile and insufficient security, since our lives will never be fulfilled without God.</p>

<p>During our time of prayer, we can ask ourselves: where is my heart? Because we know that our destination is heaven, we have to make positive and concrete acts of detachment with regard to what we own and what we use.</p>

<p>We can ask ourselves: how much do we share our goods with the needy? One criterion that St. Josemaría liked to give to families was that if you’re spending money on a celebration, or a holiday, or some special occasion, make sure a portion of what you spent is given to some needy family or to some worthwhile cause.</p>

<p>It fosters a social consciousness, something we have to infect people with all over the world, particularly our children; to think about others, particularly in moments when we’re having a good time.</p>

<p>We can ask ourselves: how much time and wealth do we contribute to apostolic works? Could we be doing a little bit more? Are we working at being rich before God? Are we using those difficult circumstances that life may have dealt us, with the will of God, like Bryna, to produce great people, like her son, who go on to build up the culture of the world?</p>

<p>At the moment of death, the state of our soul is fixed forever. Afterwards, it’s impossible to change. The destiny which awaits us is the consequence of our behavior on earth. The Book of Ecclesiastes says, “If a tree falls to the south or to the north, in the place where the tree falls, there it will lie” (Eccles. 11:3).</p>

<p>This is the reason for Our Lord’s frequent warnings to be on watch, to be vigilant (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 24:42-44, Mark 13:32-37).</p>

<p>Death is not the end of our existence, but the beginning of a new life. Christians cannot ‘write off’ or minimize the importance of our temporal existence since it is the very means by which we prepare for our definitive life with God in heaven.</p>

<p>To yield a rich harvest before God we have to sanctify this same ordinary life and the use of material goods. Every other lifestyle is built upon sand. The Psalms say, “Surely every man stands as a mere breath! Surely man goes about as a shadow!...man heaps up, and knows not who will gather” (Ps. 39:5-6).</p>

<p>Inasmuch as the goods of this world are intended for the glory of God, we should use them with a sense of detachment, not complaining either when these goods may be lacking. The absence of some good, as in Bryna’s case, if it is God’s will, should not take away our peace. We should know how to be happy in times of prosperity and in adversity.</p>

<p>Whether we are rich or poor, we should share what we have with others, by creating new jobs—if that is in our power, by promoting works of culture and formation, by giving generously to the good works of the Church.</p>

<p>A very good question for many people to ask themselves is: where would I be without the Church? All the value systems, good things the Church has given to me—education, formation, care of my soul. We have to propagate that as much as possible, and to bring that formation to the ends of the earth.</p>

<p>By considering our death, we also learn how to make good use of the days that remain to us. St. Josemaría said, “My children, the world is slipping through our fingers. We cannot lose any time, for time is short. I understand St. Paul very well when he writes to the Corinthians, ‘<em>Tempus breve est</em>.’ How brief is the time of our sojourn upon this earth! For a coherent Christian, these words ought to ring true in the depths of the soul. They are a reproach for a lack of generosity and a constant invitation to loyalty. Truly, we have so little time to love, to give, to do penance” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Newsletter No. 1; cf. Friends of God</em>, Point 39).</p>

<p>We could ask ourselves: are we going to allow our hearts to be tied to the things of this world?</p>

<p>Meditation on the eternal truths is a good antidote against sin and a real help towards giving a Christian meaning to life. We should renew our resolution to expose ourselves to those eternal truths in a regular way, particularly yearly on a retreat, so that those ideas don’t escape our conscience and our thoughts.</p>

<p>Those thoughts can inspire us to pay proper attention to our daily work, to our relations with other people, and to our duties in charity towards those in need. That will be our way to heaven. In that way, we will be truly rich before God.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady that she might help us to make good use of our circumstances, situations that God has willed for us to grow in holiness, to sow seeds, to give ourselves to the formation of our children and our grandchildren, and to really have that great yearning in our mind and heart to be rich in relation to the things of God.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Obedience</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/obedience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Obedience" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/obedience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/obedience/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>Our Lord tells us in St. John, “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to accomplish his work” (John 4:34).</p>

<p>Obedience is the submission of our will to the will of another.</p>

<p>On many occasions and throughout His life, Our Lord humbly submitted His will to the will of His Father: “Father, if it is possible, let this chalice pass from me; yet not my will, rather yours be done” (Matt. 26:39).</p>

<p>Our Lord gives great importance to the virtue of obedience.</p>

<p>He wants each one of us to die to ourselves, to our self-love, to our egoism—very often through obedience to the people that He has placed there to guide us.</p>

<p>For children, it’s parents. For husbands, it may be wives; for wives, husbands. For other people, the people that God has placed with the grace of state to guide them.</p>

<p>He says in St. John: “Amen, Amen, I say to you, unless a grain of wheat falling into the ground dies, it remains alone; but if it dies, it brings forth much fruit. He that loves his life shall lose it, and he that hates his life in this world will keep it until life everlasting” (John 12:24-25).</p>

<p>Part of our Christian vocation in following Our Lord is to try and live this virtue well.</p>

<p>There are times when it may be easy, but there can be times when it costs, but obedience is always fruitful. The Book of Proverbs says, “The obedient person speaks victory” (Prov. 21:28). God loves the obedient soul.</p>

<p>Also in St. John, Our Lord says: “Now is my soul troubled, and what shall I say? ‘Father, save me from this hour’? But for this cause, I came unto this hour” (John 12:27).</p>

<p>Our Lord came to obey, to do His Father’s will.</p>

<p>We’re told on another occasion: “What do you think?” He said.</p>

<p>“A certain man had two sons. And coming to the first, he said, ‘Son, go work today in my vineyard.’ And he, answering, said, ‘I will not.’ But afterward, being moved with repentance, he went. And coming to the other, he said in like manner.</p>

<p>“And he, answering, said, ‘I go, sir,’ and he went not. Which of the two did the father’s will? They said to him: ‘The first.’ Jesus said to them: ‘Amen I say to you, that the publicans and the harlots shall go into the kingdom of heaven before you’” (Matt. 21:28-31).</p>

<p>That’s a rather interesting phrase worth thinking about.</p>

<p>We haven’t come to do our own will or to impose our will on other people. Our Lord wants the humble submission of our will.</p>

<p>St. Paul says to the Philippians: “For let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus, for being in the form of God, he did not think being equal to God a thing to be clung to, but emptied himself, taking the form of a slave and being made in the likeness of men. In the form of man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient unto death, even unto death on a cross. For which cause God has also exalted him and given him the name which is above all names, so that in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of those that are in heaven and on earth and under the earth” (Phil. 2:5-10).</p>

<p>One of the ways in which we empty ourselves and live this virtue of humility—authentic humility—in our deeds is through this virtue.</p>

<p>The whole of Our Lord’s life could be summed up in the two words: “He obeyed.”</p>

<p>“He went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was obedient to them. And his mother treasured all these things in her heart” (Luke 2:51).</p>

<p>Our Lord also emphasized: “I have come down from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of him who sent me” (John 6:38).</p>

<p>Initially, it might be difficult to see Our Lord’s will.</p>

<p>Close to where we lived in Singapore, there was a community of nuns, some of them very elderly—elderly Irish nuns who had been all over Asia. Many had looked after orphanages in many faraway places.</p>

<p>Then one elderly nun died. One of the other young nuns told me a story that when this lady was 67, she was asked to go and start an orphanage in Fiji.</p>

<p>But she had been the Superior of many orphanages in different places, and now she was a bit old and she was a bit tired, and she didn’t really feel like going to Fiji.</p>

<p>She was sort of complaining: “I’ve always been the one to go and start in all these places, and now I’m this age,” and she said, “I won’t go. I won’t, I won’t, I won’t, I won’t, I won’t.”</p>

<p>Then the nun finished her story, saying, “You know, in the end, she went.”</p>

<p>It was a rather beautiful, formative story.</p>

<p>Initially, she didn’t feel one single bit like obeying. Every human cell in her body felt like rebelling, this holy lady.</p>

<p>But after prayer and consideration, she came to see what the will of God was, and so she went forward to live out her vocation in and through this virtue.</p>

<p>Our Lord said in St. Luke: “I have a baptism with which to be baptized, and how great is my distress until it is over!” (Luke 12:50).</p>

<p>“See, we are going up to Jerusalem,” we’re told in St. Luke, “and everything that is written about the Son of Man by the prophets will be accomplished” (Luke 18:31).</p>

<p>“For this reason, the Father loves Me because I lay down my life in order to take it up again” (John 10:17).</p>

<p>In the whole course of our Christian vocation, there may be many situations in our marriage, in our family, in our workplace, where we are called to lay down our life: to work in this particular place; to fulfill this particular job; to finish this particular task that we have in front of us.</p>

<p>He said: “No one takes it from me, but I lay it down of my own accord” (John 10:18).</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say that sometimes the most supernatural reason for doing things is because I want to, because I see this thing as the will of God (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 17).</p>

<p>This is what is being asked of me, and so I interiorize the requests. I don’t do something just because I have been asked to do this, or I have been told to do that. I do it because I want to, because I see this is the will of God, the Holy Spirit speaking to me, and this is His will for me in this particular moment. Therefore, I do it of my own accord and with great personal responsibility.</p>

<p>“I have the power to lay it down,” He says, “and I have the power to take it up again. I’ve received this command from my Father” (John 10:18).</p>

<p>In the Book of Samuel, we’re told: “I prefer obedience rather than sacrifice” (<em>cf</em>. 1 Sam. 15:22).</p>

<p>Sometimes the temptation might be to perform some great sacrifice that may be attractive to us or looks interesting, but possibly God is not asking us for that big sacrifice. Maybe He just wants us to obey in a humble way the ordinary little things that God asks of us.</p>

<p>In <em>The Forge</em>, Point 231, it says, “A sick man is brought to Jesus, who looks at him. —Contemplate the scene closely and meditate upon his words: take heart, my son.</p>

<p>“This is what Our Lord says to you when you feel the weight of your errors. Have faith! In the first place: faith. And then allow yourself to be carried like the paralytic did: with interior and submissive obedience!”</p>

<p>This virtue is supposed to have certain characteristics.</p>

<p>It’s meant to be supernatural: I see this thing as coming from God. I’m not just obeying a human person. I don’t look at the human qualities of the person who’s asked me to do this thing. They might be younger than me; they might be less qualified; they might be this, they might be that; they might be less virtuous.</p>

<p>But they have been placed in this particular situation to guide me. Therefore, with faith, I have to try and see the hand of God working in and through this person.</p>

<p>Our obedience should be intelligent. It’s not a blind obedience. We pass that obedience through our reason.</p>

<p>If there is some particular thing that we find problematic, then we ask about it. We ask for clarification. If we’re still told to go ahead, it’s better to go ahead and do it, with faith, with a supernatural outlook, with trust in God.</p>

<p>When we’re asked to do something, our obedience should be prompt.</p>

<p>“Mary went with haste into the hill country” (Luke 1:39). “The shepherds went with haste” to Bethlehem (Luke 2:16).</p>

<p>In Scripture, as soon as people see what the will of God for them is, they go quickly to fulfill that will.</p>

<p>One lady advised her child when her child began to have children after marrying. When he asked for advice on how to bring up children, this experienced lady said, ‘Teach them to obey.’</p>

<p>One great lesson that parents should try and instill in their children is to teach them to obey, and to obey with haste.</p>

<p>When I say something, will you give that priority? When I call you, you come. When I tell you to make your bed, you make your bed. When I tell you to be on time for meals, you be on time for meals.</p>

<p>The domestic Church has to cultivate many virtues. A family is meant to be a school of virtues, and this is one of them. It’s a great preparation for a child for their future marriage, for their future work, for the future contribution they have to make to society.</p>

<p>Our obedience should be interior. We don’t just obey exteriorly, grinding our teeth and getting on with it.</p>

<p>Because we see that indication was coming from the hand of God, we make it our own with our mind and heart. I do this because I want to, because I see this is the will of God.</p>

<p>God gives us the grace and the help to be able to fulfill that thing.</p>

<p>Sometimes our reason can become unreasonable. What we are asked to do might seem unreasonable.</p>

<p>There was a little girl once, five years of age, who was quite talkative, particularly when she went visiting her neighbors. One day she remarked to the lady who lived next door, “I don’t think my mother knows anything about raising children.”</p>

<p>The lady next door asked, “Well, how is that?” She said, “She makes me go to bed when I’m not sleepy, and she makes me get up when I am sleepy.”</p>

<p>Sometimes obedience does not seem reasonable. But yet, looked at from a different perspective, it can be a different story.</p>

<p>And lastly, our obedience should be responsible. When we’re asked to do something, we report back about that thing that we have done.</p>

<p>We help the person who asked us to do something to be at peace: this job has been done, and I can now tick it on my list—whether it’s our boss, whether it’s our spouse, whether it’s our parent, whoever it may be.</p>

<p>Obedience breeds peace in the humble soul. When we do what we’re asked to do, then we can relax. We’ve done the best thing. We’ve done the will of God.</p>

<p>A principal obstacle to our obedience can be pride: pride expressed as rebellion, a critical spirit, a poorly understood freedom of spirit.</p>

<p>The remedy is always humility and sincerity. Speak about it in spiritual direction.</p>

<p>These are some of the areas where the enemy can attack: trying to promote a critical spirit or a judgmental spirit, a lack of docility.</p>

<p>Obedience is not against our freedom.</p>

<p>I heard a canon lawyer many years ago, shortly after the new Code of Canon Law was promoted in 1983.</p>

<p>He was saying that in our society, law is almost a dirty word. We have to improve the public opinion of the law. Everybody wants to be out from underneath the yoke of the law.</p>

<p>He talked about the relationship between law and freedom. He said in every city, the airport is about half an hour from the center of the city. Everyone is free to go to the airport. Everyone has a right to go to the airport.</p>

<p>To go to the airport, you’ve got to go down one road, turn left here, turn right there, go around the roundabout. Maybe around another roundabout. Eventually, you turn left, and you get to the airport.</p>

<p>But he said if you take away all the laws, and you tell people that now if they don’t want to drive on the left side of the road, they can drive on the right side of the road. And when they come to the roundabout, instead of going clockwise, if they feel like it, they’re free to go anticlockwise. And if they want to drive to the airport all the way on the footpath, they can do so. And if they want to have fun, they could reverse to the airport on the wrong side of the road.</p>

<p>What would be the result? The result would be chaos. Instead of taking half an hour to get to the airport, you might never get to the airport.</p>

<p>It might take you hours and hours, because if everybody else is reversing all the way to where they’re going on the wrong side of the road, you may have a monumental traffic jam.</p>

<p>The moral of the story is that the opposite of law is not freedom; it’s chaos.</p>

<p>Freedom comes with the law. We maintain our freedom by following the law.</p>

<p>This is a very important Christian concept, not just in society in general, but in the family, in any organization, in a school, in the workplace, in the university.</p>

<p>We maintain our freedom by following the laws or the indications that are laid down to preserve everybody else’s freedom.</p>

<p>Through this virtue, we show that our self-surrender to God is real; that our love is effective; that our faith is high-quality faith; and that our intention is upright.</p>

<p>I haven’t come just to do my will, what I think is best, what I want to do. I’ve come to do what God wants me to do.</p>

<p>Therefore, obedience and things may be difficult or costly, and can demand a lot of fortitude, and possibly a lot of sacrifice. But sacrifice is the touchstone of love.</p>

<p>“Greater love than this, no man has, than to lay down his life for his friends” (John 15:13).</p>

<p>To subject our will to another in a regular way can be heroic: to our spouse, to our boss, to the law, to the organization. We have to ardently desire to do the will of the Father at all times.</p>

<p>We find that the fullness of obedience is found on Calvary. The whole of the Redemption is the fruit of the obedience of Christ.</p>

<p>“For as by one man’s disobedience many were made sinners, by one Man’s obedience many will be made righteous,” says St. Paul to the Romans (Rom. 5:19).</p>

<p>A very good aspiration or word to have on our lips occasionally is the word <em>serviam,</em> I will serve.</p>

<p>I’ve come to serve God in my family, in my workplace, in public life, in and through the individuals that God has placed around me; to serve my children; to serve my neighbors.</p>

<p>The obedience of the children of God reflects our identity with Christ. We are children of His, with the same obedience that He has.</p>

<p>The more we go along in our Christian vocation, then the more refined our obedience should be. It’s not that as we get older, we impose our will more on other people.</p>

<p>Our Lord lived obedience to the end: “obedience until death” (<em>cf</em>. Phil. 2:8). Christ is always present in obedience.</p>

<p>If we have difficulty obeying, it can be an opportunity to grow in humility.</p>

<p>Blessed Álvaro del Portillo used to say that availability is one of the signs of those people who deal constantly with the Holy Spirit.</p>

<p>We have an ongoing relationship with the Holy Spirit when we find it easy to do things. Can you do this? Can you do that? Can you come here? Can you go there?</p>

<p>In principle, yes, because I have come to serve. That’s what my life is all about in this marriage, in this family, in this organization.</p>

<p>We can’t be co-redeemers without obeying. This virtue confers a supernatural value to the whole of our life.</p>

<p>The need to obey doesn’t depend exclusively on the good it does to the soul nor on the requirements of organizational efficacy, but on its intimate union with the Redemption. It’s an intimate part of the mystery of the Cross.</p>

<p>In <em>Lumen gentium</em> of the Second Vatican Council, it says, “To carry out the will of the Father, Christ inaugurated the Kingdom of heaven on earth and revealed to us the mystery of that kingdom” (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 3, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>For us to imitate Christ and to be co-redeemers, we need to obey. If we set limits to our obedience, we reduce our union with Christ.</p>

<p>We haven’t come to impose our personal criteria. We have to decide to become a saint because that’s what our Christian vocation is all about, and that equates with submitting ourselves or lowering ourselves, emptying ourselves.</p>

<p>This virtue allows us to cut off many deviations of our will at the beginning.</p>

<p>“It happened that on the eighth day, they came to circumcise the child; they were going to call him Zechariah after his father, but his mother spoke up: ‘No, he is to be called John.’ They said to her, ‘But no one in your family has that name,’ and they made signs to his father to find out what he wanted him called. His father asked for a writing tablet and wrote, ‘His name is John.’ And they were all astonished. At that instant, his power of speech returned and he spoke and praised God” (Luke 1:59-64).</p>

<p>Only the person who has learned how to obey is capable of commanding, because they’ve discovered that the intimate sense of obedience is love, and that the mission of governance is also an act of love, part of the full and unique love that stirs souls of all who serve the Church.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to say that the task of governance anywhere in the Church is another opportunity to serve, and to cease holding some position of governance is not a failure, but another way of serving.</p>

<p>“Whatever our task,” says St. Paul to the Colossians, “work heartily, as serving the Lord and not men. … You are serving the Lord Jesus Christ” (Col. 3:23-24).</p>

<p>Precisely because we live and work in the world, we have to try to obey with more zeal and exactitude at whatever is asked of us.</p>

<p>No one in the world should make themselves untouchable, no matter how important our professional work may be, because “our food has to be to do the will of him who sent me” (<em>cf</em>. John 4:34).</p>

<p>This is what gives meaning and strength to my life: to do God’s will even in the smallest things, not in doing my preferences or my caprices.</p>

<p>This virtue is the touchstone of humility: humility put into practice, of supernatural meaning that animates us. It gives us the assurance that we are truly serving God, and not our vanity, our caprice, or our selfishness.</p>

<p>We also have to try and be obedient to the advice we receive in spiritual direction.</p>

<p>Our Lord told the lepers to go and show themselves to the priests (Luke 17:14). He didn’t cleanse them there and then. He wanted their response of obedience.</p>

<p>The blind man washes his clay-filled eyes in the pool of Siloam, and then he begins to see (John 9:7).</p>

<p>The superabundant catch of fish comes from lowering the net to the other side of the boat (Luke 5:4-6).</p>

<p>Many miracles occur after the exercise of this virtue.</p>

<p>Our obedience may sometimes require the cheerful rearrangement of our personal plans. Instead of your plan, can you change your plan and do this or do that, or pass by here or pick up this thing? This is what makes us free to be fruitful, and this is the way that we love.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord to make us personally responsible for the things that we do: obedience to the Church; obedience to the Holy Father; being docile and allowing the image of Christ to be forged in us; letting God act in us and through us.</p>

<p>Identifying ourselves with Christ means being obedient in everything. I don’t decide to obey the Church in this, this, and this, but not in that, that, and that.</p>

<p>I’m not a cafeteria Catholic, that I pick and choose what I want to obey. It’s a very safe thing always to obey what the Church tells us.</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, Point 374, it says, “Obey with your lips, with your heart, and your mind. —It is not a man who is being obeyed, but God.”</p>

<p>It helps us to be very supernatural. The spirit of service in the world can come to have greater importance when it seems that nobody wants to obey.</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, Point 381, it says, “When will you be convinced that you have to obey? And you disobey if, instead of fulfilling your plan of life, you waste your time. You have to fill every minute with work, study, and interior life.”</p>

<p>Other people may be watching and learning from your self-giving.</p>

<p>We can turn to Our Lady, who “kept all these things carefully in her heart” (Luke 2:19,51).</p>

<p>In the <em>Furrow</em>, Point 415, it says, “Discipline does not seem at all heavy when it goes together with a clean and sincere love. Even if it costs you a lot, it unites you to the Loved One.”</p>

<p>“‘Did you not know that I must be about my Father’s business?’ And they did not understand the things he said to them” (Luke 2:49-50).</p>

<p>There were things that Mary and Joseph did not understand, but yet they obeyed.</p>

<p>Mary, may you teach us to have a greater, more refined obedience in all the things that we do.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>JM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Immaculate Heart of Mary (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-immaculate-heart-of-mary-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Immaculate Heart of Mary (2026)" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-immaculate-heart-of-mary-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-immaculate-heart-of-mary-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We are told in Scripture that Our Lady kept all these things, pondering them in her heart. After the consecration of the world to the most sweet and motherly heart of Mary in 1942, many petitions were sent to the Roman Pontiff, asking him to extend to the whole Church the devotion to the Immaculate Heart of Mary that already existed in some places. Pius XII agreed in 1945, certain to find in her most loving heart the safe haven in the midst of the tempests that everywhere assails us. Through the symbol of her heart, he said, we venerate in Mary her most pure and perfect love for God and her motherly love for each one of us. In that heart of hers, he said, we can find a refuge in the midst of all the difficulties and temptations of life. We ask her to prepare for us the safe way, the way by which we will soon reach her Son. “Iter para tutum.” Prepare the safe way.</p>

<p>We are told in Scripture, “My heart rejoices in your saving power” (1 Sam. 2:1). The entrance antiphon of today’s Mass says, “I will sing to the Lord for his goodness to me.” The feast of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, which was celebrated yesterday, helps us to consider the heart as an expression and symbol of a person’s innermost being. In the Gospels, the first time the heart of Mary is mentioned is to express all the richness of Our Lady’s interior life. We are told in St. Luke, “Mary kept all these things, pondering them in her heart” (Luke 2:19).</p>

<p>The preface of the Mass attributes a number of qualities to the heart of Mary. It is wise because she understood the meaning of the Scriptures as no other person had ever done, and she kept in it the memory of the words and things relating to the mystery of salvation. It is immaculate, that is, immune from any stain of sin. It is docile because she submitted so faithfully to God’s will and to every one of his wishes. It is new, according to the ancient prophecy of Ezekiel, “A new heart I will give you and a new spirit” (Ezek. 36:26), clothed in the newness of grace merited by Christ. It is humble because she imitated the humility of Christ, who said, “Learn from me for I am gentle and humble in heart” (Matt. 11:29).</p>

<p>It is simple, free from any duplicity and full of the spirit of truth. It is clean and thus able to see God according to the words of the Beatitude, “Blessed are the clean of heart for they shall see God” (Matt. 5:8). It is firm in her acceptance of the will of God. When Simeon announced to her that a sword of sorrow would pierce her heart, when persecution broke out against her Son, or when the moment of his death was at hand, Mary remained firm in her acceptance of God’s will. It is ready, for while Christ slept in the sepulchre, she kept watch in the expectation of his resurrection, just like the spouse in the Canticle of Canticles.</p>

<p>The Immaculate Heart of Mary is called above all “Temple of the Holy Spirit,” said the Second Vatican Council, by reason of her divine motherhood and because of the continuous and all-embracing habitation of the Holy Spirit in her soul. This sublime maternity that places Mary above all other created beings was accomplished in her immaculate heart before it was accomplished in her most pure womb. The Fathers affirm, says St. Augustine, that she conceived the Word to whom she gave birth according to the flesh, first of all in her heart according to faith.</p>

<p>By her immaculate heart full of faith and love, a heart that was humble and totally dedicated to the will of God, Mary merited to carry the Son of God in her virginal womb. She always protects us as a mother. As a mother protects her small child who is everywhere surrounded by dangers and difficulties, she helps us grow continuously. How can we possibly prevent ourselves from turning to her each day? Mary, star of the sea, be our guide.</p>

<p>In The Forge, St. Josemaría says, “Make this resolute request because there is no storm that can shipwreck the most sweet heart of Mary. When you see the storm coming, if you seek safety in the firm refuge that is Mary, there will be no danger of your being hurled off course or going down.” In her heart we find a safe harbor where it is impossible for us to flounder.</p>

<p>Mary treasured all these things, all these words, and pondered them in her heart, we are told in the Communion Antiphon. She kept in her heart the angel’s announcement about her divine motherhood. She kept it as she would keep a treasure. She kept forever in her heart all the things that happened on that night in Bethlehem: all that the shepherds said in front of the manger; the presence days or months later of the Magi with their gifts; the prophecy of Simeon; and the difficulties of her journey into Egypt.</p>

<p>Later a deep impression was made on her heart by the loss of her Son at the age of twelve in Jerusalem, and the words he spoke to her and St. Joseph when in a state of great distress they found him at last. “He went down with them and came to Nazareth and was obedient to them. And his mother kept all these things in her heart” (Luke 2:51).</p>

<p>During all the years she lived on earth, Mary never forgot the events that surrounded the death of her Son on the cross and the words she heard Jesus say as he hung there: “Woman, behold your son” (John 19:26). As he pointed to John, she saw each one of us and all mankind. From that moment on, she loved us in her heart with a mother’s love, with the same love as that with which she loved Jesus.</p>

<p>In us she recognized her Son. Just as he himself had said, “As you did it to one of these, the least of my brethren, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40). But Our Lady had already acted as a mother before the redemption was consummated on Calvary, for she had been our mother from the moment when, with her fiat, she gave her cooperation to the salvation of men.</p>

<p>In the account of the wedding at Cana, St. John reveals a truly maternal feature of the heart of Mary: her attentive concern for others. A mother’s heart is always attentive, vigilant. A mother never fails to notice anything that affects her child in any way. In Cana, the motherly heart of Mary bestows her caring vigilance on some relatives or friends of hers so that they can remedy a situation that might have been embarrassing, but would not have had any really serious consequences.</p>

<p>The Evangelist, by divine inspiration, wanted to show us that she is not indifferent to anything human and that nobody is excluded from her fervent tenderness. Our little faults and mistakes, just as much bigger faults, are the object of her concern. She is interested in everything that can affect our souls, from our little bouts of forgetfulness and anxiety to the greater worries that we might sometimes have.</p>

<p>She says to her Son, “They have no wine” (John 2:3). Everyone else is otherwise occupied. Nobody else is aware of it. Even though it seems that the hour of miracles is not yet come, she is able to make it arrive sooner. Mary knows the heart of her Son well and she knows how to reach it. Now in heaven her attitude has not changed. Through her intercession our prayers reach the Lord’s presence sooner, more certainly, and better.</p>

<p>That is why today we can address to her the ancient prayer of the Church: “Remember, O virgin mother, you who are always in his presence to speak good things about us. Say something to him in our favor. We need it so much.”</p>

<p>As we address this beautiful prayer to Our Lady, it is perhaps not a matter of proposing to ourselves yet another devotion, but of learning to talk to her with more trust, with the simplicity of small children who run to their mothers at every moment. They don’t talk to them only when they have great need, but also when they are worried by the little things that happen to them. Their mothers gladly help them to solve even the smallest problems. All earthly mothers have learnt this from the mother in heaven.</p>

<p>As we consider the splendor and holiness of the Immaculate Heart of Mary, we can examine today the depths of our own soul. Whether we are open and docile to the graces and inspirations of the Holy Spirit. Whether we jealously guard our heart from anything that could separate it from God. Whether we pull up by the roots our little feelings of resentment or of envy which tend to bed themselves down within it. We know that from our heart’s richness or its poverty our words and deeds will speak. We are told in St. Matthew, “The good person out of the good treasure of their heart, they bring forth good things” (Matt. 12:35).</p>

<p>From Our Lady there springs forth torrents of the graces of forgiveness, of mercy, of help in times of necessity. That is why we ask her today to give us a heart which is pure, human, understanding towards the defects of the people around us. We can ask her to make us kind to everyone, to help us to understand people’s sorrows, whatever their circumstances, and always to be ready to help anyone who needs our assistance. “Mother of fair love, pray for us.”</p>

<p>Teach us, said St. John Paul II, to love God and our fellow men as you have loved them. Make our love for others always patient, benign, full of respect for them. Make our joy always authentic and complete so that we can communicate it to everyone.</p>

<p>We can recall today when the needs have been pressing, how the Church and her children have turned to the most sweet heart of Mary so as to consecrate the world, nations, and families. We have always had the intuitive feeling, said Pius XII, that it is only in her sweet heart that we are safe.</p>

<p>Today we can dedicate to her once again all that we are and all that we have. We place on your motherly lap the days that seem good and those that seem bad, our illnesses, weakness, work, our tiredness, and our rest, together with the noble ideals that God has placed in our souls. We place especially in your hands our journey towards Christ so that you may keep it free from all dangers and guard it with tenderness and fortitude just as a mother does. Cor Mariae dulcissimum iter para tutum. Most sweet heart of Mary, prepare for me, for all, a safe way.</p>

<p>The opening prayer of today’s Mass says, “Father, you prepared the heart of the Virgin Mary to be a fitting home for your Holy Spirit. By her prayers may we become a more worthy temple of your glory.”</p>

<p>Mary’s humility pours forth in the Magnificat. “My soul magnifies the Lord and my spirit rejoices in God my savior” (Luke 1:46–47). This prayer has a singular beauty. A lady in Asia once told me that when I read those words I could spend hours and hours just contemplating them. Mary glorifies God for making her the mother of the Savior, which is why future generations will call her blessed. God always has a preference for the humble. He is always taking care of the chosen people in accordance with his promise and now gives them the greatest honor by becoming a Jew.</p>

<p>The soul of Mary overflows in the Magnificat—overflows with peace, with joy, and gratitude. St. Josemaría says, “How great is the value of humility.” “He has looked upon the lowliness of his handmaid” (Luke 1:48). Not of her faith, nor of her charity, nor of her immaculate purity that Our Mother speaks in the house of Zachary. Her joyful hymn sings, “Since he has looked on my humility all generations will call me blessed.”</p>

<p>Pope John Paul says in the words of the Magnificat, Mary’s personal experience, the ecstasy of her heart shines forth. In them shines a ray of the mystery of God, the glory of his ineffable holiness, the eternal love which as an irrevocable gift enters into human history. The Magnificat is a fabric woven from words of Sacred Scripture. It shows how Our Lady lived in a permanent conversation with the word of God and thus with God himself.</p>

<p>Don Javier Echevarría, former prelate of Opus Dei, said therefore let us learn from Mary and speak personally with the Lord, pondering and preserving God’s words in our lives and hearts so that they may become true food for each one of us.</p>

<p>Our Lady can help us to see that we are called to be an instrument in the hands of the artist. The virtue of humility can be the foundation and the source of a Christian spiritual life. Only if we live humility well can we live charity and unity. Sometimes we don’t realize how much Our Lord uses us as instruments. That humility hopefully leads us to a deeper knowledge, to honesty, to realism, to strength. It leads us to dedication, to give ourselves to something greater than ourselves. Mary, may you teach us to leave the progress of our personal apostolate in the hands of the Holy Spirit. Our Lord will do great things through us if we are humble. “Ask of me and I will give you the nations for your inheritance, the very ends of the earth for your domain” (Ps. 2:8).</p>

<p>In The Forge, St. Josemaría says to give oneself sincerely to others is so effective that God rewards it with a humility filled with cheerfulness. This virtue is a virtue of great souls who find their reward in the act of giving. The generous person knows how to give without demanding, giving and not just the heart. Mary, may you help us to maintain and to strengthen our generosity. Don’t let our generosity diminish with the passage of time. When there is generosity and self-giving in a family, there is peace, serenity, and joy.</p>

<p>Happiness in this world is found through giving and self-giving. Our Lady and St. Joseph are continual examples of that. Generosity expands the soul, and God loves generosity. The easiest way to save our soul is through self-forgetfulness. On the ruins of our self-love, God wants to build this castle of our sanctification.</p>

<p>We could examine our conscience and see: is there some thought at the back of my mind that I am superior? Help me, Mary, to realize that I am nothing. I am a trash can, a garbage can. But what happens if I am treated like that? I am nothing, but what happens when others treat me as nothing? St. Josemaría has said you are humble not when you humble yourself, but when you are humbled by others, humbled by life, humbled by health, humbled by finances, humbled by this world, and you bear it for Christ.</p>

<p>Our Lady teaches us the virtue of humility which frees us to love and serve others selflessly, for their sake rather than our own. True humility is not feeling bad about yourself or having a low opinion of yourself or thinking yourself as inferior to others. True humility frees us from the preoccupation with ourselves, whereas a low self-opinion can tend to focus our attention on ourselves.</p>

<p>Mary, may I learn from you how to be more humble, to be truly humble of heart as Jesus has asked of us. Our limitations are no obstacle to being faithful. It is enough to be humble and allow God to act through our correspondence, to work great things in our life. First and foremost, to let ourselves be formed. If we don’t let ourselves be formed over the passage of time, then God may not be able to do all sorts of things with us. “God resists the proud but gives his grace to the humble” (James 4:6). We see that Our Lady was all the time humble of heart.</p>

<p>Mary, on this beautiful feast day, we have greater recourse to your Immaculate Heart, and ask you to fashion our heart after the wonderful model of your beautiful heart.</p>

<p><em>I thank you my God for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Multiplication of the Loaves and Fish</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-multiplication-of-the-loaves-and-fish/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Multiplication of the Loaves and Fish" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-multiplication-of-the-loaves-and-fish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-multiplication-of-the-loaves-and-fish/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We’re told in the Gospel of today: “Jesus went across the Sea of Galilee. And a large crowd followed him because they saw the signs he was performing on the sick. Jesus went up on the mountain, and there he sat down with his disciples. The Jewish feast of the Passover was near. When Jesus raised his eyes and saw that a large crowd was coming to him, he said to Philip, ‘Where can we buy enough food for them to eat?’” (John 6:1-5).</p>

<p>The story is the story of the multiplication of the loaves and the fish. It takes place on the shores of the Sea of Galilee. Our Lord is speaking to thousands of people, performing healings, and then there is a concern about the food for the people.</p>

<p>What we just read is in John Chapter 6. Each of the evangelists tells the story; it’s an indication of its importance.</p>

<p>In St. Luke, it has the apostles saying to Our Lord, “Send the crowd away, to go into the villages and the country round about to lodge and get provisions” (Luke 9:12).</p>

<p>The disciples themselves were also tired. They were in a remote place. People had to walk and go to the villages in order to buy food.</p>

<p>Then Our Lord challenges the apostles. “Where can we buy enough food for them to eat?” He is going to draw out the apostles, as He does on many other occasions, to realize their situation, to help them to see what we have and what we don’t have.</p>

<p>Our Lord is going to, in this way, let them see the greatness of the miracle that He is about to perform.</p>

<p>In St. Luke, He says, “You give them something to eat” (Luke 9:13).</p>

<p>These words must have surprised the apostles. They don’t understand. How can we give them something to eat? We don’t have anything.</p>

<p>“We have no more than five loaves and two fish—unless we are to go and buy food for all these people” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Our Lord seems to have the impression that He is very clear about what He intends to do. In St. Luke, He says, “Make the people sit down in companies of fifty” (Luke 9:13-14).</p>

<p>In St. John, it says, “He said this to test Philip, because he himself knew what he was going to do. Philip answered him, ‘Two hundred days’ wages worth of food would not be enough for each of them to have a little’” (John 6:6-7).</p>

<p>In another account He says, “two hundred denarii, which is almost a year’s wages” (Mark 6:37).</p>

<p>The apostles realize what they don’t have; what they need. Our Lord is letting them see the picture very clearly.</p>

<p>“One of his disciples, Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, said to him, ‘There is a boy here with five barley loaves and two fish, but what good are these for so many?” (John 6:8-9).</p>

<p>Our Lord is undeterred by these words—exactly what He wanted to hear from the apostles’ own lips: ‘We have nothing.’</p>

<p>“He said, ‘Have the people recline.’ Now there was a great deal of grass in that place. So the men reclined, about five thousand in number. Then Jesus took the loaves, gave thanks, and distributed them to those who were reclining, and also as much of the fish as they wanted” (John 6:10-11).</p>

<p>Our Lord takes the five loaves and the two fish in His hands and He addresses His Heavenly Father. He begins to break the loaves, divide the fish, and give them to the disciples, who distribute them to the crowd. And the food does not end until they all have their fill.</p>

<p>This is an image of the miracle of the Eucharist in the Mass that is going to take place for all time. It is going to be a multiplying of the bread, the Bread of Life, to reach every last soul, to fill in the hunger of every single person in the whole history of the world.</p>

<p>This is an important miracle. That is why all the evangelists tell the miracle. It shows the power of Our Lord, and at the same time, His compassion—His compassion for the people. He realizes they are hungry. He needs to look after their needs.</p>

<p>This is one of the great signs in the public life of Our Lord. It also foretells what will be the great memorial of His Sacrifice: the Mass, the Eucharist, the Sacrament of His Body and Blood, offered up for the salvation of the world.</p>

<p>The Eucharist in some ways is the culmination of Our Lord’s entire life: a single act of love towards His loving Father and towards each one of us.</p>

<p>As with the miracle of the loaves, Our Lord took the bread in His hands, said a prayer to His Father, broke the bread, and gave it to His disciples, and He does the same with the wine.</p>

<p>In that moment of the Last Supper and the eve of His Passion, with that gesture, He wanted to leave a testament of His new and eternal Covenant, a perpetual memory of the Paschal Mystery of His death and resurrection. All this is being foretold with the multiplication of the loaves and the fish.</p>

<p>We are invited each day and each year to renew our wonder and our joy. Easter is a time for joy, hope, optimism, renewal of our faith, particularly in this great gift of the Eucharist that God has given to us.</p>

<p>Lord, help us to receive it with gratitude, not in a passive, habitual way. Don’t ever let us get accustomed.</p>

<p>Help us to make each one of our Communions a very fervent Communion, so that we truly renew our “Amen” every time we approach the altar: “The Body of Christ.” “Amen.”</p>

<p>Lord, may it be an Amen that comes from our heart, a committed one. We give ourselves to you again in this particular moment, so that we realize that it is Jesus who I’m receiving.</p>

<p>I receive Him in a very committed way. It’s Our Lord who saved me. He comes to give me the strength to live, the Bread of Life. It is Jesus, the living Jesus.</p>

<p>Lord, help us to receive you each time as if it was our First Communion, so that we approach you with the piety of children, small children who perhaps don’t understand the gifts, through those physical signs and symbols around them, to get the message that something very important is taking place.</p>

<p>“Unless you become like little children, you cannot enter the kingdom of heaven” (Matt. 18:3).</p>

<p>This whole story is a story of how the Incarnation reaches each particular person— where they are, where they live—so that each person can live where he cannot reach on his own: the Bread of Life, the promise of immortality: “If you eat my body and drink my blood, I shall have life in you and I will raise you up on the last day” (John 6:54).</p>

<p>The miracle of the feeding of the 5,000 is both a reminder and a promise. It is a reminder of the prophet Elisha, who fed a hundred people with twenty loaves of barley and had some left over, a miracle that was performed by the Word of the Lord in the Book of Kings (2 Kings 4:38-44).</p>

<p>Our Lord connects His ability to feed the thousands with very little to the miracle of the manna, but the feeding was also something very miraculous—the anticipation of the great gift of the Eucharist.</p>

<p>This everlasting covenant, anticipated in the Old Testament by Isaiah (Isa. 6:6-7) comes to full fruition. Divine gift and abundance are perfectly realized and offered.</p>

<p>“The miracles of the multiplication of the loaves”—we’re told in the <em>Catechism</em>—"when the Lord says the blessing, breaks and distributes the loaves through his disciples to feed the multitude, prefigure the superabundance of this unique bread of his Eucharist” (<em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point 1335). The message of superabundance.</p>

<p>Christ is always there for us and will be until the end of time. “I am with you always” (Matt. 28:20).</p>

<p>Thank you, Lord, for this great gift. May I ponder it. May I react with wonder and amazement and joy and thanksgiving, so that I savor the gift.</p>

<p>We’re told in Scripture, <em>Si scires donum Dei–“</em>If you knew the gift of God” (John 4:10).</p>

<p>Our Lord tells the disciples to feed the people on their own, distribute the loaves among the people. He wanted them to recognize their limits—not to humiliate them—but to teach them true humility.</p>

<p>The words of the Psalmist say, “The hand of the Lord feeds us; He answers all our needs” (Ps. 145:16).</p>

<p>The apostles are fully aware of what is lacking. ‘How are we to buy bread so that these people may eat?’</p>

<p>Our Lord begins this great miracle with this question. It is a significant prelude to the long speech in which He reveals Himself to the world as the real Bread of Life who came down from heaven (John 6:35-59).</p>

<p>“One of his disciples, Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, said to him, ‘There is a boy here with five barley loaves and two fish’” (John 6:8-9).</p>

<p>Andrew looks around and all he finds is a boy. A small boy. But he is very little. “What is that among so many?” (John 6:9).</p>

<p>That is like the trigger that releases Our Lord to start the whole miracle. “Make the people recline” (John 6:10). Let them sit down.</p>

<p>The apostles perceive the problem of feeding so many people and they bring to Jesus what they have. The miracle was not worked from nothing, but from a simple sharing of what this little boy had brought to Him.</p>

<p>Our Lord teaches us that He wants to work many miracles—not from nothing, but rather, with the small things that we bring to Him. Our Lord doesn’t ask us for what we do not have.</p>

<p>But at the same time, He wants us to do what is there on our part. He makes us see that if each person offers the little that they have, the miracle can always be repeated.</p>

<p>Our Lord wants our effort, our total self-giving, our effort to show Him that we really want this particular miracle. We want this to happen and therefore, we do all in our power to make it happen.</p>

<p>We move heaven and earth. We use all the human means. Then God is going to come and multiply all our little acts of love, and our generosity, and our commitment, and needs us to share in His gift.</p>

<p>But like the apostles, maybe He wants us to see our nothingness. Like them, we have followed Our Lord and we try to continue to follow Him. But we can also ask ourselves, ‘With what sort of attitude?</p>

<p>Help me to follow you, Lord, with the faith of the apostles, the faith they are building up in these days after Easter.</p>

<p>Our Lord expected a certain faith from them, overcoming that attitude of incomprehension. Our Lord presented Himself on this occasion just like Moses, who had fed the people of Israel in the desert during the Exodus (Ex. 16:32-35). He presents Himself like Elisha, who fed all those people (2 Kings 4:38-44).</p>

<p>Our Lord manifested Himself, and manifests Himself today, as the one who is capable of satisfying the hunger of the world, the hunger of our hearts.</p>

<p>“I am the bread of life. He who comes to me shall not hunger. He who believes in me shall never thirst” (John 6:35).</p>

<p>When we look around us in the world, we find modern man is very hungry: hungry for truth, hungry for justice, for love, for peace, for beauty. Above all, hungry for God.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “We must hunger for God!” (Augustine, <em>Commentary on Psalm 146</em>). Each one of us has experienced that hunger. That’s why we are here. That’s why we come to look for the Bread of Life on a daily basis.</p>

<p>We have this daily hunger that we know we want to satisfy, and in that Bread of Life, we also receive all those other wonderful things: love, peace, beauty, justice.</p>

<p>It is the heavenly Father who gives us this bread. Lord, “give us this bread always” (John 6:34), to feed this hunger.</p>

<p>That bread which we need, first and foremost, is Christ, who gives Himself to us in the sacramental signs of the Eucharist, and makes us hear, at every Mass, the words of the Last Supper:</p>

<p>“Take and eat, all of you. This is my body, offered for you in sacrifice” (Matt. 26:26).</p>

<p>We’re told in the Second Vatican Council, “The unity of all believers who form one body in Christ is both expressed and brought about. All men are called to this union with Christ, who is the light of the world, from whom we go forth, through whom we live, and toward whom our journey leads us (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 3, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>Christ is our focus. We’re called to be Christocentric.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to have that hunger and to foster that hunger to prepare for Communion each day very well, maybe with those prayers that we find, in the Missal, of St. Thomas Aquinas or St. Bonaventure, or with our own personal words that we make up like little children that express the concrete desire of our heart.</p>

<p>Help us to take care of those moments of thanksgiving. May they be burning moments. “Did not our hearts burn within us as we went along the road?” (Luke 24:32).</p>

<p>The bread that we need is also the bread of the Word of God: “Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceeds from the mouth of God” (Matt. 4:4). We need the Bread and we need the Word.</p>

<p>Thank you, Lord, for the custom of reading a few words of the Gospel every day. Feed my soul with this Word of God.</p>

<p>Men can utter words of high value, but often the words of men are insufficient, ambiguous, disappointing, biased, while “the Word of God is full of truth,” we’re told in Scripture (<em>cf</em>. John 17:17). “It’s upright,” we’re told in the Psalms. The Psalms also say it’s “stable and remains forever” (Ps. 119:160, 89).</p>

<p>We need to listen to this Word continually. Assume it as the criterion of our way of thinking and acting. Get to know it. That familiarity with the Word of God is a great good in our life.</p>

<p>We achieve this by our regular reading and personal meditation. We have to make it ours day by day in our behavior and put it into practice.</p>

<p>The bread is also the bread of grace. We receive grace in all the sacraments. We need that grace. We have to hunger for it, invoke it, ask for it with sincere humility and tireless constancy, well aware that it’s the most precious thing we can possess.</p>

<p>We will come and make our abode with Him (John 14:23, 15:4-10). We become spiritual millionaires when we are in the state of grace.</p>

<p>The path that’s laid out for us along the path of our Christian vocation, which is often a mysterious one, is one of providential love, often incomprehensible on the human plane, sometimes hard and difficult.</p>

<p>But Our loving Father has given us the bread from heaven to nourish us and strengthen us, to encourage us in this pilgrimage of faith, which our vocation is.</p>

<p>We have that nutrient that keeps us going. We’re told in <em>The Way</em> how the person said, “So many Communions. I don’t see the fruit of all the Communions” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Way,</em> Point 534).</p>

<p>But you see, often the fruit of all those Communions is working silently within us. We don’t remember the food we had yesterday, but if we hadn’t eaten it, we’d be in a very different situation.</p>

<p>That bread from heaven keeps us going, keeps us in the right direction, keeps us on the straight and narrow.</p>

<p>We’re told by St. Augustine, “We can understand very well how your Eucharist is daily food. The faithful know in fact what they receive, and it is good that they should receive the daily bread necessary for this time.</p>

<p>“They pray for themselves to become good, to be persevering in goodness, faith, and a good life. ... The Word of God, which is explained to us, and in a certain sense broken every day, is also daily bread” (St. Augustine, <em>Sermon 8 on the New Testament</em>).</p>

<p>May Christ Jesus always multiply this bread for us. Lord, help me to appreciate the great gift, to penetrate the meaning of this multiplication of the loaves and the fish, all the deeper messages that are there, so that we get them.</p>

<p>“When they had their fill, he said to the disciples, ‘Gather the fragments left over, so that nothing will be wasted’” (John 6:12).</p>

<p>There’s an end part to this great event. It’s environmentally friendly. Our Lord is aware. He has eco-sensitivity: “Gather up all the pieces.”</p>

<p>But that’s going to also put a different light on the whole miracle. “So they collected them and they filled twelve wicker baskets with fragments from the five barley loaves that had been more than they could eat” (John 6:13).</p>

<p>This is an indication of the superabundance. It’s also a reminder of the little details, the small things. Five thousand people had eaten it. It was something incredible. But let’s pick up the pieces. Let’s take care of this little detail. Let’s finish things well. It’s very much part of our spirit.</p>

<p>“When the people saw the sign that he had done, they said, ‘This is truly the Prophet, the one who is to come into the world.’ Since Jesus knew they were going to come and carry him off to make him king, he withdrew again to the mountain alone” (John 6:14-15).</p>

<p>This is sometimes referred to as the Messianic Secret. It was not yet time for Our Lord to be revealed fully of who He is. The hour has not yet come. So He shies away from these occasions.</p>

<p>Also, they wanted to make Him into a sort of a human king, a political Messiah. This withdrawal of Our Lord shows, and He’s come to emphasize, “My kingdom is not of this world” (John 18:36). I’m not just a human political Messiah; I’m a supernatural Messiah.</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “As often as you eat this bread and drink the cup, you proclaim the Lord’s death until he comes” (1 Cor. 11:26).</p>

<p>“As often.” Do we proclaim the redemptive death, and kindle in our hearts, our hope of our definitive meeting with Him?</p>

<p>“When we eat this bread and drink this cup, we proclaim your death, Lord Jesus, until you come in glory” (Roman Missal, <em>Mystery of Faith</em>).</p>

<p>We remind ourselves of the great things to come, that promise of eternal life: “I will raise you up on the last day” (John 6:40).</p>

<p>St. Luke remarks, “All who had eaten were satisfied. They took up what was left over in twelve baskets of broken pieces” (Luke 9:17).</p>

<p>“The uninterrupted multiplication in the Church of the Bread of new life for the people of every race and culture” is foretold (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, Solemnity of Corpus Christi, June 22, 2000).</p>

<p>Nobody is left out. The Bread of Life is for everybody. The missionary Church has brought the Mass to every last corner of the earth.</p>

<p>“This sacramental ministry is entrusted to the apostles and to their successors. Faithful to the command of the Master, they go out and never cease to break and distribute the Eucharistic bread from generation to generation.” And so, here we are. “The People of God receive it with devout participation” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>St. Josemaría has encouraged us in that spirit to take care of our altars, of our oratories. Take care of the things of cult, of the liturgy, the external physical signs that lead us to the Bread of Life.</p>

<p>“With this Bread of Life, a remedy of immortality, countless saints and martyrs were nourished and from it drew the strength to resist all the sufferings that God had sent them. They believed in the words of Jesus that he spoke in Capernaum, ‘I myself am the living bread come down from heaven. If anyone eats this bread, he will live forever’” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Christ is the living bread, the Bread of Life. “The bread that I will give is my flesh for the life of the world” (John 6:51).</p>

<p>Scandalous words that made some people no longer walk with Him. They went away. They could not take it (John 6:66). Our Lord hopes that we will not go away, that we will stay close.</p>

<p>Our Lord wanted the mystery of our salvation, “the mystery of his saving presence in the world...to be linked with the sacrament of the Eucharist. He wanted to make himself the bread which is broken so that everyone can be nourished by his very life through participation in the sacrament of his Body and Blood” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>All the people “who listened to Him were astonished at his discourse in Capernaum. We also find this language hard to understand” (<em>cf.</em> John 6:60).</p>

<p>But therefore, we make acts of faith. “Lord, I believe; help my unbelief” (Mark 9:24). “Increase my faith” (<em>cf</em>. Luke 17:5).</p>

<p>Our Lord asked the apostles, “Will you also go away?” And they say those very useful words, “Lord, to whom will we go? You have the words of eternal life” (John 6:67-68).</p>

<p>Lord, to whom will we go? There is nowhere else to go. We come to you. We want you to stay with us.</p>

<p>The words of the disciples on the road to Emmaus: “Stay with us, Lord” (Luke 24:29). Every day, with our words, with our presence, with our coming close to Our Lord in the Blessed Eucharist, we say those same words, “Stay with us, Lord.”</p>

<p>Pope John Paul II has written an encyclical entitled with the words, “In the Blessed Eucharist” (<em>Ecclesia de Eucharistia</em>). Stay with us now and always. Give me strength for this particular day.</p>

<p>St. Augustine comments, “Who is the Bread of heaven, but Christ? But in order that man might eat Angels’ Bread, the Lord of Angels was made Man. For if he had not been made Man, we should not have his Flesh; if we had not his Flesh, we should not eat the Bread of the Altar” (St. Augustine, <em>Sermon 130</em>).</p>

<p>The Blessed Eucharist is the human being’s ongoing encounter with God in which the Lord makes himself our food and gives himself to us to transform us into him” (Pope Benedict XVI, <em>Angelus,</em> July 29, 2012).</p>

<p>Over time we get transformed into Christ.</p>

<p>We can turn to the “Woman of the Eucharist” (John Paul II, Encyclical, <em>Ecclesia de Eucharistia</em>, Point 53, April 17, 2003), who must have received Our Lord in the Masses of St. John with enormous piety.</p>

<p>The words “the Body of Christ” must have meant something very special to Our Lady. And her “Amen” must also have been something very special.</p>

<p>Mary, may you help us to savor each day, in a greater way, this great mystery of the Blessed Eucharist in our lives.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em><br />
<br />
<em>GD</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Third Sunday of St. Joseph (2026)</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-third-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Third Sunday of St. Joseph (2026)" /><published>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-third-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-third-sunday-of-st-joseph-2026/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>It’s customary for saints to be outstanding and to become well known for some particular virtue or aspect of their struggle which makes them conspicuous exemplars for the faithful.</p>

<p>For example, St. Francis of Assisi is revered for his heroic love of poverty. The Holy Curé of Ars is a model of extraordinary priestly service to souls. St. Thomas More is remembered for his devotion to both God and country, but to God first, even at the price of martyrdom.</p>

<p>In the case of St. Joseph, we have only to dwell upon the words of St. Matthew: “Joseph, the husband of Mary” (Matt. 1:16). Here we have the summary of Joseph’s vocation and the setting for his sanctity.</p>

<p>With the exception of Jesus, no one ever cared for Our Lady more than St. Joseph did. No one protected her with more vigilance. No one has ever given his life to the Lord with such total generosity as the Holy Patriarch did.</p>

<p>God’s loving providence ordained that Jesus would be born into a human family. Joseph was not only the guardian of Mary; he was also her husband.</p>

<p>According to Jewish custom of the time, matrimony involved two distinct ceremonies separated by a period of time: betrothal and the formal wedding.</p>

<p>In the ceremony of betrothal, the spouses made a firm promise as regards their future wedding and matrimonial union. The bridegroom would place the rings in the hands of the future bride and both would receive a blessing. From that moment on, the woman would be known as the wife of so-and-so.</p>

<p>The normal interval between betrothal and the wedding ceremony was about the space of a year. It was within that period that Our Lady received the news of her vocation from the angel Gabriel, and that the Incarnation took place. At the same time, St. Joseph learned about God’s plans through a dream. We’re told in St. Matthew, “So Joseph, arising from sleep, did as the angel of the Lord had commanded him, and took unto him his wife” (Matt. 1:24).</p>

<p>“He took Mary as his wife,” we’re told by John Paul II, “in humble acceptance of the mystery of her maternity. He accepted her along with her Son who would come to the world by the action of the Holy Spirit. St. Joseph can therefore be compared to Our Lady in his great docility to the will of God as revealed to him by the angel” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Redemptoris custos</em>, Point 3, August 15, 1989).</p>

<p>The wedding ceremony was the fulfillment of the marital contract entered into at betrothal. It was customary for the bride to be brought to the home of the bridegroom amid great rejoicing (Franz Michel Willam, <em>Life of Mary</em>). In this manner, the union was validated before the entire community, and, therefore, her offspring would be recognized as legitimate.</p>

<p>It is of the essence of the marital union that the spouses give their bodies to one another. Because the marriage of Mary and Joseph was an authentic marriage, these reciprocal rights existed in their union. Because of what they had learned from God, by mutual agreement, Mary and Joseph had renounced the exercise of these rights. The denial of them would have been a cause for annulment.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says that in the case of Joseph and Mary, however, we have something different because here we have a case of mutual voluntary renunciation. This understanding was the fruit of a most refined, prayerful environment.</p>

<p>We can get some understanding of this union if we look upon it and try to comprehend it with a clean heart. Joseph became a virgin for the sake of the Virgin. He protected her with great refinement and affection (Augustine, <em>Of Holy Virginity</em>).</p>

<p>St. Thomas gives various reasons for the appropriateness of the Virgin’s being united to Joseph in true matrimony (Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part III, Question 29). It was appropriate and necessary so that Mary’s pregnancy would not be a cause of scandal among relatives and neighbors.</p>

<p>It was useful that Jesus would be born into a human family as an apparently legitimate son, since no one would thus know of the mystery of His supernatural conception. It was helpful that Jesus and Mary would find support for Mother and Child in their life with St. Joseph. In this way, the arrival of the Messiah would also be hidden from the devil.</p>

<p>With this union Mary gives due honor both to the state of matrimony and virginity. Our Lady loved Joseph with a deep and pure love. She knew and understood him well, and she wants us to go to him for assistance.</p>

<p>Joseph and Mary are the model husband and wife. They are the perfect image of total self-giving to God with an undivided heart, in either apostolic celibacy or virginity lived in the middle of the world.</p>

<p>St. John Paul says, “Virginity or celibacy for the sake of the Kingdom of God not only does not contradict the dignity of marriage but presupposes it and confirms it. Marriage and virginity or celibacy are two ways of expressing and living the one mystery of the covenant of God with his people” (John Paul II, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Familiaris consortio</em>, Point 16, December 22, 1981).</p>

<p>Joseph and Mary were married in Nazareth, and here in this little village, the Word became flesh. In the wedding ceremony, Mary would receive a small dowry as was customary. It would consist of a jewel of modest value, clothing, and furniture. Perhaps she would have received a patrimony of some land.</p>

<p>In any event, all this did not add up to very much. But when someone is poor, gifts of little worth take on an enhanced value. Since Joseph was a carpenter, he would have built the best furniture possible for their home. The news of the wedding must have passed from one town to another: ‘Mary has married Joseph the carpenter.’</p>

<p>Our Lady wanted these ceremonies to take place even though she had given herself completely to God. “Marriage to a man like Joseph gave her security and tranquility” (Marie-Joseph Lagrange, <em>The Gospel of Jesus Christ</em>).</p>

<p>Joseph and Mary allowed themselves to be led by divine inspiration. We can apply to this holy couple the following truth taught by St. Thomas: “It is natural and typical that the just find in all their works inspiration from the Holy Spirit” (<em>cf</em>. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologiae</em>, Part III, Question 36).</p>

<p>God was attentive to the human love between Joseph and Mary. He supplied abundant graces to strengthen that devotion.</p>

<p>Joseph eventually came to understand that Our Lady’s Child was from the Holy Spirit and that she was to be the Mother of the Redeemer. As a consequence, he would have loved Our Lady more than ever.</p>

<p>One writer said, “Joseph loved Our Lady, not with a brotherly love but with a conjugal love. It was so deep that any carnal relation was made totally superfluous. So refined was it that he became not only a witness of Mary’s virginal purity—virgin before birth, in birth, and after birth as the Church teaches us—but he became its custodian” (Federico Suarez, <em>Joseph of Nazareth</em>). God the Father took the greatest care to prepare this virginal family for His only-begotten Son.</p>

<p>Painters have traditionally depicted Joseph as an elderly man in order to emphasize the perpetual virginity of Mary. But it’s more likely that Joseph was not much older than his wife.</p>

<p>“You don’t have to wait to be old or lifeless to practice the virtue of chastity. Purity comes from love; and the strength and joy of youth are no obstacle for noble love. Joseph had a young heart and a young body when he married Mary, when he learned of the mystery of her divine motherhood, when he lived in her company,” said St. Josemaría, “respecting the integrity God wished to give the world as one more sign that he had come to share the life of his creatures” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Christ Is Passing By</em>, Point 40).</p>

<p>We can ask the Holy Patriarch to teach us how to live this kind of love in the circumstances in which God has called us. We want this love “that lights up the [heart]” (T. Aquinas, <em>On Charity</em>) so that we may perform our ordinary work with joy.</p>

<p>In the Gospels, St. Joseph is repeatedly referred to as “father” (Luke 2:27,33,41,48). Without a doubt, this is how Jesus called the Holy Patriarch in the intimacy of their home in Nazareth.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. Luke that Jesus was known in the community as the “son of Joseph” (Luke 3:23). Joseph certainly fulfilled the duties corresponding to those of a father in the Holy Family.</p>

<p>He gave Jesus His name. He led the Holy Family into Egypt. He decided where they were to live on their return to Palestine. Jesus obeyed Joseph as if he were His natural father: “And he went down with them and came to Nazareth, and was subject to them” (Luke 2:51).</p>

<p>Jesus was conceived in a miraculous way by the action of the Holy Spirit. He was born from the virginal womb of Mary according to the divine Will.</p>

<p>One writer says God wanted to be born within a family, to be raised by a father and mother. Just as God chose Mary to be His Mother, God chose Joseph from among all men to be His father (<em>cf</em>. Jose Antonio of the Child Jesus, <em>St. Joseph</em>).</p>

<p>St. Joseph behaved and felt like a father towards Jesus. He had an ardent love for the Son of God and for the Mother of God. This love was even greater than the natural love a natural father may have for his natural son. This is because Joseph cared for Jesus as a son and at the same time worshipped Him as his God.</p>

<p>He was greatly moved at the sight of a God who would give Himself so generously for the good of mankind. This amazing spectacle caused Joseph to love Jesus in an ever-increasing way.</p>

<p>Joseph loved Jesus almost as if he had really begotten Him. He looked upon Jesus as a wondrous gift that God had bestowed on him in his ordinary human life.</p>

<p>Joseph consecrated his energies, his time, his greatest concern, his care to this gift. He sought no compensation other than the opportunity to give more of himself. His love was strong and sweet, tranquil and fervent, emotional and tender.</p>

<p>One writer said, “We can think of Joseph with Jesus in his arms, teaching the child songs, watching over his sleep, making Him little toys, treating the child with the affection shown by any parent” (<em>cf</em>. Michael Gasnier, <em>Joseph the Silent</em>).</p>

<p>Joseph must have been humbled at the awesome thought that the Son of God also wanted to be his son. In our prayer today, we can ask the Holy Patriarch to teach us how to love and cherish Jesus as he himself did.</p>

<p>“Popular trust in St. Joseph is seen in the expression ‘Go to Joseph,’ which reminds us of the famine in Egypt when the Egyptians begged Pharaoh for bread. He in turn replied, ‘Go to Joseph; what he says to you, do’ (Gen. 41:55).</p>

<p>“Pharaoh was referring to Joseph the son of Jacob, who was sold into slavery because of the jealousy of his brothers (<em>cf</em>. Gen. 37:11-28), and who—according to the biblical account— subsequently became Viceroy of Egypt (<em>cf</em>. Gen. 41:41-44).</p>

<p>“As a descendant of David (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 1:16-20), from whose stock Jesus was to spring according to the promise made to David by the prophet Nathan (<em>cf</em>. 2 Sam 7), and as the spouse of Mary of Nazareth, St. Joseph stands at the crossroads between the Old and New Testaments” (Pope Francis, Apostolic Letter, <em>Patris corde</em>, Point 1, December 8, 2020).</p>

<p>“If the first stage of all true interior healing is to accept our personal history and embrace even the things in life that we did not choose, we need now also to add another important element: creative courage.</p>

<p>“This emerges especially in the way we deal with difficulties. In the face of difficulty, we can either give up and walk away, or somehow engage with it. At times, difficulties bring out resources we did not even think we had.</p>

<p>“As we read the infancy narratives, we may often wonder why God did not act in a more direct and clear way. Yet God acts through events and people. Joseph was the man chosen by God to guide the beginnings of the history of redemption. He was the true ‘miracle’ by which God saves the child and his mother. God acted by trusting in Joseph’s creative courage.</p>

<p>“Arriving in Bethlehem and finding no lodging where Mary could give birth, Joseph took a stable and, as best he could, turned it into a welcoming home for the Son of God coming into the world (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:6-7). Faced with imminent danger from Herod, who wanted to kill the child, Joseph was warned once again in a dream to protect the child, and rose in the middle of the night to prepare the flight into Egypt (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 2:13-14).</p>

<p>“A superficial reading of these stories can often give the impression that the world is at the mercy of the strong and mighty, but the ‘good news’ of the Gospel consists in showing that, for all the arrogance and violence of worldly powers, God always finds a way to carry out his saving plan. So too, our lives may at times seem to be at the mercy of the powerful, but the Gospel shows us what counts. God always finds a way to save us, provided we show the same creative courage as the carpenter of Nazareth, who was able to turn a problem into a possibility by trusting always in divine providence.</p>

<p>“If at times God seems not to help us, [surely] this does not mean that we have been abandoned, but instead are being trusted to plan, to be creative, and to find solutions ourselves.</p>

<p>“That kind of creative courage was shown by the friends of the paralytic, who lowered him from the roof in order to bring him to Jesus when they couldn’t access him by any other means because of the crowd (<em>cf</em>. Luke 5:17-26). Difficulties did not stand in the way of those friends’ boldness and persistence. They were convinced that Jesus could heal the man, and ‘finding no way to bring him in because of the crowd, they went up on the roof and let him down with his bed through the tiles into the middle of the crowd in front of Jesus” (Pope Francis, <em>ibid</em>., Point 5).</p>

<p>They were full of initiative and daring. They vandalized the roof in order to get their friend to Jesus.</p>

<p>“When he saw their faith, he said, ‘Friend, your sins are forgiven you’ (Luke 5:20). Jesus recognized the creative faith with which they sought to bring their sick friend to him.</p>

<p>“The Gospel does not tell us how long Our Lady, St. Joseph, and the child remained in Egypt. But certainly they would have needed to eat, to find a home, and employment. It does not take much imagination to fill in those details. The Holy Family had to face concrete problems like every other family, like so many of our migrant brothers and sisters who today risk their lives to escape misfortune and hunger.” We can consider “St. Joseph as the special patron of all those forced to leave their native lands because of war, hatred, persecution, and poverty.</p>

<p>“At the end of every account in which Joseph plays a role, the Gospel tells us that he gets up, takes the child and his mother, and does what God commanded him (<em>cf</em>. Matt. 1:24; 2:14,21). Jesus and Our Lady his Mother are the most precious treasure of our faith.</p>

<p>“In the divine plan of salvation, the Son is inseparable from his Mother, from Mary, who ‘advanced, in her pilgrimage of faith, and faithfully persevered in her union with her Son until she stood at the cross’ (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 58, November 21, 1964).</p>

<p>“We should always consider whether we ourselves are protecting Jesus and Mary, for they are mysteriously entrusted to our responsibility, care, and safekeeping.</p>

<p>“The Son of the Almighty came into our world in a state of great vulnerability. He needed to be defended, protected, cared for, and raised by Joseph. God trusted Joseph, as did Mary, who found in him someone who would not only save her life, but would always provide for her and her child.</p>

<p>“In this sense, St. Joseph could not be other than the Guardian of the Church, because the Church is the continuation of the Body of Christ in history, even as Mary’s motherhood is reflected in the motherhood of the Church (<em>Catechism of the Catholic Church</em>, Point 963-970).</p>

<p>“In his continued protection of the Church, Joseph continues to protect the child and his mother, and we too, by our love for the Church, continue to love the child and his mother.</p>

<p>“That child would go on to say, ‘As you did it to one of the least of these who are members of my family, you did it to me’ (Matt. 25:40). Consequently, every poor, needy, suffering, or dying person, every stranger, every prisoner, every infirm person is ‘the child’ whom Joseph continues to protect.</p>

<p>“For this reason, St. Joseph is invoked as protector of the unfortunate, the needy, exiles, the afflicted, the poor, and the dying. Consequently, the Church cannot fail to show a special love for the least of our brothers and sisters, for Jesus showed a particular concern for them and personally identified with them.</p>

<p>“From St. Joseph, we have to learn that same care and responsibility. We have to learn to love the child and his mother, to love the sacraments and charity, to love the Church and the poor. Each of these realities is always the child and his mother” (<em>ibid</em>., Point 5).</p>

<p>Joseph does not resign himself passively, but he takes the initiative and he puts his optimism and cheerfulness into play. He can be a great example for us of <em>beginning again</em> in all sorts of situations.</p>

<p>He can teach us that we’ll win fighting. He can help us to have a warlike mentality. From his example, we can have the assurance of permanence and perseverance in the hardest of battles without giving in, without getting tired.</p>

<p>The obstacles in the course of our life, in our marriage, in our work, in our health, in our finances, the difficulties, the contradictions which without doubt exist, far from disturbing our path towards victory or making us feel nostalgic for some comfort, can make us stronger and more determined. Those things can lift us up onto a new plane.</p>

<p>St. Augustine liked to say, “There is no soul who works for God who does not grow when faced with difficulties.” The difficulties form part of the reality on which our life is built. We live and work in real situations, not Disneyland. We need to be strong people, sons and daughters of God.</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lord in our prayer to help us to take advantage of the big and small challenges of every day, to grow in faith, hope, and love like St. Joseph did.</p>

<p>A Chinese proverb says, “A gem cannot be polished without friction, nor a man made perfect without trials.” We have the help of grace. Nothing should be able to shift us from our place in the battle.</p>

<p>If at times we can’t see properly, then we should let ourselves be guided by those with the grace of state. If the struggle is uphill, we don’t abandon the attack, we continue working. The sacrifice must be a holocaust.</p>

<p>We have to try and put that interior toughness into practice: eating everything that’s placed in front of us, teaching children to do the same, realizing, as one educationalist in the States says, that “no is also a loving word” (James Stenson, Conference Talk, <em>Educating in Virtue</em>, May 1996).</p>

<p>Children learn backbone by example. We need to be demanding on ourselves in order to be demanding on them—in work, in detachment, in chastity, in practicing temperance and sobriety in the home in relation to television, or movies, or spending money, or holidays, or luxuries, or comforts.</p>

<p>“Courage is simply the willingness to be afraid but to act anyway” (Robert Anthony, <em>Beyond Positive Thinking</em>). In the course of our life, very likely there’s something to which God is calling us to do that may scare us to death. We can ask St. Joseph that we could have the courage that we need to act anyway.</p>

<p>“There are many good reasons,” we’re told in <em>The Forge</em>, “to honor St. Joseph, and to learn from his life. He was a man of strong faith. He earned a living for his family—Jesus and Mary—with his own hard work. He guarded the purity of the Blessed Virgin, who was his Spouse. And he respected—he loved!—God’s freedom when God made his choice: not only his choice of Our Lady the Virgin as his Mother, but also the choice of St. Joseph as the husband of Our Lady” (J. Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 552).</p>

<p>We can finish our prayer turning to Our Lady and ask her that she might help us to be more conscious of St. Joseph as we go about our daily tasks, to live a presence of him, and to truly put that phrase “Go to Joseph” into practice as we move through our ordinary day.</p>

<p><em>I thank you my God for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Anniversary of the Women of the Prelature</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Anniversary of the Women of the Prelature" /><published>2026-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-11T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-anniversary-of-the-women-of-the-prelature/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em><br />
<br />
In the Entrance Antiphon of today’s Mass, we read, “Sing psalms and hymns and inspired songs among yourselves, singing and chanting to the Lord in your hearts” (Eph. 5:19).</p>

<p>Today, the 14th of February, is a day of celebration and of thanksgiving in Opus Dei for all of the graces that God has given to us.</p>

<p>As we realize another year has passed, a year of our vocation, a year of the history of the Work on the earth, another year of the fulfillment of God’s plans, of how He’s using His Work to do all sorts of wonderful things in us and through us.</p>

<p>Our Father said, “Always be giving thanks to God constantly for everything: for what seems good and for what seems bad, for what is sweet and for what is bitter, for the white and for the black, for small things and for big things, for what seems meager and for what seems bountiful, for what is temporal and for what reaches unto eternity (J. Escrivá, <em>Notes</em>, December 25, 1972).</p>

<p>We all have great reasons to give thanks to God for the women of the Prelature and also for the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross, whose founding we also celebrate today: very special gifts that God has given to His Work. He crowned them in a special way.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro, on the 60th anniversary of the founding of the women of the Prelature, wrote that on the 14th of February 1930, Our Lord wanted to offer our Father a tangible proof of the divinity of the Work.</p>

<p>Before that date, as we all know, our Founder was very sure that there would not be women in Opus Dei. He told us on more than one occasion, “I had written down, because of the difference between Opus Dei and another institution that existed outside of Spain, that we would never work with women.”</p>

<p>This must have been, he said, around 1929. “Shortly afterwards, on the 14th of February 1930, I was celebrating Mass in the house of an elderly lady, when the women of the Prelature came to the world.”</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “It was a super clear, supernatural light which our Founder received in the Mass, after Communion, on that Friday, 14th of February 1930. As always, when Our Lord manifested His will to him in an extraordinary way, in the first moments, his first reaction was that of feeling a bit disturbed. Then he perceived in the intimacy of his being, those words of Our Lord to Our Lady: ‘Do not be afraid’ (Luke 2:10). And he remained full of peace.”</p>

<p>He began, as he did in 1928 with men, to work apostolically, particularly from the confessional box, with the women and young girls who came to seek his advice.</p>

<p>With great thanksgiving and gratitude to Our Lord, He liked to remember the help that a sister of ours gave him who was taken up with great pain from a great illness. She offered this treasure of her sufferings for this divine enterprise.</p>

<p>When we go back and hear the words of Don Álvaro speaking about the beginnings, we can make a great act of faith, and also of thanksgiving, because we see how God has acted in the world, and very particularly, how He acted in the life of our Father.</p>

<p>When we look around at the reality of Opus Dei, what it is in the world today, it’s a very different phenomenon to what was there in 1930. There was almost nothing. Yet because of our Father’s correspondence, his holiness, his humility, that spirit of Opus Dei has spread all over the world.</p>

<p>Everything that our Father has done and everything that he has written has great relevance for us. God speaks to us through his life and through his correspondence, beckoning us, calling us, encouraging us to walk in the footsteps of our Father, as the pathway that Our Lord has laid out for us in order that we might know Him and love Him.</p>

<p>When the Confessor of our Father heard about this new manifestation of the will of God, without intervening in any way in the organization of the Work, he confirmed to our Father with great sureness that “this is just as much from God as the rest.”</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Look at how Our Lord works. He loves us with all of His goodness. He takes care of us with the refined diligence. He gathers us up with His immense mercy. He never leaves us alone. Even more, He always reaches out with a hand to us.</p>

<p>“Fill yourself with joy, my daughter, my son, because this God of ours, omnipotent and eternal, speaks to us constantly in the silence of our prayer. And we know His voice, also in moments of dryness, because if we are ready and open, as our Father was, to put into practice what Our Lord asks of us, even though we have to go against the grain, He gives us that unequivocal sign of interior peace.”</p>

<p>We can thank God also for that peace that we have in our vocation, in our life, in the means of formation, in our own personal apostolate, in the bringing forward of all the apostolic works, in taking on our shoulders the economic responsibility for all of this great apostolic work that God wants us to do, so that we take our vocation very seriously, we are willing to carry the cross, because we know God will fill us with His interior peace.</p>

<p>“He also speaks to us,” said Don Álvaro, “through other people in spiritual direction. It was Our Lord who spoke to each one of us at the beginning of our vocation, when somebody opened up for us this joyful horizon so that we would give ourselves to the Work. Later on, we count on that blessed personal experience. Our Lord continues to reach out His hand to us all along our pathway until our final pilgrimage on this earth, making use also of spiritual direction to show His will to us.”</p>

<p>There is a conclusion from all of this, and that is that in our interior life, we have to have initiative. Initiative, but at the same time we don’t direct ourselves. Our apostolate is a directed apostolate. We need that obedience, that docility, from those who are there to guide us.</p>

<p>We have this great treasure of the spirit of Opus Dei in our hands. There are aspects of our Father’s life that we are discovering and rediscovering all the time, every time that we read some of his writings, or we discover something new about his life, or the new things that people are writing about him.</p>

<p>One of the ideas that is worth thinking about is that our Father was one of the greatest Christian feminists of the 20th century. Possibly nobody in the history of the Church has done as much for women in the world as our Father has done.</p>

<p>He encouraged women to use their talents to the full in all fields of human endeavor: in business, in politics, in medicine, in engineering, in the home, in science, in all sorts of areas. He wrote very dramatic things about the role of women in society that in many ways were ahead of their time.</p>

<p>In <em>Conversations</em> he says, “The development, maturity, emancipation of women should not mean a pretension to equality, to uniformity with men, a servile imitation of a man’s way of doing things. That would not get us anywhere. Women would turn out losers, not because they’re better than men or worse, but because they’re different.”</p>

<p>He liked to outline these particular characteristics of women and the great talents that they bring to any enterprise. He said, “Women, like men, possess the dignity of being persons and children of God. … They’re called to bring to the family, to society, and to the Church, characteristics which are their own and which they alone can give: their gentle warmth and untiring generosity, their love for detail, their quick-wittedness and intuition, their simple and deep piety, their constancy” (J. Escrivá, <em>Conversations</em>, Point 87).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul liked to say that every man coming into the world is entrusted to the care of a woman (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Mulieris dignitatem</em>, Point 30, August 15, 1988).</p>

<p>He liked to say that while both parents play a role, it’s the woman in particular that teaches the man what it means to be human. Ultimately, she teaches him what it means to love, and then this is his greatest maturity.</p>

<p>One American educationalist says that every baby coming into the world comes into the world like a self-satisfying, hedonistic gorilla. The role of parents is to turn that hedonistic, self-satisfying gorilla into an adult.</p>

<p>The little baby screams for its milk. ‘Give me my milk, and even if it’s three in the morning, get up out of bed and give me my milk because I am the most important person in the world. And I’m going to scream and scream and scream until I get it.’ The role of parents is to turn this little gorilla into an adult.</p>

<p>He says that adults are not just people who can take care of themselves, because a dog or a cat or a hothouse plant can do that. An adult is somebody who fundamentally can take care of others. An adult is somebody who can forget about themselves.</p>

<p>That’s what love is. That’s why some people never become adults, because love is sacrifice. The mother has sacrificed herself for her child. She, more than the father, teaches that lesson to the child: what love is, how to forget about yourself, how to give yourself to others.</p>

<p>He continues in <em>Conversations</em>, “It is not only outside the home that a woman achieves her perfection, as though time spent at home was time stolen from the development of her personality. … The attention given to her family will always be a woman’s greatest dignity. In the care she takes of her husband and children...in her work of creating a warm and formative atmosphere around her, a woman fulfills the most indispensable part of her mission. It follows that she can achieve her personal perfection here” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>While encouraging women to take their place in the world, to go as far as they can, to use all their talents, to play a great role in society, he also emphasizes the fundamental role that a woman plays in the family, in the home—of forming new human beings, of making that home and that family a school of deeper humanity, a school of virtue, a school of piety, the domestic Church.</p>

<p>He continues, “In all spheres, women have their own valuable contribution...which will be rendered to the extent that they are humanly and professionally equipped. Both family and society clearly need this special contribution, which is in no way secondary to that of men.”</p>

<p>We can think of all the great ways that the Catholic Church has promoted the authentic development of women all over the world through our history—the great education orders that have educated girls in every last part of the globe, the healthcare orders who took care of the sick in all sorts of ways, giving great example,</p>

<p>The Church has always promoted the care and education of women as much as possible. But St. Josemaría has sort of brought it to a different level. Their great contribution will be “insofar as they are humanly and professionally equipped.” He encourages women to go as far as they can, to be experts in various fields.</p>

<p>“The essential equality with men and women,” he says, “demands an understanding of the complementary roles which they play in the Church’s growth and in the progress of society” (<em>Conversations</em>, Point 14).</p>

<p>In marriage a man does not complete a woman or the woman does not complete a man. They are already complete in themselves. They complement each other.</p>

<p>“Not in vain,” he says, “did God make them man and woman. This diversity should be considered not in a ‘patriarchal’ sense but in its full, rich depth of tones and consequences” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>Diversity is something good. It’s willed by God, something we have to foster. God created the male and female. The male should be more male and the female should be more female.</p>

<p>“In this way,” he continues, “men are freed from the temptation of ‘masculinizing’ the Church and society, and women from seeing their mission in the People of God and in the world as no more than showing that they can do equally well the tasks which were formerly reserved to men. I think that both men and women should rightly consider themselves as the protagonists in the history of salvation, but each complementing the work of the other” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>I was on a plane a few years ago and there was a young couple with their young baby. I couldn’t help noticing how the mother was looking after the baby very well and keeping him happy.</p>

<p>Then, after a little while she passed the baby to the father. You could sort of see this young father—he did his best, he did what he could. But his way of carrying the baby, looking after the baby, and trying to satisfy the needs of the baby, compared to the mother, was just inadequate.</p>

<p>It was almost amusing to see. In spite of his best efforts, he really couldn’t hack it. In that little moment or two, you could see the difference in the quality of the talents of each individual person. We all have a different role to play.</p>

<p>When we look at the seeds that St. Josemaría has sown in the world by the will of God with the women of the Prelature, we could think, on this feast day—as we begin to look towards the hundredth anniversary that is coming up in a few years, which the Father has encouraged us to focus on—we could think of all the wonderful horizons that are opening up in front of us.</p>

<p>As the Prelate likes to tell us, we have to think back of the early people who went to each country to start the work. There’s a book about the first women who went to Japan. They left Rome. Their boat got as far as—I think it was Aden or Suez or someplace—and they found a letter waiting for them there from our Father.</p>

<p>He followed them every step of the journey. He sent these daughters of his to faraway places to plant that seed. He took great care that the seed would find good soil.</p>

<p>When we look back and see how the women of the Prelature have developed in every country, we see this great divine enterprise from a different perspective.</p>

<p>But then also we have to see how that same faith that our Father had in sending out those sisters of ours, and they themselves, who gave themselves so completely—we have to try and have the same dispositions in our apostolate, as we also “launch out into the deep” (Luke 5:4).</p>

<p>In 1988, on the 60th anniversary of the founding of the men of the Prelature, Don Álvaro talked about the spirit of the beginnings.</p>

<p>He said, “This 60th anniversary is an excellent occasion that Our Lord gives us to remind ourselves that we always have to go forward with the stimulating spirit full of the novelty of the beginnings, that spirit with which our Founder started the Work on the 2nd of October 1928, to carry out the task that God was entrusting to him, that made him the happiest person in the world because of the confidence that Our Father in heaven gave him.”</p>

<p>Each one of us is called to “launch out into the deep,” to see the new horizons of apostolate that God is placing before us, new people that we get to meet, new possibilities.</p>

<p>The pandemic, social media, there are all sorts of new means for transmitting the message of the Gospel. There are new people who are hungry to hear these things. We have to look to the future.</p>

<p>Recently, Pope Francis has talked about how there is a great spiritual emptiness in the world (Pope Francis, Apostolic Exhortation, <em>Querida Amazonia</em>, Point 108, February 2, 2020; <em>Angelus</em>, June 19, 2016).</p>

<p>Our Father would like to say this is our world. This moment of history—it is the world that God has entrusted to us.</p>

<p>He wants us to fill that spiritual emptiness with all the good things that we have to give, with the apostolate of apostolates, with the care of our homes and of our family, with all sorts of details of taste and elegance—often unconscious details that transmit a great refinement and transmit the message of the dignity of every human person.</p>

<p>Our Father has said that every corner of the homes of every supernumerary, every cooperator, has to become a corner of the home in Nazareth. It is our job to make that happen.</p>

<p>Each one of us has to help our sisters to fulfill that great goal: caring for the work of the Catering, taking care of the dining room, taking care with things of laundry, order, looking after the <em>regulae internae,</em> the criteria of separation that our Father has given us, learning how to serve in a better way so that the work of our sisters reaches further, and so that from each one of our homes and our centers, there radiates that spirit of Christian fraternity that hopefully will help to spread the seeds of many vocations in many families.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Without wanting to be exhaustive, I want to remind you of certain concrete points that we have to keep very much in mind as we try to faithfully fulfill the Work of God on this earth.”</p>

<p>Like our Father Abraham, you could say of our Founder that he believed “against all hope” (Rom. 4:18), confiding in the Word of God. That supernatural sureness that the Work would be carried out was confirmed to him by Our Lord on many different occasions. It presupposed the exercise of a heroic faith on the part of our Founder.</p>

<p>As we look to the future, we’re also called to have heroic faith in our vocation, in the Church, in the Holy Father, in Our Father God who is beside us all the time—in this particular apostolic task that God has placed in front of me, this Circle, that class, this recollection, this retreat, this town or village that I have to try and bring the Work to, with a number of journeys.</p>

<p>Lord, help me to have the same hope, confidence, fortitude, perseverance as our Father had in fulfilling these things.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro continues, “Without failing before any of the difficulties that humanly speaking were enormous, difficulties that presented themselves to him along his pathway, he didn’t vacillate in any way. He thought of that aspiration: ‘The waters will pass through the mountains’ (Ps. 104:10). Our Lord comforted him with that aspiration on the 12th of December 1931 when the obstacles to the development of the Work were truly immense.</p>

<p>“None of us in our efforts to spend ourselves to bring forth Opus Dei will ever encounter the same sort of obstacles that our Father encountered. God placed these aspirations in his soul, in his heart, so that he would transmit them to us, so that we would always walk with faith and optimism along the pathways of the earth, very confident that God is acting in us and through us.</p>

<p>“With the fortitude of God and the faith of our Founder,” said Don Álvaro, “we have to personify until the end of time ‘waters will pass through the mountains,’ overcoming all sorts of difficulties that will never be lacking.”</p>

<p>We can’t be surprised that there are difficulties or crosses or problems. That’s par for the course. It’s a given. It’s a good sign. God blesses us with the cross.</p>

<p>The Father has said that the expansion of Opus Dei goes forward in and from the cross. We’re not surprised by the cross in our life. We can thank God for those crosses. They help us to be more supernatural, to turn to our prayer a little more.</p>

<p>One time, many years ago, Don Álvaro went to visit England. He was told that they were redoing a number of the centers, doing a lot of rebuilding and extending and all sorts of developments, and that they had huge financial problems.</p>

<p>Don Álvaro said, “Wonderful. I wish you many financial problems, because then you will pray more.”</p>

<p>The problems lead us to pray, lead us to be supernatural. These were great lessons that our Father and Don Álvaro learned in the course of time that they wanted to transmit to us.</p>

<p>He continues, “This must be our attitude in our personal apostolate, and in the tasks that the Work confides to us. Sure of the power of God, with the spirit of initiative and the mentality of pioneers, we have to launch ourselves to open up new channels through which the spirit of Opus Dei can circulate, carrying to the most diverse environments that supernatural savor capable of vivifying all honorable human occupations.”</p>

<p>What an enormous horizon! Through our friends and contacts, we come to know of new environments, professions, areas where perhaps the spirit of God and the doctrine of God needs to circulate.</p>

<p>So many people who are in need of new ideas or of doctrine are in formerly Christian countries that have forgotten all their Christian formation and need to be born again.</p>

<p>We are here to carry out this great work of evangelization. God wants to use inadequate instruments with all of their miseries—that is, each one of us.</p>

<p>“We can’t dilute,” he says, “our personal responsibility, that of each one of us, into that of the directors or a supposed structure. Our Father affirmed that the Work is ‘a disorganized organization.’ That means that as a consequence, there could never be lacking our personal spontaneity, and that of all the members of the Prelature, at the time of proposing and bringing forward apostolic activities.”</p>

<p>Each one of us is to think: What can I do? What does God want me to do? Where can I have initiative and responsibility in bringing things forward?</p>

<p>“The organization of the Work,” he says, “does not hem us in in any way. Rather, through its very nature, it stimulates us. It fosters a great liberty of movement not only in professional and political areas, but that of each one of us, in the enormously wide fields of personal apostolic initiative.”</p>

<p>That word initiative is a very attractive word on the lips of a member of Opus Dei. He says, “We cannot forget that a woman of Opus Dei, a man of Opus Dei, must in all moments be a person who is an apostle.”</p>

<p>We can ask Our Lady, Mother of Fair Love, that she might help us to go very deep on this special day, and ask Our Lord to help us to have a greater spirit of wonder and gratitude for our vocation, as we look to the future and all the great horizons that the Father is placing before us.</p>

<p><em>Mater Pulchrae Dilectiones, filios tuos adiuva!</em></p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>DWM</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Lady of Lourdes</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Lady of Lourdes" /><published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/our-lady-of-lourdes/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p><em>(Proofread)</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that You are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins, and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>We're told in the story of Cana of Galilee that “the Mother of Jesus was there” (John 2:1).</p>

<p>Today is the feast of Our Lady of Lourdes.</p>

<p>John Paul II, talking about the popularity of Lourdes in the last century, would like to say that possibly it’s because also “the Mother of Jesus is there” (John Paul II, <em>Introduction to the Recitation of the Rosary</em>, August 14, 2004). Today, the World Day of the Sick, is a day to ask Our Lady of Lourdes for special things.</p>

<p>It's a day that marks the first apparition of Our Lady there in 1858 to a young girl, 14-year-old Bernadette Soubirous.</p>

<p>There were a total of eighteen apparitions in all, quite a large number. The message of Lourdes was, as always, a message of personal conversion, of prayer, of charity.</p>

<p>It was approved as a feast day by Pope Leo XIII, and Pope Pius X extended this feast day to the Universal Church. Bernadette herself was beatified and canonized by Pope Pius XI in 1925.</p>

<p>A couple of years previously, in 1854, the Church had defined as infallible the dogma of the Immaculate Conception. Then just four years later, in this very obscure little village which Lourdes is, hidden there in the Pyrenees, a place you'd pass by at the moment, you'd blink, you'd miss it, Our Lady chose to appear to this shepherd girl.</p>

<p>She appeared a number oftimes. Bernadette was eventually encouraged to ask the Lady who she was.</p>

<p>The whole phenomenon caused a lot of consternation of the local people, all sorts of interest and curiosity. And when she asked her, Bernadette said later, “She said, ‘I am the Immaculate Conception.’”</p>

<p>When she told this to the local priest and bishop, they realized there was no way that this little farming rural girl could possibly know what those words meant. But of course, they knew about the dogma that had been proclaimed four years earlier.</p>

<p>Little by little, in spite of many contradictions, and a lot of misunderstanding, which always accompanies the supernatural—Bernadette had to suffer a lot in her family: misunderstandings, accusations of fraud, all sorts of things, punishments—eventually, she was believed, and a sculptor tried to make an image of the Lady that had appeared.</p>

<p>It was a very beautiful statue. When it was finished, Bernadette was asked what she thought of the statue: “Did the Lady look anything like this?” Despite the statue being a very beautiful statue, Bernadette said, “Oh, no, no, the Lady was much more beautiful” (Bernadette Soubirous, <em>A Short Life of Bernadette of Lourdes</em>). The sculptor had done his best, but he didn't quite make it.</p>

<p>There was a curious statistic that I heard a number of years ago. Somebody was talking about the main tourist destinations in France. Of course, when you think about the main tourist destinations, I think most people in Europe certainly would think about the popular places that you hear about on the French Riviera, very stylish supper places.</p>

<p>But curiously, at the very top of the list of tourist destinations in France is Lourdes. None of these other very chic places attract anything like the numbers that Lourdes has attracted over the years. There's something special there. The Mother of Jesus was there.</p>

<p>She appeared with her message of charity, of looking out for the sick. Today is the World Day of the Sick.</p>

<p>She was there to encourage the sick, to help them. And over time, she has performed many miracles; some of them spiritual, many physical. The cures and the miracles are almost numberless.</p>

<p>I met an Australian missionary [Paul Glynn] in Japan. (I was in Japan, I met him in Singapore many years ago.) He wrote a book about Lourdes. It's a rather interesting book. It was called <em>Healing Fire from Frozen Earth.</em></p>

<p>It was like a modern history of Lourdes, written in a very secular way, for a very secular readership of the 21st century, but with very cogent descriptions. You have to admit there's something very supernatural that was taking place there.</p>

<p>Our Lord wanted to entrust Our Lady with very special riches that she would transmit to humanity, a reminder of the infinite mercy of God. Our Lady reaches out to every single person.</p>

<p>In the Litany, we refer to her as Health of the Sick, Comfort of the Afflicted. At some stage in our life, we've all been more or less sick, or we know people that have been.</p>

<p>It's wonderful to know that we have a Mother to turn to, somebody who always understands us, somebody also who can bring good out of every suffering, so that in every little bit of suffering that we might endure and that Our Lady might permit in our life, we know that she's going to take this thing and convert it into something of great value.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story of how there was a lady in the late 19th century, late 1800s, in Paris, a French lady, Catholic lady, who married a man who was the chairman of the Communist Party. He was also the editor of the Communist newspaper, a very prominent Communist.</p>

<p>She felt that God had given her this husband to convert him. He was a very intelligent man; she was just a very normal lady. She tried to brush up on her theology as best she could, or her doctrine, to engage him intellectually. But she more or less got nowhere; she didn't achieve anything. But after several years of marriage, she got very sick.</p>

<p>I think it was TB of the spine or something, and she had to be in an iron lung for a number of years. She suffered an awful lot, but she and her husband were very much in love.</p>

<p>One day, after many years, she said to him, “After I die, you will convert and become a Catholic.” He was thinking, “I think my wife is nearing her end.” Because there was nothing further from his mind.</p>

<p>Then she said, “After that, you will enter a seminary and you will be ordained a Catholic priest.”</p>

<p>He said, “Definitely my wife is losing her mind.” There was nothing further from his thoughts; it was outside the bounds of possibility.</p>

<p>Then she said, “Because I have asked God to send me enough suffering in my life, to save your soul.” He dismissed these thoughts as the thoughts of a dying woman.</p>

<p>Then she passed away, and he had an awful lot of grief because he had loved her very much. He wanted somehow to reconnect with her spirit or to relive the moments they had spent together. He took time off, and he decided to go and visit all the places that they had been to in France on their honeymoon.</p>

<p>He began to travel all over France, as they did on their honeymoon. At one stage, he found himself in a small village outside the local church, and he remembered that on their honeymoon, they had gone into the church.</p>

<p>It wasn't politically correct for him to be seen going to churches. He also hated going to churches; he had no time for that sort of thing. But he had made a promise to himself to go everywhere they had been on their honeymoon, so he went into the church.</p>

<p>Inside the church, he got this tremendous desire to go to Lourdes. Well, he had hated Lourdes. He had dismissed Lourdes as one of those Catholic superstitions and frauds in his communist newspaper. He condemned it from a height as silly superstitious stuff.</p>

<p>But here he had this great desire to go to Lourdes, so he went to Lourdes.</p>

<p>Standing in front of the grotto of Lourdes, he underwent a monumental conversion. So great were the graces of his conversion that the thought of going back to Paris and resigning from the chairmanship of the Communist Party and the editorship of the communist newspaper. It didn't cost him a thought.</p>

<p>A couple of months later, he entered a Dominican seminary, and eventually, he was ordained a priest.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says, “I did my retreat given by that Dominican priest in 1925. It's not often in the course of your life where you attend a retreat where the preacher frequently says, ‘as my wife Elizabeth used to say.’”</p>

<p>Our Lady is capable of the most monumental conversions. On feast days like today, we join the whole Church and the whole world in bringing to Our Lady our every need.</p>

<p>We know that she knows us very well. She hears our petitions, no matter what they may be.</p>

<p>That motherly assistance will fill us with peace and joy. In the last 150 years or more, she has heard the voices of so many children who pray to her.</p>

<p>Today, somebody sent me a little video clip of a Mass in Lourdes this morning, packed with thousands of people. So, the devotion to Our Lady of Lourdes is still very much alive and well.</p>

<p>Small children, when they stray from their mother, get uneasy. They can feel a bit lost, and more than a bit lost. Likewise, we have to try and make sure that we don't stray too much from Our Lady. We stay close to her.</p>

<p>In the intimacy of our personal prayer, we can ask her for things. Or see how we turn to Our Mother frequently during the day with our <em>Angelus</em>, with our Rosary, maybe in our <em>Morning Offering</em>, with our <em>Memorares</em>, or other little aspirations that we may say, asking for help in this thing or that thing, or lights to understand things a little better, or the fortitude we need to get this thing done, or that problem solved, or placing before her all of our children and grandchildren, so that we are truly a powerful force in their lives, a force of prayer.</p>

<p>I remember I had a relation whose parents were not—well, one was Catholic, one wasn't—they weren't practicing. This little girl managed to make her First Holy Communion. I remember my mother commenting, “It's the prayers of your grandmother.”</p>

<p>I always remember those words, trying to figure out, How do the prayers of my grandmother have anything to do with this little seven-year-old making her First Holy Communion?—as though saying it was a major miracle.</p>

<p>There are many things, perhaps as parents and grandparents, that we bring about through our prayer, and that God has been planning from all eternity, and our fidelity in prayer, our turning to Our Lady:</p>

<p>“Remember, O most Gracious Virgin Mary, that never was it known, that anyone who fled to your protection, implored your help, or sought your intercession was left unaided” (Prayer, <em>The Memorare</em>).</p>

<p>We know she's looking out for us all the time. She had a very clear message when she appeared in the grotto. She wanted to remind humanity of the need for conversion and penance. In nearly all of her apparitions, she said the same thing.</p>

<p>As in nearly all of her other apparitions, she's also prayed the Rosary with Bernadette, as though emphasizing the power of the Rosary.</p>

<p>She also spoke of how we can be co-redeemers with Christ, redeeming with Him, uniting our sufferings with Him on the Cross—any pain, physical or moral, difficulties in our life, challenges, contradictions, mysteries—and also voluntary mortifications that we might do some day out of generosity, offering those things to Our Lady in atonement for all the sins of men.</p>

<p>With Our Lady beside us, we can come to see how things that might appear to be a great tragedy can in fact bring about great good, and consider it through the eyes of faith.</p>

<p>I was at a special Mass about a week or so ago in Msongari in Loreto in Nairobi. It was the 100th anniversary of the Loreto Sisters in Kenya, and of course it was a very special moment. It’s possibly one of the longest-serving religious orders in Kenya.</p>

<p>Archbishop Kivuva [Martin Kuviva Musonde] said the Mass and he was saying many beautiful things about the contribution the Sisters had made to the Church in Kenya; what the Church in Kenya would not have been if it hadn't been for Loreto Sisters, and how he'd asked a number of kids, “Do you go to Loreto School?” They'd say, “No, but my mother did.”</p>

<p>He said, half the country said the same thing, in a couple of little clips that are very apt.</p>

<p>But being at this Mass and thinking about the six Sisters that arrived here in 1921, and a hundred years later, I reckon about a million girls have been educated. You can trust that beginning with the arrival point that we've reached 100 years later, it’s just unimaginable.</p>

<p>We couldn't even dream about it or think about it. Just incredible. You can't explain it in human terms. But of course, the story is one of faith and also one of heroism.</p>

<p>Along the way, there have been a lot of tragedies. There was a bus that went off the road in Meru a couple of years ago. Some students lost their lives, some lost limbs.</p>

<p>There was a train in the late 1990s that was coming from Mombasa with two Kenyan Loreto Sisters who were destined for important administrative positions, perhaps in the development of their order. There was a flood, the bridge was washed away, and when the train came there, it went into the river and that was the end of those nuns.</p>

<p>All sorts of heartbreaking tragedies have been part of the story. But when 100 years have passed and you look back, it's just amazing what has been achieved.</p>

<p>You see what God wants to do with our correspondence to grace. In our marriage, in our family, despite the contradictions or the difficulties or the things that haven't worked out, it's all a story of faith, of heroism, and of grace.</p>

<p>We can have great faith and trust in all the miracles that Our Lady wants to work in us and through us, through our fidelity, and places these examples before us.</p>

<p>This is a great message that we can transmit to people who may have illnesses, serious illnesses, maybe chronic things, or people who are born disabled, or who don't have the physical or mental talents that we might have. All these things invite us to trust more in God and to put God's power above our meager efforts.</p>

<p>He can do much greater things in a much greater way, but He just wants to use us as His humble instruments.</p>

<p>Maybe we make mistakes, and maybe things go wrong, but we just put one foot in front of the other. St. Paul tells us that we will not be tested beyond our strength (<em>cf</em>. 1 Cor. 10:13).</p>

<p>Even though there might be contradictions, or difficulties, or heartbreaks, we see these things through the eyes of faith, and we know that God has permitted this thing.</p>

<p>If He gives me this cross, He’ll give me the grace to be able to carry it. There will be no trial that will be too much.</p>

<p>If we remember that we are just children of God, children of Mary, we know that He will never let us down. The millions and millions of people that go to Lourdes every year, in many ways that's what they're stating with their feet. They go there to entrust themselves once again to Our Lady, telling her that we know that she will never give us more than we can handle.</p>

<p>St. Augustine says, “Do everything possible and ask for what is impossible” (<em>cf</em>. St. Augustine, <em>Treatise on Nature and Grace</em>).</p>

<p>St. Josemaría used to say, “We're not just here to do the possible, anybody can do the possible; we're here to do the impossible” (<em>cf</em>. Josemaría Escrivá, <em>The Forge</em>, Point 216).</p>

<p>When you look at the history of that particular religious order, you see that in many ways they've achieved the impossible.</p>

<p>Some of them were telling me that when they set up Loreto Limuru, the first school for African girls in the whole of East Africa, sometimes they didn't have food to eat. or in the emergency, the bullets were flying with the Mau Mau, all sorts of amazing challenges. But yet they hung in there.</p>

<p>Some of them were saying that when they got the initial girls that came to the first school, they managed to convince some of the chiefs to try and educate their daughters. Education was unheard of. The first group of ten or twelve came to the school, and within twenty-four hours, they all ran away. They had to be coaxed back to the school.</p>

<p>Then it was a boarding school. It was far away from where they lived, so they had to live in conditions, and they had sacks that were filled with grass. That's what the mattresses were. It was all very rudimentary.</p>

<p>But little by little they got these girls to the stage of doing the Cambridge exam. It was a big thing to be able to send the papers of these girls, after decades, to be corrected in England and get that standard.</p>

<p>This nun told me that when they sent the papers of the girls to be corrected in England, the nuns kept a carbon copy of the answers of the girls, in case the ship went down. Wow. Nothing was to stand in the way of the education of these girls.</p>

<p>You hear an anecdote or two like that, and you realize, my goodness, these were some women, with incredible ideas. That's why Archbishop Kivuva was able to say they have changed the face of education in this country. They set the standards, and they did incredible things, in the face of all sorts of difficulties.</p>

<p>Of course, their great boast is Wangari Maathai, a Nobel Prize winner. Not every school can boast of that. But of course, to achieve those sorts of things, there's commitment, there's ideals, there's the whole missionary thrust of the Church, the whole social teaching of the Church.</p>

<p>I wrote a bit of an article about this event, and I was saying: You know, we hear an awful lot about the empowerment of women in the world today in the 21st century, as though this is something enormously new.</p>

<p>But if you look back 100 years ago, these women were full of the ideals of the empowerment of women. It's very deeply there, the social teaching of the Catholic Church.</p>

<p>And they had to overcome all sorts of obstacles to make it happen: colonial governments and powers and all sorts of things. That's why their school was far away from Nairobi, near the railway.</p>

<p>We see a story of people going forward, step by step, doing things with the help of Our Lady, not being held back by anything, by any human force. We learn from this how we have to try and have that same faith.</p>

<p>John Paul II talked about how the vocation, or anybody's vocation, but particularly the vocation of Our Lady, was “a pilgrimage of faith” (John Paul II, <em>General Audience</em>, March 21, 2001; Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 58). A pilgrimage is a journeying forward, step by step.</p>

<p>The whole of your marriage vocation is a pilgrimage of faith. The whole of your Christian vocation, your apostolic vocation—there's always something for us to do. God is working there behind the scenes all the time.</p>

<p>We find many people going to shrines of Our Lady. Here in this country we have national shrines in Subukia; there's another one coming up in Kitui. Probably they will mushroom over time.</p>

<p>It’s a pretty good thing to let our children and grandchildren be aware of these places, or to go on pilgrimages there from time to time.</p>

<p>We hope to foster Marian piety, so that people also know the history of these sorts of places—particularly Lourdes, the major Marian shrine in the world—and to see how it's a place for them to go to, or a devotion to Our Lady of Lourdes, in time of difficulty.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to ask the question, “Why is it precisely the sick who go on pilgrimage to Lourdes?” He says, “...because the Mother of Jesus is there” (John Paul II, <em>Homily</em>, February 11, 1980).</p>

<p>Some powerful, attractive force. She draws them there with great power because they know that she's there somehow.</p>

<p>I heard a story recently about a very good father somewhere in the rural States. On the parish grounds, there was a grotto of Our Lady of Lourdes, as there are all over the world.</p>

<p>He had a young son, and he wanted to have the son to have a lot of Marian piety. The son happened to ask him, “What's this grotto all about?”</p>

<p>He said, “Well, this is a very, very famous grotto. It goes back a long way in history, and there's one just like it in France. This was the major one here in our parish.” Some people get the story a little bit wrong, but at least the intentions are there.</p>

<p>John Paul II says, “The miraculous cure remains, however, in spite of everything, an exceptional event. Christ's salvific power, propitiated by the intercession of His Mother, is revealed at Lourdes, particularly in the spiritual sphere. It is in the hearts of the sick that Mary makes the voice of her Son heard: a voice that dissolves miraculously the stiffening of bitterness and rebellion, and restores eyes to the soul to see in a new light the world, others, and one's destiny” (<em>ibid</em>.).</p>

<p>To people who may be suffering a lot, or long term, or God may have afflicted them with special things, this story that their suffering can be worthwhile, can be reunited to the Cross of Christ, and have enormous meritorious value—this changes everything.</p>

<p>It makes them thank God for the crosses that He sends them. It helps them to see each day in a different way. We see that all the little difficult things that we may do—it's all earning great rewards for us in heaven.</p>

<p>Our Lady leads us to her Son, who has a special love for the sick. Christ went around the place “doing good and healing all…” (Acts 10:38).</p>

<p>He loved to heal people. He didn’t heal the whole world, but He did heal an awful lot of people.</p>

<p>We see how Christ reaches out to them. We can also see in the people we know, elderly or sick, that Christ is there in this person. “Whenever you did it to one of these little ones, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>It can be a very consoling thought when we reach out in some way to people that we needn't reach out to, or we go the extra mile, or we go out of our way in some way, or maybe we don't get any thanks, or we're not appreciated: “Whenever you did it to one of these little ones, you did it to me” (Matt. 25:40).</p>

<p>Tell Our Lord, We're doing it for you. It's not just for human thanks or human glory.</p>

<p>John Paul liked to say, “Christ was sensitive to every human suffering, whether of the body or of the soul” (John Paul II, Apostolic Letter, <em>Salvifici</em> <em>Doloris</em>, Point 16, February 11, 1984). There are many people in the world who are suffering.</p>

<p>We are on the weekend of the hearts, the 14th of February, all around the place, and Valentine's. Everybody's talking about hearts, and we see lovely hearts all drawn beautifully, and they all link up together again.</p>

<p>John Paul II liked to say that our hearts are not like that, because God has taken a piece of our heart, and He's kept it for Himself in heaven. We only get that piece of our heart back when we go to heaven.</p>

<p>When we pray for a while, maybe He gives it back to us for a while as well. But he said we all suffer from a hole in the heart, and that hole can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>Nothing in this world satisfies it. If those Valentine's Day hearts drew the truth, there'd be a big jagged edge missing from all of those hearts.</p>

<p>“Our hearts are restless, Lord, until they rest in you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions</em>).</p>

<p>Christ allowed His heart to be fit by a lance on the Cross, allowed His heart to be broken, so that He could be like the patron saint of all broken hearts.</p>

<p>Our Lady allowed her heart to be pierced by a spiritual sword (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35), so that she could be there also.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen says, “Only Christ and Our Lady can mend broken hearts, but you've got to give them all the pieces.”</p>

<p>There was an English Lord who was in Nairobi about ten years ago. He came to give a talk at an Ethics Conference at Strathmore University: Lord Alton. He is the main Catholic peer.</p>

<p>In his discourse, he said one thing that was rather interesting. He said, “Only Christianity can change the hearts of men. Governments can't, NGOs can't. Only Christ can, only Christianity.”</p>

<p>This is one of the great powers of the Church, the power to change the hearts of men. We have an inroad into every human heart.</p>

<p>Our Lady has that inroad, the capacity to change hearts with beauty, with truth, and with love. Our Mother is there guiding us to those hearts, that we can give that witness, in our family, in our neighborhood, in the things we do, in the way that we carry the crosses that He gives us, knowing that there will always be sufficient graces, in difficult circumstances, that we can use to draw our friends closer to Him.</p>

<p>We can certainly ask Our Lord to heal our infirmities and resolve our problems. We can ask Him that we might be more docile to His grace, and increase our faith, our hope, our charity.</p>

<p>There were many things initially that Bernadette did not understand. It took quite a while for her to grasp what was taking place. But then, with her correspondence, as she entered a convent, she underwent a lot of sufferings in her life. And she died young, but always happy.</p>

<p>We can put our pains and our sufferings in the hands of God.</p>

<p>“Therefore,” He says, “do not be anxious about tomorrow, for tomorrow will have anxieties of its own. Sufficient for the day is its own trouble” (Matt. 6:34).</p>

<p>Everybody has a cross to carry. We solve all our problems by thinking about the others, helping that other person to correspond generously to the will of God for them.</p>

<p>One spiritual writer says, “Suffering, which in the eyes of men is so disagreeable, can be a fountain of sanctification and apostolate when it is united to Christ” (Adolphe Tanquerey, <em>The Divinization of Suffering</em>).</p>

<p>It is the great secret of Christianity that we have to communicate to other people: there is an opportunity to co-redeem with Jesus, to be beside Mary on the Cross, to atone to their hearts for all the ways in which their hearts suffer.</p>

<p>Many times, when Our Lady appeared, she talked about that heart of Christ’s that was suffering: “Behold, this heart that has loved men so much...and all I get in return are insults. And it is those that are most consecrated to me very often that hurt me most.” These were Christ’s words to St. Margaret Mary Alacoque (Émile Bougaud, <em>Life of the Blessed Margaret Mary Alacoque</em>).</p>

<p>We are called to atone to that heart of Mary, that Immaculate Heart, to offer her things that ease the pain, that say that we’re sorry, that we want to improve our life. We know that Our Mother will give us consolation, she’s Consoler of the Afflicted, Help of the Sick, Help of Christians.</p>

<p>She is always there in all those moments for us to go to her. Mary, Our Lady of Lourdes, may we spread your message with our words and with our actions.</p>

<p>May we foster that devotion to you, which we know you want us to spread around the place, and help many people to find consolation in finding joy in your Immaculate Heart.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, St. Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>OLV</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Priestly Society of the Holy Cross</title><link href="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Priestly Society of the Holy Cross" /><published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frconor-ebook.github.io/meditations/homilies/the-priestly-society-of-the-holy-cross/"><![CDATA[<p>By Fr. Conor Donnelly</p>

<p>(<em>Proofread</em>)</p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>My Lord and my God, I firmly believe that you are here, that you see me, that you hear me. I adore you with profound reverence. I ask your pardon for my sins and grace to make this time of prayer fruitful. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p>“Like living stones, let yourself be built into a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ” (1 Pet. 2:5), we are told in the letter of Saint Peter. Today is the anniversary of the founding of the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría was a diocesan priest. He had great love for all diocesan priests and all priests, but he particularly wanted to do something, and saw that God wanted him to do something, to help diocesan priests, particularly in their spiritual life.</p>

<p>On the one hand, he saw that he was called to found Opus Dei, but he was all the time searching for a way whereby that spirit of Opus Dei and the formation that was there could be extended to diocesan priests. Little by little, God let him see that that was possible.</p>

<p>On the 14th of February 1943, the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross was born. The Priestly Society is an association of priests inseparably united to Opus Dei.</p>

<p>All the formation that lay people receive in Opus Dei—to sanctify their work, to be holy in the middle of the world—priests also can receive. It provides ongoing formation for priests to help them in their spiritual life and professional life through all the various means that Opus Dei uses: regular Confessions, spiritual direction, circles, retreats, seminars.</p>

<p>It tries to foster a great priestly fraternity among the clergy, all the time in very close union with the bishop. There was a juridical problem because diocesan priests could not become members of Opus Dei because their superior is their bishop. The association of priests was formed whereby the Prelate of Opus Dei is concurrently the president of the Priestly Society of the Holy Cross.</p>

<p>That way the juridical bond of the diocesan priest with their bishop to whom they are answerable, and his care for them, is maintained. They benefit from the spirit of Opus Dei while maintaining themselves juridically incardinated in their diocese.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say that today is a day of prayer for priests. He indicated a number of special days in the year for that.</p>

<p>The anniversary of the first three priests of Opus Dei is on June 25th and the Feast of the Curé of Ars, the patron saint of all parish priests, is on August 4th. It’s a day of prayer for priests, priests of the universal Church, and also very particularly, priests of the Prelature.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría brought something like a thousand priests to the altar. Blessed Álvaro brought about 700. He’s taught us to have a great love for the institution of the priesthood, to have great love and respect for priests.</p>

<p>While priests are ordained to the ministerial priesthood, he liked to remind all lay people that they also have a participation in what is called the common priesthood of the faithful, or the universal priesthood of the faithful, that we receive with our Baptism.</p>

<p>Even though we might not be ordained to the ministerial priesthood, we are all called to live out our priesthood in union with Christ on the Cross. And ultimately that’s what priestly soul means: having the same sentiments as Christ on the Cross.</p>

<p>Lay people are not ordained to administer the sacraments, which is the main function of the ordained ministry, priestly ministry. The lay people are called to order the temporal realities.</p>

<p>While they have a priestly soul, they’re called to have a fully lay mentality. The priestly society gives this ongoing formation to priests to help them to sanctify their priestly work, to be holy in and through their ministry, to be priests 100 percent, good shepherds to the others, and to benefit in this way from all of the things which the spirit of Opus Dei gives us in terms of formation.</p>

<p>The first three priests of Opus Dei—their process of beatification is ongoing. This thing of holiness in and through the ministry is not just a nebulous idea, but something very concrete.</p>

<p>We’re told also in St. Peter, “You are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God’s own people, in order that you may proclaim the mighty acts of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light” (1 Pet. 2:9).</p>

<p>Any way that we can help our parish priests or other diocesan priests to grow in their vocation; it is something we should try and foster.</p>

<p>If you have the means to help your local priest get to an annual retreat or to a seminar or some other means of formation, it’s a very good thing to try and achieve.</p>

<p>St. Josemaría liked to say that every priest can bring a thousand souls to heaven. So, one way of fostering evangelization is that prayer and care for priests, helping them to care for their vocation, being close to them in the parish, helping them to understand also the spirit of Opus Dei through your example, through your words, through your apostolates, in all the things that we do.</p>

<p>What is a priest? A priest is somebody who offers sacrifices. In the priesthood of the Old Testament, the priest offered the sacrifices of animals, the blood of goats and cows and heifers.</p>

<p>In the New Testament, the priest also offers sacrifices. He offers the blood of Christ. The main duty of the priest is to celebrate the Mass. And when we’re called to have the priestly soul, a priestly soul is something we receive at Baptism when that character is imprinted on our soul—the seal of Baptism that gives us a participation in the priesthood of Christ.</p>

<p>Christ was most a priest when He offered Himself in sacrifice to His heavenly Father. He practiced all the priestly virtues of humility, of sacrifice, of service, of obedience, of generosity. In our daily life, we have ample opportunities on a regular basis to practice these virtues.</p>

<p>We’re told in St. John, “In truth, I tell you, unless the grain of wheat falls into the ground and dies, it remains only a single grain; but if it dies, it yields a rich harvest” (John 12:24).</p>

<p>St. Paul says, “I urge you then, brethren, remembering the mercies of God, to offer your bodies as a living sacrifice, dedicated and acceptable to God. That is the kind of worship for you as sensible people” (Rom. 12:1).</p>

<p>We’re invited to make of our lives a holocaust, to live out our priesthood in the ordinary events of every day. It’s not just those who are ordained to the ministerial priesthood that live their priesthood. But the Second Vatican Council talked about the ‘universal priesthood of the faithful” (Vatican II, <em>Lumen gentium</em>, Point 10, November 21, 1964; <em>Presbyterorum ordinis</em>, Point 2, December 7, 1965).</p>

<p>In that sense, we’re all priests. We’re called to live out our common or universal priesthood in our work, in our apostolate, in the fulfillment of our family duties, in our marriage, in saying “no” to ourselves, in uniting ourselves to the Cross of Christ and being there with Jesus.</p>

<p>The exercise of our priesthood means above all to serve. We are all called to serve. That’s the purpose of our formation and of all education.</p>

<p>There was a professor once who asked some students in secondary school, Why were they in this school with the Catholic ethos? They said, ‘We’re here to do well in our final exam so that we can get a good result, so we can get into a good university, so we can get a good degree, so we can get a good job, so we can get a good salary.’ He said that wasn’t a very good answer.</p>

<p>He went to some university students in a university with a Catholic ethos and asked them the same question. They said, ‘We’re here in this university to study and to get a good degree so we can get a good job, so we can get a good salary.’</p>

<p>This professor said, This represents the failure of Catholic education, because the purpose of all Catholic education is to serve, “because Christ came not to be served, but to serve” (<em>cf</em>. Mark 10:45).</p>

<p>We’re called to exercise our priestly soul through service. A priest who is ordained to the ministerial priesthood is ordained to serve. That’s the purpose of his ministry. All priesthood leads to that.</p>

<p>Mother Teresa tells a story of how one time a journalist came to her and asked her, What was her opinion of women priests? She said, “I often think that the person who was most cut out to be a priest was Our Lady, because she was the most dignified person that was ever created. She was conceived without original sin. She was full of grace. She had some very special privileges because of her divine maternity. There was nobody who was created so suitable for the priesthood as Our Lady. But yet her vocation was to be ‘the handmaid of the Lord’” (Luke 1:38).</p>

<p>The following day in the newspaper, Mother Teresa said there was a headline that said, ‘Mother Teresa says that women make better priests than men.’ She had to get someone to call the newspaper and say, “That wasn’t exactly what I said.”</p>

<p>Somebody else said once that a woman who wants to be a priest is as misguided as a man who wants to be pregnant. We need to get very clear ideas. If we hear women talking about the fact of how they would like to be priests, it means they have not understood the concept of the common or universal priesthood of the faithful.</p>

<p>It was very clearly expounded in the Second Vatican Council that we are already priests. We have a priestly soul. We’re called to serve.</p>

<p>We’re told in the Letter to the Hebrews, “Every high priest is taken from among human beings and is appointed to act on their behalf in relationships with God, to offer gifts and sacrifices for sins” (Heb. 5:1).</p>

<p>One time in Rome in the early 1950s, there was a consistory about to take place where they appointed cardinals. One young fellow said to St. Josemaría in a get-together: ‘Father, maybe you will be made a cardinal.’</p>

<p>St. Josemaría changed the topic very quickly but afterwards called him to his room. This young person was a medical doctor. St. Josemaría pulled up his cassock and pulled up his shirt and pulled up his undershirt and showed him a big red rash that he had across his chest.</p>

<p>The doctor immediately recognized the rash as the rash of shingles, herpes zoster, a very painful infection of the nerve roots, where people usually have a fever. They’re often in the hospital. Yet St. Josemaría was walking around and talking at that get-together and working as if nothing was the matter.</p>

<p>He pointed to the red of the rash and said, “My son, this is the only red that God has in mind for me, not the red of a cardinal’s hat.”</p>

<p>Many decades later, that medical student, Don Julián Herranz, was made a cardinal. I’m sure he remembered those words of St. Josemaría’s.</p>

<p>With our priestly soul, we take the blows, we offer up the sacrifices. We’re willing to be with Christ on the Cross. We find so many solutions to our problems there.</p>

<p>One time there was a get-together on Easter Sunday night. John Paul II invited the UNIV students to an inner patio there in the Vatican called the San Damaso.</p>

<p>At the end of the sort of get-together they had, a musical get-together, he said, “I am very happy to see all of you here from different countries. So youthful, so happy and so united among yourselves from different places, different cultures, and different backgrounds, but yet there’s a great unity among you.”</p>

<p>The master of ceremonies who had the microphone, a young student, was very quick, and added to that: “United to you, Holy Father.”</p>

<p>And as quick as a wink, the Holy Father, without missing a beat, immediately said, <em>uniti in Cristo</em>, united to Christ. It was a beautiful, spontaneous expression of the priestly soul, everything in our life united to Christ.</p>

<p>Fulton Sheen tells a story about how he went to see Pope Paul VI in 1968, just after the issuing of the encyclical of <em>Humanae Vitae</em>, which is all about the regulation of birth and conjugal love. Beautiful document. A major document of the 20th century. It was also known as the document that banned contraception.</p>

<p>The Holy Father was getting an awful lot of flack in the international press. Fulton Sheen said to him, “Holy Father, you’re well named Paul, because Paul they stoned, and now they’re stoning you.”</p>

<p>The Holy Father said, “Yes, it’s 10 in the evening before I get to open my personal mail, and with each letter, there comes a thorn. When I lie down on my bed at night, I lie down on a crown of thorns.”</p>

<p>“But,” he said, “I can’t tell you the joy, the happiness, the peace I get out of knowing that I’m making up in my body of what is lacking in the sufferings of Christ.”</p>

<p>With that, he was quoting St. Paul to the Colossians, who says, “It makes me happy to be suffering for you now. And in my own body, to make up all the hardships that still have to be undergone by Christ for the sake of his body, the Church” (Col. 1:24).</p>

<p>There is nothing lacking in the sufferings of Christ. But what is lacking is our participation in those sufferings.</p>

<p>Really, what the Holy Father was expressing was that sentiment of priestly soul that’s there within him, finding joy and peace and happiness.</p>

<p>There may be some time in our life when we come across somebody with a broken heart. This week, around the 14th of February, the whole world is looking at hearts and selling hearts and buying hearts. They’re all beautiful hearts. The hearts that are drawn on Valentine’s Day cards, one line links up with the other. Very complete hearts.</p>

<p>But Pope St. John Paul said that our hearts are not like that. He said, God has taken a piece of our heart, and He’s kept it for Himself in heaven. We only get it back when we go there.</p>

<p>“Our hearts are restless, Lord, until they rest in you” (St. Augustine, <em>Confessions,</em> Book 1:1-2).</p>

<p>Pope St. John Paul said we all suffer from a hole in the heart, and that hole can only be filled by God.</p>

<p>Even though these days we see so many beautiful, complete hearts, we also know from the human experience that hearts can be broken. Our Lady’s heart was pierced by a sword, a spiritual sword (<em>cf</em>. Luke 2:35).</p>

<p>Christ’s heart was pierced by a lance and there flowed out blood and water (John 19:34), the fountain of the sacramental life of the Church. We know that all these things can happen.</p>

<p>Our hearts may be broken some time, or we might meet people with broken hearts. Fulton Sheen said that if ever God allows hearts to be broken, it’s because He wants to enter into them a little more (<em>cf</em>. Fulton J. Sheen, <em>Through</em> the <em>Year with Fulton J. Sheen</em>).</p>

<p>Our Lady and Our Lord whose hearts are pierced, they’re a bit like the patron saints of broken hearts. They can mend all broken hearts.</p>

<p>If ever you meet someone with a broken heart, lead them to Jesus, to Mary. They find their peace and their serenity there. They learn how to begin again.</p>

<p>The heart is very important in our faith. God reads the heart. “Rend your heart and not your garments. Come back to me with all your heart” (Joel 2:12-13).</p>

<p>Our priestly soul also leads us to have a great desire to spread truth, to give doctrine, to spread doctrine in every way we can, which are good ideas, the ideas of Christ and the ideas with which He wants us to shape the world.</p>

<p>That priestly soul leads us to spend ourselves for souls, to give ourselves to the apostolate with our whole heart and mind, seeing it’s the greatest occupation and ideal we could have that fills our day and every hour with meaning and with purpose.</p>

<p>Christ came to save souls. The Church is all about souls. That apostolic zeal adds a great dynamism to our life.</p>

<p>Therefore, that leads us to never say ‘enough’ or ‘up to here and no further.’ Those words don’t exist.</p>

<p>We’ve come to give ourselves. Christ emptied Himself. He didn’t just shed one drop of His blood, but He let His blood flow copiously on the Cross.</p>

<p>We’re called to offer everything. We hold nothing back.</p>

<p>If we look at Christ on the Cross, we can get a great encouragement, an example there, a beckoning to fall in love with Him, to follow Him, and to never leave Him.</p>

<p>Our priestly soul finds perfect expression in the Mass and in the prayers of the Mass and the liturgy that can be so meaningful. In the <em>Preface</em> of the First Sunday in Ordinary Time, it says:</p>

<p>“Father, all-powerful and every living God. We do well always and everywhere to give you thanks, through Jesus Christ, Our Lord. Through his cross and resurrection, he freed us from sin and death and has called us to the glory that he has made us a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people set apart. Everywhere we proclaim your mighty works, for you have called us out of darkness into your own wonderful light.”</p>

<p>We’re told in the <em>Furrow</em>: “You say that you’re now beginning to understand what a ‘priestly soul’ means. Don’t be annoyed with me if I tell you that the facts show that you only realize it in theory. —Every day the same thing happens to you: at nighttime, during the examination, it’s all desire and resolutions; during the morning and afternoon at work, it’s all objections and excuses. Are you in this way living a ‘holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ’ (1 Pet. 2:5)?” (Josemaría Escrivá, <em>Furrow</em>, Point 499).</p>

<p>We have a priestly soul, but lay people are also called to live out their priestly soul with a very lay mentality. That’s the way that God wants us to live out our priestly soul in all situations.</p>

<p>To be a layperson is a real vocation. It has certain characteristics. Lay people are not called to imitate priests in the way they talk, the way they walk, and what they talk about. Lay people are called to be fully lay people.</p>

<p>If everybody is talking about football, then we talk about football, or whatever is the thing that people in the middle of the world talk about. We’re not meant to be ‘churchy,’ but rather, fully lay and fully up to date with the ordinary things that lay people do.</p>

<p>That priestly soul has a lot of applications. It can mean our total availability for whatever is necessary for the apostolate. It can be very useful in moments when we come to see our miseries, our limitations, and the ups and downs of each day—to carry on there where God has placed us, in this marriage, in this family, in this job—in persevering in spite of my failures, beginning again.</p>

<p>We can thank God for the priestly occasions when we don’t have what we need or what we’d like to have. It’s a moment to offer our minds and heart and soul to God and say, “Here I am because you’ve called me” (1 Sam. 3:5-10).</p>

<p>With our priestly soul, we overcome the obstacles with the spirit of the beginnings, because we know that God is with us and united to our lay mentality. It doesn’t allow us to remain passive in the face of difficulties.</p>

<p>If on some occasion we have a little bit of extra work—in cleaning or in the kitchen or in cooking at Christmas time, or we find everybody wants a barbecue, or somebody is sick in the house—these are opportunities to offer these things to God with our priestly soul.</p>

<p>Or someday we’re not feeling well, or we have to overcome our whims and our caprices, or we feel a bit rebellious—these are times to offer things to God, persevering in the apostolate entrusted to us, and the jobs that are given to us.</p>

<p>The more we think this and live it, the more truly lay mentality we’ll also have. We can ask Our Lord for the grace to live out this priestly soul a little better.</p>

<p>All the time we find Our Lady standing beside the Cross. Mary lived her priestly soul at that moment more than any other.</p>

<p><em>Stabat Mater dolorosa, iuxta Crucem lacrimósa, dum pendébat Fílius</em>. The Stabat Mater that we read on the Feast of Our Lady of Sorrows, the sequence of that Mass, is very eloquent.</p>

<p>Our Lady is the Lady of Fair Weeping. Her tears are beautiful. She has the sorrows of the one who is all beauty, fully free from the deformity of sin.</p>

<p>One writer says the sinless Spirit-filled heart of Mary is beautifully centered on the will of the Father.</p>

<p>Our Lady lived out her priestly soul by fully accepting the will of God in that moment of the Cross. She gives, she offers, she doesn’t merely let go. She doesn’t just tolerate. She doesn’t assist passively or patiently at the sacrifice of her Son. She’s totally involved.</p>

<p>That’s why the Church called her a co-redeemer. [Update: In <em>Mater Populi Fidelis</em>, a Doctrinal Note issued by the Dicastery for the Doctrine of the Faith with Pope Leo XIV’s approval on November 4, 2025, it was clarified in Points 3, 21, 22 that while her unique cooperation is acknowledged, she is not a co-redeemer nor co-redemptrix.]</p>

<p>St. Albert said, “Our Lady joined herself to the Father of Mercies in his greatest work of mercy when she shared in the Passion of her Son and ‘thus became the helper of our redemption and the Mother of our spiritual generation’” (Albertus Magnus, <em>Summa Theologica</em> <em>IV, 15</em>).</p>

<p>With that poem, the Stabat Mater from the sequence of Pentecost Sunday, we could say: <em>Fac, ut árdeat cor meum in amándo Christum Deum</em>. Make my heart to burn in loving Christ Our Lord.</p>

<p>When Cardinal Ratzinger visited Cavabianca in 1987, he said the Prelature of the Holy Cross in Opus Dei invites its members to stand by Mary there, that Our Lord may see us and each of us become a beloved disciple, hearing the words, “Behold your mother” (John 19:27).</p>

<p>Our Lady beside the Cross was silent. We can learn silence from Our Lady. Our silence can be a measure of our holocaust, of our unity to the Cross of Christ.</p>

<p>We can end our prayer by speaking to Our Lady, the Mother of all priests, thanking her for the priesthood of our Father, a priesthood that she helped so much and so continuously all throughout his life.</p>

<p>Help us, Mother, to value the great institution of the priesthood, to love priests like our Father did, to pray for them, to support them, to see what we can do for the diocesan priesthood as God wants us to do, moving heaven and earth to support that priesthood in every way we can, because we know the great evangelizing influence it can have in every country and in the whole world.</p>

<p>Mary, Mother of the Redeemer, Mediatrix of All Graces, Mother of priests, pray for us now and always.</p>

<p><em>I thank you, my God, for the good resolutions, affections, and inspirations that you have communicated to me during this meditation. I ask your help to put them into practice. My Immaculate Mother, Saint Joseph, my father and lord, my guardian angel, intercede for me.</em></p>

<p><em>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. Amen.</em></p>

<p><em>EW</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Fr. Conor Donnelly]]></summary></entry></feed>